<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="88984">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01834352</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-1289</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01834352</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Walnut Oral Immunotherapy for Tree Nut Allergy</brief_title>
  <acronym>WOIT</acronym>
  <official_title>Walnut Oral Immunotherapy for Tree Nut Allergy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if walnut oral immunotherapy can be used in
      subjects allergic to tree nuts to decrease their tree nut allergy and induce changes in
      their immune system.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Tree nut
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Concern for cross contamination in weighing tree nuts in facility with peanuts
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness of walnut oral immunotherapy (WOIT) on clinical desensitization to a second tree nut.</measure>
    <time_frame>38 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The determination of the effectiveness of WOIT in inducing clinical desensitization to a second tree nut to which the subject is allergic when compared to placebo. This will be measured by the change in the amount of tree nut the subject can consume during their food challenge at 38 weeks compared to their consumption during the baseline challenge at study entry.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects who can tolerate a 5000mg oral food challenge to walnut protein following the desensitization phase of the study</measure>
    <time_frame>38 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The percentage of subjects who can consume all of the 5000mg of walnut protein without symptoms during the food challenge  after the desensitization phase of the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of subjects who are able to reach a cumulative protein dose of 2000mg at the desensitization oral food challenge to walnut and the test tree nut.</measure>
    <time_frame>38 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The percentage of subjects who are able to consume a cumulative protein dose of 2000 mg of walnut and test tree nut without symptoms during the desensitization oral food challenge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of subjects who demonstrate clinical tolerance at the end of the study to walnut and the test tree nut.</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The percentage of subjects who are able to demonstrate clinical tolerance by  consuming all of the walnut and test tree nut without symptoms during the oral food challenge at the end of the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in walnut and test tree nut IgG4 over the course of the study.</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The increase in the walnut and test tree nut specific IgG4 over the course of the study as an indication of the impact of WOIT on the immune system.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in the walnut and test tree nut specific IgE over the course of the study.</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The decrease in the walnut and test tree nut specific IgE over the course of the study as an indication of the impact of WOIT on the immune system.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Nut Hypersensitivities</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Walnut protein flour</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Walnut protein flour administered in varying dose amounts which begin at a low dose and are increased every 2 weeks until the maximum dose is achieved.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oat flour</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oat flour administered in varying dose amounts which begin at a low dose and are increased every 2 weeks until the maximum dose is achieved.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Walnut Protein Flour</intervention_name>
    <description>The initial day escalation begins with a dose of 0.1 mg of walnut protein. The dose is then increased and administered every thirty minutes until a maximum dose of 6 mg is reached or until allergic symptoms develop. After the initial escalation day, subjects begin the build-up phase in which the dose is increased every two weeks to a maximum dose of 1500mg walnut protein at 34 weeks. After 34 weeks of build-up, the subject begins the maintenance phase in which daily dose (1500mg or the highest dose reached by 34 weeks) is taken for 4 weeks followed by a 5 gram protein oral food challenge to walnut and a 5 gram protein oral food challenge to the second tree nut (at 38 weeks). Then the  study will be unblinded. Active treatment subjects will continue on the 1500mg walnut protein daily dose for a maximum of 33 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Walnut protein flour</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oat flour</intervention_name>
    <description>The initial day escalation begins with a dose of 0.1 mg of oat flour. The dose is then increased and administered every thirty minutes until a maximum dose of 6 mg is reached or until allergic symptoms develop. After the initial escalation day, subjects begin the build-up phase in which the dose is increased every two weeks to a maximum dose of 1500mg oat flour at 34 weeks. After 34 weeks of build-up, the subject begins the maintenance phase in which daily dose (1500mg or the highest dose reached by 34 weeks) is taken for 4 weeks followed by a 5 gram protein oral food challenge to walnut and a 5 gram protein oral food challenge to the second tree nut (at 38 weeks). Then the study will be unblinded. Placebo subjects that fail the OFC will be crossed over to active treatment beginning with the initial escalation day, build-up and maintenance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oat flour</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 6 to 45 years, either sex, any race, any ethnicity with a convincing clinical
             history of walnut or another tree nut allergy and either a positive prick skin test
             (&gt; 3mm) or serologic evidence of allergic sensitization (defined as specific IgE &gt;
             0.35 kU/L) to walnut and at least one other tree nut.

          -  A positive 2000 mg oral food challenge at enrollment to walnut and to one other tree
             nut.

          -  Written informed consent from participant and/or parent/guardian

          -  Written assent from all subjects as appropriate

          -  All females of child bearing age must be using appropriate birth control

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of severe anaphylaxis to walnut or other tree nuts, defined as symptoms
             associated with hypoxia, hypotension or neurologic compromise (cyanosis or SpO2 &lt; 92%
             at any stage, hypotension, confusion, collapse, loss of consciousness; or
             incontinence).

          -  Known allergy to oat

          -  Chronic disease (other than asthma, atopic dermatitis, rhinitis) requiring therapy or
             other respiratory or medical conditions deemed by the investigator to put the subject
             at increased risk of anaphylaxis or poor outcomes from receiving OIT or undergoing
             food challenge.

          -  Poor control or persistent activation of atopic dermatitis

          -  Active eosinophilic or other inflammatory (e.g., celiac) gastrointestinal disease in
             the past 2 years.

          -  Participation in any interventional study for food allergy in the past 6 months

          -  Participant is on &quot;build-up phase&quot; of immunotherapy (i.e., has not reached
             maintenance dosing).

          -  Severe asthma (2007 NHLBI Criteria Steps 5 or 6, see Appendix 2) or poorly controlled
             mild or moderate asthma

          -  Inability to discontinue antihistamines for initial day escalation, skin testing or
             OFC

          -  Use of omalizumab or other non-traditional forms of allergen immunotherapy (e.g.,
             oral or sublingual) or immunomodulator therapy (not including corticosteroids) or
             biologic therapy within the past year

          -  Use of beta-blockers (oral), angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors,
             angiotensin-receptor blockers (ARB) or calcium channel blockers

          -  Pregnancy or lactation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wesley Burks, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UNC Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Vickery, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>UNC Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Edwin Kim, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>UNC Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kulis M, Li Y, Lane H, Pons L, Burks W. Single-tree nut immunotherapy attenuates allergic reactions in mice with hypersensitivity to multiple tree nuts. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2011 Jan;127(1):81-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2010.09.014. Epub 2010 Nov 18.</citation>
    <PMID>21093029</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hofmann AM, Scurlock AM, Jones SM, Palmer KP, Lokhnygina Y, Steele PH, Kamilaris J, Burks AW. Safety of a peanut oral immunotherapy protocol in children with peanut allergy. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2009 Aug;124(2):286-91, 291.e1-6. Epub 2009 May 27.</citation>
    <PMID>19477496</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones SM, Pons L, Roberts JL, Scurlock AM, Perry TT, Kulis M, Shreffler WG, Steele P, Henry KA, Adair M, Francis JM, Durham S, Vickery BP, Zhong X, Burks AW. Clinical efficacy and immune regulation with peanut oral immunotherapy. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2009 Aug;124(2):292-300, 300.e1-97. Epub 2009 Jul 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19577283</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Varshney P, Jones SM, Scurlock AM, Perry TT, Kemper A, Steele P, Hiegel A, Kamilaris J, Carlisle S, Yue X, Kulis M, Pons L, Vickery B, Burks AW. A randomized controlled study of peanut oral immunotherapy: clinical desensitization and modulation of the allergic response. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2011 Mar;127(3):654-60. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2010.12.1111.</citation>
    <PMID>21377034</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Wesley Burks, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Walnut hypersensitivity</keyword>
  <keyword>Tree nut hypersensitivity</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nut Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
