<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="122873">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02137772</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>8228-001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-003831-31</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02137772</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MK-8228 (Letermovir) Versus Placebo in the Prevention of Clinically-Significant Cytomegalovirus (CMV) Infection in Adult, CMV-Seropositive Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant Recipients (MK-8228-001)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase III Randomized, Placebo-controlled Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of MK-8228 (Letermovir) for the Prevention of Clinically Significant Human Cytomegalovirus (CMV) Infection in Adult, CMV-Seropositive Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant Recipients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study will evaluate the efficacy and safety of MK-8228 for the prevention of
      clinically-significant CMV infection in adult, CMV-seropositive recipients of allogeneic
      hematopoietic stem cell transplant. The hypothesis being tested is that MK-8228 is superior
      to placebo in the prevention of clinically-significant CMV infection through 24 weeks after
      transplant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Clinically-Significant CMV Infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 weeks after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Onset of Clinically-Significant CMV Infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 weeks after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Clinically-Significant CMV Infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 weeks after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with CMV Disease</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 weeks after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with CMV Disease</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 weeks after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Pre-emptive Therapy for CMV Viremia</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 weeks after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Pre-emptive Therapy for CMV Viremia</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 weeks after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Initiation of Pre-emptive Therapy for CMV Viremia</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 weeks after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">540</enrollment>
  <condition>Cytomegalovirus Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MK-8228</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK-8228 oral or intravenous (IV) formulation will be administered once daily for 14 weeks after transplant. The dose will be 240 mg once daily for participants receiving concomitant cyclosporin A and 480 mg once daily for participants not receiving cyclosporin A. Intravenous infusion will be administered only to participants who are unable to swallow tablets or who have a condition that may interfere with absorption of the tablets.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo oral or IV formulation will be administered once daily for 14 weeks after transplant. The dose will be 240 mg once daily for participants receiving concomitant cyclosporin A and 480 mg once daily for participants not receiving cyclosporin A. Intravenous infusion will be administered only to participants who are unable to swallow tablets or who have a condition that may interfere with absorption of the tablets.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-8228</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>MK-8228</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Has documented seropositivity for CMV within 1 year before hematopoietic stem cell
             transplant (HSCT)

          -  Receiving first allogeneic HSCT (bone marrow, peripheral blood stem cell, or cord
             blood transplant)

          -  Female or male participant who is not of reproductive potential, or, if of
             reproductive potential, agrees to true abstinence or to use (or have their partner
             use) 2 acceptable methods of birth control from the time of consent through 90 days
             after the last dose of study drug

          -  Able to read, understand, and complete questionnaires and diaries

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Received a previous allogeneic HSCT (previous autologous HSCT is acceptable)

          -  History of CMV end-organ disease within 6 months before randomization

          -  Has evidence of CMV viremia from a central or local laboratory at any time before
             randomization

          -  Received the following within 7 days before screening or plans to receive during the
             study: ganciclovir, valganciclovir, foscarnet, acyclovir, valacyclovir, or
             famciclovir

          -  Received the following within 30 days before screening or plan to receive during the
             study: cidofovir, CMV hyper-immune globulin, any investigational CMV antiviral agent
             or biological therapy

          -  Has suspected or known hypersensitivity to ingredients of MK-8228 (letermovir)
             formulations

          -  Has severe hepatic insufficiency within 5 days before randomization

          -  Has end-stage renal impairment

          -  Has an uncontrolled infection on the day of randomization

          -  Requires mechanical ventilation or is hemodynamically unstable at the time of
             randomization

          -  Has documented positive results for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibody,
             hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody with detectable HCV ribonucleic acid, or hepatitis B
             surface antigen (HBsAg) within 90 days before randomization

          -  Has active solid tumor malignancies with the exception of localized basal cell or
             squamous cell skin cancer or the condition under treatment (for example, lymphoma)

          -  Is pregnant or expecting to conceive, is breastfeeding, or plans to breastfeed from
             the time of consent through 90 days after the last dose of study drug

          -  Is expecting to donate eggs or sperm from the time of consent through 90 days after
             the last dose of study drug

          -  Has participated in a study with an unapproved investigational compound (monoclonal
             antibodies are excepted) or device within 28 days of the first dose of study drug

          -  Has previously participated in a MK-8228 (letermovir) study

          -  Has, is, or is planning (during the study) to participate in any study involving
             administration of a CMV vaccine or another CMV investigational agent

          -  Is a user of recreational or illicit drugs or has a recent history (&lt;=1 year) of drug
             or alcohol abuse or dependence
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Toll Free Number</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-577-8839</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 12, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cytomegalovirus Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
