<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="154868">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02106091</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AFM11-101</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-001919-78</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02106091</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Study to Assess AFM11 in Patients With Relapsed and/or Refractory CD19 Positive B-cell NHL or B-precursor ALL</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pharmacodynamically-guided, Dose-escalation, Phase I Study to Assess the Safety of AFM11 (Recombinant Antibody Construct Against Human CD19 and CD3) in Patients With Relapsed and/or Refractory CD19 Positive B-cell NHL and Adult B-precursor ALL.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Affimed Therapeutics AG</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Affimed Therapeutics AG</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Paul-Ehrlich-Institut</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether AFM11 is safe and active in the treatment
      of relapsed and/or refractory Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma (NHL) and Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia
      (ALL).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      CD19 is present on B-cells from earliest recognizable B-lineage cells during development to
      B-cell blasts and is lost only upon maturation to plasma cells. Expression of CD19 on
      B-cells at various development stages makes it an ideal target to treat B-cell associated
      malignancies, like Non-Hodgkin's lymphoma and Acute lymphoblastic leukemia.The rationale for
      the use of AFM11 is based on its ability to bind to both malignant cells via its anti-CD19
      domain and to T-cells via its anti-CD3 domains. This results in the formation of the
      &quot;immunological synapse&quot; and the subsequent T-cell activation on leading to killing of
      malignant cells.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with serious and non-serious adverse events as a measure of safety and tolerability of AFM11.</measure>
    <time_frame>From administration of the first dose of study drug and through 30 days after the last dose, up to 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure occurence of adverse events until the Final Study Visit and monitor laboratory safety parameters at least once weekly. Assess immunogenicity of AFM11 at end of treatment cycle.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) or Optimal Biological Dose (OBD) of AFM11.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic profile of AFM11and immunological markers of AFM11 activity.</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to initial dose on Day 1 and at multiple time points during the 4 weeks of treatment until up to 30 days after the last dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Concentration of AFM11 in blood samples will measured at different time points during the 4 weeks of treatment and 30 days thereafter to determine concentration-time profiles. Immunological markers like lymphocytes, cytokine and complement levels in serum will be measured at different time points during the 4 weeks of treatment and 30 days thereafter to assess the level of activity resulting from administration of AFM11.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor Response.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and at week 8.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure tumor size and activity in FDG-PET and CT-scans.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Relapsed B-Cell Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory B-Cell Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Relapsed Adult B-Precursor Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Adult B-Precursor Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AFM11</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>IV (intravenous) infusion, dose escalation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AFM11</intervention_name>
    <description>Accelerated-titration dose-escalation with 1 patient per dose-level, followed by standard dose-escalation (3 + 3 design), Treatment duration: 4 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AFM11</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (NHL patients):

          -  Patients with CD19+, relapsed or refractory histologically (WHO  classification)
             confirmed follicular lymphoma, marginal zone lymphoma, lymphoplasmocytic lymphoma,
             mantle cell lymphoma, diffuse large B-cell lymphoma, mediastinal B-cell lymphoma, or
             transformed B-cell lymphomas.

          -  Patients with either indolent or aggressive NHL.

          -  Patients who relapsed or were refractory to the approved standard therapy, which must
             have included 1 treatment line with rituximab plus chemotherapy, and who are not
             candidates for bone marrow transplant with a curative intent.

          -  Measurable disease (at least 1 lesion ≥ 1.5 cm) documented by CT scan.

          -  Disease progression requiring therapy.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤ 2.

        Exclusion Criteria (NHL patients):

          -  Total number of B-cells (healthy and malignant combined) in the peripheral blood
             exceeds the upper physiological limit (as per institutional guidance) of total B-cell
             counts in healthy individuals.

          -  Autologous Hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT) within 3 months prior to start
             of AFM11 treatment.

          -  Prior allogeneic HSCT.

          -  Abnormal hematological laboratory values as defined below:

               1. Peripheral lymphocyte count &gt; 20 × 10^9/L

               2. Platelet count ≤ 75,000/µL

               3. Hemoglobin level ≤ 9 g/dL.

          -  Known or suspected central nervous system (CNS) involvement.

               1. History of or current relevant CNS pathology as epilepsy, seizure, paresis,
                  aphasia, apoplexia, severe brain injuries, cerebellar disease, organic brain
                  syndrome, psychosis.

               2. Evidence for presence of malignant disease, inflammatory lesions, and/or
                  vasculitis on cerebral MRI.

               3. Infiltration of the cerebrospinal fluid by malignant B-cells, confirmed  by
                  lumbar puncture.

          -  Cancer chemotherapy within 4 weeks prior to start of AFM11 treatment, or at least 4
             times the respective half-lives, whichever is longer.

          -  Radiotherapy within 4 weeks prior to start of AFM11 treatment.

          -  Therapy with antibody, or antibody constructs within 4 weeks prior to start of AFM11
             treatment, or at least 4 times the respective half-lives, whichever is longer.

          -  Prior treatment with alemtuzumab (Campath®) within 3 months prior to start of AFM11
             treatment.

          -  Treatment with any investigational agent within 4 weeks prior to start of AFM11
             treatment, or at least 4 times the respective half-life, whichever is longer.

          -  Abnormal renal or hepatic function as follows: aspartate aminotransferase (AST or
             serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase [SGOT]) and/or alanine aminotransferase (ALT
             or serum glutamic pyruvic transaminase [SGPT]) ≥ 2.5 × upper limit of normal (ULN);
             total bilirubin ≥ 1.5 × ULN; serum creatinine ≥ 2 × ULN; creatinine clearance &lt; 50
             mL/minute.

          -  History of malignancy other than B-cell lymphoma or B-precursor ALL within 5 years
             prior to study entry, with the exception of basal cell carcinoma of the skin or
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix.

          -  Uncontrolled infections; known bacteremia.

          -  Regular dose of corticosteroids during the 4 weeks prior to start of AFM11 treatment
             of this study or anticipated need of corticosteroids exceeding prednisone 20 mg/day
             or equivalent, or any other immunosuppressive therapy within 4 weeks prior to start
             of AFM11 treatment.

          -  Known infection with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or chronic infection with
             hepatitis B or hepatitis C virus.

          -  Pregnant or nursing women or women of childbearing potential not willing to use an
             effective form of contraception during participation in the study and at least 3
             months thereafter. Male patients not willing to ensure that during the study and at
             least 3 months thereafter no fathering takes place.

          -  Patients with B-cell chronic lymphocytic leukemia, small lymphocytic lymphoma, and
             Waldenström's macroglobulinemia.

        Inclusion Criteria (ALL patients):

          -  Patients with CD19+ B-precursor ALL relapsed after at least induction and
             consolidation or having refractory disease and who are not candidates for bone marrow
             transplant with a curative intent.

          -  More than 5% blasts in bone marrow.

          -  In patients with high tumor burden (e.g. more than 50% blasts, elevated lactate
             dehydrogenase [LDH]) greater than 2-fold ULN, or signs of extramedullar involvement),
             a pre-treatment with 10 mg/m² dexamethasone is required for up to 5 days.

          -  Patients with Philadelphia positive ALL who failed or were intolerant to therapy with
             at least 2 approved tyrosine kinase inhibitors.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status ≤ 2.

        Exclusion Criteria (ALL patients):

          -  Autologous HSCT within 3 months prior to start of AFM11 treatment.

          -  Active acute or chronic graft-versus-host disease. All graft-versus-host disease
             medication should be omitted for at least 4 weeks prior to start of AFM11 treatment.

          -  Allogeneic HSCT within 3 months prior to start of AFM11 treatment.

          -  No treatment with donor-lymphocyte infusions within 3 months of start of AFM11
             treatment.

          -  Abnormal hematological laboratory values as defined below:

               1. Platelet count ≤ 20,000/µL

               2. Hemoglobin level ≤ 9 g/dL.

          -  Known or suspected CNS involvement.

               1. History of or current relevant CNS pathology as epilepsy, seizure, paresis,
                  aphasia, apoplexia, severe brain injuries, cerebellar disease, organic brain
                  syndrome, psychosis.

               2. Evidence for presence of malignant disease, inflammatory lesions, and/or
                  vasculitis on cerebral MRI.

               3. Infiltration of the cerebrospinal fluid by malignant B-cells, confirmed by
                  lumbar puncture.

          -  Cancer chemotherapy within 4 weeks prior to start of AFM11 treatment, or at least 4
             times the respective half-lives, whichever is longer.

          -  Radiotherapy within 4 weeks prior to start of AFM11 treatment.

          -  Therapy with antibody, or antibody constructs within 4 weeks prior to start of AFM11
             treatment, or at least 4 times the respective half-lives, whichever is longer.

          -  Prior treatment with alemtuzumab (Campath®) within 3 months prior to start of AFM11
             treatment.

          -  Treatment with any investigational agent within 4 weeks prior to start of AFM11
             treatment, or at least 4 times the respective half-life, whichever is longer.

          -  Abnormal renal or hepatic function as follows: AST (or SGOT) and/or ALT (or SGPT) ≥
             2.5 × ULN; total bilirubin ≥ 1.5 × ULN; serum creatinine ≥ 2 × ULN; creatinine
             clearance &lt; 50 mL/minute.

          -  History of malignancy other than B-cell lymphoma or B-precursor ALL within 5 years
             prior to study entry, with the exception of basal cell carcinoma of the skin or
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix.

          -  Uncontrolled infections; known bacteremia.

          -  Regular dose of corticosteroids during the 4 weeks prior to start of AFM11 treatment
             of this study or anticipated need of corticosteroids exceeding prednisone 20 mg/day
             or equivalent, or any other immunosuppressive therapy within 4 weeks prior to study
             entry.

          -  Known infection with HIV or chronic infection with hepatitis B or hepatitis C virus.

          -  Pregnant or nursing women or women of childbearing potential not willing to use an
             effective form of contraception during participation in the study and at least 3
             months thereafter. Male patients not willing to ensure that during the study and at
             least 3 months thereafter no fathering takes place.

          -  Patients with B-cell chronic lymphocytic leukemia, small lymphocytic lymphoma, and
             Waldenström's macroglobulinemia.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gudrun Beck</last_name>
    <phone>+49 6221 65307</phone>
    <phone_ext>23</phone_ext>
    <email>g.beck@affimed.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kiel</city>
        <zip>24105</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wuerzburg</city>
        <zip>97080</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 1, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
