<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9834">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01793805</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NSABP MPR-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01793805</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>NSABP Patient Registry and Biospecimen Profiling Repository</brief_title>
  <official_title>NSABP Patient Registry and Biospecimen Profiling Repository</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project (NSABP)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project (NSABP)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a study to collect and analyze tissue specimens from metastatic colorectal cancer
      (mCRC) patients for the development of a molecularly profiled tissue repository for the
      primary purpose of maintaining a patient registry for future clinical trials based on the
      molecular profile of the tumors.  The main purpose of testing these tissue specimens is to
      identify genetic alterations or biomarkers associated with colorectal cancer such that if
      new agent(s) become available, particularly those that target these genetic
      alterations/biomarkers, participants may be offered the opportunity to take part in a
      National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project (NSABP) treatment protocol.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Tissue blocks from the primary tumor site and an uninvolved margin of resection (normal
      tissue) from consenting patients will be submitted and stored at the NSABP Division of
      Pathology, in the NSABP Biospecimen Profiling Repository.  Tissue specimens will be used to
      profile molecular characteristics, including actionable mutations most commonly identified
      in colorectal cancer.  Specimens may be further interrogated by other methods to discover
      additional mechanisms and targetable genetic alterations that may predict sensitivity or
      resistance to drug therapies.

      The repository will be populated, maintained, and analyzed through continuous patient
      recruitment.  Patient tumor specimens will be interrogated to characterize an individual's
      molecular profile.  At a future date for discovery purposes, the normal tissue may be
      profiled for comparison with the profile of the tumor tissue.  NSABP will hold a database
      with molecular profiles and relevant patient information.  As agents become available for
      clinical study, particularly those matching specified profiles, the treating physician will
      be contacted so that the patient may be offered participation in that trial via a separate
      consent process.  Each NSABP trial will have a defined molecular profile for entry which
      will be specific to the agent(s) under study.  The MPR-1 patient registry and tissue
      repository and all treatment protocols associated with MPR-1 are being developed as part of
      the NSABP Oncology-Genome Assessment Guided Medicine (N-GAMe) Program.

      This registry and repository platform uses a translational science approach for more
      personalized therapy for patients with mCRC.  This analysis provides an individual molecular
      profile in an attempt to direct each patient's treatment based on the pattern of genetic
      alterations.  These efforts also may aid in the discovery of with or without new gene
      targets for future drug development.

      Approximately 1000-2000 tumor (with or without) normal tissue specimens from living mCRC
      patients will be collected, stored, and analyzed as part of this biospecimen repository.  It
      is anticipated that 200-400 participants will be registered within the first year.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>2 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To characterize common genetic/molecular profiles associated with colorectal cancer (CRC)</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of study through study completion at approximately 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is a living registry with no end date provided continued funding.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To identify subpopulations of registry patients on the basis of their molecular profiles that may be eligible for participation in available NSABP clinical trials involving novel agents</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of study through study completion at approximately 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To conduct further analysis of tumor samples for the discovery of new potential targets and mechanisms of drug resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of study through study completion at approximately 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metastatic Colorectal Cancer Patients</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Tissue blocks from the primary tumor site and an uninvolved margin of resection (normal
      tissue).
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Metastatic colorectal cancer patients.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The patient must have a diagnosis of metastatic colorectal adenocarcinoma.

          -  Representative formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tissue blocks from the primary
             colorectal tumor surgery with corresponding pathology report must be available for
             release by the local pathology department (an adequate amount of tumor tissue is
             required for analysis).  If available for release, a separate FFPE tissue block from
             an uninvolved margin of colorectal resection (normal tissue) is also requested.

          -  The patient must have a life-expectancy of  greater than or equal to 6 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of non-CRC malignancy unless the patient is considered by the physician to be
             disease-free and at low risk for recurrence.

          -  Known comorbid medical conditions that would preclude investigational treatment
             (e.g., active hepatitis B or C; symptomatic cardiac disease; renal insufficiency;
             bone marrow impairment).

          -  Psychiatric or addictive disorders or other conditions that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would preclude investigational treatment.

          -  Colonoscopy biopsies or diagnostic core biopsy procedures without surgery or
             resection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Norman Wolmark, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NSABP Foundation, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Diana Gosik, RN, BS</last_name>
    <phone>412-339-5333</phone>
    <email>diana.gosik@nsabp.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32610</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center Orlando</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32806</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Luke's Mountain States Tumor Institute - Boise</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boise</city>
        <state>Idaho</state>
        <zip>83712</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
