<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="110942">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01874665</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AP24534-12-202</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01874665</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 2 Trial of Ponatinib in Patients With Metastatic and/or Unresectable Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 2 Trial of Ponatinib in Patients With Metastatic and/or Unresectable Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor Following Failure of Prior Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ariad Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ariad Pharmaceuticals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy and safety of ponatinib in patients
      with metastatic and/or unresectable gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST) following failure
      of prior tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a non-randomized, open label, multi-center phase 2 study to evaluate the efficacy
      and safety of ponatinib in patients with metastatic and/or unresectable GIST after failure
      of prior TKI therapy.  Patients whose tumors have an activating mutation in exon 11 of
      cellular KIT (KIT) will be enrolled into Cohort A. Patients whose tumors have other
      activating mutations will be enrolled into in Cohort B.

      The primary objective is to assess clinical benefit in patients with KIT exon 11-mutant GIST
      (Cohort A) defined as clinical benefit rate (CBR), which is the composite of complete
      response (CR), partial response (PR) and stable disease (SD) lasting ≥16 weeks per modified
      response evaluation criteria in solid tumors (RECIST 1.1 [Demetri et al., 2012]) as a
      measure of disease control.  The secondary objective is to assess clinical benefit in
      patients with GIST that lacks an activating KIT exon 11 mutation (Cohort B) and in the total
      patient population.  The efficacy assessments are tumor response using Response Criteria in
      Solid Tumors (RECIST) Version 1.1, modified for GIST and assessment of progression-free
      survival (PFS) and overall survival (OS). The safety assessments include routine physical
      and laboratory evaluations, electrocardiograms (ECGs), echocardiograms (ECHOs), and adverse
      event (AE) monitoring.  Other assessments include optional 18F fluorodeoxyglucose positron
      emission tomography (FDG-PET); optional pre- and post-treatment tumor biopsy for
      pharmacodynamic studies; and pharmacokinetics (PK).  It is estimated that accrual will be
      complete within 1 year; the total estimated duration of the study is 3 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Benefit Rate (CBR)</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks after first dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess clinical benefit rate in patients with KIT exon 11-mutant GIST.  Defined as the composite of complete response (CR), partial response (PR), and stable disease (SD) lasting ≥16 weeks per modified RECIST 1.1 as a measure of disease control</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Benefit Rate (CBR)</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks after first dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess clinical benefit rate in patients with GIST that lacks KIT exon 11 mutations (Cohort B) and in the total patient population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment until the end of the study or disease progression or death due to any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as the duration of time from start of study drug administration to time of objective disease progression or death due to any cause, whichever may come first. To assess PFS in each cohort and in the total patient population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment until discontinuation or the end of the study, whichever came first, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as the composite of CR and PR. To assess objective response rate (ORR) in each cohort and in the total patient population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment until the end of the study or death, whichever came first, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as the interval between enrollment and death due to any cause, censored at the last contact date. To assess OS in each cohort and in the total patient population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment until the End-of-Treatment, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured by routine physical and laboratory evaluations, ECG, ECHO, and AE monitoring. To evaluate the safety and tolerability of ponatinib in the total patient population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters of steady-state plasma concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 month after the start of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PK samples will be taken to assess limited elements of PK in the total patient population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>GIST</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ponatinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with KIT exon 11-mutant GIST (Cohort A) and patients with GIST that lack KIT exon 11 mutations (Cohort B)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ponatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>45 mg tablet, taken orally once-daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>ponatinib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AP24534</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. GIST with failure of prior TKI therapy defined as:

               1. Histologically confirmed metastatic and/or unresectable GIST after experiencing
                  failure of prior treatment with imatinib, sunitinib, and regorafenib. If prior
                  TKI treatment was neoadjuvant therapy, then relapse must have occurred during
                  the neoadjuvant therapy in order to consider it failed therapy

               2. Patients in Cohort A must have evidence of activation mutations of exon 11 of
                  KIT in their tumors.  Demonstration of an exon 11 mutation may be based on prior
                  assessment or on evaluation of a tumor sample after enrollment in this study.
                  Patients in Cohort B must have GIST that lacks activating mutations in KIT exon
                  11, but may have evidence of another activating mutation such as in KIT exon 9
                  or PDGFR-α.  Patients may be enrolled in the study prior to determination of
                  appropriate cohort (as long as both cohorts are open for enrollment).

          2. Measurable disease per modified RECIST 1.1.  A lesion in a previously irradiated area
             is eligible to be considered as measurable disease as long as there is objective
             evidence of progression of the lesion prior to study enrollment

          3. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status of 0, 1, or 2

          4. Adequate hepatic function as defined by the following criteria:

               1. Total serum bilirubin ≤1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN), unless due to
                  Gilbert's syndrome

               2. ALT ≤2.5×ULN or ≤5.0xULN if liver metastases are present

               3. AST ≤2.5×ULN or ≤5.0xULN if liver metastases are present

          5. Adequate renal function as defined by the following criterion:

             a. Serum creatinine &lt;1.5×ULN

          6. Adequate pancreatic function as defined by the following criterion:

             a. Serum lipase and amylase ≤1.5×ULN

          7. Fully recovered (≤Grade 1 or returned to baseline or deemed irreversible) from the
             acute effects of prior cancer therapy before initiation of study drug

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Major surgery within 28 days prior to initiating therapy

          2. History of bleeding disorder

          3. History of acute pancreatitis within 1 year of study or history of chronic
             pancreatitis

          4. History of alcohol abuse

          5. Uncontrolled hypertriglyceridemia (triglycerides &gt;450 mg/dL)

          6. Clinically significant, uncontrolled, or active cardiovascular disease, specifically
             including, but not restricted to:

               1. Any history of myocardial infarction (MI)

               2. Any history of unstable angina

               3. Congestive heart failure within 6 months prior to enrollment, or LVEF less than
                  lower limit of normal per local institutional standards within 6 months prior
                  enrollment

               4. History of clinically significant (as determined by the treating physician)
                  atrial arrhythmia

               5. Any history of ventricular arrhythmia

               6. Any history of cerebrovascular accident or transient ischemic attack (TIA)

               7. Any history of peripheral vascular infarction, including visceral infarction; or
                  any revascularization procedure of any vasculature, including the placement of a
                  stent

               8. Venous thromboembolism including deep venous thrombosis (DVT) or pulmonary
                  embolism within 6 months prior to enrollment

          7. Uncontrolled hypertension (diastolic blood pressure &gt;90 mm Hg; systolic &gt;140 mm Hg).
             Patients with hypertension should be under treatment on study entry to effect blood
             pressure control

          8. Taking medications with a known risk of Torsades de Pointes

          9. Taking any medications or herbal supplements that are known to be strong inhibitors
             of CYP3A4 within at least 14 days before the first dose of ponatinib

         10. Ongoing or active infection.  This includes, but is not limited to, the requirement
             for intravenous antibiotics

         11. Known history of human immunodeficiency virus.  Testing is not required in the
             absence of prior documentation or known history

         12. Pregnant or breastfeeding

         13. Malabsorption syndrome or other gastrointestinal illness that could affect oral
             absorption of study drugs

         14. Individuals with a history of a different malignancy, other than cervical cancer in
             situ, basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, are ineligible, except if
             they have been disease-free for at least 5 years, and are deemed by the investigator
             to be at low risk for recurrence of that malignancy OR if the other primary
             malignancy is neither currently clinically significant nor requiring active
             intervention.

         15. Use of any approved TKIs or investigational agents within 2 weeks or 6 half-lives of
             the agent, whichever is longer, prior to receiving study drug

         16. Any condition or illness that, in the opinion of the investigator, would compromise
             patient safety or interfere with the evaluation of the drug
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Frank G. Haluska, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>617-494-0400</phone>
    <email>frank.haluska@ariad.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christopher D. Turner, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-494-0400</phone>
    <email>christopher.turner@ariad.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Site #008</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital, Site #047</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health &amp; Sciences University, Site #048</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fox Chase Cancer Center, Site #012</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Demetri GD, Reichardt P, Kang YK, Blay JY, Rutkowski P, Gelderblom H, Hohenberger P, Leahy M, von Mehren M, Joensuu H, Badalamenti G, Blackstein M, Le Cesne A, Schöffski P, Maki RG, Bauer S, Nguyen BB, Xu J, Nishida T, Chung J, Kappeler C, Kuss I, Laurent D, Casali PG; GRID study investigators. Efficacy and safety of regorafenib for advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumours after failure of imatinib and sunitinib (GRID): an international, multicentre, randomised, placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial. Lancet. 2013 Jan 26;381(9863):295-302. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)61857-1. Epub 2012 Nov 22.</citation>
    <PMID>23177515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gastrointestinal Neoplasms</keyword>
  <keyword>Gastrointestinal stromal tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>mesenchymal tumor</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
