<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="55383">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01972932</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHUM 2014-5056</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01972932</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Bio-K+® in the Reduction of the Risk of Clostridium Difficile Infection and Antibiotic Associated Diarrhea</brief_title>
  <official_title>Protocol CHUM 2014-5056: A Randomized, Double Blinded Placebo Controlled Study to Evaluate the Efficacy of Bio-K+® in the Reduction of the Risk of Clostridium Difficile Infection and Antibiotic Associated Diarrhea in Hospitalized Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bio-K Plus International Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centre hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal (CHUM)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bio-K Plus International Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Antibiotic-associated diarrhea (AAD) and particularly Clostridium difficile-Infection (CDI)
      are the most common causes of healthcare associated infectious diarrhea. In light of the
      results obtained in a limited number of randomized clinical trials in subjects with AAD and
      CDI in comparison with the widespread occurrence of these diseases, it is felt that the
      addition of a well-controlled clinical trial in a western environment would add value to
      support the use of a specific probiotic to counteract these diseases.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the incidence of Clostridium Difficile infection</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary objective of this study is evaluate the incidence risk ratio of CDI in hospitalized subjects treated with systemic antibiotics, taking oral administration of Bio-K+® in comparison with a placebo. Risk will be calculated for the period of antibiotic treatment plus 65 days.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the incidence of antibiotic associated diarrhea</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the incidence of AAD
To evaluate the incidence of RCDI
To determine the time to occurrence of the first symptoms (first liquid stool) of AAD or CDI -
To evaluate the impact on the duration of hospitalization
To evaluate the number of emergency room visits and re-hospitalizations for AAD or CDI
To determine the mean costs for the initial hospitalization
To evaluate the safety profile of Bio-K+®</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">800</enrollment>
  <condition>Clostridium Difficile Infection</condition>
  <condition>Antibiotic Associated Diarrhea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2 capsules orally (or via nasogastric tube)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo 2 capsules orally (or via nasogastric tube) once per day starting randomization until five days after the discontinuation of the antibiotic.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bio K+® 2 capsules orally (or via nasogastric tube)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects who meet all inclusion/exclusion criteria will be randomized to one of the following study arms: Bio K+® 2 capsules orally (or via nasogastric tube) once per day starting at randomization until five days after the discontinuation of the antibiotic. Placebo 2 capsules orally (or via nasogastric tube) once per day starting randomization until five days after the discontinuation of the antibiotic.
Assignment to the study arms will be based on a computer-generated randomization schedule prepared by a statistician before the start of the study. Subjects will be randomized in blocks of six (3 in each group), stratified by service (internal medicine, pneumology, cardiac surgery and vascular surgery). Blocks will be independent for each Hospital to ensure optimal randomization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bio-K®</intervention_name>
    <description>2 ARMS STUDY
Bio-K+® 2 capsules orally (or via nasogastric tube) once per day starting at randomization until five days after the discontinuation of the antibiotic.
Placebo 2 capsules orally (or via nasogastric tube) once per day starting randomization until five days after the discontinuation of the antibiotic.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bio K+® 2 capsules orally (or via nasogastric tube)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bio-K®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

        Only subjects who meet the following inclusion criteria will be eligible to participate in
        the study:

          -  Are at least 18 years old

          -  Able to tolerate food intake Antibiotic treatment started less than 48hrs from
             admission into the study

          -  Have an expected hospitalization period of at least three days (including subject‟s
             stay in the emergency room)

          -  Speak and understand English and/or French.

          -  Have an expected survival greater than 60 days

          -  Agree to refrain from taking probiotic products (besides the study drug) during the
             study period Have given informed consent In addition, women of child bearing capacity
             who are not pregnant at the moment of screening (pregnancy test done on-site) and
             agree to use an acceptable form of birth control for the duration of the study (e.g.
             Condom, oral contraceptives, etc.) are allowed to participate.

        Exclusion Criteria

        Subjects who meet any of the following exclusion criteria will not be eligible to
        participate in the study:

          -  Have been diagnosed with CDI in previous sixty days

          -  Have taken Streptomycin, oral Vancomycin, or Metronidazole in the last 4 weeks,
             excluding as part of the treatment regimen triggering their inclusion into the study.

          -  Are currently suffering from any health condition causing immunosuppression
             (including haematological malignancies, lymphoma, AIDS, transplant, and hemodialysis)

          -  Have received more than 10 mg of prednisone per day for at least 1 month within 3
             months prior to the participation to the study.

          -  Have active diarrhea (three or more liquid stools per 24 hour period) or
             non-controlled intestinal disease/colitis such as Crohn's disease, ulcerative colitis
             or caeliac disease Have stomas, are ostomized or are parenteral nutrition users Have
             already been randomized to one arm of this study

          -  Are known to have shown a previous reaction, including anaphylaxis, to any substance
             in the composition of the study products (i.e. Non-medicinal ingredients: Cellulose,
             hypromellose, medium chain triglycerides, sodium alginate, ascorbic acid, magnesium
             stearate (vegetal source), silicon dioxide and titanium dioxide

          -  Where receiving systemic antibiotics on admission to the hospital or who have been
             treated with antibiotics over the past two weeks Have lactose intolerance or milk
             allergy

          -  Have difficulties giving informed consent because of chronic mental disease, dementia

          -  Are not likely to comply with study requirements (provide stool for screening if
             diarrhea or answer to the follow up questionnaires)

          -  Have been known to use illicit drugs in the last two years. Have participated in
             another clinical study in the last 30 days

          -  Female subjects that are pregnant, or who intend to become pregnant or are lactating
             during the study period

          -  Female subjects of child bearing potential not currently using adequate contraception
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mikhael Laskine, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre Hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Serge Carriere, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Bio-K+International Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mikhael Laskine, MD</last_name>
      <phone>514 890 8000</phone>
      <phone_ext>1462</phone_ext>
      <email>laskine1@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Madeleine Durand, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 13, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bio-K+®</keyword>
  <keyword>Placebo</keyword>
  <keyword>AAD</keyword>
  <keyword>CDI</keyword>
  <keyword>hospitalized subjects</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Clostridium Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibiotics, Antitubercular</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
