<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="146269">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01869686</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20120351</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01869686</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate the Concentration of Denosumab in Seminal Fluid in Healthy Men After a Single Subcutaneous Dose</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label Study to Evaluate the Concentration of Denosumab in Seminal Fluid After a Single Subcutaneous Injection in Healthy Men</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Amgen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 1b, open-label, single dose study in healthy male subjects. Approximately 12
      healthy male subjects will receive a subcutaneous injection of denosumab on Day 1. Subjects
      will be followed by a 105 day treatment-free follow-up period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Denosumab concentrations in seminal fluid</measure>
    <time_frame>16 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Denosumab concentrations in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>16 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Denosumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>single subcutaneous injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Denosumab</intervention_name>
    <description>60 mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Denosumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Prolia (R)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subject has provided informed consent; Healthy male between ≥40 to ≤ 65 years of age
        (inclusive) at the time of enrollment; Subject must be willing and able to produce a semen
        sample on seven separate study visits; Subject must be willing to refrain from ejaculation
        for a 48 hour period prior to each sample collection;

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Any condition or drug therapy that might interfere with the subjects ability to ejaculate
        and produce a semen sample; Clinically significant abnormality during the screening
        physical examination, ECG, or laboratory evaluation; Known history of blood in urine or
        semen; Osteonecrosis of the jaw (ONJ) or risk factors for ONJ such as invasive dental
        procedures (eg, tooth extraction, dental implants, oral surgery in the past 6 months),
        poor oral hygiene, periodontal and/or pre-existing dental disease; Recent tooth extraction
        (within 6 months of screening visit); Evidence of hypocalcemia at screening; Known vitamin
        D deficiency; Malignancy (except non-melanoma skin cancers) within the last 5 years;
        Positive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) at screening or known diagnosis of AIDS;
        Positive Hepatitis B Surface Antigen (HepBsAg) (indicative of chronic Hepatitis B) or
        detectable Hepatitis C virus Ribonucleic acid (RNA) by Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) at
        screening (indicative of active Hepatitis C - screening is generally done by Hepatitis C
        Antibody (HepCAb), followed by Hepatitis C virus RNA by PCR if HepCAb is positive);
        History of hypersensitivity or allergic reaction to mammalian cell derived drug products
        or sensitivity to any of the products or components to be administered during dosing;
        Known intolerance to calcium or vitamin D supplements; Subject previously has entered this
        study or has been previously exposed to denosumab in the past 12 months; Has donated or
        lost ≥ 400 mL of blood or plasma within 8 weeks prior to screening; Positive urine screen
        for alcohol and/or potential drugs of abuse at screening unless medication is prescribed
        by a physician and approved by the Investigator and Amgen; Known alcohol abuse or use of
        illicit drugs within 12 months of enrollment; Subject is unwilling or unable to limit
        alcohol consumption throughout the course of the study. Alcohol is prohibited 24 hours
        prior to screening and administration of investigational product. Alcohol is limited to no
        more than 2 drinks per day for the duration of the study; where a standard drink is
        equivalent to 12 ounces of regular beer, 8-9 ounces of malt liquor, 5 ounces of wine, or
        1.5 ounces of 80 proof distilled spirits; Currently receiving treatment in another
        investigational device or drug study, or less than 30 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is
        longer) since ending treatment on another investigational device or drug study(s). Other
        investigational procedures while participating in this study are excluded; Use of any
        non-Amgen approved over-the-counter or prescription medications, within the 14 days or 5
        half-lives (whichever is longer), prior to receiving the dose of denosumab. Acetaminophen
        (up to 2 g per day) for analgesia and hormone replacement therapy (eg, androgen, thyroid)
        will be allowed. Other medications may be approved following review by the Principal
        Investigator and the Amgen Medical Monitor. Written documentation of this review and Amgen
        acknowledgement is required for subject participation; Subject likely to not be available
        to complete all protocol-required study visits or procedures, and/or to comply with all
        required study procedures to the best of the subject and Investigator's knowledge; Subject
        has any kind of disorder that, in the opinion of the Investigator, may compromise the
        ability of the subject to give written informed consent and/or to comply with all required
        study procedures; History or evidence of any other clinically significant disorder,
        condition or disease that, in the opinion of the Investigator or Amgen physician, if
        consulted, would pose a risk to subject safety or interfere with the study evaluation,
        procedures or completion
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Amgen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Overland Park</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.amgentrials.com</url>
    <description>AmgenTrials clinical trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 31, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
