<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="136041">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01733680</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>320969</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01733680</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Amiloride Hydrochloride as an Effective Treatment for ADHD</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>State University of New York - Upstate Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Upstate Medical University Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>State University of New York - Upstate Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators are proposing to test a medication derived from our prior studies of the
      gene SLC9A9.  This one gene makes NHE proteins that control how we learn and remember items,
      which is impaired in ADHD and may cause an inability to  plan, prioritize,
      self-monitor,inihibit, initiate, self-correct, or control one's behavior. The investigators
      now propose to investigate the therapeutic utility of an NHE inhibitor, amiloride
      hydrochloride, for the treatment of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) in
      medication-naïve adults with ADHD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Our specific aims and hypotheses are as follows:

      Primary Aim:  Assess the efficacy and adverse effects of amiloride in medication naive ADHD
      adults in a placebo controlled study. Hypothesis 1: Amiloride will reduce scores on our
      primary outcome measure, the Adult Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder Investigator
      Symptom Rating Scale (AISRS) and on our secondary outcome, the ADHD specific Clinical Global
      Impressions (CGI) improvement scale.  Hypothesis 2: Amiloride will be well tolerated and
      will have few side effects in adults with ADHD.

      Exploratory Aim 2: Assess effects of amiloride on ADHD-associated clinical features. We will
      also assess, in an exploratory manner, the effect of amiloride on two clinical features that
      are not well treated by current ADHD medications: deficits in emotional self-regulation
      (DESR) and executive function deficit (EFD).  Hypothesis 3 predicts that amiloride treatment
      will reduce symptoms of DESR and of EFD.

      We will recruit 40 adults who are diagnosed with ADHD in a double blind placebo controlled
      study. 20 subjects will receive amiloride hydrochloride and 20 subjects will receive placebo
      for 8 weeks. Participation in the study requires subjects to meet with the physician for a
      screening visit, baseline visit and 8 additional weekly visits.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in ADHD symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Improvement in ADHD symptoms measured by the AISRS and the CGI scales.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in executive function and emotional self-regulation.</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measuring improvement in executive function and emotional self-regulation on the  Behavior Rating Inventory of Executive Function - Adult Version</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>ADHD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Amiloride</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug: Subjects will take 5mg qd Amiloride for 2 weeks, 10mg qd Amiloride for 3 weeks, 15 mg qd Amiloride for 3 weeks.
Behavioral: Each week subjects will complete the AISRS, BRIEF-A, and CGI.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug: Subjects will take placebo for 8 weeks Behavioral: Each week subjects will complete questionnaires: AISRS, BRIEF-A, and CGI</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>amiloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will take either amiloride hydrochloride or placebo for 8 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Amiloride</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>amiloride</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Behavioral</intervention_name>
    <description>Each week of the study, subjects will complete the AISRS, BRIEF-A, and CGI to measure symptom improvement</description>
    <arm_group_label>Amiloride</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ADHD symptoms, executive function, emotional self-regulation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Medication naïve male or female adults ages 18-45 years.

          2. A diagnosis of DSM-IV  ADHD combined type based on clinical assessment by the study
             psychiatrist using the Conners Adult ADHD Diagnostic Interview;

          3. proficiency in English;

          4. A baseline score of 24 or more on the AISRS;

          5. ability to swallow pills;

          6. ability to report reliably, understand the nature of the study and sign an informed
             consent document as determined by the study psychiatrist

        Exclusion Criteria:

        We will exclude potential participants who:

          1. have had pharmacologic treatment for ADHD in the past year;

          2. are pregnant or nursing;

          3. are Investigators or their immediate family (spouse, parent, child, grandparent, or
             grandchild);

          4. have any serious, unstable medical illness including hepatic, renal,
             gastroenterological, respiratory, cardiovascular (including ischemic heart disease),
             endocrinologic, neurologic, immunologic, or hematologic disease;

          5. have severe allergies or multiple adverse drug reactions;

          6. have a current or past history of seizures;

          7. meet current DSM-IV criteria for anxiety or depression or illicit substance abuse in
             prior six months (these exclusions are feasible because, although the lifetime
             comorbidity of ADHD with these disorders is high, we and others have shown that the
             presence of these disorders at the time of ascertainment for adult ADHD studies is
             less than 10%);

          8. are judged by the study psychiatrist to be at serious suicidal risk.

          9. have current or past diagnoses of schizophrenia or bipolar disorder;

         10. have a history of hypersensitivity to amiloride or drug class members;

         11. have a history of hyperkalemia, diabetes mellitus, renal disease or anuria;

         12. have renal impairment Cr &gt; 1.5; or

         13. are taking potassium supplements, aldosterone antagonists, tacrolimus or ACE
             inhibitors.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen V Faraone, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>SUNY Upstate Medical Unversity</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Prashant Kaul, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Medical Center at Syracuse</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Prashant Kaul, MD</last_name>
    <phone>315-425-4400 x53940</phone>
    <email>Prashant.kaul@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stephen V Faraone, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>315-464-3113</phone>
    <email>sfaraone@childpsychresearch.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SUNY Upstate Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Syracuse</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>13210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen V Faraone, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Prashant Kaul, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 26, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 20, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ADHD</keyword>
  <keyword>executive function</keyword>
  <keyword>emotional self-regulation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Amiloride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
