<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="142743">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01660984</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>120178</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12-C-0178</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01660984</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Natural History Study of Children and Young Adults With Medullary Thyroid Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Longitudinal Assessment and Natural History Study of Children and Young Adults With Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Medullary thyroid cancer (MTC) is a rare cancer of the thyroid gland. In children and
      young adults, it is often part of a condition called Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia 2 (MEN2).
      MEN2 is usually caused by a genetic mutation, and it can cause a number of problems in
      addition to MTC. These problems include adrenal gland tumors, hormone changes, and problems
      with the bones and other organs. Not much is known about how MTC develops over time,
      especially in people with MEN2. Researchers want to study MTC in children and young adults
      and see how it affects their growth and development.

      Objectives:

      - To study how medullary thyroid cancer affects children and young adults over time.

      Eligibility:

      - Children and young adults younger than 25 years of age who have medullary thyroid cancer.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a brief physical exam and medical history. Blood and
           tissue samples will be collected to see whether participants have the MEN2 genetic
           mutation.

        -  Treatment will not be provided as part of this study. However, participants will be
           receiving standard care for MTC. They may be eligible for other clinical trials at the
           National Institutes of Health.

        -  Participants will have regular study visits every 6 to 12 months to evaluate their MTC
           and any treatment. Blood tests, imaging studies, and other tests may be performed as
           needed to monitor the disease.

        -  Participants and their parents/guardians will also complete questionnaires about their
           health and emotions during the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma (MTC) is a calcitonin producing tumor arising from the
           parafollicular C cells of thyroid. In children and young adults, MTC is usually seen in
           association with Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia (MEN) 2A and 2B, which are rare cancer
           syndromes resulting from germline mutations of Rearranged during Transfection (RET)
           proto-oncogene. MTC develops in virtually all patients with MEN 2, and is the leading
           cause of death in these patients. Patients with MEN 2 may have other characteristic
           manifestations such as pheochromocytoma and hyperparathyroidism in MEN 2A and
           pheochromocytoma, ganglioneuromatosis, and skeletal deformities in MEN 2B.

        -  Complete surgical resection is the only current curative treatment for MTC, and the
           tumor is unresponsive to standard chemotherapy and conventional doses of radiation
           therapy.  However, more than half the patients present with advanced or metastatic
           disease and cannot be cured surgically. Novel agents are currently under investigation
           for treatment of MTC, and vandetanib, an oral RET and receptor tyrosine kinase (RTK)
           inhibitor was recently approved by the FDA for adults with advanced or metastatic MTC.
           Vandetanib also has activity in children with hereditary MTC.

        -  However, complete responses to RTKs have not been observed, and some patients develop
           resistance to the treatment with RET and RTK inhibitors or have primary refractory
           disease.  The natural history of MTC, particularly in patients with MEN 2, the
           molecular pathways involved in tumorigenesis, and the development of resistance to
           targeted therapies are not well understood.

      Objectives:

      -The overall objective of this longitudinal study is to develop a better understanding of
      the biology and natural history of MTC, particularly in children and young adults with MEN
      2A and 2B, as well as study non-tumor manifestations of MEN 2. This will hopefully allow for
      developing more effective treatment interventions for tumor and non-tumor related
      manifestations, and more sensitive endpoints in clinical trials.

      Eligibility:

        -  Patients less than or equal to 25 years of age, must have histologically or
           cytologically confirmed MTC, confirmed by the Laboratory of Pathology, NCI

        -  Participants may be undergoing standard care or receiving treatment on a clinical trial
           while participating in this study.

      Design:

      This study will allow for longitudinal evaluations of MTC and non-tumor related
      manifestations of MEN 2A and 2B in children and young adults. Evaluations will consist of
      the following (summarized):

        1. Clinical and radiological evaluations every 6     12 months

        2. Detailed pathologic and molecular analysis of tumor specimens will be performed,
           including immunohistochemistry (IHC), comparative genomic hybridization (CGH), and
           genome sequencing.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>study growth rate of primary and metastatic tumor lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Study molecular pathways altered in MTC</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigate the psychosocial experiences</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the role of FDG PET CT/MRI in the detection and monitoring</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Describe the non-tumor related manifestations of MEN 2</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Medullary Thyroid Carcer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed MTC, confirmed by the
             Laboratory of Pathology, NCI

          -  Disease status: Patients must have evidence of active MTC as documented by either
             elevated plasma biomarkers (CEA and/or calcitonin), or presence of evaluable or
             measurable disease.

          -  Age: less than or equal to 25 years of age

          -  Performance Status: Ability to travel to the NIH and to undergo evaluations to be
             performed on this protocol.

          -  Informed Consent: All patients or their legal guardians (if the patients is&lt; 18 years
             old) must sign an IRB-approved document of informed consent to demonstrate their
             understanding of the investigational nature and the risks of this study before any
             protocol-related studies are performed. When appropriate, pediatric subjects will be
             included in all discussions.

          -  Prior and current therapy: For the purpose of this study subjects who have not
             previously received medical or surgical treatment, patients, who have previously
             received medical or surgical treatment, and subjects who are currently receiving
             medical treatment and or radiation for a MEN 2 related manifestations will be
             eligible. Prior and current treatment for MEN 2 related manifestations will be
             recorded at trial entry and throughout the study.

          -  Patients must have a primary care provider (for example a primary oncologist or
             endocrinologist) who can provide and coordinate the medical care for the patient

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  In the opinion of the investigator the patient is not able to return for follow-up
             visits or obtain required follow-up studies.

          -  Individuals who are pregnant or breast feeding or who become pregnant while enrolled
             on this trial will not be excluded from participation, but will not undergo
             radiographic evaluations or other studies for research purposes, which might
             negatively impact on the pregnancy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brigitte C Widemann, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Claudia P Derse-Anthony</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-0199</phone>
    <email>derseanthonycp@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Brigitte C Widemann, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-7387</phone>
    <email>widemanb@pbmac.nci.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>888-624-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2012-C-0178.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cakir M, Grossman AB. Medullary thyroid cancer: molecular biology and novel molecular therapies. Neuroendocrinology. 2009;90(4):323-48. Epub 2009 May 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19468197</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kebebew E, Ituarte PH, Siperstein AE, Duh QY, Clark OH. Medullary thyroid carcinoma: clinical characteristics, treatment, prognostic factors, and a comparison of staging systems. Cancer. 2000 Mar 1;88(5):1139-48.</citation>
    <PMID>10699905</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wells SA Jr, Santoro M. Targeting the RET pathway in thyroid cancer. Clin Cancer Res. 2009 Dec 1;15(23):7119-23. Epub 2009 Nov 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19934298</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 7, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>Thyroid Tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia 2</keyword>
  <keyword>Pheochromocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>RET Mutations</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Thyroid Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
