<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="153007">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01859390</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-1557</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>AQUADEK12K1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01859390</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of an Antioxidant-Enriched Multivitamin Supplement on Inflammation and Oxidative Stress in Cystic Fibrosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>AquADEKs-2</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multi-Center, Randomized, Controlled, Double-Blind Study of the Effects of an Antioxidant-Enriched Multivitamin Supplement on Inflammation and Oxidative Stress in Cystic Fibrosis Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cystic Fibrosis Foundation Therapeutics Incorporated</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Yasoo Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study will be to evaluate the effects of a modified formulation of
      AquADEKs (AquADEKs-2) on markers of inflammation, antioxidant levels and oxidative stress.

      Cystic Fibrosis (CF) is a disease that affects the organs in the body such as the lungs.
      Some of the damage to the lungs of CF patients may be caused by something called
      oxidant/antioxidant imbalance and oxidative stress.

      Oxidation in the body is kind of what happens to an apple when it turns brown after being
      cut. And, just as a squeeze of lemon juice stops the oxidation of an apple, antioxidants can
      stop the rusting (or damage) inside our bodies by unstable oxygen molecules called free
      radicals. Free radicals can help fight off bacteria and viruses but too many of them do
      damage instead.  Our bodies need antioxidants to keep things in balance so we have the right
      amount of free radicals.

      Many CF patients also have trouble digesting food and absorbing nutrients like vitamins.
      Many of the vitamins we rely on are antioxidants, like vitamins A, D, E, K and
      beta-carotene. In some people with CF, even though they take multivitamins and pancreatic
      enzymes, they still have low amounts of antioxidants. We are looking to see if taking more
      vitamins and antioxidants will help CF patients.

      AquADEKs-2 is an investigational new drug (a drug that has not received approval by the Food
      and Drug Administration [FDA]). This research study is being done with the AquADEKs-2
      compared to a control multivitamin. The study drug, AquADEKs-2 contains standard amounts of
      fat-soluble vitamins (A, D, E, K)that are contained in typical CF multivitamin supplements
      plus several antioxidants including beta-carotene, mixed tocopherols (different forms of
      vitamin E), coenzyme Q10 (CoQ10), mixed carotenoids (lutein, lycopene and zeaxanthin), and
      the minerals zinc and selenium. The control multivitamin contains standard amounts of
      vitamins A, B, D, E, and K without additional antioxidant supplementation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Sputum Myeloperoxidase (MPO) Level</measure>
    <time_frame>Between Baseline (Visit 2) and Week 16 (Visit 4)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary outcome in the study is the change in the sputum levels of MPO between baseline and week 16.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>22 weeks for each participant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Incidence of adverse events including clinically significant changes in clinical safety lab values</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Systemic Antioxidant Levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Between baseline (Visit 2) and Weeks 4 and 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in plasma levels of carotenoids (β-carotene, lutein, zeaxanthin and lycopene), CoQ10, γ-tocopherol, and erythrocyte glutathione peroxidase activity between Baseline and Weeks 4 and 16. Analyses will be performed for absolute values and values corrected for total lipids.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Systemic Markers of Inflammation and Oxidative Stress</measure>
    <time_frame>Between Baseline (Visit 2) and weeks 4 and 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in absolute neutrophil counts, high sensitivity C-reactive protein (hs-CRP), calprotectin, serum amyloid A (SAA), and myeloperoxidase (MPO) measured in plasma between Baseline and Weeks 4 and 16
Changes in malondialdehyde, protein carbonyls, and total antioxidant capacity measured in plasma between Baseline and Weeks 4 and 16
Change in 8-iso-PGF2α measured in urine between Baseline and Week 16</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Sputum Markers of Inflammation and Oxidative Stress</measure>
    <time_frame>Between Baseline (Visit 2) and Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in sputum levels of free neutrophil elastase activity, alpha1 antitrypsin (A1AT), secretory leukoprotease inhibitor (SLPI), Interleukin-8 (IL-8), and tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-α) between Baseline and Week 16
Changes in levels of 8-iso-PGF2α and 8-Oxo-2'-deoxyguanosine(8-OHdG) between Baseline and Week 16</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Systemic Vitamin Levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Between Baseline (Visit 2) and Weeks 4 and 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>• Changes in plasma levels of retinol (vitamin A), 25-hydroxy vitamin D, α- tocopherol (vitamin E), and PIVKA-II between Baseline and Weeks 4 and 16. Analyses will be performed for absolute values and values corrected for total lipids.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Lung Function Endpoints</measure>
    <time_frame>Between Baseline (Visit 2) and Weeks 4 and 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in forced expiratory volume over one second (FEV1) % predicted between Baseline and Weeks 4 and 16
Change in FEV1 (Liters) between Baseline and Weeks 4 and 16</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Growth Endpoints</measure>
    <time_frame>Between Baseline (Visit 2) and Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in weight (kg and z-score) and BMI (kg/m2 and z-score) between Baseline and Week 16</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Pulmonary Exacerbation</measure>
    <time_frame>Between Baseline (Visit 2) and End of Follow-Up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>• Time to first acute protocol-defined pulmonary exacerbation between Baseline and end of follow up</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Pulmonary Exacerbations</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to end of follow up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of acute pulmonary exacerbations between Baseline and end of follow up</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to end of followup</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of hospitalizations between baseline and end of follow up</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Cystic Fibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AquADEKs-2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two control multivitamin softgel capsules will be taken orally on a once daily basis with pancreatic enzymes and a glass of milk or fat-containing meal for 4 weeks for the screening run in period. For those subjects randomized to the AquADEKs-2 arm, two AquADEKs-2 softgel capsules will be taken orally on a once daily basis with pancreatic enzymes and a glass of milk or fat-containing meal for 16 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control multivitamin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two control multivitamin softgel capsules will be taken orally on a once daily basis with pancreatic enzymes and a glass of milk or fat-containing meal for 4 weeks for the screening run in period for all participants and for 16 weeks for those randomized to this comparative therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AquADEKs-2</intervention_name>
    <description>AquADEKs-2 contains standard amounts of fat-soluble vitamins (A, D, E, K) that are contained in typical CF multivitamin supplements plus several antioxidants including beta-carotene, mixed tocopherols (different forms of vitamin E), coenzyme Q10 (CoQ10), mixed carotenoids (lutein, lycopene and zeaxanthin), and the minerals zinc and selenium.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AquADEKs-2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Antioxidant-enriched multivitamin supplement</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>control multivitamin</intervention_name>
    <description>The control multivitamin contains standard (standard for CF multivitamin supplements) amounts of vitamins A, B, D, E, and K without added antioxidants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AquADEKs-2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control multivitamin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female ≥10 years of age

          -  Documentation of a Cystic Fibrosis (CF) diagnosis as evidenced by 1 or more clinical
             features  consistent with the CF phenotype and 1 or more of the following criteria:

               -  Sweat chloride equal to or greater than 60 milliequivalent (mEq/L) by
                  quantitative pilocarpine iontophoresis test (QPIT)

               -  2 well-characterized mutations in the cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance
                  regulator (CFTR) gene

          -  Pancreatic insufficiency documented by having a spot fecal elastase-1 (FE-1) ≤
             100μg/g in a stool sample done either historically or at the screening visit

          -  Clinically stable with no significant changes in health status within 2 weeks prior
             to randomization

          -  FEV1 ≥ 40 and ≤ 100% of predicted for age based on the Wang (males &lt; 18 years,females
             &lt; 16 years) or Hankinson (males ≥ 18 years, females ≥ 16 years) standardized
             equations at the screening visit

          -  Weight ≥ 30 kg at the screening visit

          -  Able to perform repeatable, consistent efforts in pulmonary function testing

          -  Able to tolerate sputum induction with 3% hypertonic saline and to expectorate with
             induction

          -  Written informed consent (and assent when applicable) obtained from subject or
             subject's legal representative

          -  Ability to swallow softgel capsules

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects being treated with ivacaftor (Kalydeco™)

          -  Liver enzymes aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), or
             gamma-glutamyl transferase (GGT) &gt; 3 times the upper limits of normal at the
             screening visit

          -  Use of antibiotics (oral, iv, and/or inhaled) for acute respiratory symptoms within 2
             weeks prior to randomization

          -  Active treatment for allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis (ABPA)

          -  Current use of oral corticosteroids in doses exceeding the equivalent of 10 mg
             prednisone/day or 20 mg prednisone every other day

          -  Active treatment for nontuberculous mycobacterial (NTM) infection

          -  Initiation of any new chronic therapy (e.g., ibuprofen, Pulmozyme®, hypertonic
             saline,azithromycin,Tobramycin Inhalation solution (TOBI®), Cayston® within 8 weeks
             prior to randomization

          -  Unwilling to discontinue current oral vitamin and antioxidant supplementation
             (e.g.,AquADEKs®, another source of β-carotene, vitamin A, vitamin E or
             tocopherols,vitamins D or K, n-acetylcysteine, glutathione, CoQ10, other
             over-the-counter antioxidant) for the duration of the study

          -  Use of vitamins (other than control vitamin) or antioxidants within 4 weeks prior to
             randomization

          -  Daily use of &gt; 2 cans of Boost or Pulmocare dietary supplement formulas

          -  Known hypersensitivity to oral AquADEKs®

          -  For women of child bearing potential:

               1. positive pregnancy test at Visit 1 or at Visit 2, or

               2. lactating or

               3. unwilling to practice a medically acceptable form of contraception (acceptable
                  forms of contraception: abstinence, hormonal birth control, intrauterine device,
                  or barrier method plus a spermicidal agent)

          -  Subject unlikely to complete the study as determined by the Investigator

          -  Any condition that the Investigator believes would interfere with the intent of this
             study or would make participation not in the best interest of the subject

          -  Use of investigational therapies within 4 weeks prior to randomization

          -  Current tobacco smoker

          -  Current use of anticoagulant medications

          -  Severe malnutrition based either on having a BMI less than the 5th percentile for
             subjects &lt; 18 years of age or a BMI less than 18 kg/m2 for subjects &gt; 18 years of
             age.

          -  Subjects with poorly controlled CF-related diabetes on active insulin therapy,
             defined as having a Glycosylated Hemoglobin (HgbA1c) ≥ 7.5% at the most recent
             historic evaluation of HgbA1c
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Scott Sagel, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Scott Sagel, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>720-777-2522</phone>
    <email>Scott.Sagel@childrenscolorado.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Meg Anthony, MSW</last_name>
    <phone>720-777-2945</phone>
    <email>Meg.Anthony@childrenscolorado.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tucson</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85724</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Osmara Molina, BS</last_name>
      <phone>520-891-6767</phone>
      <email>omolina@arc.arizona.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cori Daines, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Colorado</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Meg Anthony, MSW</last_name>
      <phone>720-777-2945</phone>
      <email>Meg.Anthony@childrenscolorado.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Carol Kopecky, RT</last_name>
      <phone>720-777-2613</phone>
      <email>Carol.Kopecky@childrenscolorado.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Scott Sagel, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Nemours Children's Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32806</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Omar Oquendo, NCMA,BSHM,CRC</last_name>
      <phone>407-650-7880</phone>
      <email>omar.oquendoflores@nemours.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Floyd Livingston, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Catherine Van Wagnen, RN, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>313-745-4737</phone>
      <email>cvanwag@med.wayne.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ibrahim Abdulhamid, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Denise Stacklie, RRT</last_name>
      <phone>612-626-9491</phone>
      <email>stack046@umn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Patricia Grover, RN</last_name>
      <phone>(612) 626-7425</phone>
      <email>Grove026@umn.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jordan Dunitz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Women and Children's Hospital of Buffalo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14222</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nadine Caci, RNC</last_name>
      <phone>716-878-7524</phone>
      <email>ncaci@upa.chob.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ali Jameeleh, RN</last_name>
      <phone>(716) 878-1069</phone>
      <email>jali@upa.chob.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Drucy Borowitz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lorrie Duan, RN</last_name>
      <phone>513-636-7089</phone>
      <email>lorrie.duan@cchmc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Beth Decker, BSN,RN</last_name>
      <phone>(513) 80304325</phone>
      <email>beth.decker@cchmc.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Clancy, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rainbow Babies and Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roberta (Bobbi) Ksenich, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>216-844-5733</phone>
      <email>Roberta.Ksenich@UHHospitals.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>David Weaver, RN, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>(216) 983-0469</phone>
      <email>David.Weaver@UHhospitals.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven Strausbaugh, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nationwide Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melinda Smith, RN</last_name>
      <phone>614-722-2607</phone>
      <email>melinda.smith@nationwidechildrens.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karen McCoy, Md</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn State Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hershey</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Diane Kitch, RN</last_name>
      <phone>717-531-5646</phone>
      <email>dkitch@psu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lisa Allwein</last_name>
      <phone>(717) 531-8196</phone>
      <email>lallwein@hmc.psu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gavin Graff, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Hartigan, RN, MPH, CRM</last_name>
      <phone>412-692-7060</phone>
      <email>elizabeth.hartigan@chp.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sandra Hurban, RN, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>(412) 692-7042</phone>
      <email>sandra.hurban@chp.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Orenstein, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232-5735</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>William Hardeman, BS</last_name>
      <phone>615-936-8308</phone>
      <email>william.g.hardeman@Vanderbilt.Edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Pamela Berry, RN</last_name>
      <phone>(615) 936-1826</phone>
      <email>pamela.berry@Vanderbilt.Edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bonnie Slovis, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center at Dallas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ashley Keller, MPH, BS</last_name>
      <phone>214-648-2817</phone>
      <email>Ashley.Keller@UTSouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raksha Jain, MD, MSCI</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53792</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Linda Makholm, MT (ASCP)</last_name>
      <phone>608-262-0340</phone>
      <email>Lmakholm@uwhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Rock, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patricia M Hastings</last_name>
      <phone>414-266-4707</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Theresa Kump, BA</last_name>
      <phone>(414) 337-7144</phone>
      <email>tkump@mcw.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julie Noe, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sagel SD, Sontag MK, Anthony MM, Emmett P, Papas KA. Effect of an antioxidant-rich multivitamin supplement in cystic fibrosis. J Cyst Fibros. 2011 Jan;10(1):31-6. Epub 2010 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>20961818</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Papas KA, Sontag MK, Pardee C, Sokol RJ, Sagel SD, Accurso FJ, Wagener JS. A pilot study on the safety and efficacy of a novel antioxidant rich formulation in patients with cystic fibrosis. J Cyst Fibros. 2008 Jan;7(1):60-7. Epub 2007 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>17569601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Antioxidants</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamins</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>Oxidative stress</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cystic Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antioxidants</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
