<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="102652">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02080260</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LCI-GI-PAN-REG-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02080260</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Regorafenib in Advanced Pancreatic Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study Testing Single-Agent Regorafenib in Advanced Previously-Treated Adenocarcinoma of the Pancreas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stuart Salmon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bayer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Carolinas Healthcare System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study tests regorafenib as a single agent in the treatment of locally advanced and
      metastatic pancreatic cancer patients who have progressed after prior chemotherapy with
      gemcitabine.  The prognosis for these patients is particularly grim, no other standard
      treatment options exist, and novel approaches are desperately needed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single arm, single stage Phase II study designed to evaluate progression free
      survival (PFS) in patients with locally-advanced or metastatic pancreatic cancer who have
      failed at least one prior line of therapy.  This study will initially open at the Levine
      Cancer Institute (LCI).  Additional investigational site(s) beyond the coordinating site
      will be added following activation. A total of 32 patients will be enrolled to this study
      over a two year enrollment period.  Following informed consent and eligibility check, all
      patients will start oral regorafenib therapy (160 mg  daily for 3 weeks on / 1 week off; 28
      day cycle) and will continue therapy until progression or patient withdrawal.  Patients will
      undergo radiological staging after the first two cycles of regorafenib therapy.  Patients
      with progressive disease will be removed from the study. Patients who have at least stable
      disease will continue regorafenib therapy, at the Investigator's discretion, and will be
      radiologically restaged bimonthly.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral Regorafenib</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>regorafenib</intervention_name>
    <description>Single agent drug therapy with regorafenib</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Stivarga</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically proven adenocarcinoma of the exocrine pancreas with metastatic
             disease.

          -  The site of the primary tumor must have confirmed endosonographically, surgically, or
             radiographically to have been within the pancreas.

          -  Progression on at least one prior line of chemotherapy for locally-advanced or
             metastatic pancreatic cancer.

          -  Progression while on treatment with a gemcitabine regimen for advanced pancreatic
             cancer, or within 12 months of treatment with gemcitabine as part of adjuvant
             therapy.

          -  Measurable disease on axial imaging.

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years.

          -  Life expectancy of at least 8 weeks.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status (PS) 0-2. Enrollment of
             patients with PS = 2 will be capped at 7 patients.

          -  Subjects must be able to understand and be willing to sign the written informed
             consent form.

          -  Acute toxic effects except alopecia of any prior treatment must have resolved to
             National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events
             (CTCAE) v4.0 Grade 1 or less.

          -  Adequate bone marrow, renal, and liver function.

          -  Warfarin or heparin will be allowed provided that there is no prior evidence of
             underlying coagulation abnormality.

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test performed within
             7 days prior to the start of study drug. Post-menopausal women (defined as no menses
             for at least 1 year) and surgically sterilized women are not required to undergo a
             pregnancy test.

          -  Patients (men and women) of childbearing potential must agree to use adequate
             contraception

          -  Patient must be able to swallow and retain oral medication.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous assignment to treatment during this study.

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension.

          -  Active clinically significant cardiac disease.

          -  Cerebrovascular arterial event within 6 months.

          -  Evidence or history of bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy.

          -  Any bleeding event greater than or equal to NCI CTCAE Grade 3 within 4 weeks.

          -  New venous thrombotic or embolic events, such as deep vein thrombosis or pulmonary
             embolism within 3 months.

          -  Previously untreated or concurrent cancer that is distinct in primary site or
             histology except cervical cancer in-situ, treated basal cell carcinoma, or
             superficial bladder tumor. Patients surviving a cancer that was curatively treated
             and without evidence of disease for more than 3 years are allowed.

          -  Patients with pheochromocytoma.

          -  Known history of HIV infection or current chronic or active hepatitis B or C,
             requiring antiviral medication.

          -  Ongoing infection greater than or equal to Grade 2 NCI-CTCAE v4.0.

          -  Symptomatic metastatic brain or meningeal tumors.

          -  Presence of a non-healing wound, non-healing ulcer, or bone fracture.

          -  Renal failure requiring dialysis.

          -  Dehydration Grade greater than or equal to 1 NCI-CTCAE v4.0.

          -  Patients with seizure disorder requiring medication.

          -  Persistent proteinuria greater than or equal to Grade 3 NCI-CTCAE v4.0.

          -  Symptomatic interstitial lung disease.

          -  Pleural effusion or ascites that cause respiratory compromise.

          -  History of organ allograft except corneal transplant.

          -  Known or suspected allergy or hypersensitivity to the study drugs.

          -  Any severe, uncontrolled malabsorption condition.

          -  Women who are pregnant or breast-feeding.

          -  Substance abuse, medical, psychological or social conditions that may interfere with
             the subject's participation in the study.

          -  Concurrent anti-cancer therapy other than study treatment (regorafenib).

          -  Prior use of regorafenib.

          -  Concurrent use of another investigational drug or device therapy (i.e., outside of
             study treatment) during, or within 4 weeks.

          -  Major surgical procedure, open biopsy, or significant traumatic injury within 28
             days.

          -  Prior radiation therapy or hepatic arterial therapy is permitted if more than 4 weeks
             have passed since completion and measurable disease outside of the treated area is
             present, or if progression since treatment has occurred.

          -  Use of St. John's Wort.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John S Salmon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Levine Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Neil L West</last_name>
    <phone>704-863-6187</phone>
    <email>neil.west@carolinashealthcare.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 3, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Carolinas Healthcare System</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stuart Salmon</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Sponsor-Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
