<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="36997">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02140021</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014-0021</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02140021</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevalence of Anal Dysplasia and Cancer in Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prevalence of Anal Dysplasia and Anal Cancer in Women With Cervical, Vaginal and Vulvar Dysplasia and Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn how often high-grade dysplasia or
      invasive squamous cell carcinoma of the anus occurs in women with high-grade dysplasia or
      invasive squamous cell carcinoma of the cervix, vagina, or vulva.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Anal cancer as well as cervical, vaginal, and vulvar cancer can be caused by an infection
      called human papillomavirus (HPV).  Researchers do not know how often anal cancer and
      dysplasia occur together.  Researchers also want to learn how to test for these diseases.

      If you agree to take part in this study, the following tests and procedures will be
      performed during your scheduled colposcopy or surgery.  These tests are performed to test
      for pre-cancer of the anal canal.

        -  You will have an anal pap test.  To perform this test, a small swab is placed in your
           anal canal to collect cells, similar to the pap test performed on your cervix.  This
           sample will also be used for HPV testing.

        -  You will have an anoscopy.  An anoscopy is an examination of the rectum in which a
           small tube is inserted into the anus to screen, diagnose, and evaluate problems of the
           anus and anal canal. To perform this test, acetic acid is placed on the anus and the
           area is looked at for pre-cancerous areas using a colposcope (an instrument that
           magnifies the cells of the cervix and vagina to allow for direct observation and study
           of the living tissue). The acetic acid is used to help the pre-cancerous areas show up
           better.  If you have an abnormal test result, you will be referred to a colorectal
           specialist so that you can be seen and then treated according to the standard of care.

      After the procedures described above are performed, your study participation will be over.

      This is an investigational study.

      Up to 500 women will take part in this study.  Up to 250 will be enrolled at MD Anderson.
      Up to 250 will be enrolled at the Harris Health System.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of Invasive Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Anus in Women with Cervical, Vaginal and Vulvar Dysplasia and Cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Prevalence of invasive squamous cell carcinoma of the anus estimated in women with each of the 3 diagnoses with 95% confidence intervals. Prevalence of anal dysplasia estimated in women with each of the 3 diagnoses.
Results of anoscopy used as true state of the patient. Sensitivity and specificity of anal HPV testing estimated with 95% confidence intervals to diagnose anal dysplasia in women with each of the 3 diagnoses.
Results of anoscopy used as true state of the patient. Sensitivity and specificity of combination of anal pap testing + anal HPV testing estimated with 95% confidence intervals to diagnose anal dysplasia in women with each of the 3 diagnoses.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Female Reproductive System Neoplasm</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anal Pap Test + Anoscopy</arm_group_label>
    <description>Women with high-grade dysplasia or squamous cell carcinoma of the cervix, vagina, or vulva.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anal Pap Test</intervention_name>
    <description>During scheduled colposcopy or surgery, an anal pap test performed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anal Pap Test + Anoscopy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anoscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>During scheduled colposcopy or surgery, an anoscopy performed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anal Pap Test + Anoscopy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      All patients undergo anal Pap and anal HPV testing.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Women with high-grade dysplasia or squamous cell carcinoma of the cervix, vagina, or vulva
        at The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, Texas, and Lyndon Baines
        Johnson Hospital, Houston, Texas
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Women with histologically confirmed cervical, vaginal or vulvar high-grade dysplasia,
             or invasive squamous cell carcinoma. All stages and grades will be eligible.

          2. Patients &gt;/= 18

          3. Patients must sign an approved informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients undergoing any radiation therapy for advanced cervical, vaginal, or vulvar
             squamous cell carcinoma.

          2. Patients who received prior pelvic radiation therapy.

          3. Patients with previously documented perianal squamous cell dysplasia or invasive
             squamous cell carcinoma of the anus or anal canal.

          4. Patients unwilling or unable to provide informed consent for the study.

          5. Male patients will not be included in this study.

          6. Subject is known to be pregnant including positive pregnancy test at the time of
             enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathleen Schmeler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kathleen Schmeler, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-745-3518</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lyndon B. Johnson General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77026</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas  MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Malignant Female Reproductive System Neoplasm</keyword>
  <keyword>Gynecological Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>High-grade dysplasia</keyword>
  <keyword>Carcinoma of the cervix</keyword>
  <keyword>Carcinoma of the vagina</keyword>
  <keyword>Carcinoma of the vulva</keyword>
  <keyword>Invasive squamous cell carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Anal pap test</keyword>
  <keyword>Anoscopy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Genital Neoplasms, Female</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
