<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82406">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02046148</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>V98_12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02046148</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Immunogenicity of a Trivalent Group B Streptococcus Vaccine in Healthy Pregnant Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II, Multicenter, Randomized, Observer-Blind, Controlled Study to Evaluate Safety and Immunogenicity of a Trivalent Group B Streptococcus Vaccine in Healthy Pregnant Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Vaccines</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evaluate the safety and immunogenicity of the trivalent group B streptococcus vaccine in
      healthy pregnant women. The study will also evaluate the levels of GBS serotype-specific
      antibodies in infants, placental transfer from the pregnant women to the infant and levels
      of antibodies in the breast milk.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of GBS IgG levels in infant serum at Delivery and Days 42 and 90 of age</measure>
    <time_frame>Birth, Days 42 and 90 of infant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate serotype-specific (Ia, Ib and III) GBS serum IgG antibody levels in vaccinated mothers and infant</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of GBS IgG levels in maternal serum at prevaccination, Study Day 31, at Delivery and at Days 42 and 90 postpartum</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 prevaccination, Day 31 postvaccination, delivery, Days 42 and 90 postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ratio relative to prevaccination levels of maternal serum GBS IgG antibody levels as measured at Study Day 31, Delivery and at Days 42 and 90 postpartum</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Day 31, Delivery and at Days 42 and 90 postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ratio of GBS antibody levels in infant serum relative to maternal serum at the time of Delivery</measure>
    <time_frame>Delivery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the relationship of serotype-specific (Ia, Ib and III) GBS IgG antibody levels in the infant and maternal serum</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>GBS Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GBS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>GBS vaccine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GBS vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Trivalent GBS vaccine</description>
    <arm_group_label>GBS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Normal saline</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Healthy pregnant women 18-40 years of age, inclusive and at 28 0/7 through 34 6/7
             weeks gestation.

          2. Individuals who intend to breastfeed for at least 90 days postpartum.

          3. Individuals who have given written consent after the nature of the study has been
             explained according to local regulatory requirements.

          4. Individuals in good health as determined by the outcome of medical history, physical
             examination and clinical judgment of the investigator.

          5. Individuals who can comprehend and comply with all study procedures and are available
             for follow-up.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Individuals with history of illness or an ongoing illness that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, may pose additional risk to the subject if she participates in the
             study.

          2. Individuals with known hypersensitivity to any component of the vaccine.

          3. Individuals who received or plan to receive any licensed vaccine within 14 days
             before or after the study vaccine with the  exception of inactivated influenza
             vaccine which may be administered up to 7 days before or after study vaccine.

          4. Individuals with an infection requiring systemic antibiotic or antiviral treatment
             within 7 days prior to Study Day 1.

          5. Individuals determined as high risk for serious obstetrical complication, including:

               -  Gestational hypertension, as defined by American College of Obstetricians and
                  Gynecologists guidelines (ACOG Practice Bulletin 2012)

               -  Gestational diabetes which is not controlled by diet and exercise as per
                  American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists guidelines (ACOG Practice
                  Bulletin 2013)

               -  Pre-eclampsia or eclampsia as defined by American College of Obstetricians and
                  Gynecologists guidelines (ACOG practice bulletin, 2002)

               -  HIV infection

               -  Obesity class II or greater (pre-pregnancy BMI≥35.0)

               -  multiple pregnancy

          6. Individuals with behavioral or cognitive impairment or psychiatric disease that, in
             the opinion of the investigator, may interfere with the subject's ability to
             participate in the study.

          7. Individuals who are not able to comprehend and to follow all required study
             procedures for the whole period of the study.

          8. Individuals with known or suspected impairment of the immune system including known
             or suspected HIV infection or HIV-related disease, a history of or an active
             autoimmune disorder and receipt of immunosuppressive therapy.

          9. Long term use of glucocorticoids, including oral or parenteral prednisone ≥ 20 mg/day
             or equivalent for more than 2 consecutive weeks (or 2 weeks total) within 30 days
             prior to enrollment. Use of inhaled, intranasal, or topical corticosteroids is
             allowed.

         10. Individuals participating in any clinical trial with another investigational product
             during the pregnancy or intent to participate in another clinical study at any time
             during the conduct of this study.

         11. Pregnant with a fetus with a known or suspected congenital anomaly

         12. Individuals who are acting as study personnel or immediate family members (brother,
             sister, child, parent) or the spouse of study personnel.

         13. Individuals with a fever (oral temperature ≥ 38°C/100.4 °F) within 3 days prior to
             intended study vaccination.

         14. Individuals with a history of culture confirmed GBS case in the infant(s) previously
             born to her.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Novartis Vaccines</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Novartis Vaccines</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Novartis Drug Information Services</last_name>
    <phone>+1 800 244 7668</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 21, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Maternal vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>GBS</keyword>
  <keyword>pregnant women</keyword>
  <keyword>IgG</keyword>
  <keyword>IgA</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
