<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="107715">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02075463</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>114837</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02075463</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of GSK1278863 in Recombinant Human Erythropoietin (rhEPO) Hyporesponsive Hemodialysis-dependent Chronic Kidney Disease Subjects With Anemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A 16-week, Phase 2a, Single-arm, Multi-center, Open-label Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of GSK1278863 After Switching From Recombinant Human Erythropoietin (rhEPO), in Hemodialysis-dependent Subjects With Anemia Associated With Chronic Kidney Disease Who Are Chronically Hyporesponsive to rhEPO</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study will evaluate the ability of GSK1278863 to increase the hemoglobin (Hgb)
      concentration and the safety and efficacy of GSK1278863 over 16 weeks of treatment, in
      hemodialysis-dependent subjects with anemia associated with chronic kidney disease who are
      chronically hyporesponsive to rhEPO.  The data generated will inform dose requirements for
      any chronic rhEPO hyporesponsive hemodialysis-dependent subjects included in future clinical
      trials.  The study consists of a 4-week rhEPO run-in period, a 16-week GSK1278863 treatment
      period and a 4-week Follow-up period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hgb change from baseline at Week 16</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage (%) of time within Hgb target range</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 to Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The percentage of time a subject remains in Hgb target range (10.0 to 11.5 grams [g]/deciliter [dL]) whilst on treatment during the defined period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage (%) of time below Hgb target range</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 to Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The percentage of time a subject remains below Hgb target range whilst on treatment during the defined period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage (%) of time above Hgb target range</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 to Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The percentage of time a subject remains above Hgb target range whilst on treatment during the defined period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number (%) of subjects achieving at least a 1 g/dL increase in Hgb</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of subjects achieving at least a 1 g/dL increase in Hgb as compared to baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number (%) of subjects with Hgb in the target range</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of subjects with Hgb in target range</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number (%) of subjects reaching predefined Hgb stopping criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of subjects reaching pre-defined Hgb study medication discontinuation criteria will be summarised.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in hepcidin</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in ferritin</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in transferrin</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in transferrin saturation</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in total iron</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in total iron binding capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in reticulocyte hemoglobin content</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in mean corpuscular volume (MCV)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in mean corpuscular haemoglobin (MCH)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in hematocrit</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in red blood cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in reticulocyte number</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum observed change from baseline in vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF).</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum observed change from baseline in erythropoietin (EPO).</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean final dose of GSK1278863 administered.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 16</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Population Pharmacokinetics</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, Week 4 and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluation of population pharmacokinetic parameters of GSK1278863 and relevant metabolites.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Anemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GSK1278863 Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive a fixed starting dose of 12 milligrams (mg) GSK1278863 once daily (QD) orally for first 4 weeks.  From Week 4 the dose of GSK1278863 will be adjusted based on Hgb levels and evaluated every 4 weeks until Week 16.  This starting dose may be changed during the study if there is an early indication of either lack of efficacy or the rate of rise in Hgb is too rapid</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK1278863</intervention_name>
    <description>Film coated tablets containing 1 mg, 2 mg, 5 mg or 25 mg of GSK1278863</description>
    <arm_group_label>GSK1278863 Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo tablet for GSK1278863</description>
    <arm_group_label>GSK1278863 Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Hemodialysis (HD) frequency: Stable HD regimen of three to four times weekly for a
             minimum of 12 weeks. Note: The type and frequency of dialysis must be stable during
             the study. Isolated ultrafiltration sessions for the purposes of fluid removal are
             permitted.

          -  Dialysis Adequacy: Single-pool dialyzer clearance multiplied by dialyzer time divided
             by volume of distribution of urea (Kt/Vurea) of &gt;=1.2 based on a historical value
             obtained within the prior month.

          -  rhEPO hyporesponsiveness: Historical and current intravenous (IV) rhEPO and Hgb
             values.  Average epoetin alfa dose and Hgb level for three 4-week periods for a total
             of 12 weeks prior to Week -4, and during the 4 week run-in period, must be within the
             following ranges: average epoetin alfa dose &gt;4000 and &lt;=6000 units per session and
             Hgb &gt;=8.0 and &lt;=9.5 g/dL; average epoetin alfa dose &gt;6000 units per session and Hgb
             &gt;=8.0 and &lt;=10.0 g/dL.

          -  Absolute difference between the Hgb value at Week -4 and Week 0 (Day 1), must be &lt;1.3
             g/dL. Note: Subjects who do not meet the criteria after being rescreened twice,
             should not be entered into the GSK1278863 treatment period and should be withdrawn
             from the study.

          -  Age: &gt;=18 years of age.

          -  Q-T Interval Corrected for Heart Rate (QTc): Bazett's Correction of QT Interval
             (QTcB) &lt;470 msec or QTcB &lt;480 milliseconds (msec) in subjects with bundle branch
             block. There is no corrected QT interval (QTc) inclusion criterion for a subject with
             a predominantly paced rhythm.

          -  Gender: Female and male subjects.  Females: If of childbearing potential, must agree
             to use one of the approved contraception methods from Screening until completion of
             the Follow-up Visit OR, of non-childbearing potential defined as pre-menopausal
             females with a documented tubal ligation, hysterectomy or oophorectomy; or
             postmenopausal defined as 12 months of spontaneous amenorrea [in questionable cases a
             blood sample with simultaneous follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) 23.0-116.3
             milliinternational units (MIU)/milliliter (mL) (23.0-116.3 international units
             (IU)/liter (L)) and estradiol &lt;=10 picograms (pg)/mL (&lt;=37 picomole (pmol)/L) is
             confirmatory]. Females on hormone replacement therapy (HRT) whose menopausal status
             is in doubt will be required to use one of the approved contraception methods if they
             wish to continue their HRT during the study. Otherwise they must discontinue HRT to
             allow confirmation of post-menopausal status prior to study enrollment.  For most
             forms of HRT, at least 2 weeks will elapse between the cessation of therapy and the
             blood draw; this interval depends on the type and dosage of HRT. Following
             confirmation of their post-menopausal status, they can resume use of HRT during the
             study without use of a contraceptive method.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Dialysis modality: Planned change in dialysis modality within the study time period.

          -  rhEPO: Use of methoxy polyethylene glycol epoetin beta or darbepoetin within the
             prior 8 weeks prior to Week -4.

          -  Renal transplant: Scheduled renal transplant.

          -  Transferrin saturation (TSAT): &lt;20% on the most recent sample taken over the last 12
             weeks.

          -  Ferritin: &lt;100 nanograms (ng)/mL (&lt;100 micrograms/L) on the most recent sample taken
             over the last 12 weeks.

          -  Vitamin B12: At or below the lower limit of the reference range (may rescreen in a
             minimum of 8 weeks).

          -  Folate: &lt;2.0 ng/mL (&lt;4.5 nanomoles (nmol)/L) (may rescreen in a minimum of 4 weeks).

          -  Myocardial infarction or acute coronary syndrome: Within the 8 weeks prior to Week
             -4.

          -  Stroke or transient ischemic attacks (TIAs): Within the 8 weeks prior to Week -4.

          -  Heart failure: Class III/IV heart failure, as defined by the New York Heart
             Association (NYHA) functional classification system diagnosed prior to Week -4.

          -  Hypertension: Defined using pre-dialysis vitals (Week -4) of diastolic blood pressure
             &gt;100 millimeters of mercury (mmHg) or systolic blood pressure &gt;170 mmHg.

          -  Thrombotic disease: History of thrombotic disease (e.g., venous thrombosis such as
             deep vein thrombosis or pulmonary embolism, or arterial thrombosis such as new onset
             or worsening limb ischemia requiring intervention) within the 8 weeks prior to Week
             -4, except vascular access thrombosis.

          -  Inflammatory disease: Active chronic inflammatory disease that could impact
             erythropoiesis (e.g., scleroderma, systemic lupus erythematosis, rheumatoid
             arthritis, celiac disease) diagnosed prior to Week -4.

          -  Hematological disease: Any hematological disease including those affecting platelets,
             white or red blood cells (e.g., antibody-mediated pure red cell aplasia, sickle cell
             anemia, myelodysplastic syndromes, hematological malignancy, myeloma, hemolytic
             anemia), coagulation disorders (e.g., antiphospholipid syndrome, Protein C or S
             deficiency), or any other cause of anemia other than renal disease diagnosed prior to
             Week -4.

          -  Liver disease: Current liver disease, known hepatic or biliary abnormalities (with
             the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones) or evidence at
             Screening of abnormal liver function tests [alanine transaminase (ALT) or aspartate
             transaminase (AST) &gt; 2.0 x upper limit of normal (ULN) or total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x
             ULN]; or other hepatic abnormalities that in the opinion of the investigator would
             preclude the subject from participation in the study. NOTE: Those with Hepatitis B or
             Hepatitis C are eligible provided these exclusions are not met.

          -  Major surgery: (excluding vascular access surgery) within the 8 weeks prior to Week
             -4, or planned during the study.

          -  Transfusion: Blood transfusion within the 8 weeks prior to Week -4, or an anticipated
             need for blood transfusion during the study.

          -  Gastrointestinal (GI) Bleeding: Evidence of actively bleeding peptic, duodenal, or
             esophageal ulcer disease or clinically significant GI bleeding within the 8 weeks
             prior to Week -4.

          -  Ophthalmology disease: History of proliferative retinopathy requiring treatment
             within the prior 12 months or macular edema requiring treatment.

          -  Acute infection: Clinical evidence of acute infection, evidence of underlying
             infection or history of infection requiring IV antibiotic therapy within the 8 weeks
             prior to Week -4, and also through to Day 1. Note: IV antibiotics as prophylaxis are
             allowed.

          -  Malignancy: Subjects with a history of malignancy within the prior 5 years, who are
             receiving treatment for cancer, or who have a strong family history of cancer (e.g.,
             familial cancer disorders), with the exception of squamous cell or basal cell
             carcinoma of the skin that has been definitively treated prior to Week -4.

          -  Severe allergic reactions: History of severe allergic or anaphylactic reactions or
             hypersensitivity to excipients in the investigational product.

          -  Drugs and supplements: Use of any prescription or non-prescription drugs or dietary
             supplements that are prohibited from Week -4 until the Follow-up Visit.

          -  Prior investigational product exposure: The subject has participated in a clinical
             trial and has received an experimental investigational product within the prior 30
             days to Week -4.

          -  Life Expectancy: Life expectancy is considered by the investigator to be less than 6
             months.

          -  Other conditions: Any other conditions, clinical or laboratory abnormality, or
             examination finding that the Investigator considers would put the subject at
             unacceptable risk, or an unwillingness or inability to follow the procedures, or
             lifestyle and/or dietary restrictions outlined in the protocol.

          -  Pregnancy and lactation: Pregnant females as determined by positive serum human
             chorionic gonadotrophin (hCG) test or women who are lactating at Week -4 or during
             the trial.

          -  Laboratory eligibility criteria will be assessed according to the central laboratory
             result for the screening samples

          -  Subjects who fail screening may be rescreened as soon as the investigator feels they
             may have subsequently become eligible. However, an individual subject may not be
             rescreened more than twice. There is no predetermined amount of time required to wait
             to rescreen a previously ineligible subject. Exceptions are those failing on Hgb or
             folate who may rescreen in 4 weeks and those failing for Vitamin B12 where
             rescreening may occur in 8 weeks.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90022</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 27, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>recombinant human erythropoietin</keyword>
  <keyword>GSK1278863</keyword>
  <keyword>hemodialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemoglobin</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic rhEPO hyporesponsiveness</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic kidney disease</keyword>
  <keyword>erythropoiesis stimulating agents</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epoetin Alfa</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematinics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
