<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="70605">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02050841</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LAS-212</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02050841</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Open-label, Multicenter, Post-Marketing Requirement Study to Investigate Safety, Tolerability and Efficacy of octaplasLG in the Management of Pediatric Patients Who Require Replacement of Multiple Coagulation Factors</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label, Multicenter, Post-Marketing Requirement (PMR) Study to Investigate the Safety, Tolerability and Efficacy of octaplasLG in the Management of Pediatric Patients Who Require Replacement of Multiple Coagulation Factors.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Octapharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Octapharma</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate the safety, tolerability and efficacy of
      octaplasLG in pediatric patients who require replacement of multiple coagulation factors.
      Replacement of multiple coagulation factors in pediatric patients with acquired deficiencies
      due to liver disease and in pediatric patients requiring cardiac surgery or liver surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Monitoring of adverse drug reactions (e.g., allergic reactions), TEs, TEEs and hyperfibrinolytic events</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Monitoring of clinically significant changes in laboratory parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of metabolic derangements, renal function and hematologic implications measurable by the following: Chem 7, CBC, calcium and ionized calcium.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Liver or Cardiac Surgery</condition>
  <condition>Liver Dysfunction</condition>
  <condition>Coagulopathy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>octaplasLG</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients requiring liver or cardiac surgery and/or patients with liver dysfunction
        associated with coagulopathy in whom replacement of multiple coagulation factors is
        required and plasma is ordered by the treating physician, or pre-operative PELD score ≥ 15
        for liver transplant or failure patients or pre-operative STAT score ≥3 for cardiac
        surgery patients.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients requiring liver or cardiac surgery and/or patients with liver dysfunction
             associated with coagulopathy in whom replacement of multiple coagulation factors is
             required and plasma is ordered by the treating physician, or pre-operative PELD score
             at least 15 for liver transplant or failure patients or pre-operative STAT score at
             least 3 for cardiac surgery patients.

          -  Voluntarily given, written and signed informed consent by the patient's legal
             representative(s) or guardian(s). If the child is of an age deemed old enough by the
             institution to understand the risks and benefits of the study, they should also be
             made aware of the risks/benefits of the study and provide written assent.

          -  Male or female patient 16 years of age or older.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with known homozygous congenital deficiency of protein S.

          -  Patient has a history of hypersensitivity reaction to blood or plasma-derived
             products or to any excipient of the investigational product.

          -  Patient has an already known IgA deficiency with documented antibodies against IgA.

          -  Patient has a congenital factor deficiency or platelet disorder requiring plasma
             treatment.

          -  Patient is currently participating in another study investigating a new drug product
             or another interventional clinical study that may impact coagulation factors or has
             participated during the last three (3) months.

          -  Patient received FFP, FP24 or any other plasma product other than octaplasLG within
             the last seven (7) days during this hospitalization.

          -  Patient is on ECMO (Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation) when plasma is ordered by
             the treating physician for the first infusion episode.

          -  Patient is planned recipient for a living donor OLT.

          -  Patient is pregnant.

          -  Patient is predicted to require massive blood transfusion defined as more than 40 mL
             per kilogram of all blood products in a 24-hour period

          -  Patient is receiving plasma exchange, TPE or plasmapheresis.

          -  Patient is a premature neonate defined as less than 37 weeks gestation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>16 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wolfgang Frenzel</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>International Medical Director</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Eppolito, MBA</last_name>
    <phone>215-527-4374</phone>
    <email>Michael.Eppolito@octapharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 21, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pediatric</keyword>
  <keyword>patients</keyword>
  <keyword>replacement</keyword>
  <keyword>coagulation factors</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Blood Coagulation Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemostatic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
