<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="61987">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01794936</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAF3321</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01794936</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study of VTI Doppler Probe Use to Identify Neurovascular Bundle During Prostate Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>VTI Doppler Probe For Robotic Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to evaluate the use of a disposable laparoscopic Doppler probe in
      robotic assisted prostatectomies. The Vascular Technology, Inc. (VTI) laparoscopic probe is
      simply a sterile, disposable Doppler probe that can be inserted through a laparoscopic
      trocar and placed on structures to determine if there is vascular flow demonstrating an
      audible pulse. During robotic-assisted prostatectomy, identification of vasculature is
      critical in order to prevent hemorrhage and effectively treat the underlying pathology. The
      investigators routinely utilize a combined Doppler ultrasound laparoscopic probe to identify
      vasculature during renal surgery, but Doppler ultrasound usage has not been adopted for
      prostatic surgery.

      From a mechanical standpoint, these combination probes differ from the VTI probe in that
      they are approximately 2 times the diameter of the VTI probe, and the portion of the probe
      utilized for imaging much longer and on the side of the device. The VTI probe is much
      narrower, and the portion of the probe utilized for vessel identification is at the tip of
      the probe. For robotic-assisted prostatectomy, patients will be randomized to VTI
      laparoscopic Doppler System to identify pedicles and neurovascular bundles (NVB) or to
      robotic-assisted laparoscopic prostatectomy with no Doppler probe, which is the current
      standard of care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The VTI Laparoscopic Doppler System is a blood flow detector that compensates for the loss
      of tactile sensation during laparoscopic procedures by helping the surgeon to identify
      vascular anatomy before it is visible to the eye. The system's sterile doppler probes fit
      through standard 5mm ports. It is simple to use and no special training is required. This
      study is designed to evaluate the use of the VTI (Nashua, NH) 20 megahertz (MHz)
      Microvascular Doppler probe in laparoscopic urological surgery.

      Patients will take a preoperative sexual health inventory for men (SHIM) questionnaire. The
      investigators will then assess presence or absence of arterial and venous blood flow, in
      real-time during surgery. Additionally, the investigators will evaluate the safety of
      Doppler probe use, the surgical margin status on final pathology, and the post-operative
      erectile function of the patients with a followup SHIM questionnaire (to be performed 3
      months after surgery). Finally, the robotic surgeon will document whether or not our
      original surgical plan was changed or remained the same after the Doppler use.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in SHIM Score (score of erectile function) following surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months post-operative follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients are to be evaluated for erectile function at 8 month post-operative visit using validated SHIM questionnaire.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-operative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>During surgical procedure itself (~2-3 hours)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators will evaluate whether any intra-operative complications resulted from the use of the VTI probe to assess safety. Specifically, this time frame is limited from the induction of anesthesia through the completion of the surgical procedure (typically ~2-3 hours)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Nerve Sparing Prostatectomy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VTI Probe</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>During robotic-assisted laparoscopic prostatectomy, the VTI Doppler probe (test) will utilized to measure blood blow within the neurovascular bundles. This is to be completed after the bladder neck and seminal vesicles are identified and dissected. To use the probe, the assistant surgeon will place the Doppler probe within the abdomen and systematically move it cephalad along the lateral prostate pedicles to identify NVB vessels. The Doppler flow in these regions will be quantified as arterial (strong) flow, venous (minimal) flow or no flow. The procedures will proceed by dissecting the lateral margin of prostate step by step up to the gland's apex. Blood loss and the time required to identify and dissect the NVB will be recorded.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Probe</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to not receive probe evaluation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VTI Probe</intervention_name>
    <description>The VTI 20 MHz microvascular Laparoscopic Doppler System is a blood flow detector that compensates for the loss of tactile sensation during laparoscopic procedures by eliminating misunderstandings related to surrounding vascular anatomy. The system's sterile doppler probes fit through standard 5mm ports, making it easy to use with no special training required.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VTI Probe</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients must be 18 years of age or older and be able to read, understand and
             sign consent.

          -  Any patient undergoing robotic assisted laparoscopic prostatectomy (RALP)

          -  Any patient without moderate or severe erectile dysfunction (SHIM less than 15)
             undergoing bilateral or unilateral nerve-sparing RALP is eligible for this procedure.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients undergoing a non nerve-sparing RALP will be excluded from this study

          -  Those who receive a baseline SHIM score less than 15
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ketan Badani, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 17, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ketan K. Badani</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Professor of Urology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prostate cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Nerve Sparing Prostatectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>VTI Probe</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
