<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="21694">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01900912</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GDGOPP1024012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01900912</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the Impact of Community Led Total Sanitation Programs in Mali</brief_title>
  <acronym>CLTS</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluating the Impact of Community Led Total Sanitation in Mali. A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad Nacional de La Plata</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>UNICEF</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad Nacional de La Plata</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Mali: comités d'éthique</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Behavioral change is a key ingredient for successful adoption of better sanitation practices
      in rural Africa. Sanitation programs have, for some time now, incorporated the need to raise
      awareness and emphasize the benefits of toilet usage. These endeavors, often combined with
      subsidies linked to toilet construction by households, seek to create a demand for
      sanitation goods. Yet, progress in securing the desired outcomes from sanitation programs
      has been slow. Moreover, benefits of sanitation largely take the form of externalities,
      which individuals do not take into account when making their own decisions about
      investments. This makes sanitation promotion at the household level particularly
      challenging.

      A new approach to sanitation entails a shift away from the provision of subsidies for
      toilets to individual households and a promotion of behavioral change at individual-level
      towards emphasizing collective decision-making in order to produce 'open defecation-free'
      villages. The objective of the intervention is to reduce the incidence of diseases related
      to poor sanitation and manage public risks posed by the failure to safely confine the
      excreta of some community members. The way to achieve this objective is by empowering
      communities motivated to take collective action. Local governments and other agencies
      perform at best a facilitating role. There is a growing recognition that this approach,
      referred to as Community-Led Total Sanitation (CLTS), may help with the reduction of open
      defecation practices. However, no rigorous impact evaluation of CLTS has been conducted so
      far. This proposal comprises a randomized controlled trial for studying the effect of CLTS
      in rural Mali. As a result, sound evidence will become available to see to what extent CLTS
      improves health outcomes and what is driving collective action in order to increase
      sanitation coverage.

      The direct recipients of the intervention are members of rural communities in Mali who
      aspire to live in a cleaner environment. The donor community, international organizations,
      and governments in developing countries will benefit from having simple and clear evidence
      on the effectiveness of an innovative program for improving sanitation in rural areas. They
      will learn whether the program has worked or failed to achieve its objective of eradicating
      open defecation, and about key factors explaining success and failure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The evaluation study described involves 121 communities in the Region of Koulikoro in rural
      Mali. The intervention works in the following manner: communities are facilitated (by means
      of government and NGOs staff) to conduct their own appraisal and analysis of open defecation
      (OD) and take their own action to become ODF.

      In Mali, the Open Defecation Free (ODF) status has been defined as follows: &quot;each family has
      a latrine equipped with a cover that limits the proliferation of flies from the pits; all
      members of the family exclusively use such latrine to defecate; each latrine is equipped
      with a hand washing device (water + soap / water + ash bucket)&quot;.

      Methodology

      To estimate the causal effect of CLTS the researchers need to construct a valid
      counterfactual in order to calculate what would have happened in the absence of the
      intervention. The team conducted a random assignment at the community level in order to test
      impact on some of the outcomes mentioned above. Random allocation ensures that on average,
      treated and untreated communities share the same observables and unobservables. Random
      assignment to treatment also overcomes the main selection problem found in evaluations,
      where those who are selected to receive the program may have different attributes than those
      who were not selected in the first place. These differences can be caused by observable
      attributes, more wealthy communities, more engaged leaders, better weather, etc, may be more
      willing to engage in CLTS programs, or by unobservable dimensions too. What is more
      important is that such differences can be affecting the outcomes the investigators want to
      measure. Random assignment to the program eliminates selection bias because it ensures that
      on average, communities receiving the program are similar to the ones that do not receive
      it.

      Although random assignment is at the community level, the basic units of analysis of this
      evaluation are households. The investigators are interested in health outcomes for children
      under two and under five, because diarrhea is among the main causes of child mortality.
      Also, the researchers are interested at looking at morbidity and school attendance for
      school age children. Finally, improved sanitation is supposed to produce a redistribution in
      the use of time at the household level. Another very relevant question is whether, as argued
      by defenders of CLTS (Kar and Chambers, 2008, among many others), CLTS intervention provides
      a higher satisfaction than interventions granting government subsidies to build toilets or
      latrines. Unfortunately, the program does not comprise different interventions (subsidies vs
      CLTS for example), so the team will inquire about head of household perceptions about both
      potential intervention both in treatment and control communities. In addition the
      researchers are very interested at looking at variables that are directly related to the
      success/failure of the intervention. In particular, the investigators will monitor latrine
      use, water quality, general higiene. The team will be able to determine whether lack of
      impact on health outcomes is due to lack of latrine use despite their availability, or
      whether it is due to lack of hand hygiene despite use of latrines.

      Conservative power calculations, calibrated in order to at least detect a 10% decrease in
      diarrhea incidence among 2-years old children. UNICEF has observed in areas where the
      program has already been implemented that migration is relatively low, so the researchers do
      not expect much attrition. This decrease in diarrhea can be expected even if the village
      does not become fully ODF, but take up levels are lower. 90% of the communities which have
      participated in the program were certified ODF by Unicef.

      The evaluation comprises gathering data at three different points in time: a) baseline,
      before program implementation, b) first (reduced) follow up: immediately after the
      intervention finishes, c) full follow up 12 months after program implementation in order to
      assess longer-term effects and sustainability. The investigators would be able to gather
      panel data at the community and at the household level. Also, there will be a series of
      random visits to collect other information at different points in time: these visits will be
      used to supplement information on health, school attendance, latrine usage and water
      quality.

      While random assignment allows to compare average outcomes across communities, the
      investigators would also perform multivariate regression analysis in order to improve the
      precision of our estimates and control for any potential pre-treatment differences. Panel
      data allows to use a difference in difference design and also to include initial (before the
      intervention) characteristics of households and communities. Standard errors will be
      clustered at the community level, and compared to block-bootstrapped ones too in order to
      correct for serially correlated errors arising from the short nature of the panel used.

      The communities included in the study understand and agree to be part of the study, meaning
      that they accept to work on sanitation issues with CLTS either right away or two years
      later. Program take up is implied by the acceptance of this protocol for treated
      communities. Randomization was done after the baseline was conducted. UNICEF and the
      Directorate of Sanitation of Koulikoro (DNACPN) have successfully finished the triggering
      process in the 60 communities assigned to the treatment group. The main obstacle that the
      CLTS implementing team faced was the training and mobilization of the human resources needed
      to trigger the intervention. This was a significant burden imposed by the requirements of
      the impact evaluation, resulting from the sampling framework (needed to avoid contamination
      and to ensure geographic representativeness). Communities were located farther apart
      compared to the way CLTS is usually conducted in Mali. However, the implementation team
      successfully managed to complete the triggering and so far the rest of the intervention is
      going as scheduled.

      One of the main concerns of random assignment is the potential contamination of the control
      group. This happens for example when there are interactions between members of CLTS
      communities and members of control communities. This is a problem in the presence of shared
      activities. The problem is that these interactions may cause changes in the control group.
      At the extreme, control communities and CLTS communities experience the same change, then
      the researchers will not be able to detect any effect. The researchers have ensured that the
      study communities are sufficiently scattered geographically, so that interaction is not
      expected to be very high. In order to check for interaction between family members living in
      different communities, the team added several questions in the surveys and document the
      extent of interactions. Another concern that often arises with randomized experiments is
      that control units may be receiving similar benefits from other interventions. The
      investigators will monitor control villages to ensure this does not happen and document this
      aspect of the design.

      UNICEF conducts strict monitoring follow-ups during the intervention period (first 3
      months), which will be used to inform on the operations of the intervention. These
      monitoring indicators are carefully recorded and their quality is ensured. The team will
      supplement this work in two ways by collecting more indicators during the intervention
      period and after the end of the intervention. Note that UNICEF also plans to access
      administrative school data to monitor the evolution of school attendance in the future.

      The investigators will give careful attention to the variation in impacts across different
      groups, so treatment will be interacted with gender and age indicators, pre-existing
      characteristics of communities in terms of collective decision-making, among others in order
      to identify how these factors may explain why some people or some communities gain more than
      others from the program. Looking at heterogeneity in program impacts also helps in shading
      light on the mechanism behind program's success (or failure).

      The team will visit neighboring communities in order to see if they are engaged in improved
      sanitation practices, as a result of the intervention being carried out in the study
      communities. This will help to understand and document the full range of impact from CLTS,
      including spillover effects to neighboring communities that can be attributed to CLTS. The
      team will inquire about any formal request from neighboring communities to CLTS as well as
      informal adoption of CLTS practices that may have led communities to engage on the track
      towards ending open defecation. The question of spillover effects is distinct from the
      question of contamination in this sense that one would like to account for the effects on
      neighboring villages by adding it to the impact found for participating study communities
      All the previous PRAs (Participatory Rural Appraisals) conducted in CLTS interventions in
      South Asia point to the role of leaders as a key factor in the success of the intervention.
      This dimension seems to be crucial when looking at the issue of sustainability, e.g., why
      some villages succeed in maintaining ODF status after the end of the intervention while
      others fail. Descriptive evidence (Water and Sanitation Report, 2007) argues that lowering
      diarrhea incidence is only possible if the community is in fact ODF. Otherwise, even if most
      community members use toilets, diarrhea incidence is still very high. Information on
      community attributes will also be gathered in order to develop a deeper knowledge about
      which communities may be more likely to become ODF. For example, Chambers (2008) provide
      some characteristics that make the community more prone to successfully engage in CLTS
      programs, like settlement size, soil fertility, polluted water supply, high incidence of
      diarrhea, other health interventions in the community, etc. Those are key aspects that need
      to be systematized together with the quantitative evaluation explained above to recommend
      possible improvements to the design for the future.

      The two approaches mentioned above (random assignment with regression analysis and
      qualitative information) will allow the team to have a very complete and holistic evaluation
      using sound methodologies that will provide answers to issues related with the impact of the
      intervention in several dimensions and in issues related with sustainability too. Moreover,
      the evaluation will result in some new inputs to be included in the design in future
      programs, monitoring indicators and evaluation of similar interventions.

      This is one of the first evaluations using impact evaluation techniques with quantitative
      data [and random assignment] of CLTS programs all over the developing world. It will also
      complement already existing evidence. Another advantage of this evaluation is that it will
      look carefully at behavioral outcomes that are behind the adoption of better sanitation
      practices and that are often overlooked in evaluations related to sanitation, which tend to
      focus more on health outcomes. It is widely accepted that better sanitation improves health,
      yet there is still much debate over what a cost-effective way to deliver a sanitation
      intervention may be. Success in delivery will very much depend on whether the program is
      able to identify bottlenecks that impede adoption of better sanitation practices and whether
      it is able to solve the issues that are identified.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diarrhea</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants were followed two years after the baseline survey (a year after intervention)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>diarrheal illness for children under 2 and 5</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants were followed two years after the baseline survey (a year after intervention)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To check for consistency there are several mechanisms: (1) self-reported information- The mother/female caretaker was questioned regarding the health of children under the age of 5 years. In order to account for the possibility that individuals have different conceptions of  diarrhea, we will employ an image chart (&quot;stool chart&quot; ) that depicts images of feces ranging from severe diarrhea to constipation. Respondents were asked to point to the image that most closely resembles their last bowel movement (or their child's last bowel movement) ), (2) health post records, (3) random visits from enumerators to health posts, (4) maintaining a case registry for diarrhea in the participating villages.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>child anthropometrics</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants were followed two years after the baseline survey (a year after intervention)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The height and weight of each child under 5 will be measured in order to determine the impact of CLTS on child nutritional status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Psychological outcomes: knowledge, risk perceptions, self efficacy;</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants were followed two years after the baseline survey (a year after intervention)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Community outcomes: level of cooperation and trust, social cohesion, wealth disparities, leadership, speed of diffusion of the new practice of latrine use within social networks;</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants were followed two years after the baseline survey (a year after intervention)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Experimental games can be used to estimate the level of cooperation within communities. A first goal would be to test if and how communication and public exposure of contributions for a public good to the group scrutiny affects the level of cooperation. A public good experiment involves providing endowments to players and asking them to choose how much of their resources to invest in a group project. When making their decision, they know that the experimenter will collect all contributions, double the amount and redistribute it among participants. They are asked to all put their chosen amount in an envelope at the same time and without discussing it. In this situation, no one, except the experimenter, knows how much each of them contributes, but they do know the total contribution. An interesting variation on this game is to let the group members talk before they fill their envelop. Another variation consists in changing the nature of contributions from private to public.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Non-health outcomes: school attendance</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants were followed two years after the baseline survey (a year after intervention)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For children at school age. Similarly, we plan to use (1) self reported information, (2) random visits by study staff at schools on a given day, and (3) school records.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Non-health outcomes: time use</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants were followed two years after the baseline survey (a year after intervention)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>It is believed improved sanitation produces substantial time savings for the households, which can be used to increase labor supply, domestic work or time spent at school. The investigators will look at the effect on time allocation of adults and children, including the time burden for caring for sick children/relatives.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24000</enrollment>
  <condition>Diarrhea</condition>
  <condition>Respiratory Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CLTS communities</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>60 Communities randomly assigned to CLTS intervention, carried out by Unicef</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rural communities</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>60 Communities will participate from CLTS and 60 will be kept as controls.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CLTS</intervention_name>
    <description>The goal of CLTS is to obtain Open Defecation Free (ODF) villages. CLTS aims to trigger the community's desire for change, propel them into action and encourage innovation, mutual support and appropriate local solutions, in order to foster greater ownership and sustainability. The phases are: pre-triggering (a group of trained-CLTS people visit the community and request a date to discuss sanitation-related issues for the following days), triggering (people are made to express their views on sanitation issues and their needs), monitoring (involves visits of the community twice a week for a period of 1-3 months) and certification (an external committee evaluates the village for certification as an ODF community).</description>
    <arm_group_label>CLTS communities</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Community Led Total Sanitation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Villages located in rural Mali.

          -  CLTS targets small villages (less than 4500 inhabitants).

          -  Open defecation is present

        Exclution criteria:

        -Villages where CLTS is already in place
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria L. Alzua, Ph.D Econ</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad Nacional de La Plata</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rural Communities in Mali</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bamako</city>
        <state>Koulikoro</state>
        <country>Mali</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mali</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 16, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidad Nacional de La Plata</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Maria Laura Alzua</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator - Prof</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>sanitation</keyword>
  <keyword>diarrhea incidence and prevalence</keyword>
  <keyword>health</keyword>
  <keyword>social networks</keyword>
  <keyword>Cooperation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Tract Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
