<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="163252">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02065596</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CASE12Z13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02065596</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant for Sickle Cell Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant for Sickle Cell Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase I/II study of patients with sickle cell disease. It aims to find out if
      people with sickle cell disease can be cured by changing their immune system before they
      have blood stem cell transplants. Doctors will give patients a new drug (fludarabine) to see
      if this drug changes patients immune system and reduces the patient's cells (host) from
      rejecting donor cells (graft) after the patient gets a Hematopoietic (blood) stem cell
      transplant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objective

      1. To evaluate the safety and feasibility of hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT) after
      treatment with fludarabine in adult patients with Sickle Cell Disease (SCD).

      Secondary Objective(s), in HSCT for SCD

        1. To evaluate the rates of disease-free and overall survival in both MSD and alternate
           graft donor (MUD, haploidentical, or cord blood-derived) recipients

        2. To evaluate fertility in matched sibling and alternate-donor graft recipients

        3. To evaluate GVHD rates in MSD and Alternate Graft Donor recipients in SCD.

        4. To evaluate cerebral, pulmonary, renal, and generalized vasculopathy before and after
           HSCT in SCD.

        5. To evaluate hematopoiesis and erythropoiesis before and before HSCT in SCD.

        6. Modulation of SCD Phenotype by Allogeneic Transplantation We will perform rigorous
           clinical follow-up, per routine care, to evaluate those consequences of SCD that will
           be modified by allogeneic transplantation in the short-term (4-12 weeks), in the
           medium-term (12-24 weeks) and in the long-term (&gt;24 weeks). Short-term changes would
           include disappearance of stress hematopoiesis and erythropoiesis; medium- and long-term
           changes would include effects on pain, fertility (TSH, LH), cognition (routine
           cognitive assessments), and end-organ damage (including urine albumin-to-creatinine
           ratios and tricuspid regurgitant jet velocities, as indicated).

      Procedures:

      The study will start with at least 10 and up to 25 patients. They will be given the lowest
      starting dose of fludarabine. This is done to make sure it is safe. Researchers will watch
      the patients during what is called the dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) period. Their safety
      will be monitored by a Safety Monitoring Committee, which is made up of people who run
      research studies. The study will not take new patients until the DLT period is done.

      If at least 3 of the 10 patients enrolled do not benefit, the maximum tolerated dose (MTD)
      will be considered exceeded. After the DLT period is complete, patients will receive a stem
      cell transplant from a genetically matched donor. Patients will be continued to be monitored
      for a year after the transplant.

      To prepare for the transplant patients will have to undergo the following treatments:

        -  an exchange transfusion

        -  a stem cell graft infusion from either a:

             -  perfectly matched sibling donor (called MSD),

             -  perfectly matched but unrelated donor (called MUD),

             -  a half-matched related donor (called Haploidentical), or

             -  a cord blood donor

        -  rabbit antithymocyte globulin (ATG)

        -  cytoxan  (a type of chemotherapy)

        -  Fludarabine (you get this medicine a few weeks before transplant and again, as part of
           the routine chemotherapy treatment). This is the main drug being studies in this
           research

        -  total body irradiation (also called TBI)

        -  tacrolimus, mycophenolate (MMF) and/or methotrexate (MTX). These drugs will weaken your
           immune system. They are given to lower your chances of getting GVHD and rejecting the
           donor cells.

      Patients will be in the study for approximately 14 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Probability of Engraftment</measure>
    <time_frame>42 Days after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of patients with engraftment (as defined as recovery of ANC to 500 cells per cubic mm) compared to the total number of patients treated as a function of the patient's age.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean time to engraftment</measure>
    <time_frame>42 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The average time to for engraftment (as defined as recovery of ANC to 500 cells per cubic mm) to occur  estimated using a Kaplan-Meier curve as a function of the patient's age.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Progression</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The average time (in days) to disease progression estimated using a Kaplan-Meier curve</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The average time (in days) patients are alive after treatment estimated using a Kaplan-Meier curve</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Follicular Stimulating Hormone Levels</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated difference in changes in Follicular Stimulating Hormone Levels after transplant, among patients with matched sibling donors compared to patients with alternate donors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Luteinizing Hormone Levels</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated difference in changes in Luteinizing hormone Levels after transplant, among patients with matched sibling donors compared to patients with alternate donors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Testosterone Levels</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated difference in changes in Testosterone Levels after transplant, among male patients with matched sibling donors compared to patients with alternate donors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Graft versus Host Disease</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number patients with Grade III-IVGraft versus Host Disease as defined by CTCAE v4.0 in matched sibling compared to alternate-donor graft recipients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cerebral Vasculopathy</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vasculopathy may clinically manifest as a history of stroke. The difference in number of strokes before and after transplantation will be evaluated with paired statistical tests (t-test or McNemar).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal Vasculopathy</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vasculopathy may clinically manifest as macroalbuminuria (≥300mg/g urinary albumin-to-creatinine ratio) or as a depressed estimated glomerular flow rate (eGFR). Evidence of renal vasculopathy before and after transplantation will be evaluated with paired statistical tests (t-test or McNemar).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary Vasculopathy</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vasculopathy may clinically manifest as pulmonary arterial systolic pressure (PASP) by echo. Difference in PASP levels before and after transplantation will be evaluated with paired statistical tests (t-test or McNemar).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hematopoiesis</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Levels of stress hematopoiesis will be assessed by measuring telomere lengths with PCR before and after transplantation. These levels will be evaluated with paired statistical tests (t-test or McNemar).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Erythropoiesis</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Levels of stress erythropoiesis will be assessed by measuring telomere lengths with PCR before and after transplantation. These levels will be evaluated with paired statistical tests (t-test or McNemar).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Disease</condition>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Anemia</condition>
  <condition>SCD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immunomodulation with Fludarabine prior to HSCT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fludarabine given beginning at 25mgm/m2 three times per day. Patients may be escalated up to 25mgm/m2 five times per day depending on dose-limiting toxicity</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>the study will begin with enrollment of an initial safety cohort of at least 10 subjects at the lowest dose, after which enrollment will pause until the dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) period has been completed. If a patient experiences DLT, defined as failure to engraft. In which case, the patient may be advanced to two higher doses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immunomodulation with Fludarabine prior to HSCT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fludarabine monophosphate</other_name>
    <other_name>Fludarabine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant (HSCT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Three weeks after Immunomodulation patients will be infused with matched bone marrow from a sibling, unrelated donor, haploidentical donor, or cord blood. Patients will be followed for the following year.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immunomodulation with Fludarabine prior to HSCT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have one of the following inherited hemoglobin gene disorders:

               1. Hemoglobin SS

               2. Hemoglobin SC

               3. Hemoglobin S-Beta-zero-Thalassemia or

               4. Hemoglobin S-Beta-plus Thalassemia

          -  Disease Morbidity

          -  For matched sibling donor grafts (low-risk e.g., matched sibling donor), patients
             must have evidence for morbid disease that has failed conventional therapy:

               1. 2 or more painful episode/year (requiring Emergency Department or inpatient
                  care) x 3 years or

               2. 2 or more diagnoses of Acute Chest Syndrome within 5 years, or

               3. 2-year mortality 5-10%

          -  Baseline LDH&gt;600 IU or

          -  history of sepsis, with or without a WBC&gt;13.5, or

          -  on chronic transfusions

          -  For alternate donor grafts (moderate risk e.g., haploidentical or matched unrelated
             donor), patients must have history of high-level vasculopathy:

               1. Urine Albumin to Creatinine Ratio of &gt;300mg/g or eGFR 50-90 ml/min x 2
                  evaluations within 3 months or

               2. history of overt clinical stroke, or progressive cerebral vasculopathy
                  radiographically or

               3. 2 or more diagnoses of Acute Chest Syndrome within 5 years, or

               4. *excessively morbid disease. These patients can be considered for moderate-risk
                  alternate donor transplants. The palliative nature of the transplant will be
                  explicit in the consent.

               5. 2-year mortality &gt;10-15%

             i. Baseline WBC&gt;13.5 and on chronic transfusions or baseline LDH&gt;600 or age &gt;35 yo,
             or ii. Baseline TRV ≥3 m/s, or iii. Chronic transfusion therapy and age &gt;35 yo or
             male gender, or iv. Baseline LDH&gt;600 and age &gt;35 yo or history of sepsis or v.
             history of sepsis and age &gt;35 yo or male gender.

          -  For alternate donor grafts (high risk or untested, e.g. umbilical cord blood),
             patients must have a &gt;15% risk of 2-year mortality:

               1. baseline TRV ≥3 m/s and baseline WBC &gt;13.5 or on chronic transfusions or history
                  of sepsis or age &gt;35 yo, or

               2. baseline WBC&gt;13.5 and chronic transfusions or baseline LDH&gt;600 or age &gt;35 yo or

               3. Age &gt;35 yo and chronic transfusions or

               4. Chronic transfusions and male gender.

          -  Available suitable donor

               1. 6/6 HLA-matched sibling donor (HLA A, B, and DRB1), bone marrow only

               2. 8/8 HLA-matched unrelated donor (HLA A, B, C, DRB1), bone marrow only

               3. 4/8, 5/8, 6/8, 7/8 Haploidentical donor, bone marrow only or

               4. Cord Blood, availability of 2 units with 6/8, 7/8, or 8/8 match (HLA-A, B, &amp; C)

          -  Patients must have adequate hematologic, hepatic, and renal function as defined
             below:

          -  Direct bilirubin within 1.5 X normal institutional limits

          -  ALT (SGPT) &lt; 2.5 X institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Creatinine clearance &gt;50 mL/min/1.73 m2 for patients with creatinine levels above
             institutional normal, using 4-value Cockcroft-Gault.

          -  Contraception/Child Bearing The effects of Fludarabine, cytoxan, ATG,
             tacrolimus/sirolimus and MTX are cumulatively known to be deleterious to the health
             of the developing human fetus.  For this reason, and because of teratogenic
             potential, all women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate
             contraception (double barrier method of birth control or abstinence) for the duration
             of study participation and for 12 months after completing treatment.

          -  Subjects must have the ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written
             informed consent document.

        Should a woman become pregnant or suspect that she is pregnant while she or her partner is
        participating in this study, she should inform the treating physician immediately.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  eGFR &lt;50 ml/min

          -  ≥2.0 liter-per-minute pm home oxygen requirement

          -  An estimated Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction ≤40% (echo or MUGA)

          -  Hepatic cirrhosis (Biopsy Proven)

          -  HIV positive, ineligible because of the increased risk of lethal infections when
             treated with marrow suppressive therapy.  Appropriate studies will be undertaken in
             patients receiving combination antiretroviral therapy when indicated

          -  Red cell alloimmunization to a degree that precludes extended transfusion

          -  Patients with uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to ongoing
             or active infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris,
             cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit
             compliance with study requirements

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women are excluded from this study because the
             immunomodulatory treatment, preparative regimen, and anti-GVH therapy contain agents
             with the potential for teratogenic or abortifacient effects. Further, this treatment,
             if indicated, is for a chronic condition, and can be delayed until the pregnancy has
             been successfully concluded. Because there is an unknown, but potential risk for
             adverse events in nursing infants secondary to treatment of the mother with,
             breastfeeding should be discontinued if the mother is treated with these agents.
             These potential risks may also apply to other agents used in this study.

          -  Subjects must not have evidence for impaired liver function due to iron overload, +/-
             hepatitis. Patients will be evaluated by hepatology if ferritin &gt;1500, if history of
             hepatitis, or ALT/ALP are &gt;1.5 X ULN.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jane Little, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jane Little, MD</last_name>
    <phone>216-844-1272</phone>
    <email>jane.little@uhhospitals.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Case Medical Center, University Hospitals Seidman Cancer Center, Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 18, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sickle Cell Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Sickle Cell Anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>GvHD</keyword>
  <keyword>fludarabine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Sickle Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine monophosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
