<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="11766">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02114606</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-3521</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02114606</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diagnosis and Monitoring of Eosinophilic Esophagitis Using the Cytosponge</brief_title>
  <official_title>Diagnosis and Monitoring of Eosinophilic Esophagitis Using the Cytosponge</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Cambridge</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>C.U.R.E.D. Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The current endoscopic methods for diagnosing and monitoring treatment response in
      Eosinophilic Esophagitis (EoE) are costly, inconvenient, and risky. Novel diagnostic methods
      are needed, and the minimally-invasive Cytosponge holds great promise. It has been shown to
      be safe and accurate in Barrett's esophagus, it has the advantage (over the string test) of
      obtaining a true tissue sample, and our preliminary data supports its further study in EoE.
      The proposed prospective cohort study, conducted by experts in esophageal diseases and EoE,
      will assess the accuracy of Cytosponge compared to endoscopy and biopsy in EoE, and
      determine the safety and acceptability of this technique. Use of the Cytosponge would
      fundamentally change the paradigm for clinical management of EoE by allowing collection of
      non-endoscopic esophageal biopsies, thus minimizing the need for invasive testing. It would
      also facilitate future genetic, mechanistic, and pathogenesis research in EoE.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study design overview (all Aims) This will be a prospective cohort study, with patient
      enrollment conducted at UNC and Mayo Clinic with sample analysis performed by the University
      of Cambridge. In Aim 1, patients with EoE will be enrolled, tissue will be obtained from
      both the Cytosponge and endoscopy, and the methods will be compared for a single time point
      to determine accuracy of Cytosponge for quantifying esophageal eosinophil counts. In Aim 2,
      the patients who are being treated will be followed and tissue will be assessed over time
      with both Cytosponge and endoscopy to determine the utility of Cytosponge for monitoring
      treatment response in patients with EoE. For all patients, safety will be monitored and
      subjects will complete a survey about the acceptability of Cytosponge (Aim 3).

      Cytosponge protocol:

      After the study has been explained and a patient provides informed consent, the Cytosponge
      will be administered prior to endoscopy by the research coordinator under physician
      supervision. The string, attached to a 3-inch cardboard tab, will be held loosely at the
      mouth by the coordinator, and the subject will swallow the sponge capsule with an ounce of
      water. The string will be held without tension to allow the capsule to advance into the
      stomach. Five minutes after ingestion, the back of the throat will be sprayed with 1%
      lidocaine spray, and the expanded sponge withdrawn by gentle traction on the string. After
      retrieval, the string is cut and the sponge (which contains the tissue specimen) is placed
      in a container, immersed in fixative, and stored in a refrigerator at 4°C. The fixative is
      then spun in a centrifuge, and the pelleted cells are embedded in a paraffin block using
      standard techniques.

      Upper endoscopy and biopsy:

      After the Cytosponge has been removed, the patient will undergo standard of care (routine
      care) upper endoscopy and biopsy, as clinically indicated. During this exam, we will record
      all endoscopic features of EoE, including rings, furrows, white plaques, decreased
      vascularity, and strictures. The severity of the endoscopy findings will be measured using
      the recently validated EREFS scoring system.23 Four esophageal biopsies will be taken both
      from the distal (5 cm above the gastro-esophageal junction) and proximal (15 cm above the
      gastro-esophageal junction) esophagus. This number of biopsies has been shown to maximize
      the diagnostic sensitivity for EoE.24

      Histology and eosinophil counts:

      All tissue samples from the Cytosponge and endoscopy will be coded with a subject's ID
      number, but will otherwise be masked for all clinical data, including EoE activity,
      symptoms, patient characteristics, and treatments prescribed. Using the paraffin blocks,
      pathology slides will be cut and the tissue processed with routine H&amp;E staining. The slides
      will then be digitized, and using the Aperio ImageScope (Aperio Technologies, Vista, CA),
      the maximum eosinophil density (eosinophils/mm2 [eos/mm2]) will be determined using our
      previously validated protocol.25 For purposes of comparison to previous studies, eosinophil
      density will then be converted to eosinophil counts (eos/hpf) for an assumed hpf size of
      0.24 mm2, the size of an average field as reported in the literature.26 The study
      pathologists from UNC and Mayo Clinic will review the specimens from their sites, and the
      study pathology from Cambridge will provide a second review of all specimens to ensure the
      most accurate quantification of eosinophil counts possible.

      Safety and accessibility assessments:

      Patients will be assessed at multiple points to determine the safety of the Cytosponge in
      EoE. We will assess for any symptoms or events as soon as the sponge capsule is swallowed,
      as well as immediately after the expanded sponge is removed. We will also contact them 1 and
      7 days after the endoscopy to assess for adverse events. For Aim 3, we will administer the
      acceptability survey at the 7 day follow-up point, so patients have adequate time to reflect
      on their experiences with both tissue collection approaches. In particular this survey will
      record the patient's experience with swallowing the Cytosponge, whether they would do it
      again, and whether they prefer the Cytosponge or endoscopy for diagnosis and monitoring of
      EoE.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cytosponge accuracy and utility</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The accuracy of Cytosponge for quantifying esophageal eosinophil counts in patients with active EoE (aim 1) and use in monitoring treatment response in patients with EoE (aim 2) will be assessed through comparing pathology from the Cytosponge with pathology from the gold standard of endoscopy with biopsy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cytosponge safety and acceptability</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days after baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Acceptability will be measured the Impact of Events Scale. This widely used scale was developed to assess the distress associated with a specific life event. It includes measures of both the intrusiveness of the event, and any avoidance responses by the subject in response to the event. The scale will be administrated both shortly after, and 7 days after, the sampling. In order to allow the subjects to have time to reflect on the experience and to compare with the EGD, the 7 day measurements will represent the primary acceptability outcome of the study. Secondary acceptability outcomes will include a visual analogue scale of acceptability of the Cytosponge, performed after the Cytosponge is administered. Also, the subject will be asked whether he/she would be willing to repeat the assay, and, assuming similar accuracy between Cytosponge and upper endoscopy, whether he/she would rather undergo surveillance by Cytosponge or standard esophagogastroduodenoscopy (EGD) with biopsies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Eosinophilic Esophagitis</condition>
  <condition>EoE</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aim 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who have been diagnosed with EoE as per recent guidelines, and who have active eosinophilia and active symptoms. This will include patients who are newly diagnosed with EoE, patients who have stopped treatment but have had a flare, or patients who have not responded to EoE treatment. Samples will be taken once at a single time point.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aim 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>To determine the utility of Cytosponge for monitoring treatment response in patients with EoE, we will enroll patients with EoE who are undergoing either topical steroid or dietary treatment. For subjects undergoing topical steroid treatment, they will be followed after they have received a course of either fluticasone or budesonide. For subjects undergoing dietary elimination, they will be followed after the initial elimination diet, as well as during the trigger identification phase when food groups are added back. Patients will be followed and tissue will be assessed over time with both Cytosponge and endoscopy; samples will be taken at up to 6 time points.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Paraffin embedded esophageal tissue samples obtained by the cytosponge.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients diagnosed with Eosinophilic Esophagitis (EoE) who are currently on treatment or
        are not currently being treated.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female subjects, age 18-80 years,

          -  Diagnosis of EoE with current active disease,

          -  Have previously and recently received an upper endoscopy during which absence of
             findings putting the subject at higher risk for these theoretical concerns
             (conditions such as varices and stricture) will be documented.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of esophageal stricture precluding passage of the endoscope or sponge,

          -  Pregnancy, or planned pregnancy during the course of the study,

          -  Any history of esophageal varices, liver impairment of moderate or worse severity
             (Child's- Pugh class B &amp; C) or evidence of varices noted on any past endoscopy,

          -  Any history of esophageal surgery, except for uncomplicated fundoplication

          -  History of coagulopathy, with INR&gt;1.3 and/or platelet count of &lt;75,000.

          -  Are not able to discontinue blood thinning medications such as aspirin, clopidogrel,
             and/or warfarin for 5 days prior and 7 days after procedures,

          -  Are allergic to local anesthetics such as lidocaine,

          -  Have not fasted the night before administration of the Cytosponge.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Evan Dellon, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UNC-Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Susan Moist, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>919-966-7655</phone>
    <email>susan_moist@med.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55902</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Debra Geno</last_name>
      <phone>507-538-0367</phone>
      <email>Geno.Debra@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Katzka, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27516</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan Moist, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>919-966-7655</phone>
      <email>susan_moist@med.unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Evan Dellon, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hirano I, Moy N, Heckman MG, Thomas CS, Gonsalves N, Achem SR. Endoscopic assessment of the oesophageal features of eosinophilic oesophagitis: validation of a novel classification and grading system. Gut. 2013 Apr;62(4):489-95. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2011-301817. Epub 2012 May 22.</citation>
    <PMID>22619364</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gonsalves N, Policarpio-Nicolas M, Zhang Q, Rao MS, Hirano I. Histopathologic variability and endoscopic correlates in adults with eosinophilic esophagitis. Gastrointest Endosc. 2006 Sep;64(3):313-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16923475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dellon ES, Fritchie KJ, Rubinas TC, Woosley JT, Shaheen NJ. Inter- and intraobserver reliability and validation of a new method for determination of eosinophil counts in patients with esophageal eosinophilia. Dig Dis Sci. 2010 Jul;55(7):1940-9. doi: 10.1007/s10620-009-1005-z. Epub 2009 Oct 15.</citation>
    <PMID>19830560</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dellon ES, Aderoju A, Woosley JT, Sandler RS, Shaheen NJ. Variability in diagnostic criteria for eosinophilic esophagitis: a systematic review. Am J Gastroenterol. 2007 Oct;102(10):2300-13. Epub 2007 Jul 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17617209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 8, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Eosinophilic Esophagitis</keyword>
  <keyword>EoE</keyword>
  <keyword>Cytosponge</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Esophagitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eosinophilic Esophagitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
