<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="122638">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01830972</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UX001-CL202</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01830972</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Open Label Phase 2 Extension Study of Higher Dose Sialic Acid (ER Tablets + IR Capsules) in Patients With GNE Myopathy</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label Phase 2 Extension Study to Evaluate the Long Term Safety and Efficacy of Sialic Acid-Extended Release (SA-ER) Tablets and Sialic Acid-Immediate Release (SA-IR) Capsules in Patients With GNE Myopathy or Hereditary Inclusion Body Myopathy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ultragenyx Pharmaceutical Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ultragenyx Pharmaceutical Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      GNE myopathy or hereditary inclusion body myopathy (HIBM) is a severe progressive metabolic
      myopathy caused by a defect in the biosynthetic pathway for sialic acid (SA). The purpose of
      the study is to measure long term safety and the effects of Sialic Acid-Extended Release
      (SA-ER) tablets and Sialic Acid-Immediate Release (SA-IR) capsules.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      GNE myopathy or hereditary inclusion body myopathy (HIBM) is a severe progressive metabolic
      myopathy caused by a defect in the biosynthetic pathway for sialic acid (SA). Substrate
      replacement therapy is a potential therapeutic strategy based on the success of replacing
      missing SA and reducing muscle disease in a relevant mouse model of the human disease
      (Malicdan et al., 2009). Successful use of SA replacement therapy in humans is believed to
      depend upon providing steady long-term exposure to the compound in an extended release form
      (such as Sialic Acid-Extended Release [SA-ER]), given SA's short half-life. Following a
      Phase 1 study to establish the pharmacokinetics for SA-ER and an ongoing Phase 2 study to
      assess the pharmacodynamic effect of restoring sialylation of muscle by treatment over 48
      weeks, Ultragenyx is conducting this study to evaluate the long term safety and efficacy of
      an increased dosed of SA-ER combined with Sialic Acid-Immediate Release (SA-IR) capsules as
      treatment, for up to 36 additional months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess long-term safety of SA-ER and SA-IR in HIBM subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">56</enrollment>
  <condition>GNE Myopathy</condition>
  <condition>HIBM</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>open label, 12000 mg/day</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SA-ER tablets and SA-IR capsules</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>open label, 12000 mg/day</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Enrollment in, and successful completion of the UX001-CL201 protocol OR (for 10
             treatment naïve subjects):

               -  Have a confirmed diagnosis of GNE Myopathy

               -  Aged 18 -65 years of age, inclusive

               -  Able to walk ≥ 200 meters and &lt; 80% of predicted normal during the 6MWT
                  (orthotics and assistive devices allowed)

          -  Must be willing and able to provide written, signed informed consent after the nature
             of the study has been explained, and prior to any research-related procedures

          -  Must be willing and able to comply with all study procedures

          -  Sexually active subjects must be willing to use an acceptable method of contraception
             while participating in the study

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test at Baseline and
             be willing to have additional pregnancy tests during the study.  Females considered
             not of childbearing potential include those who have been in menopause for at least
             two years, or have had tubal ligation at least one year prior to Baseline, or who
             have had total hysterectomy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of any investigational product (other than SA-ER tablets) to treat GNE Myopathy

          -  Ingestion of N-acetyl-D-mannosamine (ManNAc) or similar SA-producing compounds

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding at Baseline or planning to become pregnant (self or
             partner) at any time during the study• Has had any hypersensitivity to SA or its
             excipients that, in the judgment of the investigator, places the subject at increased
             risk for adverse effects

          -  Have any co-morbid conditions, including unstable major organ-system disease(s) that
             in the opinion of the investigator, places the subject at increased risk of
             complications, interferes with study participation or compliance, or confounds study
             objectives.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NYU Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hadassah University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 10, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
