<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="18294">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01876810</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>082/2012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01876810</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT01900145</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Initial Screening of Gemfibrozil as a Novel Treatment for Tobacco Addiction</brief_title>
  <official_title>Testing the PPAR Hypothesis of Nicotine Dependence in Humans: Gemfibrozil as a Novel Treatment for Tobacco Addiction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate the effect of gemfibrozil on nicotine
      reinforcement and cue-elicited craving. Other objectives of this study include screening for
      the ability of gemfibrozil to aid smoking abstinence during a brief quit attempt and
      examining the validity of using laboratory measures of tobacco dependence to predict smoking
      abstinence. It is hypothesized that gemfibrozil will result in diminished nicotine
      reinforcement, an attenuated response to smoking cues, and an increase in smoking abstinence
      compared with placebo. It is also hypothesized that the laboratory measures will prove valid
      in predicting abstinence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Animal studies have shown that drugs acting as agonists at alpha-type peroxisome
      proliferator-activated receptors (PPARα) suppress nicotine self-administration, attenuate
      relapse to nicotine-seeking behavior in the reinstatement model, and block nicotine-induced
      neuronal firing and dopamine release in reward pathways of the brain. These results have
      been demonstrated with synthetic PPARα agonists and with fibrate drugs (clofibrate,
      fenofibrate), which are used clinically to treat elevated cholesterol and triglycerides
      levels. Thus, PPARα is a potential target for the treatment of tobacco addiction. This is
      the first human study to investigate whether a fibrate drug (gemfibrozil, Lopid®) can reduce
      nicotine reward and aid smokers in becoming tobacco abstinent.

      The objectives of this study are:

        1. to investigate the effect of gemfibrozil on laboratory measures of nicotine
           reinforcement and cue-elicited craving

        2. to screen for the ability of gemfibrozil to aid smoking abstinence during a brief quit
           attempt

        3. to examine the validity of using laboratory measures of tobacco dependence to predict
           smoking abstinence and possible gemfibrozil-related increases in smoking abstinence

      This outpatient study will be conducted at the Center for Addiction and Mental Health (CAMH)
      in Toronto, Canada. This site will enroll 40 adult smokers who intend to quit smoking in the
      next 3 months.

      The study is a double-blind, placebo-controlled, crossover design comparing the effects of
      gemfibrozil and placebo. The study will comprise two 2-week medication phases with a washout
      period of at least one week.  At the end of the first medication week laboratory measures
      will be taken and during the second medication week participants will make a quit attempt
      and abstinence will be assessed.

      Outcome measures include laboratory assessments of nicotine reinforcement and smoking cue
      reactivity. The measure of nicotine reinforcement is the percentage of nicotine cigarette
      puffs chosen during a forced-choice task. Measures of cue reactivity include tobacco
      craving, mood, and autonomic responsivity. Other measures are days of smoking abstinence
      during the quit-attempt weeks. Abstinence is assessed by self-reports of no smoking and by
      breath carbon monoxide &lt; 5 ppm on clinic visits. Other assessments of abstinence include
      self-reported tobacco craving and withdrawal.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Nicotine Reinforcement and Smoking Cue Reactivity</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of nicotine cigarette puffs chosen during a forced-choice task and tobacco craving, mood, and autonomic responsivity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Smoking abstinence during quit-attempt weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Self-reports of no smoking and breath carbon monoxide &lt; 5 ppm. Also assessed by self-reported tobacco craving and withdrawal.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Nicotine Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gemfibrozil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>600 mg of gemfibrozil (one capsule) twice daily for two weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One lactose pill twice a day for two weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gemfibrozil</intervention_name>
    <description>600 mg of gemfibrozil (one capsule) twice daily for two weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gemfibrozil</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lopid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>One lactose pill twice a day for two weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo pill</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lactose</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  19-65 year old males and females

          -  smoking at least 10 cigarettes per day for at least 2 years

          -  intend to quit smoking within the next 3 months

          -  medically and psychologically healthy as determined by screening criteria

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  currently attempting to quit smoking

          -  treatment for tobacco addiction in the past 3 months

          -  use of nicotine replacement products, bupropion, or varenicline in the past 3 months
             as an aid to quit or reduce smoking

          -  use of any oral tobacco product in the past 3 months

          -  history of drug or alcohol dependence within last 5 years

          -  consumption of more than 15 alcoholic drinks per week on average during the past
             month

          -  use of any illicit drug more than once per week on average during the past month

          -  current use of gemfibrozil or other fibrate medication

          -  current use of any medication that is contraindicated for gemfibrozil or that would
             interfere with the protocol in the opinion of MAI/QI. This includes, but is not
             limited to, anticoagulants, statins, other fibrates, other lipid-lowering agents such
             as niacin or herbal remedies, and any oral or injected medications for diabetes.

          -  any pre-existing gall-bladder disease or operation in the past 12 months

          -  any history of or current cardiovascular, liver, hepatic or renal disease

          -  diabetes

          -  pregnant, nursing, or become pregnant during the study

          -  use of psychoactive drugs or medications as revealed by urine toxicology
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bernard Le Foll, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marie Gendy</last_name>
    <phone>416-535-8501</phone>
    <phone_ext>36032</phone_ext>
    <email>marie.gendy@camh.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Patricia DiCiano, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>416-535-8501</phone>
    <phone_ext>34002</phone_ext>
    <email>Patricia.DiCiano@camh.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5S 1S8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bernard Le Foll, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre of Addiction and Mental Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5S 2S1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marie Gendy</last_name>
      <phone>416-535-8501</phone>
      <phone_ext>36032</phone_ext>
      <email>marie.gendy@camh.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Patricia DiCiano, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>416-535-8501</phone>
      <phone_ext>34002</phone_ext>
      <email>paricia.diciano@camh.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bernard LeFoll, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.camh.net/research</url>
    <description>Information about research at the Centre for Addiction and Mental Health, Canada's largest mental health and addiction teaching</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bernard Le Foll</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Scientist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gemfibrozil</keyword>
  <keyword>Nicotine Dependence</keyword>
  <keyword>Smoking</keyword>
  <keyword>Cigarettes</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tobacco Use Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gemfibrozil</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
