<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="25177">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02062814</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02062814</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 2 Randomized, Controlled, Blinded Study Omalizumab With Oral Food Immunotherapy in Children and Adults With Multiple Food Allergies</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Randomized, Controlled, Blinded Study in a Single Center Using Omalizumab With Oral Food Immunotherapy in Children and Adults With Multiple Food Allergies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To develop a potentially curative therapy for patients with multi food allergy.We
      hypothesize that study subjects with multi food allergy who receive a combination of
      amalizumab and multi oral food therapy (OIT) can be rapidly desensitized and tolerate higher
      doses of food with fewer overall reactions than those who receive placebo and OIT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Our phase 1 study results show that multiple oral immunotherapy given in the same method
      with omalizumab can be safe and show trends towards efficacy (attachment 3). Therefore, a
      phase 2 randomized, controlled, blinded study has been proposed to further test safety and
      efficacy in a larger group of subjects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of omalizumbab treated subjects who have the ability to tolerate an oral dose of 4000mg of each food protein 6 weeks after discontinuing omalizumab.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 25</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Immune System Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>omalizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>45 pts will receive study drug. Study drug will be dosed per Genentech Global Dosing schedule.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>15 pts will receive placebo study drug, 45 will receive omalizumbab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>omalizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Xolair will be randomized to 45 participants, and 15 pts will receive placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>omalizumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>xolair</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1.Moderate to severe peanut and/or egg and/or milk and/or tree nut and/or seed
             allergic subjects between the ages of 4 to 55 years old.

             2.Sensitivity to food allergen will be documented by a positive skin prick test
             result (see Appendix for details) or allergen-specific ImmunoCAP IgE level, with 7
             kU/L as a lower limit of eligibility.

             3.Sensitivity to food allergen based on a double-blind, placebo-controlled, oral food
             challenge (DBPCFC), at maximum of cumulative 182.7 mg of food allergen protein dose
             (see Appendix for details).

             4.All female subjects of child-bearing potential will be required to provide a human
             chorionic gonadotropin urine sample for pregnancy testing that must be negative 48
             hours before being allowed to participate in the study.

             5.Subjects must plan to remain in the study area during the trial. 6.Subjects must be
             trained on the proper use of the EpiPen (see Appendix) to be allowed to enroll in the
             study.

             7.All female subjects of child-bearing potential must be compliant with a
             medically-approved method of contraception (please see Pregnancy section under
             Patient Disposition in this IND document)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No absolute contraindications are known. However, the risk of serious systemic
             anaphylactic reactions to food allergens suggests a number of preexisting conditions
             that should be considered relative contraindications. Among those conditions are
             acute infections, autoimmune disease, severe cardiac disease, and treatment with
             beta-adrenergic antagonistic drugs (beta-blockers).

               1. Subjects with a total IgE at screening of &gt;2,000 kU/L

               2. Previous reaction to omalizumab

               3. Subjects having a history of severe anaphylaxis to food allergens that will be
                  desensitized in this study requiring intubation or admission to an ICU, frequent
                  allergic or non-allergic urticaria, or history consistent with poorly controlled
                  persistent asthma.

               4. Subjects with unstable angina, significant arrhythmia, uncontrolled
                  hypertension, chronic sinusitis, or other chronic or immunological diseases
                  that, in the judgment of the investigator, might interfere with the evaluation
                  or administration of the test drug or pose additional risk to the subject (e.g.,
                  gastrointestinal or gastroesophageal disease, chronic infections, scleroderma,
                  hepatic and gallbladder disease, chronic non-allergic pulmonary disease).

               5. Subjects with an FEV1 or PEF less than 80% predicted (moderate persistent
                  asthma) with or without controller medication (if able to perform the maneuver)
                  at screening, an oral desensitization visit, or a food challenge visit.

               6. Subjects who are current users of oral, intramuscular, or intravenous
                  corticosteroids, tricyclic antidepressants, or are taking a beta-blocker (oral
                  or topical).

               7. Subjects routinely using medication that could induce adverse gastrointestinal
                  reactions during the study.

               8. Subjects refusing to sign the EpiPen Training Form (see Appendix).

               9. Women who are pregnant or breast feeding.

              10. Subjects with a history of oat allergy (since oat is the placebo agent in the
                  DBPCFC, as per IND 14477) .

              11. Subjects with other food allergies must agree to eliminate these other food
                  items from their diet so as not to confound the safety and efficacy data from
                  the study.

              12. Subjects with a diagnosis of eosinophilic esophagitis, eosinophilic colitis, or
                  eosinophilic gastritis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kari Nadeau, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tina Dominguez, PA</last_name>
    <email>safar_inquiry@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford Alliance for Food Allergy Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mountain View</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94040</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kari Nadeau, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://foodallergies.stanford.edu/research/</url>
    <description>Information on Stanford Alliance Food Allergy Research</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 4, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple food allergies</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Food Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immune System Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Omalizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
