<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="156229">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01684592</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R34DA032683-01A1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01684592</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phone-Based Postpartum Continuing Care for Smoking Cessation</brief_title>
  <acronym>PPCC</acronym>
  <official_title>Phone-Based Postpartum Continuing Care: Smoking Cessation Beginning in Pregnancy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chestnut Health Systems</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Maryland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chestnut Health Systems</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Smoking is a leading cause of death and other negative health outcomes. While a high
      percentage of women quit smoking during pregnancy, the majority relapse in the first 6
      months postpartum. We propose developing and pilot testing a phone-based postpartum
      continuing care (PPCC) protocol based on existing evidence-based approaches to increase
      smoking cessation, reduce relapse, increase early re-intervention, and reduce infant
      exposure to environmental tobacco smoke in the postpartum period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The large majority of women who quit smoking during pregnancy relapse in the first six
      months postpartum, highlighting a need for effective postpartum continuing care that
      supports women through the challenging postpartum period when stress is high and motivation
      to stay quit may decline. Existing relapse prevention interventions (typically delivered
      during pregnancy) have been found to be of little benefit during the postpartum period,
      suggesting the need for a more formal continuing care approach. Phone-based protocols for
      smoking cessation have been widely disseminated and effective because they address the need
      for flexible access, but are passive and not typically utilized by women in the postpartum
      period.

      The proposed pilot study will develop and test a Phone-based Postpartum Continuing Care
      (PPCC) model that draws from existing evidence-based protocols--the 5 A's and Recovery
      Management Checkups (RMC)-- shown to be effective with other populations. The experimental
      PPCC will reinforce the importance of abstinence, relapse prevention, and reduced smoking
      through proactive re-intervention (i.e., RMC) with the 5 A's at times when postpartum women
      are more likely to relapse, and provide education and monitoring of the infant's direct and
      indirect exposure to nicotine through breastfeeding and secondhand smoke. We will evaluate
      PPCC's effectiveness relative to a passive referral to a 24/7 hotline, which is current
      standard care.

      Approximately one hundred thirty women in their first or second trimester of pregnancy who
      were nicotine-dependent in the past year, currently smoke, or quit within the past 90 days
      will be recruited at their first prenatal appointment at the Maryland Women's Center (MWC)
      in Baltimore, Maryland. All women will receive the clinic's standard of care for smoking
      cessation--the 5 A's --during pregnancy from their physician. Half will be randomly assigned
      to an experimental group getting PPCC for 6 months postpartum and half to a control group
      receiving only a referral to a passive 24/7 state quit line postpartum. It is expected that
      in the 6 months following childbirth women in the experimental PPCC (relative to those in
      the control group) will: a) smoke fewer cigarettes, b) smoke fewer days, c) go longer before
      postpartum relapse, d) have less time between relapse and talking to a health professional
      about smoking, e) have less time between relapse and resumption of abstinence , f) smoke
      fewer times while breastfeeding, g) smoke fewer times while in the same room as the infant,
      and h) reduce their infant's cotinine levels.

      The aims of this pilot project are to develop PPCC from existing evidence-based approaches,
      demonstrate the feasibility of implementing the PPCC intervention with at least 80%
      compliance and at least 80% follow-up at each wave, and evaluate the effect size associated
      with receiving standard care vs. standard care + PPCC in order to understand the promise of
      and appropriate power required for a larger clinical trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in self-reported cigarettes per day smoked at 6 months postpartum</measure>
    <time_frame>Baby's birth and 6 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Days of self-reported smoking multiplied by the average number of self-reported times they smoke per day.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in self-reported cigarettes per day smoked at 3 months postpartum</measure>
    <time_frame>Baby's birth and 3 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Days of self-reported smoking multiplied by the average number of self-reported times they smoke per day</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in number of days smoked cigarettes at 3 months postpartum</measure>
    <time_frame>Baby's birth and 3 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Days in past 90 days minus days of any tobacco use (regardless of frequency of use). Urine cotinine levels will asses the validity of self reported abstinence at measurement points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in number of days smoked cigarettes at 6 months postpartum</measure>
    <time_frame>Baby's birth and 6 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Days in past 90 days minus days of any tobacco use (regardless of frequency of use). Urine cotinine levels will asses the validity of self reported abstinence at measurement points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Days before relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Days from quit date to first use of any tobacco (including 0 for same day). Quit date is checked against prior self reports, positive cotinine, and records.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time between Relapse and talking to a health professional about smoking</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The days between the first day smoking after at least 7 days of abstinence to the first time they talk to a health professional (either physician, quitline, or PPCC counselor)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time between Relapse and the Resumption of Abstinence</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Days between first use of tobacco after quit date to the first period of 7 days without use.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Times mother smoked while breastfeeding</measure>
    <time_frame>Baby's birth to 6 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Based on the days of smoking while breastfeeding (or within 30 minutes of breastfeeding) times the frequency of use on day.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Times mother smoked in the room with infant</measure>
    <time_frame>Baby's birth to 6 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Based on the days of smoking in the room times the frequency of number of times smoked in the room on a day.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cotinine level of the infant</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Based on NicCheck I urine cotinine test conducted with infant at 6 months postpartum using the &quot;cotton roll&quot; method of urine collection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">130</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking Cessation</condition>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard care for smokers during pregnancy and referral to 24/7 quitline postpartum (passive)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care plus PPCC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard care for smoking during pregnancy and proactive phone-based postpartum continuing care (PPCC) for 6 months postpartum</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Phone-based postpartum continuing care</intervention_name>
    <description>PPCC Counselors will make initial contact with participants in the experimental group at 36 weeks gestation (i.e., one week prior to full-term), will call again within one week after the baby's birth, and eight additional times over the course of the first six months postpartum. The PPCC protocol will be developed based on the 5 A's (standard of care during pregnancy) and the Recovery Management Checkup model where relapse is expected and efforts are made to take a more proactive approach to identify women who are having cravings or have relapsed and re-intervene with them as soon as possible to assist them in regaining smoking abstinence. Women in the experimental group will also have the option of calling the PPCC line 24 hours a day, 7 days a week.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care plus PPCC</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PPCC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard care</intervention_name>
    <description>All women will receive the standard of care approach (5 A's and referral to a 24/7 quit line postpartum) from MWC during pregnancy. The 5 A's brief intervention was modified by ACOG for use with pregnant women and is recommended to help pregnant women quit smoking. It includes the following steps: Ask about tobacco use, Advise to quit, Assess willingness to make a quit attempt, Assist in quit attempt, and Arrange follow-up.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care plus PPCC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  first or second trimester of pregnancy

          -  age 18 or older

          -  self-reported tobacco use in the past 90 days or nicotine-dependence in the past year

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  intend to terminate their pregnancy

          -  intend to move out of the city within the next 12 months

          -  are unable to provide informed consent and participate in English
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Victoria H Coleman-Cowger, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chestnut Health Systems</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mishka Terplan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Maryland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chestnut Global Partners</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bloomington</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>61701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maryland Women's Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coleman-Cowger VH. Smoking cessation intervention for pregnant women: a call for extension to the postpartum period. Matern Child Health J. 2012 Jul;16(5):937-40.</citation>
    <PMID>21710186</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 11, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>smoking cessation</keyword>
  <keyword>relapse prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>postpartum</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Smoking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
