<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="80581">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01870947</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CASE5811</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01870947</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assisted Exercise in Obese Endometrial Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>REWARD (Revving-Up Exercise for Sustained Weight Loss by Altering Neurological Reward and Drive): A Pilot Study of Assisted Exercise in Obese Endometrial Cancer Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an assisted exercise trial involving exercise on a stationary bike, brain imaging
      and DNA(genetics)sampling. The purpose of this study is to find out if performing a
      progressive, supervised assisted exercise program on a stationary bike improves quality of
      life, increases motivation to continue to exercise, improves dietary behavior and leads to
      sustained weight loss in women who have had early-stage endometrial cancer. Questionnaires
      will be used to assess exercise motivation and dietary behavior. Brain's responses to
      different visual images will also be assessed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objective:

      To evaluate changes in body weight, fitness, bi-manual dexterity, exercise motivation and
      self-reported eating behavior (via questionnaires) before and after a 16-week exercise
      intervention (EOT)and 4 weeks post-EOT in obese EC patients who will be randomized to
      perform 'assisted', voluntary or no exercise (healthy living educational information only).

      Secondary Objective:

      To objectively examine food behavior as determined by neuronal response to high- versus
      low-calorie visual stimuli under fasted (hunger) and fed (satiated) states in brain regions
      of interest (reward and motivation circuitry) using blood oxygenation level dependent (BOLD)
      functional MRI before and after a 16-week exercise intervention (EOT) and 4 weeks
      post-intervention (EOT+4) in obese EC patients performing 'assisted', voluntary or no
      exercise (healthy living educational information only).

      Patients will be randomized to receive either the assisted exercise (n=10), voluntary
      exercise (n=10) or no exercise (n=6) group. Subjects in the voluntary group will exercise on
      a stationary recumbent exercise cycle and pedal at their preferred rate. Subjects in the
      assisted exercise group will cycle on the same stationary exercise bike; however, a motor
      will provide assistance to the patient in order to maintain a pedaling rate 35% greater than
      their voluntary rate. Subjects in the exercise groups will complete 45 minute to 1-hour
      sessions, three times per week for eight weeks. The control group will be asked to complete
      all exercise, body composition and fMRI testing similar to the exercise groups. Patients in
      the No Exercise/Educational Information Only control group will complete the same set of
      questionnaires as the patients in the exercise groups.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight change from pre- to post-intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks after exercise intervention (EOT)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Body Composition from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>at 4 weeks after exercise intervention(EOT)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Body fat, lean mass and bone mass will be measured with a Lunar iDXA™ (GE Healthcare, Madison, WI. BMI will be computed (weight in kg divided by square of height in meters) and categorized as: &lt; 18.5 (underweight), 18.5 to 24.9 (normal weight), 25.0 to 29.9 (overweight)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Motivation to Exercise from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks after exercise intervention (EOT)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate motivation to exercise using the Exercise Motivations Inventory (EMI-2) 122 and the Intrinsic Motivational Inventory (IMI) modified for exercise. Past physical activity habits will be assessed with the Godin Leisure-Time Exercise (LSI) questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Eating Behavior from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks after exercise intervention (EOT)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Eating behavior will be assessed using the Three-Factor Eating Questionnaire (TFEQ). The TFEQ includes 51 items and addresses three dimensions of human eating behavior; restraint, disinhibition, and perceived hunger.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Quality of Life (QoL)from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks after exercise intervention (EOT)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - General (FACT-G) is a 27-item core questionnaire evaluating various domains of QoL including, physical, functional, family-social, and emotional well-being. The FACT-En is a 16-item subscale specific for endometrial cancer (EC) and assesses hormone withdrawal, pelvic symptoms, and possible adjuvant therapy side effects. Short-form Medical Outcomes (SF-36) consists of 36 questions scored on a Likert scale, producing overall physical and mental component summary measures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Depression from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks after exercise intervention (EOT)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Beck Depression Inventory (BDI) is a 21-item, Likert-scaled instrument of depressive symptoms that is well-validated and frequently used in lifestyle research studies. Each item is rated on a 4- point scale ranging from 0 to 3 (higher scores are associated with greater symptoms).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercise Session Adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks after exercise intervention (EOT)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Barriers to adhering to the exercise protocol will be assessed prospectively using an elicitation procedure similar to that suggested in the theory of planned behavior, whereby an open-ended question is asked to solicit the barrier without any preconceived notion of what the barrier might be. Specifically, participants in the exercise groups will be asked to book their weekly supervised exercise sessions with the Exercise Specialist/Physiologist. Participants cancelling an exercise session or requesting to be removed from the study will be asked why they are no longer interested in completed the program.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Stage I Endometrial Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Uterine Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>'Assisted-Rate' Exercise Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in the assisted exercise group will cycle on the same stationary exercise bike; however, a motor will provide assistance to the patient in order to maintain a pedaling rate 35% greater than their voluntary rate. Subjects in the exercise groups will complete 45 minute to 1-hour sessions, three times per week for eight weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>'Voluntary-Rate' Exercise Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in the voluntary group will exercise on a stationary recumbent exercise cycle and pedal at their preferred rate. Subjects in the exercise groups will complete 45 minute to 1-hour sessions, three times per week for eight weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>No exercise/educational information only control group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise on stationary recumbent exercise cycle</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>'Assisted-Rate' Exercise Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>'Voluntary-Rate' Exercise Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health Education</intervention_name>
    <description>Informational brochure (&quot;Better Health and You,&quot; Weight Control Information Network, June, 2004)</description>
    <arm_group_label>'Assisted-Rate' Exercise Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>'Voluntary-Rate' Exercise Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>'Assisted-Rate' Exercise Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>'Voluntary-Rate' Exercise Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Exercise Motivations Inventory (EMI-2)</other_name>
    <other_name>Intrinsic Motivational Inventory (IMI)</other_name>
    <other_name>Three-Factor Eating Questionnaire (TFEQ)</other_name>
    <other_name>Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - General (FACT-G)</other_name>
    <other_name>FACT-En</other_name>
    <other_name>Short-form Medical Outcomes (SF-36)</other_name>
    <other_name>Beck Depression Inventory (BDI)</other_name>
    <other_name>Godin Leisure-Time Exercise (LSI)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neuroimaging</intervention_name>
    <description>Imaging data will be acquired on a Siemens 3.0T Wide-Bore Verio MRI scanner.</description>
    <arm_group_label>'Assisted-Rate' Exercise Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>'Voluntary-Rate' Exercise Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MRI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Genetic and Biomarkers</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be asked to fast for approximately 12 hours and will have approximately 2 Tbs. of blood drawn at baseline and the end of treatment (EOT).</description>
    <arm_group_label>'Assisted-Rate' Exercise Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>'Voluntary-Rate' Exercise Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DNA Testing</other_name>
    <other_name>Biomarker Testing</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult (&gt;18 years) women of all races

          -  Histologically confirmed Stage I ) endometrial adenocarcinoma (EC), grade 1 or 2,
             with no adjuvant chemotherapy. Patients will be eligible to enroll as soon as 3
             months after completion of treatment but no later than 2 years after completion of
             treatment.

          -  BMI ≥ 30.0 (obese)

          -  Approved to be contacted by the patient's treating gynecologic oncologist

          -  Meets screening criteria (discussed in Section 3.4 below)

          -  Receives medical clearance from the patient's primary care physician (PCP) or
             gynecologic oncologist to exercise in this study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals unable to read and provide informed consent.

          -  Women currently participating in a structured weight loss or exercise program in the
             past 6 months

          -  Participants who do not consent to be in the study or who will be unavailable for
             follow-up assessments,

          -  Pre-existing medical conditions that would be a barrier for participation in
             supervised exercise
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nora Nock, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Case Medical Center, University Hospitals Seidman Cancer Center, Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Case Medical Center, University Hospitals Seidman Cancer Center, Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nora Nock, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>216-368-5653</phone>
      <email>nora.nock@case.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 4, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stage I endometrial adenocarcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise and Physical Fitness</keyword>
  <keyword>Diet</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uterine Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
