<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="34954">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01659320</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P30 MH085943-04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01659320</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Open Treatment of Minocycline in Geriatric Depression</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study will examine whether elderly depressed patients whose depressive
      symptoms do not respond satisfactorily to therapy with a mood stabilizer or antidepressant
      alone gain any benefit from taking minocycline alone or in addition to their antidepressant
      or mood stabilizer medication. Minocycline is a commonly used antibiotic medication with
      anti-inflammatory properties.  It is hoped that information gained from this study will help
      the investigators better understand the role of inflammation in depression, and whether
      decreasing inflammation will lead to improvement in the symptoms of depression and cognitive
      function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary objective of this study is to provide hypothesis generation data that may later be tested through a placebo controlled trial.  Accordingly, we will examine whether minocycline alone or as an augmenting agent of antidepressants or mood stabilizers reduces depressive symptoms and disability and promotes remission of major depression</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Open label treatment using minocycline.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Minocycline</intervention_name>
    <description>Minocycline 100 mg twice daily for 8 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age: Participants must be 55 years old or older (female patients must be
             postmenopausal);

          2. Diagnosis: Major depression, either unipolar or bipolar without psychotic features
             (by Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM) IV criteria and
             assessed on the Structured Clinical Interview for the Diagnostic and Statistical
             Manual for Mental Disorders (SCID);

          3. Severity of depression: 17-item Hamilton Depression Rating Scale(HRSD)&gt;14;

          4. Failure to achieve substantial improvement of depressive symptoms (entry HDRS&gt;14)
             after at least 6 weeks of treatment with a mood stabilizer or an antidepressant
             (SSRI, SNRI, or TCA) reaching therapeutic dosages (daily dose of at least: fluoxetine
             20 mg, sertraline 150 mg, paroxetine 20 mg, citalopram 20 mg, escitalopram 10 mg,
             venlafaxine 150 mg, duloxetine 60 mg).

          5. Fluency in English

          6. Capacity to provide informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. High suicide risk, i.e. intent or plan to attempt suicide in near future;

          2. Presence of any current Axis I psychiatric disorder (other than unipolar or bipolar
             major depression or generalized anxiety disorder) including substance abuse (those
             with a history of substance abuse must be abstinent for at least 3 months prior to
             entry);

          3. Axis II diagnosis of antisocial personality disorder, schizotypal or severe
             borderline personality, mental retardation and pervasive developmental disorder
             (DSM-IV);

          4. Dementia of more than mild severity (MMSE &lt; 20);

          5. History of psychiatric disorders such as psychotic depression, primary psychotic
             disorder

          6. Acute or severe medical illness, i.e., delirium, metastatic cancer, decompensated
             cardiac, liver or kidney failure, major surgery, stroke or myocardial infarction
             during the three months prior to entry, advanced autoimmune deficiency, or &quot;end
             stage&quot; chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; or drugs known to cause depression,
             e.g., reserpine, alpha-methyl-dopa, steroids, sympathomimetics withdrawal;

          7. Presence of a significant neurological disease such as Parkinson's disease, primary
             or secondary seizure disorders, intracranial tumors, severe head trauma;
             neurodegenerative diseases i.e. Multiple Sclerosis;

          8. History of intolerance to minocycline or other tetracyclines; use of concomitant
             drugs that may provide reason to believe that minocycline is contraindicated;

          9. Patients on anticoagulants (except low-dose aspirin); patients on ergot alkaloids

         10. Patients on MAOIs;

         11. Patients' unwillingness or inability to gradually withdraw all other psychotropic
             medications (except for the following:  Antidepressants, mood stabilizers, and low
             and stable doses of opiates and non-benzodiazepine hypnotics, e.g. zolpidem (5 or 10
             mg), zaleplon (5 or 10 mg).

         12. Inability to perform any of the ADLs (MAI: ADL subscale) even with assistance, e.g.
             walking with a cane is not an exclusion criterion;

         13. Inability to speak English;

         14. Corrected visual acuity &lt; 20/70;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>George S. Alexopoulos, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bryony Lucas</last_name>
    <phone>914-682-9100</phone>
    <phone_ext>2497</phone_ext>
    <email>brl2013@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Geriatric Psychiatry</name>
      <address>
        <city>White Plains</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10605</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>George S. Alexopoulos, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 2, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Minocycline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
