<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="112541">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01784666</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-P-002449/1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01784666</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adjunctive Isradipine for the Treatment of Bipolar Depression</brief_title>
  <acronym>Isradipine</acronym>
  <official_title>Adjunctive Isradipine for the Treatment of Bipolar Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study investigates the medication isradipine, which is currently approved by the FDA to
      treat high blood pressure, in the treatment of depression in bipolar disorder. Isradipine or
      placebo (contains no active medication) will be used as an &quot;add-on&quot; to lithium, valproate,
      and/or atypical antipsychotics for individuals currently experiencing a major depressive
      episode. Our hypothesis is that isradipine will be superior to placebo in improving
      depressive symptoms.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary Aim: To estimate the antidepressant efficacy of isradipine versus placebo as an
      adjunct to lithium, valproate, and/or other atypical antipsychotics among individuals with
      bipolar I disorder in a nonpsychotic major depressive episode.

      Hypothesis: Isradipine will be superior to placebo in improvement of depressive symptoms
      assessed by the Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in MADRS (4 weeks)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs week 4 (and, for placebo nonresponders in 1st 4 weeks, week 8 vs week 4)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) in isradipine-treated epochs versus placebo-treated epochs</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Bipolar Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Isradipine-Isradipine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive isradipine in phase 1 (4 weeks) and phase 2 (4 weeks)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo -&gt; Isradipine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo non-responders after the 1st 4 weeks will be re-randomized 1:1 to placebo or isradipine for the next 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo-Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo nonresponders for the 1st 4 weeks will be re-randomized 1:1 to placebo or isradipine for the subsequent 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Isradipine</intervention_name>
    <description>The study uses the Sequential Parallel Comparison design (SPCD), with two 4-week phases: n=30 subjects are randomized 1:1 to isradipine versus placebo add-on for 4 weeks, with the placebo nonresponders re-randomized 1:1 for a further 4 weeks. The SPCD will allow us to pool data from both phases to estimate the isradipine treatment effect. Subjects who respond in phase 1, and all subjects who receive isradipine in phase 1, continue blinded treatment in phase 2 to preserve the blind, but only phase 1 results are analyzed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Isradipine-Isradipine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo -&gt; Isradipine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects (n=15) are randomized to placebo add-on for 4 weeks, with the nonresponders re-randomized 1:1 to isradipine vs placebo for a further 4 weeks. Subjects who respond in phase 1 continue blinded treatment in phase 2 to preserve the blind, but only phase 1 results are analyzed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo -&gt; Isradipine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo-Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18-65

          -  written informed consent

          -  meets DSM-IV criteria (by SCID-I/P) for bipolar I disorder, current episode depressed

          -  MADRS score of at least 20 (i.e., moderate depression) and no greater than 34 (i.e.,
             severe depression) at screen and baseline visit

          -  YMRS score &lt; 12 at screen and baseline visit

          -  currently treated with a lithium preparation (carbonate or citrate) at stable dose
             for at least 4 wks with level &gt;0.6 and &lt;1.0; and/or valproate at stable dose for at
             least 4 wks at level &gt;60 and &lt;110; and/or other atypical antipsychotic at stable dose
             for at least 4 weeks (at least minimum FDA-labeled dose)

          -  Caucasian by self-report - please see discussion below

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Psychotic features in the current episode, as assessed by YMRS item #8 &gt; 6 [where
             treatment guidelines urge use of antipsychotics  that may confound isradipine
             results]

          -  felt by the study clinician to require inpatient hospitalization for adequate
             management (to include serious suicide or homicide risk, as assessed by evaluating
             clinician)

          -  3 or more failed pharmacologic interventions in the current major depressive episode,
             excluding lithium/valproate/other atypical antipsychotic [response rates for these
             subjects is likely to be extremely low and would require a substantially larger-scale
             study to identify treatment effects]

          -  obsessive-compulsive disorder, or any diagnosis of a DSM-IV anxiety disorder where
             the anxiety disorder and not bipolar disorder is the primary focus of clinical
             attention

          -  current substance use disorder other than nicotine, by SCID-I/P

          -  a primary clinical diagnosis of a personality disorder, or comorbid diagnosis of
             antisocial or borderline personality disorder

          -  pregnant women or women of child bearing potential who are not using a medically
             accepted means of contraception (to include oral contraceptive or implant, condom,
             diaphragm, spermicide, intrauterine device, tubal ligation, or partner with
             vasectomy)

          -  women who are breastfeeding

          -  other unstable medical illness including cardiovascular, hepatic, renal, respiratory,
             endocrine, neurological, or hematological disease, based on review of medical
             history, physical examination, and screening laboratory tests (this will include any
             clinical or laboratory evidence of hypothyroidism; if maintained on thyroid
             medication must be euthyroid for at least 1 month before Visit 1)

          -  history of hypertension or current treatment for hypertension

          -  current use of isradipine or history of anaphylactic reaction or intolerance to
             isradipine or any component of the preparation

          -  ECG abnormalities at entry: prolonged QTc or complete or incomplete bundle branch
             block

          -  patients who have taken an investigational psychotropic drug within the last 3 months

          -  patients receiving other excluded antipsychotics or antidepressants within 2 weeks
             prior to study entry

          -  patients requiring continued treatment with excluded medications (see below).

        Excluded medications: antidepressants, antipsychotics, and anticonvulsants (other than
        valproate), which could influence calcium signaling or impact mood; other calcium channel
        blockers; any other antihypertensive because of the risk of cause hypotension; any other
        drug known to interact with isradipine. Benzodiazepines or other sedative-hypnotic agents
        (e.g., zolpidem) may not be initiated after study entry; subjects requiring these agents
        will be removed from the study. Allowed: Sedative-hypnotic agents if dosage has been
        stable for 4 weeks prior to study entry; thyroid or estrogen replacement provided dosage
        has been stable for 3 months. Acceptable anticonvulsants include lamotrigine, valproate,
        gabapentin, topiramate, oxcarbazepine, carbamazepine.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roy H Perlis, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Roy H Perlis, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <email>rperlis@chgr.mgh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hannah Rosenfield, BA</last_name>
    <email>hrosenfield@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roy H Perlis, MD MSc</last_name>
      <phone>617-726-7426</phone>
      <email>rperlis@chgr.mgh.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Hannah Rosenfield, BA</last_name>
      <phone>617-643-6310</phone>
      <email>hrosenfield@partners.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roy H Perlis, MD, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 7, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 4, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Roy Perlis</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bipolar Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Lithium</keyword>
  <keyword>Valproate</keyword>
  <keyword>Isradipine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bipolar Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Isradipine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
