<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="18213">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01772810</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NS2010-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01772810</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Study of Human Spinal Cord-derived Neural Stem Cell Transplantation for the Treatment of Chronic SCI</brief_title>
  <acronym>SCI</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Open-label, Multi-site, Safety Study of Human Spinal Cord-derived Neural Stem Cell Transplantation for the Treatment of Chronic SCI</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Neuralstem Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Neuralstem Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a safety study of human spinal cord-derived neural stem cell (HSSC) transplantation
      for the treatment of chronic spinal cord injury.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The treatment will consist of removal of spinal instrumentation (in order to allow
      monitoring of the cell grafts by serial MRI for long-term), followed by laminectomy or
      laminoplasty of 1-4 vertebral segments overlying the region of spinal cord injury (no
      laminectomy if previous laminectomy). The dura will be opened midline and direct injections
      into spinal parenchyma performed. 6 HSSC injections will be administered bilaterally (3 on
      each side of midline): 2 at rostral and caudal edge of the injury site and 1 into
      approximately one segment length inferior to the injury site. The injections will target
      lateral funiculi, the most rostral injection site being in the first segment caudal to the
      neurological level defined by ISNCSCI examination. Each injection in the first 4 subjects of
      Group A will consist of 1 x 105 cells in 10μL volume. In the second 4 subjects of Group A,
      each injection will consist of 2 x 105 cells in 10μL volume:

        -  Group A1, n=4, T2 - T12: 1 x 105 cells in 10μL/injection x 6 injections

        -  Group A2, n=4, T2 - T12: 2 x 105 cells in 10μL/injection x 6 injections

      Post-operatively, subjects will receive routine standard of care for laminectomy subjects
      who undergo an intradural procedure. Prior to and after the transplant, subjects will be
      required to remain on immunosuppressive therapy for 3 months. Immunosuppressive therapy will
      consist of: 1) basiliximab (Simulect®)) 20mg intravenously (IV) within 2 hours prior to the
      onset of the surgery, then again at day 4 post transplantation; 2) tacrolimus (Prograf®)
      initially dosed at a maximum of 0.1 mg/kg divided every 12 hours by mouth (po) on post
      transplant day 1, and then maintained at a dose that provides a trough serum level of 4-8
      ng/ml (adjusted for IV use as necessary); and 3) mycophenolate mofetil (CellCept®) starting
      from 500mg p.o.

      twice daily, progressively increased over 2 weeks to 1.0 gram twice daily as tolerated. The
      decision to continue immunosuppression therapy will be at the discretion of the site
      Principal Investigator. Mycophenolate mofetil may be dosed down to half or discontinued
      prior to the end of the 3-month period if the subject experiences adverse reactions to the
      immunosuppressive agents. If adverse reactions still persist, the tacrolimus dose can be
      further reduced in half and then further considered to be discontinued. The Safety
      Monitoring Board (SMB) will be convened at approximately 1 month (4 weeks) intervals after
      the first subject and will review the available safety data of all treated subjects.
      Starting from Week 13 post cell injection, tacrolimus and mycophenolate mofetil will be
      gradually withdrawn over 2 weeks. During this period and the ensuing weeks and months, the
      subject's blood will be monitored for the appearance of antibodies against donor cell HLAs.
      Signs of graft rejection will also be monitored by changes in MRI intensity of the graft
      area. If antibodies are detected, the immune suppression regimen will be re-instituted and
      maintained for as long as tolerable by the subject.

      Subjects will be assessed for adverse events including pain and infection, motor function,
      and quality of life. Additional assessments will be made to measure any postoperative
      changes from baseline in neurologic deficits, neurophysiology, imaging studies, bladder or
      bowel function, allodynia, and neuropathic pain (see Schedule of Events). Subjects will be
      followed postoperatively at 2 weeks, monthly for 6 months during the study and at every 6
      months thereafter in post-study safety follow-up for total 60 months post stem cell
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary objective of the study is to determine the safety of human spinal stem cell transplantation for the treatment of paralysis and related symptoms due to chronic spinal cord injury (SCI)</measure>
    <time_frame>The primary outcome measure will be assessed over a 60 month period.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary outcome measure is the incidence of adverse events in the study population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The secondary objective of the study is to evaluate the graft survival in the transplant site by MRI.</measure>
    <time_frame>An MRI will be performed at Visits 5, 10, 16, 19 and 24.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The secondary outcome measures of the study is to evaluate the ability of HSSC transplantation to positively affect AIS level ISNC SCI motor and sensory index scores, bowel and bladder function, pain, UAB IMR scores, SCIM scores, evoked sensory and motor potentials, and electromyogram (EMG).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injury (SCI)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical implantation of human spinal cord stem cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Surgical implantation of human spinal cord derived neural stem cells as follows:
Group A1 will consist of 4 patients receiving 1x100000 cells in 10uL/injection x 6 injections.
Group A2 will consist of 4 patients receiving 2x100000 cells in 10ul/injections x 6 injections</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Human spinal cord stem cells.</intervention_name>
    <description>Human spinal cord stem cell implantation in paralysis patients due to a spinal cord injury.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical implantation of human spinal cord stem cells</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>spinal cord injury (SCI)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Have the ability to understand the requirements of the study, provide written
             informed consent, understand and provide written authorization for the use and
             disclosure of Protected Health Information (PHI) [per Health Insurance Portability
             and Accountability Act (HIPAA) Privacy Ruling] and comply with the study procedures

          2. Men and women 18-65 years old

          3. Women must have a negative serum pregnancy test and practice an acceptable method of
             contraception or be of non-childbearing potential (post-menopausal for at least 2
             years or who have undergone hysterectomy or oophorectomy or surgical sterilization)

          4. At least 1 year but no more than 2 years from time of injury at the time of surgery

          5. SCI injury classified as AIS-A complete as confirmed by the PI and a Physical
             Medicine and Rehabilitation doctor or other SCI Medicine board certified physician
             based on a complete ISNC SCI examination

          6. Neurologic level of injury:

             a. Group A: within cord segments T2-T12

          7. Confirmation of bone fusion by CT scan

          8. Agrees to the visit schedule as outlined in the informed consent

          9. All required vaccinations current at the time of enrollment: tetanus/diptheria
             (TDAP),herpes zoster/shingles (Zostavax®: within last 10 years and must be prior to
             surgery),pneumonia (Pneumovax®), seasonal/H1N1 flu vaccines (as appropriate for
             season). Any missing vaccination will be provided at the screening if consented by
             the otherwise eligible patient who will then be scheduled for surgery no less than 30
             days post vaccination.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. SCI due to penetrating trauma such as gun shot or stabbing wound

          2. SCI injuries involving complete spinal cord transection

          3. Etiology of paraplegia or weakness related to other or additional neurologic process

          4. MRI evidence of syrinx, multiple cysts, or a cyst with greater than 2cm in length or
             injury site involving greater than 2cm of the cord

          5. Current or peak Panel Reactive Antibody (PRA) due to alloantibodies &gt; 20% receiving
             their first allograft

          6. Receipt of any investigational drug or device within 30 days

          7. Receipt of any cell infusion other than blood transfusion

          8. Any concomitant medical disease or condition noted below:

               1. Coagulopathy with INR &gt; 1.4 at the time of surgery

               2. Active infection

               3. Active hypotension requiring vasopressor therapy

               4. Skin breakdown over the site of surgery

               5. Malignancy

               6. Primary or secondary immune deficiency

               7. Persistent MRI artifact that would prevent imaging post-op

               8. Creatinine &gt;1.5, liver function tests (SGOT/SGPT, Bilirubin, Alk Phos) &gt; 2x
                  upper limit of normal, hematocrit/hemoglobin &lt; 30/10, total WBC &lt; 4000,
                  uncontrolled hypertension (systolic &gt; 180 or diastolic &gt; 100) or uncontrolled
                  diabetes (defined as hemoglobin A1C &gt;8), evidence of GI bleeding by hemoccult
                  test, , positive tuberculosis (TB test: PPD/Mantoux), hepatitis B or C, or human
                  immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

          9. Presence of any of the following conditions:

               1. Current drug abuse or alcoholism

               2. Unstable medical conditions

               3. Unstable psychiatric illness including psychosis and untreated major depression

         10. Any condition that the Investigator or primary physician feels may interfere with
             participation in the study

         11. Any condition that the surgeon feels may pose complications for the surgery

         12. Known hypersensitivity to basiliximab, tacrolimus, or mycophenolate mofetil

         13. Unable or unwilling to participate in physical and/or occupational therapy as
             scheduled

         14. Inability to provide informed consent as determined by screening protocol.

         15. Stage III or above decubitus wound, other open wound, or active colostomy;

         16. Autoimmune diseases, for which chronic corticosteroids or immunosuppression therapy
             may be needed;

         17. Implanted spine stimulator;

         18. Uncontrolled spasticity;

         19. Uncontrolled neuropathic pain.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amber Faulise, B.S.</last_name>
    <phone>858-657-5175</phone>
    <email>rfaulise@ucsd.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSD Medical Center, Division of Neurosurgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92103-8893</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joseph Ciacci, MD</last_name>
      <email>jciacci@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Martin Marsala, MD</last_name>
      <email>mmarsala@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joseph Ciacci, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Martin Marsala, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://neuralstem.com</url>
    <description>Related Information</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Paralysis due to spinal cord injury (SCI)</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
