<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="122849">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02106572</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AB03</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-003446-16</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02106572</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Therapeutic Instillation of Mistletoe</brief_title>
  <acronym>TIM</acronym>
  <official_title>Intravesical Mistletoe Extract in Superficial Bladder Cancer: A Phase III Efficacy Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Abnoba Gmbh</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Abnoba Gmbh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>Egypt: Ministry of Health and Population</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this phase III study is to assess the efficacy of abnobaVISCUM® 900 compared with
      Mitomycin C (MMC) monotherapy in patients with superficial bladder carcinoma by evaluation
      of the time to tumor recurrence. Secondary objective is to evaluate the safety of
      abnobaVISCUM® 900, in particular, to compare the toxicity of the two treatments. Another
      secondary objective is the treatment efficacy as measured by calculated prognosis for
      recurrence and progression after 1 year, the tumor grading in case of a recurrence and by
      measurement of Quality of Life.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, open-label, active-controlled, prospective, multinational Phase III
      confirmative study with 2 treatment groups and an adaptive design (Bauer and Köhne, 1994).
      The study is designed to compare the efficacy of treatment with abnobaVISCUM® 900 with
      Mitomycin C (MMC).  Patients with completely resected superficial bladder carcinoma (Stage
      Ta or T1) with an intermediate risk classification according to the European Association of
      Urology (EAU) and without CIS and/or G3 tumors and with one immediately post operative MMC
      40 mg intravesical instillation will be eligible for inclusion in the study.

      The study comprises a screening period of not more than 4 weeks, a treatment period of 12
      months for abnobaVISCUM® 900 and MMC and a follow-up period of 12 months. Patients will be
      screened within 4 weeks after the transurethral resection of the bladder (TURB) and the
      immediately post operative MMC 40 mg intravesical instillation. A re-resection should be
      performed before inclusion if indicated. Every patient is to provide written informed
      consent before any study related procedures will be performed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to tumor recurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>up to two years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary objective of the study is to assess the efficacy of abnobaVISCUM® 900. Primary efficacy criterion will be the time to tumor recurrence.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity and tolerability of the study medication</measure>
    <time_frame>up to two years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The secondary objective, namely safety including toxicity and tolerability of the study medication, will be assessed by the monitoring of adverse events (AEs) according to the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), laboratory assessments (hematology, biochemistry and urinalysis) and a global judgment of tolerability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prognosis after 1 year for recurrence and progression</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A secondary efficacy endpoint is prognosis after 1 year for recurrence and progression, estimated by the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Bladder Cancer Calculator.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>up to two years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A secondary efficacy endpoint is measurement of Quality of Life with the EORTC QLQ-C30 and BLS24 questionnaires.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor grading</measure>
    <time_frame>up to two years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A secondary efficacy endpoint is the tumor grading in case of a recurrence by cytology, ultrasound, and cystoscopy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">546</enrollment>
  <condition>Superficial Bladder Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>abnobaVISCUM 900</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>intravesical instillation of abnobaVISCUM 900</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mitomycin C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>intravesical instillation of Mitomycin C</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>abnobaVISCUM 900</intervention_name>
    <description>intravesical instillation of abnobaVISCUM 900 13 times during treatment period</description>
    <arm_group_label>abnobaVISCUM 900</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>viscum album extract</other_name>
    <other_name>mistletoe extract</other_name>
    <other_name>abnobaVISCUM</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mitomycin C</intervention_name>
    <description>intravesical instillation of Mitomycin C 10 times during treatment period</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mitomycin C</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MMC</other_name>
    <other_name>Mitomycin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed and dated written informed consent for data protection and willingness to
             participate and comply with the study protocol prior to any study-related procedures

          -  Completely resected (detrusor muscle in the TUR specimen has to be present)
             superficial bladder carcinoma (Stage Ta or T1) with classification as
             intermediate-risk according to the EAU (without CIS and/or G3) and one immediately
             post operative intravesical MMC instillation of 40 mg, completed re-resection if
             indicated

          -  Karnofsky Performance Status of 50% to 100% (corresponding to Eastern Cooperative
             Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status of 0 to 2)

          -  Life expectancy of ≥ 2 years at the time point of study inclusion

          -  Normal renal and liver function, normal cardiac and hematology profiles (patients
             with laboratory values slightly outside the reference range may be included, unless
             the investigator considers the abnormality as clinically significant)

          -  Female patients of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test
             (β-human chorionic gonadotropin test) at Screening. Pregnancy during the treatment
             period including 12 weeks after the last instillation has to be excluded

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Locally infiltrative or metastatic bladder tumor (Stage T2 or greater), low-risk or
             high-risk Stage Ta and T1 tumors (according to EAU classification), a bad prognosis
             regarding progression (CIS or G3), presence of upper urinary tract tumors or lesions
             which were not completely removed by TURB

          -  Urinary tract infection, benign prostatic obstruction grade II or III, neurogenic
             bladder, stress incontinence, bladder or urethral diverticula, fistulas or urethral
             stenosis

          -  Patients with acute systemic illness, such as inflammatory infections with fever &gt;
             38°C

          -  Patients with previous recurrence of a superficial bladder cancer or radiotherapy of
             the bladder or other intravesical treatment within the last 6 months, or patients
             with previous mistletoe therapy

          -  Patients with other previous or co-existing malignancies or CIS

          -  Patients having any previous or concurrent therapy with a systemic chemo- /
             immunotherapeutical treatment regimen, in particular vinca alkaloids, bleomycine and
             doxorubicine, or patients who are treated with pyroxidine hydrochloride (vitamin B6)

          -  Untreated coagulation disorders or inadequate anticoagulation therapy

          -  Leukocyte count &lt; 4,000/mm3 or platelet count &lt; 100,000/mm3

          -  Serum creatinine &gt; 1.7 mg/dL

          -  Patients with known hypersensitivity to the excipients of the study medication
             (monosodium phosphate, disodium phosphate, ascorbic acid)

          -  Patients with a known hypersensitivity to mistletoe products and MMC

          -  Patients who were administered within a 4-week period before Visit 1 any other
             experimental drug under investigation

          -  Male patients planning to father a child or sperm donation from the first
             administration of study medication until 3 months after the last administration of
             the study medication

          -  Male patients unwilling to use barrier contraception ie, condoms and spermicide, from
             the day of first administration of the study medication until 12 weeks after
             administration of the study medication

          -  Patients with a history of alcohol and / or drug abuse

          -  Patients who are unable to be regularly observed, not permitting adequate follow-up
             and compliance to the protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Herbert Ruebben, Prof.Dr.Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Director of the Urological Clinic of the University Hospital Essen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Juergen Eisenbraun, Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>+49 7231 315070</phone>
    <email>eisenbraun@abnoba.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Theodor Bilharz Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Giza</city>
        <zip>12411</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tarek El Leithy, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+2 01222117206</phone>
      <email>tleithy@thewayout.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tarek El Leithy, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hani Nour, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinic of Urology of the University Hospital of Essen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Essen</city>
        <zip>45122</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Herbert Ruebben, Prof.Dr.Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 201 723</phone>
      <phone_ext>3211</phone_ext>
      <email>herbert.ruebben@uk-essen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ruebben Herbert, Prof.Dr.Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephan Tschirdewahn, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 4, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>superficial bladder cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>viscum album extract</keyword>
  <keyword>mistletoe extract</keyword>
  <keyword>abnobaVISCUM</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrence rate</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mitomycins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mitomycin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Viscum album peptide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
