<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="100929">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02038959</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AD-12-11-4701</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02038959</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Connect.Parkinson: Connecting Individuals With Parkinson Disease to Specialists in Their Homes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Using Technology to Deliver Multi-disciplinary Care to Individuals With Parkinson Disease in Their Homes: the Connect.Parkinson Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Rochester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Patient Centered Outcome Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Parkinson Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Rochester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Connect.Parkinson is a randomized comparative effectiveness study, comparing usual care
      enhanced with educational materials to usual care, educational materials, and the delivery
      of specialty care via telemedicine into patient's homes. The study's specific aims are the
      following:

        1. To demonstrate the feasibility of using telemedicine to deliver specialty care into the
           homes of individuals with Parkinson disease who have limited access to care;

        2. To show that such an approach can improve quality of life;

        3. To establish that the telemedicine can enhance the quality of care; and

        4. To demonstrate that this remote approach to care saves time, reduces travel, and
           decreases care partner burden.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Connect.Parkinson is a national study examining the feasibility and effectiveness of using
      video calls to bring expert Parkinson disease care directly into patients' homes. Currently,
      access to care for Parkinson disease is limited by distance, disability, and the
      distribution of doctors. Approximately 200 individuals with Parkinson disease (who due to
      distance, disability, disparity, or doctor distribution have limited access to care) will be
      randomized to one of two arms in this comparative effectiveness study.  The first (control)
      arm will be the individual's &quot;usual care&quot; supplemented by educational materials on their
      condition.  This usual care may include care from a generalist, care from a neurologist, or
      in-person care from a Parkinson specialist. The care received by the control group will vary
      but will be an accurate reflection of usual care in this country. The second (intervention)
      arm will be usual care supplemented by educational materials and care from a Parkinson
      disease specialist delivered via web-based video conferencing into the patient's home. The
      participants will also be asked with they have a primary care partner, and care partners
      will be invited to enroll, for a total of approximately 400 participants.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of Virtual Visits for Parkinson Disease</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Feasibility of virtual visits will be determined by the number of participants who complete at least one virtual visit successfully.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of care provided via virtual visits</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessed as the change in quality of life, measured by the Parkinson Disease Questionnaire 39 (PDQ-39).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will measure the change in overall quality of life reported from baseline to the end of the study using the EuroQoL 5D-5L.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Global Impression of Change</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>At the conclusion of the study, participants will be asked to describe how they feel their health has changed since the beginning of the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognition</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will assess changes in cognition from baseline to the end of the study using the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA), administered remotely.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parkinson disease severity</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parkinson disease clinical characteristics will be assessed by a physician independent rater, blinded to treatment group, at baseline and at the conclusion of the study, using the Movement Disorder Society Unified Parkinson Disease Rating Scale (MDS-UPDRS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Care</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will assess change in the perceived quality of care using the Patient Assessment of Chronic Illness Care (PACIC).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Value to patients and care partners</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will assess value to patients and caregivers using questions about time and travel to Parkinson disease appointments,  as well as healthcare resource utilization  (including hospitalizations and other visits).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Care partner burden</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured as the change in the Multidimensional Caregiver Strain Index (MCSI).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">480</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care and Educational Materials</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with Parkinson disease will receive educational materials from the National Parkinson Foundation, complete a baseline assessment survey and virtual visit with a physician independent rater, then continue with their usual care in their communities for the duration of the study. After 12 months, they will have another virtual study assessment with an independent rater, after which they will  receive a free, one-time virtual consultation with a Parkinson disease specialist in their state.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Virtual Visits and Educational Materials</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with Parkinson disease randomized to the virtual visit intervention will receive educational materials from the National Parkinson Foundation, complete a baseline assessment  and virtual study assessment with a physician independent rater, and then receive four virtual care visits with a Parkinson disease specialist in their state. Specialists will provide recommendations for care to participants and their designated local health care provider. At 12 months, these individuals will again be assessed by the independent rater, who will be blind to treatment assignment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Care partners</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Care partners will be enrolled with the participants for whom they care. Care partners will complete a survey at baseline and at the end of the study, including assessments of time and travel for assisting with Parkinson disease visits and the Multidimensional Caregiver Strain Index (MCSI).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Virtual Visits</intervention_name>
    <description>Virtual visits will be completed using HIPAA-compliant video conferencing software from SBR Health and Vidyo, designed specifically for use in the healthcare industry. The software is available for Windows and Mac OS, as well as iOS devices (iPad and iPhone).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Virtual Visits and Educational Materials</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Telemedicine</other_name>
    <other_name>Teleneurology</other_name>
    <other_name>Video call</other_name>
    <other_name>Video conferencing</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals with clinically diagnosed Idiopathic Parkinson disease in the judgment of
             the independent rater

          -  No better alternative explanation for the parkinsonism

          -  Access to a non-public, internet-enabled device (e.g., computer, tablet computer,
             smart phone) that has the capacity for web-based video conferencing

          -  Be physically located at time visits are conducted in a state where the participating
             physician is licensed to practice medicine

          -  Have a local care provider that the study team can contact

          -  Live at home, in a senior housing complex, or assisted living facility

          -  Be fluent in English (all participating states) or Spanish (participants in Florida
             and Massachusetts only)

          -  Willing and able to provide informed consent

          -  Care partner (if applicable) must be able and willing to provide informed consent to
             participate if he or she so chooses.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently hospitalized

          -  Condition (e.g., prominent psychosis) that precludes study participation as
             identified by the medical professional (site investigator or nurse).

          -  Participation in another telemedicine study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>E. Ray Dorsey, MD, MBA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Rochester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Meredith A Achey, BM</last_name>
    <phone>5852766825</phone>
    <email>connect@parkinson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Meredith A Achey, BM</last_name>
      <phone>585-276-6825</phone>
      <email>connect@parkinson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Irene Richard, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rachel Biemiller, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kevin M Biglan, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dorsey ER, Venkataraman V, Grana MJ, Bull MT, George BP, Boyd CM, Beck CA, Rajan B, Seidmann A, Biglan KM. Randomized controlled clinical trial of &quot;virtual house calls&quot; for Parkinson disease. JAMA Neurol. 2013 May;70(5):565-70. doi: 10.1001/jamaneurol.2013.123.</citation>
    <PMID>23479138</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grana MJ, Bull MT, Venkataraman V, Dorsey ER, Biglan KM. Web-based clinical assessments for Parkinson's disease: reliable and feasible. Mov Disord. 2012 Sep 15;27(11):1466. doi: 10.1002/mds.25121. Epub 2012 Sep 18.</citation>
    <PMID>22991090</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abdolahi A, Scoglio N, Killoran A, Dorsey ER, Biglan KM. Potential reliability and validity of a modified version of the Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale that could be administered remotely. Parkinsonism Relat Disord. 2013 Feb;19(2):218-21. doi: 10.1016/j.parkreldis.2012.10.008. Epub 2012 Oct 25.</citation>
    <PMID>23102808</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Willis AW, Schootman M, Tran R, Kung N, Evanoff BA, Perlmutter JS, Racette BA. Neurologist-associated reduction in PD-related hospitalizations and health care expenditures. Neurology. 2012 Oct 23;79(17):1774-80. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e3182703f92. Epub 2012 Oct 10.</citation>
    <PMID>23054239</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Willis AW, Schootman M, Evanoff BA, Perlmutter JS, Racette BA. Neurologist care in Parkinson disease: a utilization, outcomes, and survival study. Neurology. 2011 Aug 30;77(9):851-7. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e31822c9123. Epub 2011 Aug 10.</citation>
    <PMID>21832214</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 8, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parkinson disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinson's</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinson's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>telemedicine</keyword>
  <keyword>virtual visits</keyword>
  <keyword>video calls</keyword>
  <keyword>video conferencing</keyword>
  <keyword>virtual house calls</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
