<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="139732">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02139982</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2009A145-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02139982</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Study of Regional Hemodynamic Changes After Specific Brachial Plexus Block by Ultrasound Guidance</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Study of Regional Hemodynamic Changes After Specific Brachial Plexus Block by Ultrasound Guidance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wenzhou Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Health and Family Planning Commission of Zhejiang Province, China</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wenzhou Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Health and Family Planning Commission of Zhejiang Province</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase 1 Sympathetic block leads to vasodilatation and increases in blood flow. However,
      regional hemodynamic changes of radial and ulnar artery after specific nerve block of
      brachial plexus remains unclear. The aim of the study is to assess the effect of specific
      nerve block of brachial plexus on hemodynamics of upper extremity, and provides evidence for
      further research in patient undergoing microvascular surgery.

      Phase 2 There is no literature about dose-finding studies of sympathetic block after
      brachial plexus block. Little is known regarding the relationship between concentration of
      local anaesthetic and vasodilation of upper extremity. The aim of this randomized,
      double-blind, prospective dose-response study is to determine the ED50 and ED95 of
      ropivacaine in sympathetic block of upper extremity after supraclavicular block
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Phase 1 Brachial plexus block (BPB) is a widely used regional anesthetic technique for upper
      limb surgery. The effect of sympathetic block of BPB can leads to vasodilatation and
      increase blood flow and skin temperature in the ipsilateral upper limb. At the level of the
      axillary region, the sympathetic nerves innervating the radial and ulnar artery travel with
      the brachial plexus, but it is unclear which specific nerve: musculocutaneous, radial,
      ulnar, and median innervates radial or ulnar artery. Radial and ulnar artery and their
      branches are common donor or recipient vessels in the vascular reconstruction surgery and
      their hemodynamic changes  may affect the blood flow of vascular anastomoses in vascular
      reconstruction. Sometimes, brachial plexus could be partially blocked intentionally or
      unintentionally, with the resultant regional hemodynamic changes unclear.

      As the use of ultrasound guided peripheral nerve block getting increasingly popular,
      peripheral nerve can be blocked visually, with good accuracy and ease. It has made specific
      nerve block in the axillary region possible. Can specific nerve block increase the blood
      flow of target artery (radial or ulnar artery) and benefit microvascular surgery, or will it
      decrease the blood flow in other arteries and have a negative impact on microvascular
      surgery?  In this study, the investigators will measure the hemodynamic changes of radial
      and ulnar artery after performing specific nerve blocks of the musculocutaneous, radial,
      ulnar, or median nerves respectively in patients without vascular disease. The aim is to
      assess the effect of specific nerve block on hemodynamics of upper extremity, and provided
      evidence for further research in patients undergoing microvascular surgery.

      The subjects of study are patients undergoing upper extremity operation. All patients will
      be randomized into 4 groups according to the specific nerve block (SNB) of brachial plexus:
      group MC (musculocutaneous), group UL (ulnar), group RA (radial) and group ME (median).
      Patients are randomised to the four groups by random number(generated by computer) in sealed
      envelopes. Sample randomization will be done in four groups by random-number using sealed
      envelopes. Each patient will receive allocated SNB of brachial plexus (musculocutaneous,
      radial, ulnar, or median) followed by Axillary brachial plexus block successively using
      ultrasound guidance combined neurostimulation. All nerve blocks will be performed by a
      single dedicated anesthetist. A second investigator, who is blinded to the protocol and
      patient allocation, will perform the measurements.

      Sensory blockade will be assessed by pinprick sensation (22 G needle) and compare with the
      opposite forearm/hand for normal, hypoesthesia or no sensation. Success of SNB is defined as
      only loss of sensation in the cutaneous distribution of the specific nerve
      (musculocutaneous, ulnar, radial, or median nerves) at 30min after SNB. If hypoesthesia or
      no sensation is detected in the innervation areas of any other nerve, the patient will be
      excluded. Success of BPB is defined as the absence of sensation to in all innervation areas
      of above four nerves 30min after the BPB.

      Measurement of hemodynamic parameters   The ulnar artery and radial artery is located at 1
      cm proximal to the ulnar or radial styloid process. Specific points will be located with
      skin marker to provide consistency with all measurements taken. Hemodynamic parameters will
      is measured by Pulsed-wave Doppler (PWD) ultrasound. The probe will be placed on the ventral
      wrist parallel to the long axis of the forearm without undue pressure on the artery during
      the PWD measurements. The volume gate will be positioned in the center of the arterial
      lumen, and the size of the gate will be 1/3 lumen of the artery. The angle of insonation is
      adjusted and maintained at 50-60 degrees. Once a desired PWD spectral waveform is achieved,
      the arterial hemodynamic parameters will be recorded.

      Phase 2 The subjects of study are patients undergoing upper extremity operation under
      supraclavicular brachial plexus block. All patients will be randomly assigned to receive
      30ml ropivacaine in concentrations of 0.125%, 0.2%, 0.25%, 0.375%, 0.5%, or 0.75%. Patients
      are randomised to the four groups by random number(generated by computer) in sealed
      envelopes.  All nerve blocks were performed by a single dedicated anaesthetist who remains
      blinded to the concentration of ropivacaine.

      A second investigator, who is blinded to the protocol and patient allocation, will perform
      the measurements. Another investigator, who is not present during the conduct of the BPB and
      blinded to the concentration of ropivacaine used will assess each blockade. Patient are also
      blinded.

      The brachial plexus will be visualized using a high-frequency linear ultrasound transducer
      in the supraclavicular fossa. After skin disinfection and infiltrating with 1% lidocaine,
      nerve stimulation needle will be inserted using in-line technique,and advanced among the
      divisions of brachial plexus with electric impulses (2 Hz, 0.3mA, 0.1 ms) of nerve
      stimulator. If visible contraction of the innervated muscle is elicited, the needle will be
      withdrawn slowly until the corresponding muscle contraction disappears to avoid
      intrafascicular puncture. The local anesthetic will be injected at three locations: adjacent
      to the superficial divisions of the plexus, adjacent to the middle divisions and inferior
      divisions. The proportion of the volume injected in each area is at the discretion of the
      expert operator according to the spread of local anesthetic.

      The efficacy of the block will be assessed by pinprick sensation (22 G needle) and compared
      with the opposite arm/hand for normal, hypoesthesia or no sensation. For patients with an
      ineffective block, supplementary local anesthesia will be administered according to the
      distribution of the block and site of surgery after measurement. If the patient experienced
      any pain during surgery, supplementary analgesia, sedation, or general anesthesia will be
      administered as required.

      Patient's arm is in supination. The brachial artery will be located in 2 cm proximal to the
      antecubital fossa. Hemodynamic Parameters will be measured by Pulsed-wave Doppler(PWD)
      ultrasound. The probe will be parallel the long axis of the arm without undue pressure on
      the artery during the PWD measurements. The volume gate will be positioned in the center of
      the arterial lumen, and the size of the gate will be 1/3 lumen of the artery. The angle of
      insonation will be adjusted and maintained at 50-60 degrees. Once a desired PWD spectral
      waveform is achieved, the arterial hemodynamic parameters will be recorded. The
      cross-sectional area (CSA) of the artery will be assessed with B-mode imaging. Probe should
      be as perpendicular as possible to the long axis of the artery to obtain as round an
      arterial section as possible. The image at end diastole will be chosen and measured with the
      cine loop.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in hemodynamic parameters of radial/ulnar artery from baseline to 30min after specific nerve block followed by 30min after brachial plexus block(phase 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 30 min after specific nerve block, 30 min after brachial plexus block</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>These parameters included peak systolic velocity (PSV, cm/s), end-diastolic velocity (EDV, cm/s), time average maximum velocity (TAMAX),and was measured by Pulsed-wave Doppler(PWD) ultrasound.The cross-sectional area of the artery was assessed with B-mode imaging.Blood flow (BF) = TAMAX× CSA×60s</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in hemodynamic parameters of brachial artery from baseline to 30min after brachial plexus block(phase 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 30 min after brachial plexus block</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>These parameters included peak systolic velocity (PSV, cm/s), end-diastolic velocity (EDV, cm/s), time average maximum velocity (TAMAX), resistance index (RI), and pulsatility index (PI),The cross-sectional area of the artery imaging.Blood flow (BF) = TAMAX× CSA×60s</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in skin temperature from baseline to 30 min after specific nerve block followed by 30 min after brachial plexus block(phase 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 30 min after specific nerve block, 30 min after brachial plexus block</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Skin temperature was measured at four different points within the cutaneous innervation areas of the musculocutaneous(lateral skin of forearm), ulnar(hypothenar region), radial (thumb-index web) and median(thenar)  Specific points were located with skin marker to provide consistency of measurement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Success of Brachial Plexus Block ( phase 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 min after brachial plexus block</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Success of Brachial Plexus Block(BPB) was defined as the absence of sensation to in all innervation areas of above four nerves (musculocutaneous, ulnar, radial, and median nerves) 30min. after the BPB and no pain during the surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in skin temperature from baseline to 30min after brachial plexus block(phase 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline,30 min after brachial plexus block</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Skin temperature was measured at the thenar</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>10</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Upper Limb Nerve Block</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group MC(phase 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>specific nerve block:musculocutaneous nerve block</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group UL( phase 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>specific nerve block:ulnar nerve block</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group RA (phase 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>specific nerve block:radial nerve block</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group ME (phase 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>specific nerve block:median nerve block</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group A(phase 2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>30ml ropivacaine 0.125%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group B(phase 2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>30ml ropivacaine 0.2%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group C(phase 2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>30ml ropivacaine 0.25%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group D(phase 2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>30ml ropivacaine 0.375%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group E(phase 2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>30ml ropivacaine 0.5%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group F(phase 2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>30ml ropivacaine 0.75%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>specific nerve block</intervention_name>
    <description>specific nerve blocks of the musculocutaneous, radial, ulnar, or median nerves at axillary region</description>
    <arm_group_label>group MC(phase 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>group UL( phase 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>group RA (phase 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>group ME (phase 1)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ropivacaine</intervention_name>
    <description>Different concentration of ropivacaine</description>
    <arm_group_label>group A(phase 2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>group B(phase 2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>group C(phase 2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>group D(phase 2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>group E(phase 2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>group F(phase 2)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Naropin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologist physical status I-III patients

          -  aged 18-70 yr

          -  weighing 40-80 kg

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  infection at the site of needle insertion

          -  coagulopathy

          -  international normalized ratio &gt;1.4

          -  platelet count &lt;80×109 litre-1

          -  allergy to local anaesthetics

          -  peripheral neurological disease

          -  peripheral vascular disease

          -  patients do not agree to sign the informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ting Li, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wenzhou Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Second Affiliated Hospital &amp; Yuying Children hospital of Wenzhou Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wenzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>325027</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.wzhealth.com/content/32.aspx</url>
    <description>The Second Affiliated Hospital &amp; Yuying Children hospital of Wenzhou Medical University</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.zjwst.gov.cn</url>
    <description>Health and Family Planning Commission of Zhejiang Province, China</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li J, Karmakar MK, Li X, Kwok WH, Ngan Kee WD. Regional hemodynamic changes after an axillary brachial plexus block: a pulsed-wave Doppler ultrasound study. Reg Anesth Pain Med. 2012 Jan-Feb;37(1):111-8. doi: 10.1097/AAP.0b013e318234007e.</citation>
    <PMID>22030722</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shemesh D, Olsha O, Orkin D, Raveh D, Goldin I, Reichenstein Y, Zigelman C. Sympathectomy-like effects of brachial plexus block in arteriovenous access surgery. Ultrasound Med Biol. 2006 Jun;32(6):817-22.</citation>
    <PMID>16785004</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hermanns H, Braun S, Werdehausen R, Werner A, Lipfert P, Stevens MF. Skin temperature after interscalene brachial plexus blockade. Reg Anesth Pain Med. 2007 Nov-Dec;32(6):481-7.</citation>
    <PMID>18035293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sahin L, Gul R, Mizrak A, Deniz H, Sahin M, Koruk S, Cesur M, Goksu S. Ultrasound-guided infraclavicular brachial plexus block enhances postoperative blood flow in arteriovenous fistulas. J Vasc Surg. 2011 Sep;54(3):749-53. doi: 10.1016/j.jvs.2010.12.045. Epub 2011 Mar 2.</citation>
    <PMID>21367563</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hingorani AP, Ascher E, Gupta P, Alam S, Marks N, Schutzer RW, Multyala M, Shiferson A, Yorkovich W, Jacob T, Salles-Cunha S. Regional anesthesia: preferred technique for venodilatation in the creation of upper extremity arteriovenous fistulae. Vascular. 2006 Jan-Feb;14(1):23-6. Erratum in: Vascular. 2006 Mar-Apr;14(2):118. Multyala, Manykiam [corrected to Multyala, Manikyam].</citation>
    <PMID>16849019</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Breschan C, Kraschl R, Jost R, Marhofer P, Likar R. Axillary brachial plexus block for treatment of severe forearm ischemia after arterial cannulation in an extremely low birth-weight infant. Paediatr Anaesth. 2004 Aug;14(8):681-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15283829</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ebert B, Braunschweig R, Reill P. [Quantification of variations in arm perfusion after plexus anesthesia with color doppler sonography]. Anaesthesist. 1995 Dec;44(12):859-62. German.</citation>
    <PMID>8594960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Badal JJ, Kiesau A, Boyle P. Effects of median nerve block on radial artery diameter and peak velocity. Local Reg Anesth. 2010;3:5-10. Epub 2010 Feb 23.</citation>
    <PMID>22915862</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van der Werff JF, Medici G, Hovius SE, Kusuma A. Axillary plexus blockade in microvascular surgery, a steal phenomenon? Microsurgery. 1995;16(3):141-3.</citation>
    <PMID>7637621</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sonntag BV, Murphy RX Jr, Chernofsky MA, Chowdary RP. Microvascular steal phenomenon in lower extremity reconstruction. Ann Plast Surg. 1995 Mar;34(3):336-9; discussion 339-40.</citation>
    <PMID>7598395</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lange KH, Jansen T, Asghar S, Kristensen PL, Skjønnemand M, Nørgaard P. Skin temperature measured by infrared thermography after specific ultrasound-guided blocking of the musculocutaneous, radial, ulnar, and median nerves in the upper extremity. Br J Anaesth. 2011 Jun;106(6):887-95. doi: 10.1093/bja/aer085. Epub 2011 Apr 6.</citation>
    <PMID>21474476</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lehtipalo S, Winsö O, Koskinen LO, Johansson G, Biber B. Cutaneous sympathetic vasoconstrictor reflexes for the evaluation of interscalene brachial plexus block. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2000 Sep;44(8):946-52.</citation>
    <PMID>10981571</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morgan RF, Reisman NR, Wilgis EF. Anatomic localization of sympathetic nerves in the hand. J Hand Surg Am. 1983 May;8(3):283-8.</citation>
    <PMID>6875230</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campero M, Verdugo RJ, Ochoa JL. Vasomotor innervation of the skin of the hand: a contribution to the study of human anatomy. J Anat. 1993 Jun;182 ( Pt 3):361-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8226291</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kurt E, Ozturk S, Isik S, Zor F. Continuous brachial plexus blockade for digital replantations and toe-to-hand transfers. Ann Plast Surg. 2005 Jan;54(1):24-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15613878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van den Berg B, Berger A, van den Berg E, Zenz M, Brehmeier G, Tizian C. [Continuous plexus anesthesia to improve circulation in peripheral microvascular interventions]. Handchir Mikrochir Plast Chir. 1983 Jun;15(2):101-4. German.</citation>
    <PMID>6884859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fredrickson MJ, Smith KR, Wong AC. Importance of volume and concentration for ropivacaine interscalene block in preventing recovery room pain and minimizing motor block after shoulder surgery. Anesthesiology. 2010 Jun;112(6):1374-81. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3181d6929d.</citation>
    <PMID>20460999</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Casati A, Baciarello M, Di Cianni S, Danelli G, De Marco G, Leone S, Rossi M, Fanelli G. Effects of ultrasound guidance on the minimum effective anaesthetic volume required to block the femoral nerve. Br J Anaesth. 2007 Jun;98(6):823-7. Epub 2007 May 3.</citation>
    <PMID>17478453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gupta PK, Pace NL, Hopkins PM. Effect of body mass index on the ED50 volume of bupivacaine 0.5% for supraclavicular brachial plexus block. Br J Anaesth. 2010 Apr;104(4):490-5. doi: 10.1093/bja/aeq017. Epub 2010 Feb 18.</citation>
    <PMID>20167584</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 7, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Wenzhou Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ting Li</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>associate chief physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hemodynamics</keyword>
  <keyword>anaesthetics</keyword>
  <keyword>brachial plexus</keyword>
  <keyword>peripheral nerves</keyword>
  <keyword>skin temperature</keyword>
  <keyword>sympathetic nervous system</keyword>
  <keyword>dose-response relationship</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ropivacaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
