<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="77329">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02031445</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C012013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02031445</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of MRX-6 Cream 2%</brief_title>
  <acronym>C012013</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of MRX-6 Cream 2% in Pediatric Subjects With Mild to Moderate Atopic Dermatitis Followed by an Open Label Extension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Celsus Therapeutics PLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Celsus Therapeutics PLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Israel: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Randomized, double-blind, parallel group, placebo-controlled, multicenter, efficacy and
      safety study in subjects with mild to moderate atopic dermatitis.

      Following the double blind period, subjects will be allowed to continue treatment with
      topical MRX-6 Cream 2% in an open-label extension.  Demonstrate the efficacy of MRX-6 Cream
      2% compared to Vehicle for the treatment of the signs and symptoms of atopic dermatitis and
      demonstrate the safety of MRX-6 Cream 2% for the treatment of the signs and symptoms of
      atopic dermatitis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigator's Global Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse Events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <condition>Atopic Dermatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>BID</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MRX-6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BID</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MRX-6</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>MRX-6</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects, ≥2 years of age and ≤17 years of age, of any race or ethnicity

          -  Must have clinical diagnosis of mild to moderate atopic dermatitis (AD) at both
             Screening and Baseline Visits, defined as IGA score of 2 or 3 (Hanifin and Rajka,
             Rothe 1980)

          -  Must have AD affecting ≥ 5% total body surface area (TBSA) at Baseline

          -  History of AD for at least 3 months prior to Baseline

          -  Informed consent/assent in accordance with the International Conference on
             Harmonization (ICH) Good Clinical Practice (GCP) Guideline (40 CFR 63.1335) and
             applicable regulations, before completing any study-related procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of topical corticosteroids within 7 days prior to Baseline

          -  Use of systemic corticosteroids, topical calcineurin inhibitors, photo-therapy (eg,
             PUVA, UVB) or immunosuppressive therapy (eg, cyclosporine) within 14 days prior to
             Baseline

          -  Subjects that require systemic therapy for the treatment of atopic dermatitis

          -  Use of systemic anti-infective or antibiotic treatment within 14 days prior to
             Baseline

          -  Subjects who present with clinical conditions other than AD that may interfere with
             the evaluation (eg, generalized erythroderma, acne, Netherton's Syndrome, psoriasis)

          -  Secondary infection of AD (bacterial, viral or fungal) within the skin area under
             study or open skin infections in any area at Baseline

          -  Women of childbearing potential who are lactating or pregnant as determined by urine
             pregnancy test at Screening.  • History of MRX-6 cream 2% sensitivity or to any
             component of the test article

          -  History of severe anxiety and/or depression; any history of suicide attempt

          -  Subjects with a history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) as determined by
             medical history

          -  Subjects with any screening clinical laboratory result outside the normal range that
             is clinically relevant in the opinion of an appropriately qualified physician

          -  Subjects who, in the opinion of the Investigator, would be non compliant with the
             visit schedule or study procedures

          -  Participation in any other investigational trial within 6 weeks of Baseline, or
             during study conduct

          -  Chronic condition(s) which are either unstable or not adequately controlled

          -  Use of non-sedating anti-histamines within 7 days of first dose or at any time during
             study conduct

          -  Drug or alcohol abuse, mental dysfunction, or other condition limiting the subject's
             ability to be compliant with study-related procedures
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pablo Jimenez, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-350-0702</phone>
    <email>pj@celsustx.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tel Aviv Sourasky Medical Center address</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel Aviv</city>
        <zip>64239</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eli Sprecher, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 7, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis, Atopic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
