<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="65395">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01842438</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>03979</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01842438</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Couple Support Intervention for Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Psychosexual Support Following Prostate Cancer Surgery: Feasibility and Outcomes of a Couple-based Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Stirling</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Prostate Cancer UK</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Stirling</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Even with careful prostate surgery, men find it difficult to have an erection. Our previous
      research shows that couples are not often supported to cope with the effects of surgery on
      their sexual relationships. In this study, the investigators will design a way of supporting
      couples, and test how well it works.

      The investigators will decide what the support should include (e.g. duration, frequency and
      timing of the support). The investigators will do this by looking at available literature on
      the subject.

      The investigators will recruit 68 couples to the study, half will receive standard care and
      the other half will be invited to attend six sessions of psychosexual support with specially
      trained professionals (trained by men affected by prostate conditions and a cancer/couple
      support specialist). Before and after the support, men and their partners will be asked to
      complete questionnaires which measure quality-of-life, emotional needs, and their
      relationship. The investigators will ask the couples to fill out the questionnaires again
      six-months later to see if the support has long-term benefits. At the end of the study the
      investigators will also interview 10 couples to find out their views of the support, and
      another 10 couples about standard treatment.

      When the investigators have tested this support, they expect to see men and their partners
      tell us that their quality of life has improved, and they have higher satisfaction with
      their relationship. The investigators will calculate the overall cost of providing this
      support, and the benefits it has on reducing the need for other health-care services (like
      GP use).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Scientific abstract

      Evidence shows significant unmet psychosexual needs for couples affected by prostate cancer.
      Studies have identified the contribution that psychosocial interventions could have for
      couples, e.g. strengthening healthy adaptation and better communication, developing coping
      skills for distressed couples, and facilitating healthy spousal communication to address the
      sexual rehabilitation needs.

      This is a feasibility study with a built-in pilot, which will examine the acceptability,
      feasibility and outcomes of a psychosexual intervention to support couples, drawing on the
      MRC complex intervention framework.

      The intervention will be developed from the extant and our pilot work. Men in outpatient
      surgical follow-up clinics will be screened using EPIC, and recruited if scoring under the
      clinical threshold for potency. 68 couples will be randomised to two arms, one receiving six
      sessions of couple-support from specially trained counsellors and the others receiving
      standard care. The primary outcome measure is health-related quality-of-life. Pre, post and
      6-month follow-up outcomes will be measured in both individual (quality of life;
      anxiety/depression) and in relational terms (relationship between couples). An economic
      analysis will identify population costs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>EPIC (Expanded Prostate cancer Index Composite)</measure>
    <time_frame>6months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>EPIC is a quality of life tool used in prostate cancer studies, focused on physical and sexual outcomes. It is validated with population norms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HADS (Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>6months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>the HADS has two scales: one anxiety and one depression. It is validated with population norms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SCORE15 (systemic core outcome measure)</measure>
    <time_frame>6months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>SCORE15 is an index of Family Function and Change, with 15 items.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">136</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral: psychosexual intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>6-sessions of couple support focused on relationships and psychosexual functioning</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will not receive the intervention during the life-span of the project</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Behavioral: psychosexual intervention</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral: psychosexual intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Score of ≤60 on EPIC  (a signal of potency)

          -  &gt;11 weeks post-operative for PCa (to recruit people who have recovered from the
             immediate effects from surgery and begun to regain some functioning. Follow-ups are
             held at 6weeks, 12weeks, 6months from surgery, until no further follow-up is
             required).

          -  Has a partner

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Does not have a partner (this is a couple intervention, the study can therefore only
             include men with a partner).

          -  Prognosis of ≤1year (Most men who have had recent surgery will have a good prognosis,
             consequently it is unlikely that many men will be excluded by this criteria.)

          -  Unable to provide informed consent.

          -  Residing in Dumfries and Galloway. The recruiting clinic sees patients from a wide
             catchment area. However to prevent excess burden on participants traveling to the
             intervention site in Edinburgh, the investigators will exclude those living in
             Dumfries and Galloway.

          -  &gt;2 years from surgery (since long term adaptation will have commenced).

          -  Unable to communicate in English (this is a feasibility trial, if the study moves to
             a full scale trial in future then it will seek to include couples and
             interpreters/translators).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Liz Forbat, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Stirling</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Liz Forbat, PhD</last_name>
    <email>elizabeth.forbat@stir.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Western General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edinburgh</city>
        <state>Lothian</state>
        <zip>EH4 2XU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Prasad Bollina, MBBS; FRCS</last_name>
      <phone>0044 131 537 1000</phone>
      <email>Prasad.Bollina@luht.scot.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alan McNeill, MBBS; FRCS</last_name>
      <email>Alan.McNeill@nhslothian.scot.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 24, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Stirling</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr Liz Forbat</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Reader</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sexual Dysfunctions, Psychological</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
