<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="70336">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01690741</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ISK-N101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01690741</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 1 Trial of Intravenously Administered Nerofe™ in Subjects With Advanced Malignancies</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Open-Label, Dose-Escalation Study Evaluating the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, Pharmacodynamics, and Clinical Effects of Intravenously Administered Nerofe™ in Subjects With Advanced Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Immune System Key Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Immune System Key Ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Israel: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will be the first to test the anti-cancer peptide Nerofe in humans. It will
      evaluate the safety, pharmacokinetic behavior, and pharmacodynamic and clinical effects of
      Nerofe given intravenously every other day to patients with advanced malignant disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1 single-center, open-label, non-randomized, dose-escalation study, to be
      conducted in 2 phases.  The Dose Escalation Phase will determine the maximum tolerated dose
      (MTD) of Nerofe and evaluate its safety and tolerability, pharmacokinetics,
      pharmacodynamics, immunogenicity, and preliminary clinical effects.  The subsequent Dose
      Confirmation Phase will be a cohort expansion at or below the MTD of Nerofe.  Subjects will
      be treated with IV doses of Nerofe thrice weekly (on alternating days) in consecutive,
      28-day cycles.  Subjects will be evaluated regularly for safety.  Subjects who tolerate the
      drug and who do not experience progressive disease, intolerable toxicity, or meet any of the
      other withdrawal criteria may continue to receive Nerofe for up to 6 cycles, at the
      discretion of the Principal Investigator.  Throughout the trial, oversight will be provided
      by the Clinical Safety Committee.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety, as determined by frequency, nature, and severity of adverse events; and the profile of dose-limiting toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic effects of Nerofe, through the measurement of serum concentrations of biomarkers (including cytokines and circulating soluble T1/ST2 receptor) and peripheral blood mononuclear cell expression of T1/ST2 receptor</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical effects of Nerofe on cancer, as assessed by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic behavior of Nerofe: plasma concentrations in ng/mL</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose (Cycle 1 Days 1 and 29 only); and 0.25, 1, 2, 4h, 6, 8, and 24h following the end of infusion (Cycle 1 Days 1 and 29)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic behavior of Nerofe: plasma half-life in minutes</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 Day 1 and Day 29</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between pretreatment fresh/archival tumor tissue T1/ST2 receptor expression and biological activity of Nerofe</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nerofe</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Nerofe administered intravenously 3x/week</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nerofe</intervention_name>
    <description>Nerofe administered intravenously 3x/week</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nerofe</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tumor-Cells Apoptosis Factor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males and females at least 18 years of age.

          2. Pathologically confirmed locally advanced and/or metastatic solid tumor for which
             standard therapy proven to provide clinical benefit does not exist, is no longer
             effective, or cannot be tolerated.

          3. Evaluable disease, either measurable on physical examination or imaging by Response
             Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors, or by informative tumor markers.

          4. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status of ≤1.

          5. Acceptable clinical laboratory values at screening, as indicated by:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥1,500/mm3;

               -  Platelets ≥75,000/mm3;

               -  Total bilirubin ≤1.5 × the upper limit of normal (ULN);

               -  AST (SGOT) ≤2.5 × the ULN;

               -  ALT (SGPT) ≤2.5 × the ULN;

               -  Serum creatinine ≤1.5 mg/dL; and

               -  Negative serum hCG test in women of childbearing potential.

          6. Willing and able to provide written Informed Consent and comply with the requirements
             of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any chemotherapy, immunomodulatory drug therapy, anti-neoplastic hormonal therapy
             (unless dose has been stable for 3 months), immunosuppressive therapy,
             corticosteroids &gt; 20 mg/day prednisone or equivalent, or growth factor treatment (eg,
             erythropoietin) within 14 days prior to initiation of study drug.

          2. Presence of an acute toxicity of prior chemotherapy, with the exception of alopecia
             or peripheral neuropathy, that has not resolved to ≤ Grade 1, as determined by NCI
             CTCAE v 4.0.

          3. Life expectancy &lt;20 weeks.

          4. Major surgery or radiation therapy within 28 days prior to initiation of study drug.

          5. Receipt of radiotherapy to &gt;25 % of bone marrow.

          6. Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or acquired immunodeficiency
             syndrome-related illness.

          7. Known active hepatitis B or C or other active liver disease (other than malignancy).

          8. Active infection requiring systemic therapy.

          9. Uncontrolled congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association Classification 3 or
             4), angina, myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular accident, coronary/peripheral
             artery bypass graft surgery, transient ischemic attack, or pulmonary embolism within
             3 months prior to initiation of study drug.

         10. Uncontrolled arterial hypertension, or anti-hypertensive drugs whose type or dose has
             been changed within 3 months prior to screening or whose dose is anticipated to
             change within cycle 1.

         11. History of pre-syncope or orthostasis.

         12. Risk of syncope, in the judgment of the principle investigator.

         13. History of or ongoing cardiac dysrhythmias requiring treatment, atrial fibrillation
             of any grade, or persistent prolongation of the QTc (Fridericia) interval to &gt; 450
             msec for males or &gt; 470 msec for females.

         14. Pregnant or lactating female.

         15. Any severe, acute, or chronic medical or psychiatric condition, or laboratory
             abnormality that may increase the risk associated with study participation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yoram Devary, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Immune System Key Ltd</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Raanan Berger, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>972-3-5302290</phone>
    <email>raanan.berger@sheba.health.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Aliza Ackerstein</last_name>
    <phone>972-3-5308402</phone>
    <email>aliza.ackerstein@sheba.health.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Oncology and Radiotherapy, Cancer Research Center, Chaim Sheba Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel Hashomer</city>
        <state>Ramat Gan</state>
        <zip>52621</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Raanan Berger, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>972-3-5302290</phone>
      <email>raanan.berger@sheba.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Aliza Ackerstein</last_name>
      <phone>972-3-5308402</phone>
      <email>aliza.ackerstein@sheba.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raanan Berger, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.immunesk.com/</url>
    <description>Immune System Key Ltd. Website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sandler U, Devary O, Braitbard O, Ohana J, Kass G, Rubinstein AM, Friedman ZY, Devary Y. NEROFE--a novel human hormone-peptide with anti-cancer activity. J Exp Ther Oncol. 2010;8(4):327-39.</citation>
    <PMID>21222365</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 8, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 12, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Malignancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Solid tumors</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
