<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="73765">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01770743</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EBS.AVA.208 / DMID 11-0055</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HHSN272201000035C</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01770743</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 2 Safety and Immunogenicity Study for an Anthrax Vaccine Using 3 Schedules and Two Dose Levels</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2, Randomized, Parallel-Group, Active-Controlled, Double-Blind Study to Evaluate the Safety and Immunogenicity of AV7909 for Post-Exposure Prophylaxis of Anthrax Using Three Immunization Schedules and Two Dose Levels in Healthy Adult Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emergent BioSolutions</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emergent BioSolutions</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the safety and immunogenicity of an anthrax vaccine.
      The vaccine schedule and dose will also be assessed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The safety and immunogenicity of AV7909 for post-exposure prophylaxis of anthrax will be
      evaluated using a randomized, parallel-group, active-controlled, double-blind design with
      three immunization schedules and two dose levels in healthy adult volunteers.  Safety will
      be assessed by clinical laboratory tests (hematology, serum chemistry, and urinalysis),
      monitoring of adverse events, vital signs, and physical examinations.  Reactogenicity
      (systemic and injection site reactions) will be assessed by the subjects using subject
      e-diaries for 7 days after each immunization and by the investigator at in-clinic visits 7
      and 14 days after each  immunization, and at other visits, if applicable.  Immunogenicity
      will be measured as toxin neutralizing antibody (TNA) response and seroconversion rates.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxin Neutralizing Antibody (TNA) Level at Day 63</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 63</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Immunogenicity measured by the lower bound (LB) of the 95% confidence intervals (CIs) for the proportion of subjects in each study arm with Day 63 TNA 50% neutralization factor (NF50) values greater than or equal to threshold</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety will be evaluated by adverse events, including assessment of symptoms, physical exam findings, clinical laboratory tests, and vital signs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TNA Level at Day 42</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 42</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Immunogenicity measured by the percentage of subjects in each study arm with Day 42 TNA NF50 values greater than or equal to threshold</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TNA Level at Day 28</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Immunogenicity measured by the percentage of subjects with Day 28 TNA NF50 values greater than or equal to threshold</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TNA Seroconversion Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 84</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Immunogenicity measured by the percentage of subjects who have seroconverted (defined as a 4-fold increase over Day 0 in TNA NF50 value) at Days 21, 28, 35, 42, 49, 63, and 84</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">168</enrollment>
  <condition>Anthrax</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AV7909 (Day 0 and 14)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Route of administration:  Intramuscular Dose: 0.5 mL Schedule:  Day 0 and Day 14</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AV7909 (Day 0 and 28)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Route of administration:  Intramuscular Dose: 0.5 mL Schedule:  Day 0 and Day 28</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AV7909 (Day 0, 14, and 28)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Route of administration:  Intramuscular Dose: 0.5 mL Schedule:  Day 0, Day 14,and Day 28</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AV7909 Reduced Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Route of administration:  Intramuscular Dose: 0.25 mL Schedule:  Day 0, Day 14,and Day 28</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BioThrax</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Route of administration:  Intramuscular Dose: 0.5 mL Schedule:  Day 0, Day 14,and Day 28</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AV7909</intervention_name>
    <description>Anthrax Vaccine Adsorbed plus CPG 7909 Adjuvant</description>
    <arm_group_label>AV7909 (Day 0 and 14)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>AV7909 (Day 0 and 28)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>AV7909 (Day 0, 14, and 28)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>AV7909 Reduced Dose</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AV7909 Anthrax Vaccine</other_name>
    <other_name>NuThrax</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BioThrax</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>BioThrax</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Anthrax Vaccine Adsorbed (AVA)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Be 18-50 years old

          -  Be in good health

          -  Have access to a computer and the internet so you can complete a diary

          -  Agree to abstain from sex the first 84 days of the study or practice birth control if
             you are a woman who is able to get pregnant

          -  Have not donated blood for the previous 8 weeks

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A known anaphylactic response, severe systemic response, or serious hypersensitivity
             reaction to a prior immunization.

          -  A history of latex allergy.

          -  Have received a shot (vaccine), including flu shots, in the past 6 weeks or plan to
             get a shot for 4 weeks after the last study shot is given.

          -  Have previously served in the military any time after 1990 or plan to enlist in the
             military from Screening through Day 84.

          -  Prior immunization with anthrax vaccine, recombinant protective antigen (rPA)
             vaccine, or known exposure to anthrax organisms.

          -  Have participated in anthrax therapeutic or vaccine studies (monoclonal anti-PA or
             anthrax immune globulins or anthrax vaccines).

          -  Participation in any investigational study involving use of a pharmacological
             intervention within 30 days before the Screening visit or planning to participate in
             a study requiring dosing through the 12-month safety follow-up telephone call.

          -  Have a known diagnosis of any immunodeficiency disease including but not limited to:
             acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS), common variable immunodeficiency disease,
             immunoglobulin A (IgA) deficiency, or hypogammaglobulinemia.

          -  Past history of significant autoimmune disease such as rheumatoid arthritis, lupus
             erythematous, psoriasis in the area of vaccinations, or requires immunotherapy,
             glomerulonephritis, or autoimmune thyroiditis.

          -  Have received immunosuppressive therapy with cytotoxic drugs or Rituximab within the
             past 2 years.

          -  A history of cytotoxic chemotherapy or radiation therapy.

          -  Chronic (&gt;10 days) daily oral or parenteral corticosteroid therapy in the past 12
             months.

          -  Any lung disease, including reactive airway disease, which requires the daily use of
             medications.

          -  A female currently breastfeeding or with a positive pregnancy test.

          -  A history of drug or alcohol abuse within 12 months prior to Screening, or a positive
             result on a urine drug screen for cocaine, marijuana, opiates, methamphetamines,
             benzodiazepines, or oxycodone.

          -  Any tattoo or other skin condition in the deltoid region on either arm that may
             obscure the assessment of the injection sites.

          -  A medical condition that, in the opinion of the PI or designee, could adversely
             impact the subject's participation or safety or the conduct of the study.

          -  Any planned elective in-patient surgery during the study period.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Hopkins, MD, MPH, TM</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emergent BioSolutions</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Miami Research Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Costal Carolina Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mount Pleasant</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29464</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Central Texas Allergy and Asthma</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Braunfels</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78130</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jean Brown Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84124</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 16, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>post-exposure prophylaxis</keyword>
  <keyword>toxin neutralization assay</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anthrax</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
