<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="4687">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01656902</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAG-G-H-1202</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01656902</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Effectiveness Study to Evaluate NOVOCART® 3D Plus Compared to the Microfracture to Treat Articular Cartilage Defects of the Knee</brief_title>
  <acronym>N3D</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective Randomized Controlled Multicenter Phase-III Clinical Study to Evaluate the Safety and Effectiveness of NOVOCART® 3D Plus Compared to the Standard Procedure Microfracture in the Treatment of Articular Cartilage Defects of the Knee</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tetec AG</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tetec AG</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Paul-Ehrlich-Institut</authority>
    <authority>Austria: Agency for Health and Food Safety</authority>
    <authority>Switzerland: Swissmedic</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      For the cartilage cell product NOVOCART® 3D plus, which is used in the study described here,
      the company TETEC AG obtained an expanded production authorization from the medication
      monitoring authorities in compliance with Section 13, Para. 1 of the Medicinal Products Act
      in 2003. This entitles TETEC AG to produce the pharmaceutical product and already distribute
      it. More than 6000 patients were already successfully treated with NOVOCART® 3D in Europe
      since 2003. In order to obtain a general market authorization for NOVOCART® 3D plus, this
      control group study is conducted, in which the superiority of the safety and effectiveness
      of carrier-bound Autologous Chondrocyte Transplantation with NOVOCART® 3D plus compared to
      the standard of care microfracture surgery needs to be proven. This study further aims at
      developing and validating known and new biologic markers for the quality and clinical
      efficacy of the product as requested in the context of identity, purity and potency
      characteristics of the medicinal/investigational product.

      The patients will receive one of the therapeutic procedures in the study. The treatment
      procedure which will be used will be decided by a previously specified random process. This
      type of study meets the high quality requirements of the statutorily specified safety and
      quality regulations which are also referred to as &quot;Good Clinical Practice&quot; (GCP). The
      probability of the patient being allocated to one of the two treatments is 2:1; that is, an
      approx. 67% probability of therapy with NOVOCART® 3D plus and an approx. 33% probability of
      therapy with microfracture. Neither the patient, nor the investigator will be able to
      influence the treatment assignment.

      Patients will be screened for eligibility at the Screening Visit. Each patient will remain
      in the study for 36 months post-implant for the effectiveness assessments, and then an
      additional two years to complete the planned post-market phase. Each patient will be in the
      study for up to five years.

      Cells and tissues collected from this study will be used in other in vitro-controlled
      experiments aimed at developing and validating known and novel biologic markers to quantify
      cell quality in the context of identity, purity and potency. Prognostic values of these
      biologic markers will be examined by correlating them with clinical data collected in this
      study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective IKDC score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline assessment to 36-month follow-up assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint is the change from baseline in the &quot;2000 International Knee Documentation Committee&quot; (IKDC) subjective score to 36-month visit.
The IKDC will be recorded for NOVOCART® 3D plus and microfracture patients at baseline visit 1 and at the 6 weeks, 3-, 6-, 12-, 24-, 36-, 48,- and 60-month follow-up assessments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective IKDC score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline assessment to 24-month follow-up assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In addition to the primary endpoint, another secondary efficacy endpoint is the change from baseline in the subjective IKDC score to 24-month visit. A sequentially rejecting, hierarchical test procedure will be employed to test this secondary endpoint after the test primary efficacy variable was passed.
The IKDC will be recorded for NOVOCART® 3D plus and microfracture patients at baseline visit 1 and at the 6 weeks, 3-, 6-, 12-, 24-, 36-, 48,- and 60-month follow-up assessments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>IKDC objective physician score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline assessment to 36-month follow-up assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The IKDC objective physician score will be recorded for both arms at baseline visit 1 and at the 6 weeks, 3-, 6-, 12-, 24-, 36-, 48,- and 60-month follow-up assessments. A sequentially rejecting, hierarchical test procedure will be employed to test these secondary endpoints in the a-priori defined order given here after the test primary efficacy variable was passed.
The change from baseline to the 36-month visit in the IKDC objective physician score and from baseline to the 24-month visit will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>IKDC objective physician score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline assessment to 24-month follow-up assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The IKDC objective physician score will be recorded for both arms at baseline visit 1 and at the 6 weeks, 3-, 6-, 12-, 24-, 36-, 48,- and 60-month follow-up assessments. A sequentially rejecting, hierarchical test procedure will be employed to test these secondary endpoints in the a-priori defined order given here after the test primary efficacy variable was passed.
The change from baseline to the 36-month visit in the IKDC objective physician score and from baseline to the 24-month visit will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline assessment to 36-month follow-up assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The KOOS will be recorded for both arms at baseline visit 1 and at the 6 weeks, 3-, 6-, 12-, 24-, 36-, 48,- and 60-month follow-up assessments.
A sequentially rejecting, hierarchical test procedure will be employed to test these secondary endpoints in the a-priori defined order given here after the test primary efficacy variable was passed. The change from baseline to 36-month visit in the Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) and from baseline to 24-month visit will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline assessment to 24-month follow-up assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The KOOS will be recorded for both arms at baseline visit 1 and at the 6 weeks, 3-, 6-, 12-, 24-, 36-, 48,- and 60-month follow-up assessments.
A sequentially rejecting, hierarchical test procedure will be employed to test these secondary endpoints in the a-priori defined order given here after the test primary efficacy variable was passed. The change from baseline to 36-month visit in the Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) and from baseline to 24-month visit will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MOCART Score (MRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline assessment to the 36-month assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Another secondary efficacy endpoint is the in vivo performance (grading on quality of cartilage fill) measured by the change from baseline to the 36-month assessment of the Magnetic Resonance Observation of Cartilage Repair Tissue (MOCART) score. These assessments will be performed on a subset of patients (64 in each treatment group).
The MRI will be recorded at 3, 12, 36 and 60 months follow-up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life as measured by the SF-36 survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline assessment to 36-month follow-up assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Another secondary efficacy endpoint is the change from baseline to the 36-month visit in the SF-36 to measure clinical utility and summarize health-related quality-of-life and cost-effectiveness. The SF-36 will be recorded for NOVOCART® 3D plus and microfracture patients at baseline visit 1 and at the 6 weeks, 3-, 6-, 12-, 24-, 36-, 48,- and 60-month follow-up assessments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life as measured by the SF-36 survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline assessment to 24-month follow-up assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Another secondary efficacy endpoint is the change from baseline to the 36-month visit in the SF-36 to measure clinical utility and summarize health-related quality-of-life and cost-effectiveness. The SF-36 will be recorded for NOVOCART® 3D plus and microfracture patients at baseline visit 1 and at the 6 weeks, 3-, 6-, 12-, 24-, 36-, 48,- and 60-month follow-up assessments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical time (cut-to-suture time)</measure>
    <time_frame>Transplantation (24 +-5 days post-arthroscopy) and/or arthroscopy (&gt;= 1 day after screening), depending on the study arm</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The surgical time will be measured in minutes and recorded for NOVOCART® 3D plus patients at arthroscopy (&gt;= 1 day after screening) and transplantation (24 +-5 days post-arthroscopy); for microfracture patients surgical time will be measured in minutes and recorded at arthroscopy (&gt;= 1 day after screening).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of incision</measure>
    <time_frame>Only for verum group at transplantation (24 +-5 days post-arthroscopy)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The length of incision will be measured in cm and recorded for NOVOCART® 3D plus patients at transplantation (24 +-5 days post-arthroscopy)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Any unanticipated adverse event</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline assessment up to 60-months follow-up assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Event descriptions, onset, resolution dates, relationship to the IP and procedures of any AEs will be recorded. Each event will be categorized by seriousness and intensity to facilitate complete safety reporting throughout the trial.
While comparisons between treatment groups can be made for each class of AE, there is no statistical hypothesis governing acceptance of this endpoint at the end of the clinical study because of the different AE profiles associated with the two treatment arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">261</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Articular Cartilage Defects in the Knee Joint</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>N3D plus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>NOVOCART® 3D plus (Autologous Chondrocyte Transplantation System)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Microfracture</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Microfracture is the standard care surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NOVOCART® 3D plus</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>N3D plus</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Autologous Chondrocyte Transplantation System</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Microfracture</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Microfracture</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Microfracture according to Steadman</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient is ≥18 and ≤65 years old at time of screening.

          -  Patient has a localized articular cartilage defect of the femoral condyle or the
             trochlea of the knee. 2 localized cartilage defects are accepted if the total defect
             size is ≤ 6 cm2, both cartilage defects are located at the femoral condyle and/or the
             trochlea and both cartilage defects are to be treated with NOVOCART® 3D plus or
             microfracture..

          -  Patient has a defect size ≥2 and ≤6 cm2 post-debridement.

          -  Patient has an intact (≤Grade 2 ICRS classification) articulating joint surface (no
             &quot;kissing lesions&quot;).

          -  Patient has an intact meniscus (maximum 1/2-resection).

          -  Patient has a stable knee joint or sufficiently reconstructed ligaments. If not,
             ligament repair has to be done within 6 weeks to the planned cartilage treatment
             (ACT/microfracture).

          -  Patient has free range of motion of the affected knee joint or ≤10° of extension and
             flexion loss.

          -  Patient has a defect of grade III or IV according to the ICRS classification.

          -  Patient has a maximum baseline score of 60/100 on the 2000 IKDC subjective knee
             evaluation.

          -  Patient is willing and able to give written informed consent to participate in the
             study and to comply with all study requirements, including attending all follow-up
             visits and assessments and postoperative rehabilitation regimen.

        Preoperative Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient is the investigator or any subinvestigator, research assistant, pharmacist,
             study coordinator, other staff or relative thereof directly involved in the conduct
             of the protocol.

          -  Patient is unable to undergo magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).

          -  Patient has prior surgical treatment of the target knee using mosaicplasty and/or
             microfracture (Note: prior diagnostic arthroscopy with debridement and lavage are
             acceptable). Anterior cruciate ligament repair are accepted, if the target knee is
             stable or a primary ACL reconstruction is performed within 6 weeks to the planned
             cartilage treatment (ACT/microfracture).

          -  Patient has radiologically apparent degenerative joint disease in the target knee as
             determined by Kellgren and Lawrence grade ≥2.

          -  Patient has chronic inflammatory arthritis, and/or infectious arthritis.

          -  Patient has joint space narrowing &gt;1/3 in the target knee when compared to the other
             knee or &lt;3 mm joint space measured on X-ray.

          -  Patient has an instable knee joint or unsufficiently reconstructed ligaments. If
             ligament repair is necessary, the repair has to be performed within 6 weeks to the
             planned cartilage treatment (ACT/microfracture).

          -  Patient has malalignment (no valgus- or varus-deformity) in the target knee. In
             suspected cases, the mechanical axis must be established radiographically through
             complete leg imaging during standing and in a.p. or rather p.a. projection. The
             Mikulicz line is not allowed to deviate more than 5 mm of the Eminentia
             intercondylaris. If alignment is necessary, surgery has to be performed within 6
             weeks to the planned cartilage treatment (ACT/microfracture).

          -  Patient has prior surgical treatment of clinical relevance of the target knee.

          -  Patient has an osteochondral defect.

          -  Patient has bilateral lower limb pain or low back pain.

          -  Patient has a known systemic connective tissue disease.

          -  Patient has a known history of diabetes.

          -  Patient has a known autoimmune disease.

          -  Patient has a known immunological suppressive disorder or is taking
             immunosuppressants.

          -  Patient is currently systemically or intra-articularly taking steroids and/or has
             used steroids within the last 30 days prior to the planned arthroscopy (tissue
             harvest/microfracture).

          -  The patient has a known history of HIV/AIDS.

          -  The patient has a known history of Treponema pallidum (syphilis).

          -  The patient has an active hepatitis B or C infection with verified antigens. Patients
             with a cured hepatitis B or C infection and/or verified antibodies are not excluded.

          -  The patient has at the site of surgery an active systemic or local microbial
             infection, eczematization or inflammable skin alterations (including Protozoonosis:
             Babesiosis, Trypanosomiasis (e.g. Chagas-Disease), Leishmaniasis, persistent
             bacterial infections, like Brucellosis, spotted and typhus fever, other
             Rickettsiosis, Leprosy, Recurrent Fever, Melioidosis or Tularaemia).

          -  Patient has a known history of cancer.

          -  Patient is taking indomethacin  or other NSAIDs as acute anti-pain and/or
             anti-inflammatory medication.

          -  Patient has a known history of osteoporosis; also patients with primary
             hyperparathyroidism, hyperthyroidism, chronic renal failure or patients with prior
             pathological fractures independent of the genesis.

          -  Patient has any degenerative muscular or neurological condition that would interfere
             with evaluation of outcome measures including but not limited to Parkinson's disease,
             amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS), or multiple sclerosis (MS).

          -  Patient has a body mass index (BMI) &gt;35 kg/m2.

          -  Patient is a woman who is pregnant, lactating or anticipates becoming pregnant within
             24 months after surgery.

          -  Patient is currently participating, or has participated in any other clinical study
             within 3 months prior to the screening visit.

          -  Patient has known current or recent history of illicit drug or alcohol abuse or
             dependence defined as the continued use of alcohol or drugs despite the development
             of social, legal or health problems.

          -  Patient has psychiatric or cognitive impairment that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would interfere with the patient's ability to comply with the study
             requirements, e.g., Alzheimer's disease.

          -  Patient has any other condition, which, in the opinion of the investigator, would
             make the patient unsuitable for the study.

        Intraoperative Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient has a defect size &lt;2 or &gt;6 cm2 post-debridement.

          -  Patient has &gt;2 independent cartilage lesions of a total defect size of  &gt;6 cm2 that
             are not located at the femoral condyle and/or the trochlea in one knee that need to
             be treated with NOVOCART® 3D plus or microfracture.

          -  Patient is indicated for concurrent meniscus transplant.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter Angele, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universitätsklinikum Regensburg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Silvia Rombach</last_name>
    <phone>+49 7121 514 87 790</phone>
    <email>rombach@tetec-ag.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Felix Michnacs</last_name>
    <phone>+49 7121 514 87 78</phone>
    <email>felix.michnacs@tetec-ag.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinische Universität Wien</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wien</city>
        <zip>1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patrick Platzer, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+43 (0)4 04 00 59 01</phone>
      <email>patrick.platzer@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patrick Platzer, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christian Albrecht, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Theresienkrankenhaus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mannheim</city>
        <zip>68165</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gerald Mannheim, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0)6 21 42 44 254</phone>
      <email>g.zimmermann@theresienkrankenhaus.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gerald Zimmermann, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Florian Schwoebel, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Timo Markl, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orthopädische Klinik und Poliklinik der LMU München</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muenchen</city>
        <zip>81377</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter Müller, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0)8 97 09 53 781</phone>
      <email>peter.mueller@med.uni-muenchen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Müller, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthias Pietschmann, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tobias Düll, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joerg Hausdorf, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Regensburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Regensburg</city>
        <zip>93042</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter Angele, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0)9 41 94 46 803</phone>
      <email>peter.angele@klinik.uni-r.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Angele, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Johannes Zellner, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Werner Krutsch, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christian Pfeifer, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Berufsgenossenschaftliche Unfallklinik Tübingen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tübingen</city>
        <zip>72076</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wilhelm Loewe, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0)7 07 16 06 11 66</phone>
      <email>wloewe@bgu-tuebingen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wilhelm Loewe, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Markus Gühring, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christoph Gonser, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Atesch Ateschrang, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Basel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basel</city>
        <zip>4031</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Geert Pagenstert, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+41 (0)6 12 65 25 25</phone>
      <email>gpagenstert@uhbs.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Geert Pagenstert, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jochen Paul, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Royal Orthopaedic Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <zip>B31 2AP</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dr. Kirti Moholkar, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0)121 685 4161</phone>
      <email>kirti.moholkar@nhs.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kirti Moholkar, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Devon and Exeter Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Exeter</city>
        <zip>EX2 5DW</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter Schranz, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0)139 240 3576</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Schranz, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vipul Mandalia, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 20, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Autologous Chondrocyte Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>NOVOCART 3D plus</keyword>
  <keyword>knee joint pain</keyword>
  <keyword>safety</keyword>
  <keyword>efficacy</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>TETEC</keyword>
  <keyword>cartilage</keyword>
  <keyword>ACT</keyword>
  <keyword>cartilage repair</keyword>
  <keyword>tissue</keyword>
  <keyword>MOCART</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
