<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="77215">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01878045</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999913151</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-DK-N151</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01878045</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mechanisms of Diabetic Kidney Disease in American Indians</brief_title>
  <official_title>Determinants of Diabetic Nephropathy in American Indians</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - An ongoing study is looking at American Indians who have kidney problems caused by type 2
      diabetes. Kidney disease due to type 2 diabetes is a major problem in American Indians.  We
      previously found that early treatment of kidney disease with losartan was probably
      beneficial for reducing progression of the disease.  Researchers now want to see if these
      benefits continue to be seen several years after the end of the treatment study.

      Objectives:

      - To study long-term benefit of losartan treatment for diabetic kidney disease in American
      Indians with type 2 diabetes.

      Eligibility:

      - Participants in the American Indian diabetic kidney disease study (OH95-DK-N037).

      Design:

        -  Participants will have a physical exam and medical history before starting the study.
           Blood and urine samples will be collected.

        -  Participants will have a set of tests as part of this study. Those who have severe
           kidney problems, such as kidney failure, will only have a basic kidney exam with scans.
           The remaining participants will have a full urine collection and analysis. They will
           also provide a kidney biopsy.

        -  Treatment will not be provided as part of this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this protocol is to examine the long-term impact of treatment with the
      angiotensin receptor blocker losartan on progression of diabetic kidney disease in American
      Indians with type 2 diabetes. All participants were enrolled previously in a 6-year
      randomized clinical trial under Protocol OH95-DK-N037.  Once randomized treatment was
      completed, the subjects continued to be followed under that protocol with annual renal
      clearance studies. Of the 170 participants originally enrolled in the trial, about 110
      remain and they are eligible to enroll in this observational study.  The present protocol
      replaces the clinical trial protocol and expands the scope of observational studies to be
      conducted in these well-characterized patients.

      Participants will continue to undergo annual renal clearance studies to measure glomerular
      filtration rate and renal plasma flow, unless they have developed kidney failure. At the
      initial visit, we will also conduct tests of the peripheral and autonomic nervous system to
      determine the frequency and severity of diabetic neuropathy in this cohort and identify
      linkages between diabetic kidney disease and diabetic neuropathy.  We will also perform a
      kidney biopsy at the initial visit to examine the extent of structural changes that have
      occurred since the last kidney biopsy done at the end of the clinical trial.  Tissue from
      this biopsy will also be used for further gene expression and epigenetic studies. Data from
      these studies will be used to guide the search for candidate biomarkers for diabetic
      end-organ damage in serum and urine and to identify mechanisms of diabetic kidney disease
      that may be amenable to new treatment strategies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>End-Stage Renal Disease</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Nervous System</condition>
  <condition>Diabetic Kidney Disease</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        To be eligible for participation in the study, subjects must meet the following criteria:

          -  Previous enrollment in protocol OH95-DK-N037.

          -  Willingness, after receiving a thorough explanation of the study, to participate.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects will be excluded for the following reasons:

          -  Clinically significant disorders of the liver [cirrhosis, portal hypertension,
             hepatitis, increased bilirubin (greater than or equal to 1.5 mg/dl), decreased serum
             albumin (&lt; 3.5 gm/l)], cardiovascular disease (angina pectoris, history of myocardial
             infarction, left ventricular ejection fraction &lt; 40%, congestive heart failure of New
             York Heart Association Class I to IV), cerebrovascular disease, peripheral vascular
             disease, pulmonary diseases (asthma and restrictive or obstructive lung disease
             requiring therapy), renal-urinary disorders (calculi, urinary tract obstruction,
             glomerulonephritis, chronic infection), gastrointestinal disorders (nausea, vomiting,
             diarrhea or anorexia sufficient to cause weight loss or wasting), or hematocrit
             levels less than or equal to 30 percent in women or less than or equal to 35 percent
             in men.

          -  Renovascular or malignant hypertension; uncontrolled hypertension (systolic blood
             pressure greater than or equal to 160 or diastolic greater than or equal to 95 mm Hg)
             despite treatment with three antihypertensive drugs; or hypertension that is being
             treated with antihypertensive medicines and the primary care physician or the patient
             refuses to adopt the blood pressure treatment regimen outlined in the study protocol.

          -  Hematuria of unknown etiology.  Prior to entry into the study, any subject with
             hematuria should be evaluated, the etiology established and documented, and treatment
             rendered as appropriate.

          -  Chronic debilitating disorders with or without treatment (e.g., systemic lupus
             erythematosus (SLE), cancer, amyloidosis, and chronic infection) that would interfere
             with the assessment of kidney function or that might reduce the chances of survival
             for a sufficient length of time to evaluate the efficacy of treatment.

          -  Currently receiving a drug regimen that includes:  steroids, immunosuppressants, or
             investigational new drugs.

          -  Pregnancy.  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test prior
             to entry and prior to each renal clearance study.

          -  Hypersensitivity to iodine.

          -  Bleeding disorders, since kidney biopsies could not be performed safely in these
             individuals.

          -  Massive obesity with body mass index greater than or equal to 45 kg/m(2).  Kidney
             biopsies are more difficult and present greater hazards to persons with massive
             obesity.

          -  Conditions likely to interfere with informed consent or compliance with the protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert G Nelson, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lois Jones, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(602) 200-5213</phone>
    <email>ljones@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Robert G Nelson, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(602) 200-5205</phone>
    <email>rnelson@phx.niddk.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NIDDK, Phoenix</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85014</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brenner BM, Cooper ME, de Zeeuw D, Keane WF, Mitch WE, Parving HH, Remuzzi G, Snapinn SM, Zhang Z, Shahinfar S; RENAAL Study Investigators. Effects of losartan on renal and cardiovascular outcomes in patients with type 2 diabetes and nephropathy. N Engl J Med. 2001 Sep 20;345(12):861-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11565518</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lewis EJ, Hunsicker LG, Clarke WR, Berl T, Pohl MA, Lewis JB, Ritz E, Atkins RC, Rohde R, Raz I; Collaborative Study Group. Renoprotective effect of the angiotensin-receptor antagonist irbesartan in patients with nephropathy due to type 2 diabetes. N Engl J Med. 2001 Sep 20;345(12):851-60.</citation>
    <PMID>11565517</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levey AS, Cattran D, Friedman A, Miller WG, Sedor J, Tuttle K, Kasiske B, Hostetter T. Proteinuria as a surrogate outcome in CKD: report of a scientific workshop sponsored by the National Kidney Foundation and the US Food and Drug Administration. Am J Kidney Dis. 2009 Aug;54(2):205-26. doi: 10.1053/j.ajkd.2009.04.029. Epub 2009 Jul 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19577347</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>American Indians</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetic Nephropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Kidney Biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>Retinopathy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Nephropathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
