<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35088">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01828320</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01 HD071065-01A1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01828320</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Triple Vulnerability? Circadian Tendency, Sleep Deprivation and Adolescence</brief_title>
  <official_title>Triple Vulnerability? Circadian Tendency, Sleep Deprivation and Adolescence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Berkeley</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Berkeley</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There is an urgent need to identify modifiable mechanisms contributing to risk and
      vulnerability among youth. The investigators test the hypothesis that eveningness, the
      tendency to go to sleep late and wake late, is an important contributor to, and even cause
      of, vicious cycles that escalate vulnerability and risk among youth. This study seeks to
      determine whether two interventions to reduce eveningness can reduce risk and confer
      resilience in critical aspects of health, development and functioning in youth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Teens who exhibit a circadian tendency toward eveningness ('night-owls') follow a delayed
      sleep schedule, increasing activity later in the day and both going to sleep and getting up
      later, compared to morning-types ('larks'). The circadian tendency toward eveningness during
      adolescence arises from a confluence of psychosocial, behavioral and biological factors and
      is an important contributor to, and maybe even cause of, vicious cycles that escalate
      vulnerability and risk for poor health and major forms of psychopathology. Indeed, an
      evening circadian tendency has been associated with a wide range of adverse effects
      including poorer health, poorer academic performance, poorer self-regulation, greater use of
      substances, greater tendency for impulsivity, more depression and anxiety, greater emotional
      instability and more aggressive and antisocial behavior. While the biological shift toward
      eveningness during puberty may be difficult to modify, the psychosocial and behavioral
      contributors are modifiable. Moreover, modifying these contributors will eliminate key
      factors that exacerbate the biological shift. The proposed research will advance current
      knowledge on the role of eveningness as a mechanism contributing to poorer outcomes during
      adolescence. The investigators aim to reduce eveningness among 10-18 year olds via an
      intervention which integrates evidence-based treatments derived from basic research on the
      circadian system (Treatment 1) compared to a psychoeducational intervention that highlights
      the interplay between sleep, diet, exercise and stress (Treatment 2). The investigators will
      randomly allocate adolescents with an evening circadian tendency, and who are 'at risk' in
      at least one of five health domains (emotional, cognitive, behavioral, social, physical), to
      either: (a) Treatment 1 (n = 86) or (b) Treatment 2 (n = 86). Measures will be taken
      pre-treatment, post-treatment, and at 6 and 12 months post-treatment. This research is a
      first step within a longer term plan to accelerate knowledge on the potentially powerful
      positive effects, for the developing neural system, of simple, disseminable psychosocial
      interventions specifically designed to target modifiable risk factors across adolescence.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep: Total sleep time</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to post treatment, which is an average of 9 weeks after the beginning of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Emotional Health: Positivity ratio via Ecological Momentary Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to post treatment, which is an average of 9 weeks after the beginning of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive Health: Prior semester GPA</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 and 12 month followup</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">172</enrollment>
  <condition>Eveningness/Sleep</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Integrates evidence-based treatments derived from basic research on the circadian system</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Psychoeducation on the inter-associations between sleep, diet, exercise and stress.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Behavior Therapy for Insomnia, Interpersonal and Social Rhythms Therapy, Chronotherapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychoeducation</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria.

          1. Scoring within the lowest quartile of the Children's Morningness-Eveningness
             Preferences Scale (CMEP; 27 or lower) and a 7-day sleep diary showing a sleep onset
             time of of 10:40 pm or later for 10-13 year olds, 11 pm or later for 14-16 year olds,
             and 11:20 pm or later for 17-18 year olds at least 3 nights per week. Must have had
             the current pattern of late bedtimes for the last 3 months.

          2. 'At risk' in one of the five health domains where 'risk' is defined as at or above
             one standard deviation over the normative average 1-5 on the screening instrument for
             each domain (see Table 6 for derivation of cutoffs);

          3. Age between 10 and 18 and living with a parent or guardian;

          4. English language fluency;

          5. Able and willing to give informed assent.

        Exclusion criteria.

          1. An active, progressive physical illness (e.g., cancer, respiratory disorder) or
             neurological degenerative disease directly related to the onset and course of the
             sleep disturbance;

          2. Evidence from clinical diagnosis or report by youth or parent of sleep apnea,
             restless legs or periodic limb movements during sleep (254). Youth presenting with
             provisional diagnoses of any of these disorders (e.g., sleep apnea) will be referred
             for a non-study polysomnography (PSG) evaluation at the parent's discretion and will
             be enrolled only if the diagnosis is disconfirmed;

          3. Mental retardation, autism spectrum disorder, or other significantly impairing
             pervasive developmental disorder. Based on previous recruitment experiences in our
             youth depression study, we expect this exclusion to be invoked very infrequently
             (once every few years);

          4. Bipolar disorder or schizophrenia or another current Axis I disorder if there is a
             significant risk of harm and/or decompensation if treatment of that comorbid
             condition is delayed as a function of participating in any stage of this study.
             Otherwise, we will allow all other comorbid psychiatric conditions to (i) to maximize
             representativeness and (ii) because a byproduct may be that BRIGHT constitutes a
             helpful 'transdiagnostic' treatment for youth across psychiatric disorders.

          5. A medication-free group may be difficult to recruit and would likely be
             unrepresentative. Hence, participants will not be excluded on the basis of stable use
             of medications (&gt; 4 weeks). Nonetheless, we have a careful 'other treatment' tracking
             system in place so we can enter 'other treatments' as an initial factor in all
             analyses.

          6. History of substance dependence in the past six months;

          7. Current suicide risk sufficient to preclude treatment on an outpatient basis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Allison G Harvey, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Berkeley</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Allison G Harvey, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>510 642 7138</phone>
    <email>aharvey@berkeley.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kerrie Hein, MA</last_name>
    <phone>510 643 3797</phone>
    <email>kerriehein@berkeley.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Berkeley</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berkeley</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94720</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 6, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 2, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Berkeley</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Allison Harvey</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Clinical Psychology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Risk: Emotional, Cognitive, Behavioral, Social, Physical</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sleep Deprivation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
