<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8134">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01778504</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130028</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-M-0028</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01778504</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Studying Childhood-onset Behavioral, Psychiatric, and Developmental Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Diagnosis and Treatment of Childhood-onset Behavioral Disorders, Neuropsychiatric Disorders and Neurodevelopmental Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Many psychiatric, behavioral, and developmental disorders are genetic. This means that
      they tend to run in families. Some begin in childhood, while others do not appear until
      adulthood. Researchers want to look at people of all ages who have these disorders that
      started in childhood. They will also look at relatives of people with these disorders. This
      information will allow doctors to learn more about childhood behavioral problems and how
      they are inherited. It may also help doctors treat those disorders.

      Objectives:

      - To study the onset and treatment of childhood behavioral, psychiatric, and developmental
      disorders.

      Eligibility:

        -  Individuals of any age who have a psychiatric, autism spectrum, or developmental
           disorder, or other behavioral problems.

        -  Family members of individuals with the above disorders. This group may include parents,
           grandparents, siblings, aunts/uncles, cousins, and children.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a medical history and physical exam. They will have
           a psychiatric history with tests of thinking, judgment, and behavior. Blood and urine
           samples will be collected. Brain imaging scans will be performed to look at brain
           function. They may have a spinal tap to collect cerebrospinal fluid.

        -  Relatives will have a medical history and physical exam. They will also have a
           psychiatric history with tests of thinking, judgment, and behavior. Blood and urine
           samples will be collected. Brain imaging scans will be performed to look at brain
           function.

        -  A relative   s exams may reveal a behavioral or other disorder. If so, he or she may
           re-enroll on the study as a person with the disorder.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a diagnostic and treatment protocol designed to provide opportunities for
      identifying new clinical syndromes, providing cases for instruction and training, and
      permitting longitudinal assessments of a variety of childhood behavioral, psychiatric and
      developmental disorders.  Disorders of particular interest are:  autism, disorders of social
      cognition and other neurodevelopmental disorders; childhood psychiatric disorders and
      particularly those with acute symptom onset; and unique clinical presentations of pediatric
      behavioral syndromes, such as those associated with genetic disorders or those with a unique
      family history.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gain knowledge about the course of specific neurodevelopmental and neuropsychiatric disorders in order to better characterize the natural history of such diseases, which can be used to generate hypotheses for future protocols</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3500</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Obsessive Compulsive Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Pediatric Autoimmune Neuropsychiatric Disorders Associated With Streptococcal In</condition>
  <condition>Pediatric Acute-Onset Neuropsychiatric Syndrome (PANS)</condition>
  <condition>Global Developmental Delay</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Participants will be eligible if they:

          -  Are aged birth to 99 years

          -  Have a diagnosed or undiagnosed neuropsychiatric disorder, neurodevelopmental
             disability or abnormal behaviors; OR are a relative of a participant with one of the
             disorders of interest.

          -  Have the ability to understand and sign an informed consent on behalf of themselves
             or their minor children, or have a legal guardian (or designated DPA),Children older
             than age 7 years with the capacity to provide assent will be asked to provide
             written, informed assent for study participation.

          -  Are under the care of a primary physician.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Participants will not be eligible if they:

          -  Are unwilling or unable to be evaluated, treated and followed as clinically
             indicated. Examples might include children with severe behavioral problems who refuse
             physical examination or individuals with phlebotomy phobias that prohibit blood
             collection.

          -  The participant does not have a primary healthcare provider.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan E Swedo, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Susan E Swedo, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-5323</phone>
    <email>swedos@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-M-0028.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beneke M, Rasmus W. &quot;Clinical Global Impressions&quot; (ECDEU): some critical comments. Pharmacopsychiatry. 1992 Jul;25(4):171-6.</citation>
    <PMID>1528956</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bodfish JW, Symons FJ, Parker DE, Lewis MH. Varieties of repetitive behavior in autism: comparisons to mental retardation. J Autism Dev Disord. 2000 Jun;30(3):237-43.</citation>
    <PMID>11055459</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Constantino JN, Davis SA, Todd RD, Schindler MK, Gross MM, Brophy SL, Metzger LM, Shoushtari CS, Splinter R, Reich W. Validation of a brief quantitative measure of autistic traits: comparison of the social responsiveness scale with the autism diagnostic interview-revised. J Autism Dev Disord. 2003 Aug;33(4):427-33.</citation>
    <PMID>12959421</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Children and Adolescents</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History Study</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurodevelopmental Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Autism</keyword>
  <keyword>Obsessive  Compulsive Disorder</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Developmental Disabilities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Child Development Disorders, Pervasive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Compulsive Personality Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
