<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="58707">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01907334</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>38-2013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01907334</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose-Response of Salmeterol in Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dose-response of Salmeterol Delivered by Advair Diskus in Children: Bioassay by Methacholine Challenge Using Oscillometry as the Endpoint</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Teva Branded Pharmaceutical Products, R&amp;D Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To examine whether a breathing test (methacholine challenge using impulse oscillometry) can
      be used to tell the difference between two different doses of an inhaled drug, salmeterol,
      delivered by Advair in children with asthma
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      During the study the subject will have to attend 4 study visits: 2 screening visits and 2
      treatment visits.

      Before each study visit, the subject has to stop using certain asthma medications.

      At Screening Visit 1a, the parent/guardian will read and sign the informed consent form to
      allow the subject to take part in this study.  The subject, if appropriate, will be asked to
      sign the last page to indicate his/her assent to be in the study.

      The study coordinator will conduct an interview to find out about the subject's medical
      history, diseases other than asthma, previous medication and any medication that the subject
      will take during his/her participation in this study.  Vital signs, i.e. blood pressure,
      heart rate, and respiration, and height and weight will be measured, and an
      electrocardiogram (ECG) which is a test to measure the electrical activity of the subject's
      heart, will be performed.  The subject will be examined by a Pediatric Pulmonary physician
      and  will be taught the proper way to use a Diskus® inhaler.  The subject has to be able to
      show that he/she can do this correctly.

      At Screening Visit 1b, if all of the tests are in the appropriate range the subject will
      take 2 puffs of Flovent from a Diskus®. One hour later, the subject will perform a breathing
      test called impulse oscillometry.  Essentially, a sound is sent down into the lungs and a
      computer converts the return sound into a number.  Then the subject will begin a breathing
      test with methacholine, a drug that makes the airways smaller.  He/she will begin by
      inhaling a low dose in a nebulizer and then performing oscillometry.  After a 5 minute
      interval he/she will breathe in increasing doses, up to 6 times or until his/her breathing
      test increases by 40%.  Albuterol will be administered immediately after the end of the
      challenge and the subject will be monitored until his/her breathing returns to within 20% of
      where it was before the challenge.

      If the methacholine test results are within the appropriate range the subject will be
      eligible for the treatment phase and will be scheduled for Visit No. 2.

      At each treatment visit, the subject will take 2 puffs of study drug from two Diskus®
      inhalers, either 1 puff of Flovent and 1 puff of Advair, or 1 puff of Advair from two
      different inhalers.  This is done in a blinded manner so the study coordinator does not know
      which treatment is used each time.  There will be a 1 hour wait time after the medication is
      administered before the methacholine challenge is started. Albuterol will be administered
      immediately after the end of the challenge and the subject will be monitored until his/her
      breathing returns to within 20% of where it was before the challenge.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacodynamics Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>response to methacholine after administration of salmeterol</measure>
    <time_frame>1 to 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A measure of the airway responsiveness to methacholine at both visits 2 and 3 post administration of salmeterol using oscillometry as the endpoint.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>total resistance (R5)</measure>
    <time_frame>an estimated one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>large airway resistance (R20)</measure>
    <time_frame>an estimated one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>small airway resistance (R5-R20)</measure>
    <time_frame>an estimated one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>area of reactance plot (AX area)</measure>
    <time_frame>an estimated one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Advair Diskus100/50 µg and Advair Diskus 100/50 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Advair Diskus 100/50 µg and Advair Diskus 100/50 µg will be administered in a blinded fashion.  One hour after receiving the dose of Advair a methacholine challenge will be performed to determine the PC40R5. After the PC40R5 has been reached or a negative result after the highest methacholine concentration, 64 mg/mL, subjects will inhale albuterol through a valved holding chamber to reverse bronchoconstriction and their lung function will be monitored until it has returned to within 20% of that day's baseline R5.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Advair Diskus 100/50 µg and Flovent Diskus 100 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Advair Diskus 100/50 µg and Flovent Diskus 100 µg will be administered in a blinded fashion.  One hour after receiving the dose of Advair and Flovent a methacholine challenge will be performed to determine the PC40R5. After the PC40R5 has been reached or a negative result after the highest methacholine concentration, 64 mg/mL, subjects will inhale albuterol through a valved holding chamber to reverse bronchoconstriction and their lung function will be monitored until it has returned to within 20% of that day's baseline R5.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Advair Diskus100/50 µg</intervention_name>
    <description>Advair Diskus 100/50 µg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Advair Diskus100/50 µg and Advair Diskus 100/50 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Advair Diskus 100/50 µg and Flovent Diskus 100 µg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>fluticasone</other_name>
    <other_name>salmeterol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Flovent Diskus 100 µg</intervention_name>
    <description>Flovent Diskus 100 µg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Advair Diskus 100/50 µg and Flovent Diskus 100 µg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>fluticasone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methacholine Chloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Methacholine Chloride in quadrupling concentrations from 0.25 to 64 mg/mL will be given based upon subject's baseline response.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Advair Diskus100/50 µg and Advair Diskus 100/50 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Advair Diskus 100/50 µg and Flovent Diskus 100 µg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Albuterol</intervention_name>
    <description>Albuterol will be administered at the end of each methacholine challenge.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Advair Diskus100/50 µg and Advair Diskus 100/50 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Advair Diskus 100/50 µg and Flovent Diskus 100 µg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  parent/legal guardian and subject must be able to speak and understand   English and
             patient must be willing and able to give assent to take part in the study

          -  diagnosed with asthma for at least 6 months

          -  able to demonstrate inhalation technique with study device

          -  if taking inhaled corticosteroids, dose must be stable for 2 weeks

          -  no significant concomitant medical conditions or abnormal physical findings on
             screening except for those consistent with asthma and allergic rhinitis

          -  airway responsiveness to methacholine with a baseline provocational dose causing an
             increase of at least 40% in R5 (PC40R5) at no more than 8 mg/mL

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  female who has started menstruating

          -  past or present history of any allergic reaction to any of the medications or
             formulations administered in this study

          -  prior treatment with systemic corticosteroids in last 30 days or more than 4 courses
             in previous 12 months

          -  use of short-acting beta-agonist more than two times per week in the previous month

          -  use of long-acting beta-agonist in the 3 weeks before the first methacholine
             challenge or during the study

          -  change in dosage of inhaled corticosteroids in previous 30 days, nasal steroids in
             previous 15 days and montelukast in last 7 days

          -  history of life-threatening asthma, including loss of consciousness, intubation
             and/or admission to ICU

          -  hospitalization for acute asthma within past year

          -  inability to withhold the following medications before methacholine
             challenges:

          -  short-acting beta-agonists at least 6 hours

          -  regular long-acting beta-agonists at least 3 weeks

          -  inhaled corticosteroid at least 2 hours

          -  montelukast at least 24 hours

          -  aspirin and non-steroid anti-inflammatory drugs at least 48 hours

          -  caffeine at least 4 hours
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leslie Hendeles, PharmD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sandra Baumstein, PharmD</last_name>
    <phone>352-273-6183</phone>
    <email>sbaumstein@cop.ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida Asthma Research Lab</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32610-0486</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Leslie Hendeles, PharmD</last_name>
      <phone>352-273-6027</phone>
      <email>hendeles@cop.ufl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sandra Baumstein, PharmD</last_name>
      <phone>352-273-6183</phone>
      <email>sbaumstein@cop.ufl.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leslie Hendeles, PharmD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>oscillometry</keyword>
  <keyword>asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>methacholine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Albuterol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Salmeterol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluticasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methacholine Chloride</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluticasone, salmeterol drug combination</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
