<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="164697">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01757197</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1202012180</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ML28046</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01757197</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Study of Tocilizumab for Patients With Glucocorticoid-refractory Acute GVHD After Allogeneic Hematopoetic Stem Cell Transplant (HSCT)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Tocilizumab (an Anti-human IL-6 Receptor Monoclonal Antibody) as a First Line Therapy for Patients With Glucocorticoid-refractory Acute Graft vs. Host Disease (aGVHD) After Allogeneic Hematopoetic Stem Cell Transplant (HSCT), a Phase II Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if Tocilizumab is a safe and effective treatment
      for steroid-refractory acute graft versus host disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This clinical trial is testing a drug called Tocilizumab (a monoclonal antibody) as a first
      line therapy for subjects with steroid-refractory acute graft versus host disease (acute
      GVHD) after undergoing a bone marrow transplant. The purpose of the study is to test the
      safety and efficacy of Tocilizumab at differing dose schedules.  There are 2 phases to this
      study. Both phases include subjects with acute GVHD have not responded to steroid treatment.
      Subjects enrolled in Phase IIp will receive Tocilizumab 8 mg/kg every week or every 2 weeks.
      Subjects enrolled in Phase II will receive one of two dose schedules determined by the
      results of Phase IIp. Depending on the dose they are assigned to, subjects will receive
      Tocilizumab every week or every 2 weeks for a total of 8 doses. The study medication may be
      interrupted, withheld or stopped for different reasons. However, subjects will be asked to
      follow up periodically for one year after starting Tocilizumab treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response and safety of toclizumab at differing doses for treatment of subjects with glucocorticoid-refractory acute graft versus host disease</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free overall survival at 100 days, 6 months and one year from the time of the first tocilizumab infusion.</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toclizumab response in each organ</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of toclizumab on Karnofsky Performance Status</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Glucocorticosteroid Refractory Acute GVHD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Toclizumab will be administered on Day 0. The administration of tocilizumab will be every 2 weeks for a total of 8 doses.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Toclizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>8 mg/kg IV, once every 1-2 weeks. The maximum dose per infusion should not exceed 800 mg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>All Patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ACTEMRA®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men or women ≥ 18 and ≤ 80 years of age

          -  Karnofsky Performance Status Scale ≥ 50%

          -  Glucocorticosteroid refractory acute GVHD Grade 2-4 by the Glucksberg functional
             classification.

          -  Patients who had experienced aGVHD grade 2-4 and responded to glucocorticosteroids in
             the past then had a flare of aGVHD requiring increasing immune suppression to 1 mg/kg
             of prednisone or equivalent are eligible for this study if they are refractory to
             steroids and provided that they did not receive a second line therapy for aGVHD in
             the past.

          -  Glucocorticosteroid refractory GVHD is defined as the following:

               -  No response to corticosteroid therapy at ≥ 1.0 mg/kg methylprednisolone or
                  equivalent after the onset of acute GVHD for a minimum of 3 and a maximum of 7
                  days OR

               -  Progression of at least 1 overall grade within 3 days of glucocorticosteroid use
                  OR

               -  Incomplete response by 14 days of glucocorticosteroid use

          -  Ability to comply with planned procedures

          -  Ability to understand the information provided and to provide written evidence of
             informed consent

          -  Willingness of females of childbearing potential to use adequate contraception.

          -  Post-menopausal for at least 1 year or surgical sterilization or hysterectomy at
             least 3 months prior to screening

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with only grade 1 acute GVHD

          -  Concurrent medical condition or disease that may interfere with clinical trial
             participation

          -  Relapsed or persistent malignancy.

          -  Receiving other drugs for the treatment of glucocorticosteroid refractory GVHD.

          -  Severe hepatic veno-occlusive disease or sinusoidal obstruction syndrome.

          -  History of hypersensitivity or severe allergic reactions to humanized or murine
             monoclonal antibodies

          -  Receipt of any experimental, unregistered therapy within or outside a clinical trial
             within 30 days or 5 plasma half-lives (whichever is shorter) before dosing

          -  Planned or current participation in any other clinical trial for treatment of GVHD
             during this clinical trial. Subjects are permitted on this trial if 30 days (or 5
             half-lives) have passed since enrollment on other investigational drugs. If a subject
             develops another condition, he/she is permitted on other clinical trials to treat
             that condition. Subjects are not permitted to go on other clinical trials for steroid
             refractory acute GVHD. Subjects are permitted to participate in trials for chronic
             GVHD.

          -  Pregnancy (a negative serum or urine pregnancy test should be performed for all women
             of childbearing potential within 7 days of treatment) or lactation.

          -  Pre-existing or recent onset of demyelinating disorders

          -  Pre-existing or recent onset of gastrointestinal perforation

          -  Treatment with any investigational agent within 4 weeks of screening or 5 half-lives
             of the investigational drug (whichever is longer)

          -  Receipt of a live vaccine within 4 weeks prior to first infusion

          -  Previous treatment with Natalizumab (Tysabri®)

          -  History of severe allergic or anaphylactic reactions to humanized or murine
             monoclonal antibodies

          -  Known active UNCONTROLLED bacterial, viral, fungal, mycobacterial, or other infection
             (including tuberculosis or atypical mycobacterial disease, but excluding fungal
             infections of nail beds).

          -  Concomitant malignancies.

          -  History of psychiatric disorder that would interfere with normal participation in
             this protocol

          -  Significant cardiac or pulmonary disease (including obstructive pulmonary disease)

          -  ANC &lt; 0.5 x 103

          -  History of drug, alcohol, or chemical abuse within 6 months prior to screening

          -  Serum creatinine  &gt; 1.9 mg/dL (168 µmol/L). Patients with serum creatinine values
             exceeding limits may be eligible for the study if their estimated glomerular
             filtration rates (GFR) are &gt;30

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt; 3 times upper
             limit of normal (ULN) unless liver GVHD is suspected

          -  Any other disease, metabolic dysfunction, physical examination finding, or clinical
             laboratory finding giving reasonable suspicion of a disease or condition that
             contraindicates the use of an investigational drug or that may affect the
             interpretation of the results or render the patient at high risk from treatment
             complications
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Usama Gergis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>June Greenberg, RN</last_name>
    <phone>212-746-2651</phone>
    <email>jdg2002@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Cornell Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>June Greenberg, RN</last_name>
      <phone>212-746-2651</phone>
      <email>jdg2002@med.cornell.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 1, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 13, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glucocorticoids</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
