<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="148119">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02039687</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>APCP-112</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02039687</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Efficacy of ARA 290 on Corneal Nerve Fiber Density and Neuropathic Symptoms of Subjects With Sarcoidosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double Blind, Placebo Controlled Phase 2 Dose Ranging Study of the Effects of ARA 290 on Corneal Nerve Fiber Density and Neuropathic Symptoms of Subjects With Sarcoidosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Araim Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Araim Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether ARA 290, a new class of compound, is
      effective in the treatment of the neuropathic symptoms of sarcoidosis.  Brief interaction of
      ARA 290 with the innate repair receptor results in anti-apoptotic and anti-inflammatory
      activities in myriad of cells, tissues and organs throughout the body to activate repair
      mechanisms and accelerate healing, including the nerve damage that can be associated with
      sarcoidosis.  In this study, subjects with sarcoidosis and symptoms of small fiber
      neuropathy will administered ARA 290 or placebo by subcutaneous injection daily for 28 days.
      In addition to monitoring the safety of the treatment, the symptoms of the subjects will be
      assessed with several questionnaires, function tests, and measurement of nerve fibers in
      their cornea and skin (via a non-invasive test and a biopsy, respectively).  The total
      participation time for each patient will be 16 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in corneal nerve fiber density</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurement of corneal nerve fiber density is a non-invasive procedure performed at baseline and at the end of dosing and at 12 weeks follow-up.  The nerve fiber density in sarcoidosis patients is reduced compared to normal humans, a measurement of small fiber loss.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the 6 minute walk test</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurement of the distance a patient can walk in 6 minutes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>• Frequency of adverse events, serious adverse events, and laboratory parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>• Change in the scores of the Small Fiber Neuropathy Screening List, BPI, NPSI, RAND-36, and FAS questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient reported pain level, function, and quality of life questionnaires</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-epidermal nerve fiber density</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurement of small fiber density in skin biopsies.  Density is reduced in sarcoidosis patients, an indication of neuropathy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuropathy of Sarcoidosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1 mg per day ARA 290</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 mg ARA 290 administered subcutaneously for 28 consecutive days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4 mg per day ARA 290</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>4 mg ARA 290 administered subcutaneously for 28 consecutive days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>8 mg per day ARA 290</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>8 mg ARA 290 administered subcutaneously for 28 consecutive days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 mL placebo administered subcutaneously for 28 consecutive days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ARA 290</intervention_name>
    <description>A small peptide that activates the innate repair receptor to induce anti-inflammatory and tissue repair mechanisms.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1 mg per day ARA 290</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4 mg per day ARA 290</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>8 mg per day ARA 290</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        •  Established diagnosis of sarcoidosis with both of the following two criteria:

          1. Score of 4 or greater on Brief Pain Inventory  &quot;pain now&quot; or &quot;average pain&quot; questions
             (BPI; 0 (least discomfort)-10 (worst discomfort))

          2. Discomfort defined as distal pain/discomfort plus one of the following: 1)
             dysesthesia, 2) burning/painful feet worsening at night, or 3) intolerance of sheets
             or clothes touching the legs or feet

        AND either of the following two criteria

          1. Corneal nerve fiber density reduced compared to normal (i.e., greater than 1 standard
             deviation less than the mean of a normative population)

          2. A previous skin biopsy (obtained within the prior 2 years) showing a reduced
             intraepidermal nerve fiber density ((i.e., greater than 1 standard deviation less
             than the mean of a normal age and gender relevant population)

        In addition, subjects must:

          -  Be able to read and understand the written consent form, complete study-related
             procedures, and communicate with the study staff

          -  Be willing to comply with study restrictions

          -  Be willing to check in with the study center via the telephone

          -  Between 18 and 70 years of age (inclusive)

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) &lt; 40 kg/m2 (inclusive)

          -  If female of childbearing potential, a negative urine pregnancy test at screening and
             acceptable contraception will be maintained during the screening and dosing period
             and 1 month beyond. Acceptable contraception consists of hormonal methods such as
             oral, implantable, injectable, or transdermal contraceptives for a minimum of 1 full
             cycle (based on the subject's usual menstrual cycle period) before study entry,
             intrauterine device (IUD), or double barrier method (condoms, sponge, diaphragm, or
             vaginal ring with spermicidal jellies or cream).

          -  Able to complete self-administered questionnaires (RAND-36, SFNSL, BPI, FAS, NPSI)

          -  Refrigerator and freezer at home for storage of study medication.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinically relevant abnormal history of physical and mental health other than
             conditions related to sarcoidosis, as determined by medical history taking (as judged
             by the investigator)

          -  Clinically relevant abnormal laboratory results, vital signs, or physical findings
             other than conditions related to sarcoidosis or could interfere with conduct of
             6-minute walk assessment (as judged by the investigator)

          -  Other medical conditions known to be associated with small nerve fiber loss, except
             for diabetes in good control (as judged by the investigator)

          -  Known clinically relevant abnormalities in ECG (as judged by the investigator)

          -  Illicit drug abuse or excessive alcohol consumption (as judged by the investigator)

          -  History of serious malignancy within the last 5 years other than a basal cell or
             squamous cell carcinoma of the skin that has been removed

          -  History of severe allergies, or has had an anaphylactic reaction or significant
             intolerability to prescription or non-prescription drugs or food (as judged by the
             investigator)

          -  Anti-TNF therapy, other biological anti-inflammatory agents, or immunoglobulins
             administered within the 3 months prior to screening.

          -  Use of erythropoiesis stimulating agents within the two months prior to screening or
             during the trial

          -  Participation in an investigational drug trial in the 3 months prior to
             administration of the initial dose of study drug or more than 4 times in the calendar
             year preceding study enrollment

          -  Inadequate venous accessibility as judged by clinicians (physician or nurse)

          -  Inability or unwillingness to self-administer ARA 290 via subcutaneous injections (or
             not have access to home health care for assistance in administration)

          -  If female, pregnant or breast-feeding

          -  Any other condition that in the opinion of the investigator would complicate or
             compromise the study, or the well-being of the subject
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Micheal Brines, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Araim Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daniel Culver, DO FCCP</last_name>
      <phone>216-444-6508</phone>
      <email>culverd@ccf.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Tani Martin, RN BSN CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>2194449975</phone>
      <email>martint5@ccf.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniel Culver, DO FCCP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leiden University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leiden</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Monique van Velzen, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+31 071 526 2301</phone>
      <email>m.van_velzen@lumc.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leon Aarts, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 16, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>neuropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>sarcoidosis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoidosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
