<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="65415">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01864538</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TH-CR-413</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01864538</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 2 Biomarker - Enriched Study of TH-302 in Subjects With Advanced Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Biomarker - Enriched Study of TH-302 in Subjects With Advanced Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Threshold Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Threshold Pharmaceuticals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to determine the response rate, duration of
      response,progression-free survival and overall survival of subjects with advanced melanoma
      treated with TH-302.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hypoxia is an independent marker of a poor prognosis for subjects with metastatic melanoma
      (Simonetti 2012, Lartigau 1997). Hypoxic melanoma cells are more likely to exhibit a
      stem-cell like phenotype with an associated increased propensity for invasion, angiogenesis,
      and metastasis formation compared to normoxic cells. Moreover, this phenotype is also
      associated with treatment resistance. TH-302, a hypoxia activated prodrug (HAP), was
      designed to target the hypoxic nature of tumours while having a minimal effect on normoxic
      tissue. TH-302 belongs to a class of alkylating agents that have significant experimental
      and clinical activity (Brock 1989). Preclinical data support the hypothesis that TH-302
      targets hypoxic regions of tumours and is also able to kill tumour cells in normoxic regions
      as a result of cytotoxin diffusion, leading to significant effects on tumour growth (Meng
      2011). TH-302 has been investigated in over 700 subjects with solid tumours or hematologic
      malignancies, including subjects with metastatic melanoma. In this subset a disease control
      rate of 63% (3 subjects with partial responses and 9 subjects with stable disease out of a
      total of 19) was observed in an early phase clinical trial of TH-302 (Weber 2010).
      Predictive biomarkers for response and toxicity have yet to be identified for subjects with
      advanced melanoma treated with TH-302. Optimal patient selection may be critical to maximize
      the clinical benefit. A predictive biomarker approach will be investigated to try to
      identify subjects most likely to benefit from TH-302. Given the hypoxia-targeting mechanism
      of TH- 302, it is believed that hypoxia biomarkers will be the most informative for
      identifying subjects likely to benefit from TH- 302; however, additional biomarkers
      including DNA repair biomarkers will also be investigated. In addition, this approach will
      also have potential to synergise with future immunotherapeutic approaches as suppressive T
      regulatory cells are thought to reside within hypoxic niches within the tumour
      microenvironment that would be amenable to targeting by TH-302.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify potential imaging, serum, and tissue biomarker(s) that predict for response and toxicities to TH-302.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence and severity of adverse events associated with TH-302.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of efficacy endpoints including the changes in RECIST measurements with established and potential biomarkers and changes in biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The correlation of toxicity (CTCAE 4.03) with biomarkers and changes in biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of TH-302 administration with tumor immune infiltrates</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of characteristics of melanoma such as BRAF status with HIF activity or hypoxic biomarkers thereof, and activity of TH-302</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TH-302</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>480 mg/m2 by iv infusion over 30 - 60 min on Days 1, 8, and 15 of a 28-day cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TH-302</intervention_name>
    <description>480 mg/m2 by iv infusion over 30 - 60 min on Days 1, 8, and 15 of a 28-day cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TH-302</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. At least 18 years of age

          2. Ability to understand the purposes and risks of the study and has signed a written
             informed consent form approved by the investigator's Regional Ethics
             Board/Independent Ethics  Committee (REB/IEC)

          3. Histologically documented cutaneous malignant melanoma, which is recurrent or
             metastatic and is not curable by surgical or other means.

          4. Adequate tumour tissue (greater than 0.5cm3 preferred, 3 X core biopsy acceptable)
             available and agreement from subjects that this tissue from their primary and/or
             metastatic tumour be made available for assessment of potential biomarkers.

          5. Ability and availability to complete all prescribed biomarker studies (Screening and
             after Cycle 2).

          6. Recovered to Grade 1 from reversible toxicities of prior therapy

          7. Presence of clinically and/or radiologically documented disease. At least one site of
             disease (which will not be removed during the course of the study) must be
             uni-dimensionally measurable as per RECIST 1.1 or clinically quantifiable (such as in
             the case of skin disease)

          8. ECOG performance status of 0 - 1.

          9. Prior treatment with any number of immunotherapies (e.g., IL2, ipilimumab), targeted
             therapies (e.g., vemurafenib) are permitted but no more than one 1 prior chemotherapy

         10. Acceptable liver function

         11. Acceptable renal function

         12. Acceptable hematologic status (without growth factor support for neutropenia or
             transfusion dependency):

         13. Normal 12-lead ECG (clinically insignificant abnormalities permitted)

         14. Female subjects of childbearing age must have a negative urine HCG test unless prior
             hysterectomy or menopause (defined as age above 55 and twelve months without
             menstrual activity). Female subjects should not become pregnant or breast-feed while
             on this study. Sexually active male and female subjects should use effective birth
             control.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Anticancer treatment with radiation therapy, targeted therapies, chemotherapy,
             immunotherapy, hormones or other antitumour therapies within 28 days prior to first
             dose of TH-302.

          2. Subjects who have received any other investigational drug or agent within 28 days of
             first dose of TH-302

          3. Current use of drugs with known cardiotoxicity

          4. Significant cardiac dysfunction:

          5. Seizure disorders requiring anticonvulsant therapy

          6. Progressing brain metastases (unless previously treated and stable disease for a
             period of greater than or equal to 3 months on repeat MRI following definitive
             treatment).

          7. History of other malignancies, except: adequately treated non-melanoma skin cancer,
             curatively treated in-situ cancer of the cervix, or other solid tumours curatively
             treated with no evidence of disease for greater than 2 years

          8. Severe chronic obstructive or other pulmonary disease with hypoxemia (requires
             supplementary oxygen, symptoms due to hypoxemia or oxygen saturation less than 90% by
             pulse oximetry after a 2 minute walk) or in the opinion of the investigator any
             physiological state likely to cause hypoxia of normal tissue.

          9. Major surgery, other than diagnostic surgery, within 4 weeks prior to  Cycle 1 Day 1,
             without complete recovery

         10. Active, uncontrolled bacterial, viral, or fungal infections, requiring systemic
             therapy

         11. Prior therapy with an hypoxic cytotoxin

         12. Known infection with HIV or active infection with hepatitis B or hepatitis C

         13. History of allergic reaction to a structural compound or biological agent similar to
             TH-302

         14. Pregnancy or breast-feeding

         15. Concomitant disease or condition that could interfere with the conduct of the study,
             or that would, in the opinion of the investigator, pose an unacceptable risk to the
             subject in this study

         16. Unwillingness or inability to comply with the study protocol for any reason.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tillman Pearce, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Threshold Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Lawson</last_name>
    <phone>650-474-8226</phone>
    <email>elawson@thresholdpharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Clarence Eng</last_name>
    <phone>650-474-8222</phone>
    <email>ceng@thresholdpharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cross Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G1Z2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Smylie</last_name>
      <phone>780-432-8762</phone>
      <email>michael.smylie@albertahealthservices.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Smylie, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Juravinski Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8V5C2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yvonne Kindrade</last_name>
      <email>Yvonne.kindrade@jcc.hhsc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elaine McWhirter, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>London Health Sciences Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A4L6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Scott Ernst</last_name>
      <phone>519-685-8640</phone>
      <email>Scott.ernst@lhsc.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Scott Ernst, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Odette Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M4N3M5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Teresa Petrella</last_name>
      <phone>416-480-5842</phone>
      <email>teresa.petrella@sunnybrook.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Teresa Petrella, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princess Margaret Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ranuka Srinivasan</last_name>
      <email>ranuka.srinivasan@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anthony Joshua, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.thresholdpharm.com</url>
    <description>Threshold Pharmaceuticals Company Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 6, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 13, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TH-302</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced Melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic</keyword>
  <keyword>Biomarker</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
