<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="99040">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01774058</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ILOFLOW2.0</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01774058</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Intraoperative Arterial Measurement of the Blood Flow Volume After Iloprost Stimulation in Diabetics and Non-diabetics</brief_title>
  <acronym>ILOFLOW</acronym>
  <official_title>The Intraoperative Arterial Measurement of the Blood Flow Volume After Iloprost Stimulation in Diabetics and Non-diabetics: Implication for Outcome-prediction and Perioperative Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Prim PD Dr Afshin Assadian</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Wilhelminenspital Vienna</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wilhelminenspital Vienna</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Austria: Federal Office for Safety in Health Care</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Iloprost® and all those prostaglandins have very good effects in using in the peripheral
      occlusive diseases (PAOD). Iloprost®, a stable prostacyclin mimetic, is an effective
      vasodilatator, has anti-thrombotic, leukocyten and endothelium-stabilising properties,
      reduces reperfusion injury after prolonged ischaemia and improves polyneuropathy and the
      healing of ulcers which are caused of PAOD. At the current stage it is not clear, which
      mechanism is predominant for diabetics with or without neuropathy.

      This study is undertaken to investigate the increase of the blood flow volume on the common
      femoral artery after Iloprost® application and surgery reconstruction and therefore
      investigate the effect for diabetics and none diabetics in order to polyneuropathy. The
      blood flow will be measured via an ultrasound instrument.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a single center, controlled, non- randomized trial evaluating the increase of
      the blood flow volume on the common femoral artery after admission of 3000ng Ilomedin®
      intraarterial into the common femoral artery during vascular surgery because of PAOD. All
      patients provide written informed consent.

      General Practitioners and Specialists referred patients to the department. Patients were
      stratified by their clinical presentation, their walking distance, Doppler index and their
      angiografie pictures ( PAOD stage IIb-IV of Fontaine). ( PAOD phase IIb  was defined because
      of a walking distance less than 200 metres, and this was measured in this center, III
      because of pain without walking, IV because of ulcers or gangrene.)  All participants were
      older than eighteen years. Patients who gave their written informed consent underwent a
      standardized vascular screening, including a health questionnaire and laboratory assessment
      and a check of the internal specialist and the anestheasia. Before each surgery a
      measurement of the nerve conduction velocity was performed in order to determine the
      polyneuropathy. Exclusion criteria comprised immaturity, all exclusion criterias of
      ilomedin®, pregnancy and spinal anesthesia.

      One day before surgery the patients got ilomedin® infusion (2A a 10mg into 250ml saline over
      4 hours) intravenous at the department. Surgery was standardized by performing
      Thrombendarterectomy in the common femoral artery, profunda and the superficial artery or by
      performing bypass reconstruction from the common femoral artery after thrombendarterectomy,
      to the femoropopliteal artery above the knee under general anesthesia with the systemic
      administration of 5000 IU Heparin before clamping the peripheral vessels.  Before surgery
      reconstruction the first measurement with the Sono TT FlowLab (em-Tec GmbH, Munich)
      ultrasound instrument was done and then after surgery reconstruction. Therefore there were
      different measuring heads exactly fitting around the vessels. Then the administration of
      3000ng Ilomedin® in 15ml saline was injected into the common femoral artery via a a cannula
      over two minutes if the systolic blood pressure of the patient was over 100mm Hg. The blood
      flow volume was measured again after five and ten minutes on the same point. Those results
      were documented. As well on table-angiography was made. Then the skin of the patient was
      closed.

      Before discharge from the hospital every patient was controlled by ultrasound  and  doppler
      index and the walking distance and then after six weeks and six months again.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The measurement of the blood flow volume is done with the Sono TT FlowLab (em-Tec GmbH, Munich) ultrasound instrument on the common femoral artery.</measure>
    <time_frame>The measurement is done at the beginning of surgery on the common femoral artery, then after 5 and ten minutes after ilomedin administration again. the results are documented.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Before surgery reconstruction the first measurement with the Sono TT FlowLab (em-Tec GmbH, Munich) ultrasound instrument was done and then after surgery reconstruction. Therefore there were different measuring heads exactly fitting around the vessels. Then the administration of 3000ng Ilomedin® in 15ml saline was injected into the common femoral artery via a a cannula over two minutes if the systolic blood pressure of the patient was over 100mm Hg. The blood flow volume was measured again after five and ten minutes on the same point. Those results were documented.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Gangrene</condition>
  <condition>Arteriosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Peripheral Occlusive Artery Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ilomedin, bloodflow volume, measurement,</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Surgery was standardized by performing Thrombendarterectomy in the common femoral artery, profunda and the superficial artery or by performing bypass reconstruction from the common femoral artery after thrombendarterectomy, to the femoropopliteal artery above the knee under general anesthesia with the systemic administration of 5000 IU Heparin before clamping the peripheral vessels.  Before surgery reconstruction the first measurement with the Sono TT FlowLab (em-Tec GmbH, Munich) ultrasound instrument was done and then after surgery reconstruction. Therefore there were different measuring heads exactly fitting around the vessels. Then the administration of 3000ng Ilomedin® in 15ml saline was injected into the common femoral artery via a a cannula over two minutes. The blood flow volume was measured again after five and ten minutes on the same point. Those results were documented in ml/min. As well on table-angiography was made.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ilomedin</intervention_name>
    <description>3000ng ilomedin in 15ml salt water will be injected intraarterial into the common femoral artery over 2 minutes for one time,then the investigators will measure the blood flow volume after 5 and then after 10 minutes on the common femoral artery. The patients will be observed by the anaesthesiologist. The patient will get ilomedin one day before the surgery and then for 6 day after surgery into the vein. (10microgramm/o,5ml in 250ml salt water)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ilomedin, bloodflow volume, measurement,</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ilomedin</other_name>
    <other_name>Product Code 1-22460</other_name>
    <other_name>ATC Code: B01AC11</other_name>
    <other_name>concentrate and solvent for injection</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  women between 18-99 years

          -  men between 18-99 years

          -  patients with diabetes and non diabetes

          -  patients with peripheral artery occlusive diseases and who undergo surgical treatment
             in distal  vessels

          -  spinal anaesthesia

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnancy

          -  heart attack in the last 6 months

          -  stroke in the last 6 months

          -  hypotension

          -  edema of the lungs

          -  heart failure

          -  heart diseases

          -  chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)

          -  ulcus ventriculi

          -  renal diseases

          -  coronary diseases

          -  immaturity

          -  general anaesthesia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Afshin Assadian, Prim PD Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Georg Hagmüller Institute for Vascular Research Wilhelminenspital Vienna, Austria</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Afshin Assadian, Prim. PD Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>+34(0)1491504101</phone>
    <email>afshin.assadian@wienkav.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kornelia Hirsch, Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>+34(0)1491504101</phone>
    <email>kornelia.hirsch@wienkav.at</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Surgery Departement, Georg Hagmüller Institute for Vascular Research Wilhelminenhospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1160</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Afshin Assadian, Prim  PD Dr</last_name>
      <phone>+34(0)1491504101</phone>
      <email>afshin.assadian@wienkav.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kornelia Hirsch, Dr</last_name>
      <phone>+34(0)1491504101</phone>
      <email>kornelia.hirsch@wienkav.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Afshin Assadian, Prim. PD.Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Wilhelminenspital Vienna</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prim PD Dr Afshin Assadian</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prim PD Dr</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>bloodflow volume</keyword>
  <keyword>ilomedin</keyword>
  <keyword>measurement</keyword>
  <keyword>intraarterial</keyword>
  <keyword>neuropathy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arteriosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gangrene</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Iloprost</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
