<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="139586">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01955382</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999913209</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-I-N209</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01955382</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Oral Activated Charcoal on the Ability of an Antimalarial Drug to Kill Parasites in Malian Children With Mild Malaria</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Oral Activated Charcoal on Parasite Clearance Rates in Response to Intravenous Artesunate in Malian Children With Uncomplicated Plasmodium Falciparum Malaria</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Malaria is caused by small parasites carried by some mosquitoes. People can get malaria if
      an infected mosquito bites them. Malaria destroys red blood cells. Most malaria is mild, but
      some children develop severe malaria, which kills about 660,000 people annually. About 9 in
      10 who die of malaria are Sub-Saharan African children, most under 5 years old. Scientists
      can save many lives if they find out how to prevent or relieve severe malaria.

      Objective:

      - To know if a common medicine called activated charcoal can reduce severe malaria symptoms.

      Eligibility:

      - Children 2 to 11 years old with mild malaria who live in Kenieroba, Mali.

      Design:

        -  For the first 2 days and nights, participants will stay in the hospital.

        -  They will have their medical history taken, and a physical exam.

        -  Blood will be drawn from a thin tube inserted in their hand or forearm. This will be
           done 3 times overall. A drop of blood will be taken from a finger prick 12 times
           overall.

        -  An antimalarial drug will be injected into the tube in the arm 4 times. Each time the
           drug is given, participants will drink a small cup of either water or activated
           charcoal.

        -  For the following 3 days, participants will take an antimalarial pill.

        -  On day 7, participants will visit the hospital. A drop of blood from a finger prick
           will be tested for malaria parasites.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      While the incidence of Plasmodium falciparum malaria declines (1) the proportion of cases
      with severe malaria (SM) may increase (2). The mortality associated with SM in endemic
      countries remains high despite the use of artesunate (AS) (3). Safe, cheap, and effective
      adjunct therapies preventing the development of, or reducing the mortality from, SM could
      have considerable and rapid public health impact. We discovered that oral administration of
      activated charcoal (oAC), a safe treatment for acute poisoning (4), protects mice from
      experimental cerebral malaria and demonstrated in a randomized controlled trial (RCT) in
      African adults that oAC is safe and does not interfere with the pharmacokinetics of AS (5).
      Here, we propose the next step to evaluate the efficacy of adjunct treatment with oAC in
      Malian children and to explore its mode of action. Before testing adjunct treatment with oAC
      in children with SM, we will perform an open-label RCT in children with uncomplicated
      malaria (UM) to demonstrate non-inferiority of intravenous (IV) AS plus adjunct oAC vs. IV
      AS alone with regards to parasite clearance rate. This study will be conducted in African
      children, because they are the primary target population for such an intervention. Although
      the adequate standard-of-care treatment for UM is oral (PO) administration of an
      artemisinin-based combination therapy (ACT), we will treat participants with IV AS. Like ACT
      treatment of UM, AS is the WHO-recommended first-line treatment for SM (1). In order for the
      data obtained from UM cases to be meaningful for our future studies in children with SM, we
      will administer AS to the UM cases in this trial via the same IV route that is used to
      administer AS to SM cases. Exploratory objectives include: (i) to compare the kinetics of
      plasma cytokines in both groups, and (ii) to preserve RNA for gene transcription analysis
      for future studies into the mode of action of oAC. The study will be nested within an
      NIAID-funded study (Principal Investigators Drs. Fairhurst, Diakite) that assesses parasite
      clearance rates in response to AS treatment in Kenieroba (6). Children aged 2-10 years with
      UM and initial parasite densities 10,000   70,000 parasites per micro L will be enrolled.
      Parasite clearance rates will be expressed as the parasite half-life (Ph), estimated from
      parasite clearance curves using a formula that has been validated in this cohort (7).
      Children will be randomized 1:1 to receive IV AS+oAC or IV AS only, respectively, until
      complete specimen and data sets for 35 children per group are obtained. oAC will be
      administered as Actidose Aqua[registered] at 0, 6, 12, and 18 hours. AS will be administered
      IV following WHO recommendations for use of AS in SM (8), followed by 3 daily doses of
      amodiaquine (AQ). Subsequently and in a separate study, we plan a proof-of-concept RCT to
      determine whether adjunct oAC reduces disease severity and morbidity (assessed by scoring
      systems (9)) in hospitalized children with SM and to define the mode of action of oAC. Since
      oAC is a licensed, inexpensive drug without sophisticated storage requirements, which has an
      extremely long shelf life at room temperature and can be given orally or via nasogastric
      tube at high doses without major side effects (4, 10), this drug has an ideal profile for
      use at the primary health-care level to reduce mortality from SM, or even prevent the
      development of SM.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare parasite clearance half- life in patients treated with oAC + IV AS or IV AS</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum cytokine levels 2, 24, and 48 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Whole- blood transcriptional profiles at 0, 24 ans 48 h</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the safety of adjunct treatment with oAC</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral Activated Charcoal</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA

               1. Age 2 to 10 years, inclusive

               2. Resident of Kenieroba

               3. Uncomplicated malaria*

               4. P. falciparum density 10,000   70,000/micro L, inclusive

               5. Willingness to participate in the study as evidenced by informed consent of the
                  child   s parent or guardian

               6. Ability to swallow oral medication

        Uncomplicated malaria: axillary temperature &gt; 37.5oC or history of fever in the past few
        days and no criteria of SM (see next paragraph) and no other etiologies of febrile illness
        (e.g., respiratory tract infection) on clinical examination.

        Severe P. falciparum malaria: parasitemia of any density and any one of the following:
        coma (Blantyre coma score less than or equal to 2), convulsions (witnessed by
        investigator), severe prostration, severe anemia (hemoglobin less than or equal to 6
        g/dl), respiratory distress, hypoglycemia (serum glucose less than or equal to 40 mg/dl),
        jaundice/icterus, shock (systolic blood pressure less than or equal to 70 mmHg, rapid
        pulse, cool extremities), cessation of eating and drinking, repetitive vomiting.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

          1. Severe malaria

          2. Any medical condition or history, including allergy to AS, AQ, artemether or
             lumefantrine, that poses a risk to the prospective participant

          3. Any condition that in the opinion of the investigator would render the participant
             unable to comply with the protocol (e.g., psychiatric disease)

          4. Any health condition that in the opinion of the investigator would confound data
             analysis or pose unnecessary risks to study participants (e.g., severe malnutrition,
             acquired or inherited immunodeficiency)

          5. Requirement for any medication for any concurrent illness or condition

          6. Participation on cohort study #13-I-N107

          7. Repetitive vomiting
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rick M Fairhurst, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mahamadou Diakite, Pharm.D.</last_name>
    <phone>Not Listed</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rick M Fairhurst, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-7393</phone>
    <email>rfairhurst@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universite des Sciencies, Techniques et Technologies de Bamako</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bamako</city>
        <country>Mali</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mali</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roberts L, Enserink M. Malaria. Did they really say ... eradication? Science. 2007 Dec 7;318(5856):1544-5.</citation>
    <PMID>18063766</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ceesay SJ, Casals-Pascual C, Erskine J, Anya SE, Duah NO, Fulford AJ, Sesay SS, Abubakar I, Dunyo S, Sey O, Palmer A, Fofana M, Corrah T, Bojang KA, Whittle HC, Greenwood BM, Conway DJ. Changes in malaria indices between 1999 and 2007 in The Gambia: a retrospective analysis. Lancet. 2008 Nov 1;372(9649):1545-54. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61654-2.</citation>
    <PMID>18984187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Meara WP, Bejon P, Mwangi TW, Okiro EA, Peshu N, Snow RW, Newton CR, Marsh K. Effect of a fall in malaria transmission on morbidity and mortality in Kilifi, Kenya. Lancet. 2008 Nov 1;372(9649):1555-62. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61655-4.</citation>
    <PMID>18984188</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parasite Clearance Rate</keyword>
  <keyword>Parasite Half Life</keyword>
  <keyword>Actidose Aqua</keyword>
  <keyword>Severe Malaria</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malaria, Falciparum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Charcoal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antimalarials</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
