<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="38525">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01939522</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OVG 2013/03</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-001024-19</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01939522</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Protection Against Pneumococcal Infection in Children With T1DM</brief_title>
  <acronym>T1DM</acronym>
  <official_title>An Open Label Single-arm Trial of the Immunogenicity and Reactogenicity of a 13-valent Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine (Prevenar13速) Given to Children With Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus Who Have Not Previously Received a Primary Schedule of Immunisation With Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccines in Infancy.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Children/ young people with diabetes may be at a higher risk of acquiring certain
      infections. These infections include those caused by a bacterium called the pneumococcus
      which can cause pneumonia, meningitis and ear infections. In the UK older children with
      diabetes are given a vaccine against the pneumococcus bug called Pneumovax (or PPS23 for
      short). Although PPS23 causes a good immune response in children over 2 years of age it is
      not actually known how well PPS23 protects against infection in children of any age. In
      addition there is some data in adults and children that PPS23 may result in a reduced
      response to future doses of pneumococcal vaccines (hyporesponsiveness). Because of the lack
      of information on how well PPS23 protects and potential hyporesponsiveness the investigators
      would like to study the use of an alternative vaccine against pneumococcus called Prevenar13
      (or pCV13). This vaccine is known to be safe and to work well in babies and young children
      and there have been no concerns about hyporesponsiveness. It has been approved for use in
      children up to 17 years of age but there is little information on the size and duration of
      immune response to PCV13 in children aged 6 years and older.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pneumococcal serotype-specific (SpVS) antibody concentrations at 3 months following a single dose of 13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV13)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The geometric mean concentration (GMC), together with 95% confidence intervals, of SpVS antibody at baseline, 3 months and 12 months following a single dose of PCV13.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pneumococcal serotype-specific GMC for serotypes 4, 7F &amp; 19A at 3 months after immunisation with a single dose of PCV13 in the children who have had a prior dose of PPS23 vs those who have not.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The difference between the pneumococcal serotype-specific geometric mean antibody concentrations (GMC) for serotypes 4, 7F and 19A at three months after immunisation with a single dose of 13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV13) in the children who have had a prior dose of 23-valent pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine (PPS23) versus those who have not.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pneumococcal serotype-specific (SpVS) antibody concentrations at baseline and 12 months following a single dose of 13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV13).</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of children with vaccine pneumococcal serotype-specific (SpVS) antibody concentrations &gt;0.35mcg/ml at baseline and 12 months following a single dose of 13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV13).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GMC of SpVS antibody at baseline, 3mnth and 12mnth following 1 dose of PCV13</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the GMC, together with 95% confidence intervals, of SpVS antibody at baseline, 3mnth and 12mnth following 1 dose of PCV13</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pneumococcal serotype-specific GMC for all vaccine-specific serotypes (VS)  at baseline, 3 months and 12 months following immunisation with a single dose of PCV13 in children who have had a prior dose of PPS23 and those who have not.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The difference between the pneumococcal serotype-specific GMC for all vaccine-specific serotypes (VS) at baseline, 3 months and 12 months following immunisation with a single dose of PCV13 in children who have had a prior dose of 23-valent pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine (PPS23) versus those who have not.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pneumococcal serotype-specific antibody concentrations for all VS in children who have had a prior dose of 23-valent pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine (PPS23) and those who have not.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The difference between the proportion of children with pneumococcal serotype-specific antibody concentrations &gt;0.35mcg/ml for all VS in children who have had a prior dose of 23-valent pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine (PPS23) versus those who have not.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vaccine-specific serotype antibody concentration between baseline and 3 months with HbA1C.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The correlation coefficient for the increase in VS antibody concentration between baseline and 3 months and HbA1C at baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood glucose control in the week preceding and the week following immunisation with PCV13</measure>
    <time_frame>One week after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A descriptive analysis of blood glucose control in the week preceding and the week following immunisation with PCV13</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prevenar13速 (13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Prevenar13 administered as a single dose, 0.5ml Intramuscular liquid form intervention at baseline.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV13)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Prevenar13速 (13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Prevenar13速</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of T1DM and being followed in the Oxfordshire Children's Diabetes Service.

          -  Aged between 6 years and 17 years.

          -  Parent/legal guardian willing and able to give informed consent.

          -  No previous immunisation with a pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV).

          -  Willing to allow the General Practitioner to be notified of participation in the
             study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known allergic reaction to the vaccine antigen or any of the excipients.

          -  Bleeding diathesis or condition associated with prolonged bleeding time that would
             contraindicate intramuscular injection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dominic F Kelly, MB BChir, MRCPCH, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>01865231693</phone>
    <email>dominic.kelly@ouh.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Julie Edge</last_name>
    <phone>01865231673</phone>
    <email>julie.edge@ouh.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oxford University Hospitals NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <state>Oxfordshire</state>
        <zip>OX3 9DU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dominic F Kelly</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 6, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 4, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>pneumococcal</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumococcal Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
