<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="11760">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02123706</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STEM-104-M-CHF</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02123706</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase IIa, Single-blind, Placebo-controlled, Crossover, Multi-center, Randomized Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability, and Preliminary Efficacy of a Single Intravenous Dose of Ischemia-tolerant Allogeneic Mesenchymal Bone Marrow Cells to Subjects With Heart Failure of Non-ischemic Etiology</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase IIa, Single-blind, Placebo-controlled, Crossover, Multi-center, Randomized Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability, and Preliminary Efficacy of a Single Intravenous Dose of Ischemia-tolerant Allogeneic Mesenchymal Bone Marrow Cells to Subjects With Heart Failure of Non-ischemic Etiology</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stemedica Cell Technologies, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CardioCell, LLC; A Stemedica Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stemedica Cell Technologies, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      TITLE:	A phase IIa, single-blind, placebo-controlled, crossover, multi-center, randomized
      study to assess the safety, tolerability, and preliminary efficacy of a single intravenous
      dose of ischemia-tolerant allogeneic mesenchymal bone marrow cells to subjects with heart
      failure of non-ischemic etiology PROTOCOL NUMBER:	STEM-104-M-CHF INVESTIGATIONAL PRODUCTS:
      Ischemia-Tolerant Allogeneic Mesenchymal Bone Marrow Cells (aMBMC), (adult human) PHASE:	IIa
      INDICATION:	Heart failure of non-ischemic etiology
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will enroll 20 subjects and will consist of 2 cohorts.  Enrolled subjects will be
      randomized at 1:1 into an experimental group (n=10) or a placebo group (n=10), respectively.
      Subjects in the experimental group will receive 1.5 million cells per kg and subjects in the
      placebo group will receive 1 mL/kg Lactated Ringer's Solution. At 90 days the two groups
      will change arms and the placebo group will receive 1.5 million cells per kg and the
      initially treated group will receive a Lactated Ringer's Solution (LRS) at a volume of 1
      mL/kg.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the safety of human ischemia-tolerant allogeneic mesenchymal bone marrow cells (aMBMC) administered intravenously to subjects with heart failure (HF) of non-ischemic etiology (N-IHF).</measure>
    <time_frame>up to  450 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Left Ventricle Ejection Fraction (LVEF) from baseline to day 90 post infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to day 90 post initial infusion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline and days 90 post-initial infusion and after the crossover to day 90 post new infusion.  MRI, echocardiogram and exercise capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, day 30, 60 &amp; 90 days post infusion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-ischemic Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Human Allogeneic Mesenchymal Stem Cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One time infusion of 1.5 million cells per kg administered at a constant rate of 2 mL/min.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lactated Ringer's Solution</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One time intravenous infusion of receive 1 mL/kg LRS administered at a constant rate of approximately 2 mL/min</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Human Allogeneic Mesenchymal Stem Cells</intervention_name>
    <description>Self-renewing, multipotent progenitor cells with the capacity to differentiate into several distinct mesenchymal lineages including osteoblasts, chondrocytes, adipocytes, endothelial cells, vascular smooth muscle cells, and cardiomyocytes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Human Allogeneic Mesenchymal Stem Cells</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mesenchymal Stem Cells</other_name>
    <other_name>Marrow Stromal Cells</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Lactated Ringer's Solution</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lactated Ringer's Solution</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males and females ≥18 years of age

          2. LVEF ≤35% on echocardiogram within 6 months of randomization to undergo MRI

          3. Screening cardiac MRI at baseline with

               1. Ejection fraction ≤40%

               2. No evidence of hyper-enhancement

          4. Patients with non-ischemic heart failure etiology, as documented by absent or
             non-obstructive coronary artery disease on x-ray angiography or coronary computed
             tomography within the past 3 years

          5. On  stable maximally tolerated medical therapy (at the discretion of the
             investigator) including ACE-inhibitors, angiotensin receptor blockers, beta-blockers,
             and mineralocorticoid receptor antagonists, as tolerated, for at least 6 months

          6. NYHA class II-III symptoms

          7. Ability to understand and provide signed informed consent

          8. Reasonable expectation that patient will receive standard post-treatment care and
             attend all scheduled safety follow-up visits

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Pregnant or nursing women or those of childbearing age and not using an effective
             method of contraception.

             2. Acute myocardial infarction, acute coronary syndrome, or stroke within 3 months 3.
             Cardiac surgery within 3 months prior to randomization or the likelihood of a
             requirement for such procedures during the study period 4. Current ICD or CRT or
             implantation planned with 6 months of infusion 5. Presence of clinically significant,
             uncorrected valvular heart disease, hypertrophic or restrictive cardiomyopathy,
             active myocarditis, or uncontrolled hypertension 6. History of cardiac arrest or
             life-threatening arrhythmias within 3 months 7. Treatment with parenteral inotropic
             agents within 1 month of randomization 8. Anticipated cardiac transplantation within
             1 year 9. Illness other than heart failure with life expectancy less than 1 year 10.
             Received an experimental drug or device within 30 days of randomization 11. Left
             ventricular assist device or implantation planned in the next 6 months 12. Patients
             with complex congenital heart disease 13. Uncontrolled seizure disorder. 14. Presence
             of immune deficiency. 15. Clinically significant hematologic, hepatic, or renal
             impairment as determined by screening clinical laboratory tests.

             16. Presence of any other clinically-significant medical condition, psychiatric
             condition, or laboratory abnormality, that in the judgment of the investigator or
             sponsor for which participation in the study would pose a safety risk to the subject
             17. Inability to comply with the conditions of the protocol. 18. Malignancy within
             the previous five years, except adequately treated basal cell carcinoma, provided
             that it is neither infiltrating nor sclerosing, and carcinoma in situ of the cervix.

             19. Active myocarditis or early postpartum cardiomyopathy (within six months). 20.
             Systemic corticosteroids, cytostatics, immunosuppressive drug therapy
             (cyclophosphamide, methotrexate, cyclosporine, azathioprine, etc.), and DNA depleting
             or cytotoxic drugs taken within four weeks prior to study treatment.

             21. Porphyria. 22. Allergy to sodium citrate or any &quot;caine&quot; type of local anesthetic.
             23. Any contraindication for gadolinium use for MRI 24. Patient scheduled for hospice
             care. 25. Clinically relevant abnormal findings in the clinical history, physical
             examination, ECG, or laboratory tests at the screening assessment that would
             interfere with the objectives of the study or would preclude safe completion of the
             study. Abnormal findings could include: known HIV infection or other immunodeficiency
             state, chronic active viral infection (such as hepatitis B or C), acute systemic
             infections (defined as patients undergoing treatment with antibiotics),
             gastrointestinal tract bleeding, or any severe or acute concomitant illness or
             injury.

             26. Any other medical, social, or geographical factor that would make it unlikely
             that the patient could comply with study procedures (e.g., alcohol abuse, lack of
             permanent residence, severe depression, disorientation, distant location, or
             noncompliance)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Javed Butler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University Centers for Heart Failure Therapy &amp; Transplantation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gail Snell, RN, CCRC</last_name>
      <phone>404-712-0531</phone>
      <email>gsnell@emory.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Javed Butler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University Bluhm Cardiovascular Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anna Huskin, RN, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>312-695-4067</phone>
      <email>ahuskin@nmh.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Allen S Anderson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania Heart Failure and Transplant Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Scott Ritter</last_name>
      <phone>215-573-2999</phone>
      <email>sritter@mail.med.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kenneth B Margulies, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 9, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Heart failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-ischemic heart failure</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
