<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35288">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02085720</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Elderly OSA/Ng/2011</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02085720</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevalence of OSAS in Chinese Elderly and Its CPAP Compliance</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prevalence of Obstructive Sleep Apnea Syndrome and CPAP Adherence in the Elderly Chinese Population</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Hong Kong: Joint CUHK-NTEC Clinical Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective: Obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome (OSAS) is a common form of sleep-disordered
      breathing (SDB) causing sleep fragmentation, daytime sleepiness, cognitive function
      impairment, and poor health status in addition to increased risk of cardiovascular
      complications. OSAS is equally common among the middle-aged male Caucasian and Hong Kong
      (HK) Chinese populations with a prevalence of at least 4%. However, the prevalence of OSAS
      in the elderly population in Asia including HK is unknown.

      Study Design: A sleep questionnaire will be conducted for 1000 subjects aged at least 60 yrs
      in the elderly community centers focusing on symptoms of OSAS, subjective sleepiness,
      restless leg syndrome, and sleep-related habits and routines, in addition to past medical
      history and medications. Home sleep study with the EMBLETTA device capable of recording
      sleep (a single EEG channel), respiratory events, snoring, respiratory efforts and oximetry
      will be performed on 300 subjects randomly. Those who have negative or technical inadequate
      EMBLETTA study with a high pre-test probability of moderate to severe OSA will be invited to
      undergo hospital-based polysomnography for confirmation of their sleep apnoea status.
      Subjects with AHI&gt;15/hr regardless of symptoms or those with AHI 5-15/hr plus comorbid
      conditions or excessive daytime sleepiness will be offered continuous positive airway
      pressure (CPAP) titration followed by CPAP treatment, with serial assessment of subjective
      sleepiness, quality of life, and cognitive function.

      Outcome measures: the prevalence rates of SDB (AHI&gt;10, &gt;15 and &gt;30/hr), OSAS, and other
      sleep disturbances, such as restless leg syndrome (RLS). In addition, we will examine the
      factors which are predictive of the presence of SDB in this population, and assess the CPAP
      acceptance, compliance, and treatment outcome of those with OSAS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS) is a common form of sleep-disordered breathing (SDB)
      characterized by repetitive episodes of cessation of breathing during sleep due to upper
      airway collapse. It causes sleep fragmentation, disabling daytime sleepiness, impaired
      cognitive function and poor quality of life. In addition, OSAS is associated with non-fatal
      and fatal cardiovascular consequences including sudden death, in addition to an increased
      risk of road traffic accidents. OSAS is equally common among the middle-aged male Caucasian
      and Hong Kong (HK) Chinese populations with a prevalence of at least 4%. However, the
      prevalence of OSAS in the elderly in Southeast Asia is unknown. Sleep disturbances, such as
      daytime sleepiness, SDB and non-respiratory causes including insomnia, restless leg syndrome
      are common in the elderly. There are also more frequent and sometimes prolonged nocturnal
      awakenings, leading to a decline in sleep efficiency (total time asleep as percentage of
      time in bed). However, the disruption of sleep architecture can be exaggerated by the
      presence of OSAS. The associated hypersomnolence can exacerbate the normal tendency in older
      people to sleep during the day, affecting their functional independence.

      While OSAS produces large negative impacts on health and quality of life, the recognition is
      not always straightforward because of the presence of co-morbidities and normal age-related
      changes in sleep quality and behavior. Once OSAS is suspected, it is not only relatively
      easy to diagnose, but usually responds well to treatment with CPAP.

      Method A sleep questionnaire will be conducted for 1000 subjects aged at least 60 yrs in the
      elderly community centers focusing on symptoms of OSAS, subjective sleepiness, restless leg
      syndrome, and sleep-related habits and routines, in addition to past medical history and
      medications. Home sleep study with the EMBLETTA device capable of recording sleep (a single
      EEG channel), respiratory events, snoring, respiratory efforts and oximetry will be
      performed on 300 subjects randomly.  Descriptions of the device and the validity of the
      methods used to collect and display data have been published previously among both local
      Chinese and other populations. It is a multi-channel screening tool that measures airflow
      through a nasal cannula connected to a pressure transducer, providing an AHI based on
      recording time. It also detects both respiratory and abdominal efforts through the effort
      sensor and can differentiate between obstructive and central events. The body position is
      detected by the built-in sensors. Respiratory events are scored when desaturations of at
      least 4% occurred in the absence of moving artifacts and irrespective of co-existing changes
      in snoring or heart rate. A hypopnea is defined as a decrease in airflow by 50% of baseline
      for at least 10 seconds. Data are included in the analysis if the total recorded evaluation
      time of 4 hrs or longer is obtained during the EMBLETTA study.

      Those who have negative or technical inadequate EMBLETTA study with a high pre-test
      probability of moderate to severe OSA will be invited to undergo hospital-based
      polysomnography for confirmation of their sleep apnoea status.

      As OSA may increase the risk of cardiovascular mortality, all elderly subjects with AHI ≥ 15
      or those with AHI ≥ 5 plus either cardiovascular risk factors or Epworth Sleepiness Score
      (ESS) score ≥ 10 received patient education program. Subjects who agreed for CPAP therapy
      were offered basic CPAP education package consisting of a 10-min CPAP education programme by
      a respiratory nurse explaining the basic operation and care of the CPAP device and the mask,
      educational brochure on OSA and CPAP treatment in Chinese, and careful mask fitting, and a
      short trial of CPAP therapy with the AUTOSet CPAP device (RESMED, Sydney, Australia) for
      approximately 30 minutes for acclimatization in the afternoon. Attended CPAP titration will
      be performed with the AUTOSET auto-titrating device in our hospital. Throughout the night
      and the next morning the nurses on duty would deal with any discomfort related to the CPAP
      treatment. The CPAP pressure for each patient will be set at the minimal pressure needed to
      abolish snoring, obstructive respiratory events and airflow limitation for 95% of the night
      as determined by the overnight AutoSet CPAP titration study. The patients subsequently will
      be followed up by physicians and nurses at the CPAP clinic in 1 month and 3 months later to
      deal with any problem with the CPAP device or mask fit. Subjects who agreed for home CPAP
      treatment will be prescribed nasal CPAP units with time clocks to assess objective
      compliance (run time). ESS, sleep apnea-specific quality of life index (SAQLI), and
      cognitive function tests will be performed at baseline and at 3 months after CPAP treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of OSAS in Chinese elderly</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects who have completed the questionnaires and consented for sleep study  are invited to undergo a portable at-home sleep study (Embletta). It is a multi-channel screening tool that measures airflow through a nasal cannula connected to a pressure transducer, providing an AHI based on recording time. It also detects both respiratory and abdominal efforts through the effort sensor and can differentiate between obstructive and central events. The body position is detected by the built-in sensors. Respiratory events are scored when desaturations of at least 4% occurred in the absence of moving artifacts and irrespective of co-existing changes in snoring or heart rate. A hypopnea is defined as a decrease in airflow by 50% of baseline for at least 10 seconds. Data are included in the analysis if the total recorded evaluation time of 4 hrs or longer is obtained during the Embletta PDS study. Significant OSAS is defined as AHI ≥ 15 or AHI ≥5 plus ESS ≥ 10.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of restless leg syndrome (RLS)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>RLS is a disorder characterized by disagreeable leg sensations that usually occur before sleep onset, causing an almost irresistible urge to move the legs. As minimal criteria for diagnosis, the following four features were required: (1) desire to move the extremities, often associated with paresthesias and/or dysesthesias; (2) motor restlessness; (3) worsening of symptoms at rest, with at least temporary relief by activity; and (4) worsening of symptoms in the evening or at night.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CPAP compliance among Chinese Elderly</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Elderly subjects who agree for home CPAP treatment are prescribed nasal CPAP units with time clocks to assess objective compliance (run time).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">819</enrollment>
  <condition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Restless Leg Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Chinese elderly OSAS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be recruited in the community elderly center with home sleep study done. Those with significant OSAS will be prescribed with CPAP therapy and subsequent compliance is monitored.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CPAP therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>As OSA may increase the risk of cardiovascular mortality, all elderly subjects with AHI ≥ 15 or those with AHI ≥ 5 plus either cardiovascular risk factors or ESS score ≥ 10 received patient education program. Elderly subjects who agree for home CPAP treatment were prescribed nasal CPAP units with time clocks to assess objective compliance (run time). ESS, sleep apnea specific quality of life index (SAQLI), and cognitive function tests were performed at baseline, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months after CPAP treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chinese elderly OSAS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  aged ≥ 60 years

          -  able to give consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  none
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susanna SS Ng, MBChB</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Community centers for elderly</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <state>Hong Kong SAR</state>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Engleman HM, Douglas NJ. Sleep. 4: Sleepiness, cognitive function, and quality of life in obstructive sleep apnoea/hypopnoea syndrome. Thorax. 2004 Jul;59(7):618-22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15223874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marin JM, Carrizo SJ, Vicente E, Agusti AG. Long-term cardiovascular outcomes in men with obstructive sleep apnoea-hypopnoea with or without treatment with continuous positive airway pressure: an observational study. Lancet. 2005 Mar 19-25;365(9464):1046-53.</citation>
    <PMID>15781100</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barceló A, Piérola J, de la Peña M, Esquinas C, Sanchez-de la Torre M, Ayllón O, Alonso A, Agusti AG, Barbè F. Day-night variations in endothelial dysfunction markers and haemostatic factors in sleep apnoea. Eur Respir J. 2012 Apr;39(4):913-8. doi: 10.1183/09031936.00039911. Epub 2011 Aug 18.</citation>
    <PMID>21852330</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Masa JF, Rubio M, Findley LJ. Habitually sleepy drivers have a high frequency of automobile crashes associated with respiratory disorders during sleep. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2000 Oct;162(4 Pt 1):1407-12.</citation>
    <PMID>11029353</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young T, Palta M, Dempsey J, Skatrud J, Weber S, Badr S. The occurrence of sleep-disordered breathing among middle-aged adults. N Engl J Med. 1993 Apr 29;328(17):1230-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8464434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bearpark H, Elliott L, Grunstein R, Cullen S, Schneider H, Althaus W, Sullivan C. Snoring and sleep apnea. A population study in Australian men. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 1995 May;151(5):1459-65.</citation>
    <PMID>7735600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ip MS, Lam B, Lauder IJ, Tsang KW, Chung KF, Mok YW, Lam WK. A community study of sleep-disordered breathing in middle-aged Chinese men in Hong Kong. Chest. 2001 Jan;119(1):62-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11157585</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feinsilver SH, Hertz G. Sleep in the elderly patient. Clin Chest Med. 1993 Sep;14(3):405-11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8222559</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hume KI, Van F, Watson A. A field study of age and gender differences in habitual adult sleep. J Sleep Res. 1998 Jun;7(2):85-94.</citation>
    <PMID>9682179</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ng SS, Chan TO, To KW, Ngai J, Tung A, Ko FW, Hui DS. Validation of Embletta portable diagnostic system for identifying patients with suspected obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome (OSAS). Respirology. 2010 Feb;15(2):336-42. doi: 10.1111/j.1440-1843.2009.01697.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20199644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dingli K, Coleman EL, Vennelle M, Finch SP, Wraith PK, Mackay TW, Douglas NJ. Evaluation of a portable device for diagnosing the sleep apnoea/hypopnoea syndrome. Eur Respir J. 2003 Feb;21(2):253-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12608438</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hui DS, Chan JK, Choy DK, Ko FW, Li TS, Leung RC, Lai CK. Effects of augmented continuous positive airway pressure education and support on compliance and outcome in a Chinese population. Chest. 2000 May;117(5):1410-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10807830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flemons WW, Reimer MA. Development of a disease-specific health-related quality of life questionnaire for sleep apnea. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 1998 Aug;158(2):494-503.</citation>
    <PMID>9700127</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 7, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Susanna SS Ng</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Specialist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Restless Legs Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
