<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="161324">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01749995</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AZGS2012061</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01749995</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Validation of the Use of the Freund Clock Drawing Test to Screen for Cognitive Dysfunction in Cancer Patients Undergoing Comprehensive Geriatric Assessment</brief_title>
  <acronym>PROACTIVE</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Validation of the Use of the Freund Clock Drawing Test (CDT) to Screen for Cognitive Dysfunction in Cancer Patients Undergoing Comprehensive Geriatric Assessment (CGA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>General Hospital Groeninge</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>General Hospital Groeninge</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Belgium: Ethics Committee</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A Comprehensive Geriatric Assessment (CGA) has become a fundamental aid in the evaluation
      and treatment planning of older cancer patients. Systematic reviews of trials of geriatric
      assessments have shown effectiveness when interventions are implemented. Although CGA is a
      fundamental tool in the care of the geriatric patient, the integration and application of
      this tool in oncologic practice are still in evolution. Cognition is one of the domains
      examined within a CGA. Studies have noted that up to 25% to 50% of older patients had
      cognitive abnormalities that warranted further evaluation. Cognitive dysfunctions can
      influence the ability to weigh the risks and benefits of cancer therapy, to comply with the
      suggested treatment plan, and to recognize the symptoms of toxicity that need medical
      attention. Recently, the Freund Clock Drawing Test (CDT) has been proposed as a quick and
      simple screening tool to assess cognitive dysfunction. A retrospective analysis on 105
      cancer patients at the General Hospital Groeninge showed that a cut-off score of ≤ 4 for the
      CDT has a good AUC, sensitivity and specificity.

      Aims

        1. To validate the Clock Drawing Test as a screening tool to identify elderly cancer
           patients in need of a more in-depth cognitive evaluation within a comprehensive
           geriatric assessment (CGA)

        2. Further registration of data in a database coupled to the Cancer Registry in the
           General Hospital Groeninge as set up by the PROGERCAN study
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design: A prospective, observational, cohort study. All geriatric patients who are diagnosed
      with cancer will be screened by an oncology clinical nurse specialist or study collaborator
      with the G8 questionnaire. Patients who screen positive, will be refered to the
      multi-disciplinary onco-geriatric program where a member of the geriatric oncology team will
      implement a comprehensive geriatric evaluation under supervision of an oncologist and/or
      geriatrician, who will then formulate recommendations and might suggest referral to other
      health care providers.

      Population: All consenting patients, aged ≥ 70, who are referred for anti-cancer treatment
      in the General Hospital Groeninge and who are in need of a CGA.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validation of the Freund Clock Drawing Test, and its predefined cut-off of ≤ 4, as a screening tool to identify elderly cancer patients in need of a more in-depth cognitive evaluation with the Folstein MMSE within comprehensive geriatric assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Validation of the Freund Clock Drawing Test by use of Receiver Operating Characteristic (ROC) analysis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Further registration of data in a database coupled to the Cancer Registry in the General Hospital Groeninge as set up by the PROGERCAN study</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>During the PROGERCAN study, a database was set up in which the results of the CGA were coupled to the data available in the Cancer Registry of the General Hospital Groeninge. In this project, we aim continue this registration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the Mini-Cog (Cognitive screening tool consisting of a clock drawing with 3-word recall test) when using the Freund CDT</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the time-saving</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determination of the time-saving when using the Freund Clock Drawing Test instead of the Folstein MMSE</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the Freund scoring system with other scoring systems (such as Watson and colleagues), when using a predrawn circle</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To develop a tumour tissue database (bio bank) of elderly cancer patients, solely for scientific purposes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Elderly Cancer Patients</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All consenting patients, aged ≥ 70, who are referred for anti-cancer treatment in the
        General Hospital Groeninge and who are in need of a CGA.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients should have reached the age of 70 or more at the moment of enrolment

          -  Patients should be eligible for standard CGA as per local practice (e.g. on the basis
             of positive screening with G8 or referred by a treating physician on the basis of
             clinical suspicion of vulnerability or frailty)

          -  Histologically confirmed diagnosis of cancer. All stages of cancer are eligible.

          -  Patients should be fluent in Dutch or French

          -  Patients must receive their primary oncology care (surgery, course of (neo)adjuvant
             or palliative chemotherapy, radiotherapy, targeted therapy, palliative care,
             experimental treatment as part of a clinical trial,...) planned in the General
             Hospital Groeninge

          -  Patients can be included before or at the start of a line of treatment but not during
             a line of treatment

          -  Patients should have signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who do not match the inclusion criteria

          -  Patients who are visiting the oncology clinic for a second opinion and do not wish to
             be treated in the General Hospital Groeninge

          -  Patients who already started a respective line of treatment

          -  Patients deemed fit on the basis of negative screening (negative result on G8) unless
             the treating physician suspects vulnerability or frailty based on clinical judgement
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>70 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General Hospital Groeninge, Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kortrijk</city>
        <zip>8500</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ketelaars L., Pottel L., Lycke M., Goethals L., Ghekiere V., Santy L., Boterberg T., Van Den Noortgate N., Pottel H., Debruyne PR. Use of the Freund clock drawing test within the mini-cog as a screening tool for cognitive impairment in elderly patients with or without cancer. Journal of Geriatric Oncology. Published online on November 5 2012.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 11, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>General Hospital Groeninge</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Philip Debruyne</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Consultant Medical Oncologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Elderly cancer patients</keyword>
  <keyword>Screening tool</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>Freund Clock Drawing Test</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cognition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
