<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="116101">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02037568</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-2639</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02037568</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improved Outcome in Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant (HSCT) Patients by Reducing Caregiver Distress</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improved Behavioral Outcome in Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant Patients by Reducing Caregiver Distress: Behavioral and Physiological Evidence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Patient Centered Outcome Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      PURPOSE: As this is a randomized controlled trial, all subjects receiving stress management
      psychoeducation will be expected to obtain a new set of coping skills that will allow them
      to better deal with the stressors of caregiving for an allogeneic HSCT patient.  It is
      expected that improving caregiver status will improve patient quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific Aims

        -  Create a Community Advisory Board (CAB) consisting of allogeneic HSCT patients,
           caregivers, blood cancer oncologists, support staff and study investigators to provide
           input.

        -  Assess patient QOL following an allogeneic HSCT using the FACT-BMT as the primary
           patient outcome. Patients whose caregivers receive fPER will have improved QOL compared
           to caregivers assigned to TAU.

        -  Test the impact of fPER on a caregiver composite distress score (encompasses
           depression, anxiety, and stress) as the primary caregiver outcome. Caregivers receiving
           fPER will have reduced distress.

        -  Assess biomarkers of allostatic load in patients prior to transplant and caregivers
           during the transplant process using novel biomarkers (hair cortisol and telomeres).
           fPER will be associated with reduced allostatic load in caregivers compared to TAU.
           Patient hair cortisol collected only before transplant will relate to QOL at intake.

      OUTLINE: Caregivers are randomized to 1 of 2 groups.

      All patients and caregivers, regardless of randomization, are informed of what to expect
      during the transplant process and how to locate available support resources within each
      program. Patients and caregivers are given information that is specific to their involvement
      in the transplantation process and recovery phase.

        -  Group I (treatment as usual [TAU]): Subjects randomized to TAU will be encouraged to
           participate in available support programs at their respective centers which are very
           similar between sites and include individual counseling as well as support groups. Due
           to the impact of our prior intervention on caregiver distress, we will provide each
           caregiver randomized to TAU a workbook prepared for someone to use without inclusion of
           one-on-one sessions with a therapist.

        -  Group II (PsychoEducation and Relaxation [fPER]): Caregivers will participate in the
           fPER intervention prior to transplant. The fPER consists of 10 sessions to include 4
           weekly 60-minute sessions followed by 4 biweekly 60-minute sessions and two additional
           sessions between day 100 and 6 months post-transplant.  Each fPER session will be
           devoted to a separate topic with the goal of assisting the caregiver in the development
           and application of stress-management coping skills including learning problem-solving
           skills, identifying cognitive distortions, application of relaxation techniques, use of
           the emWave2, coping skills training, effective use of social support, and establishing
           appropriate goals. All caregivers in fPER will be provided a Caregiver Workbook that
           includes information about the session topics and homework assignments. fPER sessions
           will be delivered either at the clinic during patient visits or via video chat. fPER
           will also include incorporation of Smartphone technology to make the interventionist
           available by video chat.

      Caregivers and patients undergo psychosocial assessments prior to randomization, and at 6
      weeks, 3 months and 6 months after transplant (anchored to the day of transplant as day 0).
      At each phase, patients and caregivers will complete the same battery of questionnaires that
      includes the Center for Epidemiological Studies-Depression scale (CES-D), the perceived
      stress scale (PSS), and the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI). Additionally the patient
      will complete the FACT-BMT each time while the caregiver completes the Caregiver Reaction
      Assessment (CRA) and Carer Support Needs Assessment Tool (CSNAT). The patient and the
      caregiver will additionally complete a demographic questionnaire that includes questions
      regard age, diagnosis, income, and other standard questions regarding nutrition, health
      behaviors, and health services utilization. At study completion, an exit questionnaire will
      address each subject's evaluation of the study and the group in which they were assigned.

      Blood and hair samples from caregivers will be collected every three months: baseline
      (patient and caregiver), 3 (caregiver) and 6 (caregiver) months post-transplant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient quality of life over time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (prior to transplant), 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The total score on the Functional Assessment of Cancer Treatment - Blood/Marrow Transplant (FACT-BMT) is a well validated measure of patient quality of life.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Caregiver Distress over time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (prior to transplant), 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A composite score is created from a principal component analysis (PCA) that incorporates caregiver PSS, CESD, and STAI similar to our prior studies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Perceived stress Over Time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (prior to transplant), 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Perceived Stress Scale (PSS) is a well validated 14 item measure of self perceived loss of control.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Depression over time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (prior to transplant), 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Center for Epidemiological Studies Depression Scale is a well validated 20 item scale measuring symptoms. Study psychologists will be notified if any subject scores 16 and over for follow up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Anxiety over time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (prior to transplant), 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The 40 item Spielberger State-Trait Anxiety Inventory will assess anxiety in subjects. It is a well validated measure of subject anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in adrenal activity over time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (prior to transplant),  3 months (caregvier only), and 6 months after transplant in caregivers.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Cortisol measured in hair will be used as a retrospective measure of activation of the hypothalamic pituitary adrenal axis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in caregiver telomere length over time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (prior to transplant), 3 months and 6 months after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Telomere length will be assessed as a measure of cellular aging.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in caregiver telomerase activity over time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (prior to transplant), 3 months and 6 months after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Telomerase activity will be assessed as a measure of the ability to reverse cellular aging processes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in caregiver burden over time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (prior to transplant), 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The 24 item caregiver reaction assessment (CRA) will assess caregiver burden.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">450</enrollment>
  <condition>Hematopoietic/Lymphoid Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Caregiver Self-Directed</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Orientation class; laboratory biomarker analysis; questionnaire administration; survey administration; treatment as usual psychosocial care; caregiver workbook.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Caregiver Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Orientation class; laboratory biomarker analysis; questionnaire administration; survey administration; Psychoeducation and Relaxation (fPER), which included one-on-one psychoeducation, and stress management intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fPER</intervention_name>
    <description>Briefly in order, the sessions will include: 1) Overview and introduction to stress management, 2) Stress and the mind-body connection, 3) How our thoughts can lead to stress, 4) Coping with stress, 5) Strategies for maintaining energy and stamina, 6) Coping with uncertainty and fear of unknown, 7) Managing changing relationships/communicating needs, and 8) Getting the support they need, modeled after a successful intervention for patient groups. Manualization is crucial for successful wider implementation. Sessions 9 and 10 will provide booster sessions in which the interventionist will assess current challenges for the caregiver, provide review, and emphasize further coping skills training that might assist the caregiver in managing current stressors such as coping with the &quot;new normal.&quot;</description>
    <arm_group_label>Caregiver Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Other Names:</other_name>
    <other_name>&quot;fone&quot; PsychoEducation and Relaxation</other_name>
    <other_name>fPER</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  - DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS (Meets all of the following criteria):

               -  Patient undergoing allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT)

               -  Primary caregiver of a BMT patient for 50% of the time

          -  PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

               -  Able to read and speak English

               -  Has telephone access

          -  CAREGIVER CHARACTERISTICS:

               -  Able to read and speak English

               -  Willingness to use a Smartphone

               -  No serious medical condition likely to influence cortisol assessment in their
                  hair

               -  Alcohol consumption limited to &lt; 2 drinks/day

               -  Least 18 years of age

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

               -  No history of a psychiatric illness unrelated to the HSCT within the past 18
                  months

               -  No steroid medications (caregiver)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark L Laudenslager, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado Denver (Anschutz Medical Campus)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark L Laudenslager, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>303-724-9276</phone>
    <email>mark.laudenslager@ucdenver.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ben W Brewer, PsyD</last_name>
      <phone>720-848-1161</phone>
      <email>benjamin.brewer@ucdenver.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ben Brewer, PsyD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Presbyterian/St. Luke's Medical Center (PSLMC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80218</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Teri Simoneau, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>720-754-4850</phone>
      <email>Teri.Simoneau@HealthONEcares.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Terese L Simoneau, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>stress</keyword>
  <keyword>caregiving</keyword>
  <keyword>anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>psychoeducation intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>psycho-oncology</keyword>
  <keyword>allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
