<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="156451">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01980992</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCO 11-0197</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>FAI001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01980992</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Oral Immunotherapy for Wheat Allergy</brief_title>
  <acronym>Wheat OIT</acronym>
  <official_title>Oral Immunotherapy for Wheat Allergy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hugh.Sampson</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being done to learn about the medical effects, the safety, and the immunologic
      effects of Wheat Oral Immunotherapy (OIT) treatment.  The goal of the study is to find out
      whether subjects can develop the ability to eat wheat (the food allergen) regularly without
      allergic symptoms after stopping the study treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Food allergy affects 6-8 percent of children in the United States. Wheat is one of the eight
      most common foods inducing allergic reactions in the US. Current treatment for food allergy
      is complete avoidance of the food and to carry antihistamines and self-injectable
      epinephrine if an accidental reaction occurs. However, accidental exposure to allergens in
      processed foods may be difficult to avoid. Currently, several therapeutic strategies are
      being investigated to prevent and treat food allergies. Since immunotherapy injections for
      food allergy are associated with a high rate of allergic reactions, alternate approaches to
      treatment are needed. Oral (by mouth) immunotherapy (OIT) is one approach that has been
      tried in some studies in the treatment of food allergies. The intent of the study is to
      examine the clinical effects and safety of wheat OIT. This study will last 2 years. All
      eligible subjects will receive a wheat oral food challenge (OFC). Those who react to 1923mg
      or less of vital wheat gluten will be randomized to Wheat OIT or a placebo. All eligible and
      enrolled subjects will have a 1-year and 2-year OFC.  Placebo subjects will crossover to
      Wheat OIT at the 1-year time point. At selected visits, blood and urine collection, physical
      examination, prick skin tests, and atopic dermatitis and asthma evaluations will occur.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of desensitized participants (while on daily wheat OIT) as measured by the ability to consume at least 5923 mg of Vital Wheat Gluten after a 9923 mg wheat Oral Food Challenge (OFC) performed 1 year after initiating treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determine in wheat allergic children, whether relative to placebo, daily oral administration of Vital Wheat Gluten escalated to a maximum of 1544 mg/day of Vital Wheat Gluten increases desensitization as measured by consuming without dose limiting symptoms 5923 mg of wheat protein on a 9923 mg wheat OFC performed 1 year after initiating treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of subjects in the initial active treatment group who achieve ad-lib consumption of wheat as demonstrated by a 9923 mg Vital Wheat Gluten OFC 8-10 weeks after therapy discontinuation at the 2 year time point.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of subjects who achieve the targeted maintenance dose of wheat OIT during the desensitization phase of the study.</measure>
    <time_frame>44 Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of subjects that achieve desensitization in the placebo cross over group after 1 year of dosing.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of all serious adverse events during the study.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Wheat Allergy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wheat OIT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active treatment participants receive Vital Wheat Gluten, and have up to four oral food challenges as directed by the protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo for Vital Wheat Gluten followed by crossover to open-label active therapy (Vital Wheat Gluten), and up to three oral food challenges as directed by the protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Wheat OIT</intervention_name>
    <description>Vital Wheat Gluten dispensed by the central manufacturer. Study product will be dispensed in vials for low doses, capsules for mid-range doses, and bulk powder with dosing scoops for the higher doses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Wheat OIT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vital Wheat Gluten</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 4-30 years either sex, any race, any ethnicity

          -  Positive Prick Skin Test to wheat greater than 3mm compared to control and/or a wheat
             specific IgE &gt;= 0.35 kUA/L

          -  Positive baseline challenge to wheat (&lt;= 1923 mg of vital wheat gluten)

          -  Written informed consent from subject and/or parent/guardian

          -  Written assent from all subjects as appropriate

          -  All females of child bearing age must be using appropriate birth control

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of anaphylaxis to wheat resulting in hypotension, neurological compromise or
             mechanical ventilation

          -  Known allergy to corn

          -  Known celiac disease

          -  Chronic disease (other than asthma, atopic dermatitis, rhinitis) requiring therapy
             (e.g., heart disease, diabetes)

          -  Active eosinophilic gastrointestinal disease in the past two years

          -  Participation in any interventional study for the treatment of food allergy in the
             past 6 months

          -  Subject is on &quot;build-up phase&quot; of immunotherapy (i.e., has not reached maintenance
             dosing).  Subjects tolerating maintenance allergen immunotherapy can be enrolled.

          -  Severe asthma, uncontrolled mild or moderate asthma. More information on this
             criterion can be found in the protocol.

          -  A burst of oral, IM or IV steroids of more than 2 days for an indication other than
             asthma in the past 1 month

          -  Inability to discontinue antihistamines for initial day escalation, skin testing or
             OFC

          -  Use of omalizumab or other non-traditional forms of allergen immunotherapy or
             immunomodulator therapy (not including corticosteroids) or biologic therapy within
             the past year

          -  Use of beta-blockers (oral), angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors,
             angiotensin-receptor blockers (ARB) or calcium channel blockers

          -  Use of investigational drug within 90 days or plan to use investigational drug during
             the study period

          -  Pregnancy or lactation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hugh A Sampson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hugh A Sampson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kyrsten Spann, MS</last_name>
      <email>safar.inquiry@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kari Nadeau, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ann &amp; Robert H. Lurie Children's Hospital of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wendy Lankenau, RN, BSN, CPN</last_name>
      <phone>312-227-6378</phone>
      <email>WLankenau@luriechildrens.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jacqueline A Pongracic, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kim Mudd, RN</last_name>
      <phone>410-502-1711</phone>
      <email>kmudd2@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert A Wood, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>100029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Beth Strong, RN, MSN</last_name>
      <phone>212-241-0957</phone>
      <email>Beth.strong@mssm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hugh A Sampson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hugh.Sampson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dean for Translational Biomedical Sciences, Director, Jaffe Food Allergy Institute</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Food Allergy</keyword>
  <keyword>Wheat Allergy</keyword>
  <keyword>Oral Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wheat Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
