<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="92449">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01952054</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-0007</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01952054</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Denosumab for Breast Cancer With Bone Mets</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Denosumab to Define the Role of Bone Related Biomarkers in Breast Cancer Bone Metastasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if denosumab in combination with a
      hormonal drug can help lower the number of circulating tumor cells (CTCs) in patients with
      breast cancer that has spread to the bone.  The safety of this combination will also be
      studied.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Drug Administration:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will receive denosumab
      through a needle under your skin on Day 1 of each 28-day study cycle.

      Starting on Day 1 of Cycle 2, you will also begin taking a hormonal drug every day. The
      study doctor will choose the hormonal drug you receive based on your previous hormonal
      therapy for breast cancer. The study doctor will give you instructions for taking your
      hormonal drug.

      Study Visits:

      On Day 1 of Cycle 2:

        -  Blood (about 3 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  Blood (about 5 teaspoons) will be drawn for CTC testing and to check your immune
           system.

        -  Urine will be collected to test for a biomarker that is used to measure the rate of
           bone breakdown.

        -  If the study doctor thinks it is needed, you will have a PET scan, a bone scan, or an
           MRI to check the status of the disease.

      On Day 1 of Cycle 3, blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn for routine tests.

      Length of Study:

      You may receive the denosumab and hormonal therapy combination for up to 13 weeks. You will
      be taken off study if the disease gets worse or intolerable side effects occur.

      End of Study Visit:

      After your last dose of the study drug, the following tests and procedures will be
      performed:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 3 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  Blood (about 5 teaspoons) will be drawn for CTC testing and to check your immune
           system.

        -  Urine will be collected to test for a biomarker that is used to measure the rate of
           bone breakdown.

        -  If the study doctor thinks it is needed, you will have a PET scan, a bone scan, or an
           MRI to check the status of the disease.

      This is an investigational study.   Denosumab is FDA approved and commercially available to
      prevent bone-related events caused by breast cancer that has spread to the bone. Using
      denosumab to lower CTCs in patients with breast cancer that has spread to the bone is
      investigational.

      Up to 35 patients will take part in this study. All will be enrolled at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction of Circulating Tumor Cells (CTCs)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint is percentage of patients that have low circulating tumor cells (CTC), defined as less than 5 CTCs and also including CTC 0 in 7.5 ml whole blood.  For the primary endpoint, McNemar's test will be applied to test the change of percentage of patients that are low CTCs over 4 weeks.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Denosumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive a single subcutaneous (SC) administration of Denosumab 120 mg every 4 weeks (+/- 5days). Starting week 5, in addition to receiving Denosumab every 4 weeks, participants receive a hormonal agent. Each physician can choose hormonal agent, but exclude the agent that the participants received at adjuvant therapy setting.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Denosumab</intervention_name>
    <description>120 mg subcutaneously on Day 1 of every 28 day cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Denosumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AMG 162</other_name>
    <other_name>Prolia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients have histological confirmation of breast carcinoma.

          2. Patients have disease free interval (DFI) for ≥ 1 year. Definition for DFI: 1) If
             patients received adjuvant chemotherapy: DFI is the time between the date of last
             dosing of adjuvant chemotherapy to the date of disease progression. 2) If patients
             received neoadjuvant chemotherapy or adjuvant hormonal therapy: DFI is the time
             between the date of the definitive surgery to the date of disease progression.

          3. Patients have metastatic disease, with predominantly bone metastasis with 2 or more
             lesions, and has not been treated. Patients can have soft tissue involvement (Lymph
             node and skin) and/or oligo-metastatic site at major organ site (i.e. lung, liver,
             etc).

          4. Patients have positive ER expression in the primary tumor site by IHC (defined as
             &gt;/=10%) (PR status is not required)

          5. Adequate hematologic function: 1)Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;/= 1.0 x 10^9/L, 2)
             Platelet count &gt;/= 50 x 10^9/L, 3) Hemoglobin &gt;/= 9.0 g/dL

          6. Adequate cardiac function (LVEF &gt;/= 45%)

          7. Adequate Renal function: Calculated creatinine clearance &gt;30 ml/min

          8. Adequate Hepatic function: 1) Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &lt;/= 2.5 x ULN; 2)
             Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &lt;/= 2.5 x ULN; 3) Alkaline phosphatase (Alp) &lt;/= 2.5 x
             ULN; 4) Total bilirubin &lt;/= 2.0 x ULN

          9. Serum calcium or albumin-adjusted serum calcium &gt;/=2.0mmol/L (8.0mg/dL) and &lt;/= 2.9
             mmol/L (11.5mg/dL)

         10. Patients have ability and willingness to sign written informed consent.

         11. Patients are 18 years of age or older.

         12. Female patients of childbearing potential (A female not free from menses &gt; 2 years or
             not surgically sterilized) must be willing to use highly effective contraception to
             prevent pregnancy or agree to abstain from heterosexual activity throughout the
             study. Highly effective contraception, defined as male condom with spermicide,
             diaphragm with spermicide, intra-uterine device. Highly effective contraception must
             be used by both sexes during the study and must be continued for 5 months after the
             last dose of denosumab.

         13. Female patients of childbearing potential must have negative serum pregnancy test &lt;/=
             21 days prior to starting study treatment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient has known sensitivity to any of the products to be administered during the
             study (e.g., mammalian derived products, calcium, or vitamin D).

          2. Patients receiving concurrent anti-cancer therapy (chemotherapy, immunotherapy,
             radiation therapy and biological therapy) while taking study medication.

          3. Patients with metastatic sites that requires chemotherapy and/or non-hormonal
             targeted therapy.

          4. Patients with active infection and requiring IV or oral antibiotics.

          5. Patients with concurrent disease or condition that would make them inappropriate for
             study participation, or any serious medical disorder that would interfere with
             patients' safety.

          6. Patients have HER2-positive breast carcinoma (IHC staining more than 3+ or HER2 gene
             amplification by FISH)

          7. Patients with initial diagnoses of stage IV disease.

          8. Patient is pregnant or breast feeding, or planning to become pregnant within 5 months
             after the end of treatment.

          9. Patient is of child bearing potential and is not willing to use, in combination with
             her partner, two highly effective methods of contraception or abstinence during
             treatment and for 5 months after the end of treatment.

         10. Male patients.

         11. Patients have prior history or current evidence of osteonecrosis/osteomyelitis of the
             jaw.

         12. Patients have active dental or jaw condition which requires oral surgery, including
             tooth extraction.

         13. Patients have non healed dental/oral surgery, including tooth extraction.

         14. Patients planned invasive dental procedures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Naoto Ueno, MD,PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Naoto Ueno, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-2817</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone metastasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer that has spread to the bone</keyword>
  <keyword>Denosumab</keyword>
  <keyword>AMG 162</keyword>
  <keyword>Prolia</keyword>
  <keyword>Hormonal agent</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
