<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="122822">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02071472</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DCIC 13 16</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02071472</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Electronic Pharmaceutical Record Used for Medication Reconciliation by a Pharmacist Associated to the Anesthesiologist Consultation</brief_title>
  <acronym>DP-CONCIL</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Impact of an Electronic Pharmaceutical Record Used for Medication Reconciliation by a Pharmacist Associated to the Anesthesiologist Consultation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Grenoble</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Grenoble</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <authority>France: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective is to evaluate the impact of an electronic pharmaceutical record used for
      medication reconciliation by a pharmacist associated to the anesthesiologist consultation

      Experimental intervention:

      medication reconciliation by a pharmacist using an electronic pharmaceutical record before
      the anesthesiologist consultation for planned surgery patients. The clinical pharmacist
      communicates the recommendations regarding the drug therapy to the anesthesiologist orally
      and using a specific formulary.

      Control intervention:

      Conventional anesthesiologist consultation for planned surgery patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Anesthesiology consultation is mandatory in France for planned surgery. It is part of the
      concept of anesthesia safety. The main goal is to assess the anesthetic and surgical risk
      including clinical and drug features likely to interfere with the anesthesia. The medication
      reconciliation is a central part of this consultation especially in order to assess the
      allergic risk and hemostasis disorders.

      However, access to comprehensive and reliable data concerning the consumption of health
      products by the patient represents a major challenge. The &quot;Dossier Pharmaceutique&quot; (DP) is
      an electronic pharmaceutical record including medications (prescribed medications, over the
      counter medications, complementary and alternative medicines) delivered by community
      pharmacists over a four month period. Hospital pharmacists have access to the DP of
      hospitalized patients in order to improve the quality of the medication reconciliation.
      These informations regarding medication of the patients will be shared with
      anesthesiologists.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with a potential or documented adverse drug event collected by using trigger tool method</measure>
    <time_frame>within the first 30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of medications reported by the anesthesiologist in the medical record</measure>
    <time_frame>winthin 2 to 4 weeks between anesthesiogist consultation and surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with a documented adverse drug event over the perioperative period</measure>
    <time_frame>within the first 30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Demographic, clinical and therapeutic characteristics of all included participants</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants having an electronic pharmaceutical record (DP) open</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1076</enrollment>
  <condition>Electronic Health Records</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DP medication reconciliation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>medication reconciliation by a pharmacist using an electronic pharmaceutical record associated to the anesthesiologist consultation for planned surgery patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>conventional anesthesiologist consultation for planned surgery patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DP medication reconciliation</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>DP medication reconciliation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patient coming for anesthetics consultation before a planned surgery

          -  age above18

          -  available electronic pharmaceutical record (DP)

          -  at least one medication prescribed before hospital admission

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Minor patients ou majors protected by law

          -  Not speaking French patient

          -  Person who are not free by law or administrative decision
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pierrick BEDOUCH, PharmD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Grenoble</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pharmacy Department - University Hospital of Grenoble</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <state>Isère</state>
        <zip>38043</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
