<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="136139">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01863680</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EMR200113_001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01863680</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 3 Trial to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of COL-1620 Vaginal Progesterone Gel</brief_title>
  <official_title>Open-label, Single-arm, Multicenter Phase III Trial to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of COL-1620 8% Vaginal Progesterone Gel for Luteal Phase Support in In-vitro Fertilization and Embryo Transfer (IVF/ET) Cycles in Japanese Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck KGaA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck KGaA</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Pharmaceuticals and Medical Devices Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this trial is to demonstrate the non-inferiority of the clinical
      pregnancy rate per embryo transfer to the historical standard value in in-vitro
      fertilization (IVF)/embryo transfer (ET) cycles in Japan (Japan Society of Obstetrics and
      Gynecology [JSOG] 2009 registry data: 24.3 percent [%]). The secondary objectives of this
      trial are to assess the biochemical pregnancy rate per ET, pharmacokinetics, and safety of
      COL-1620.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with Clinical pregnancy per Embryo Transfer</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 5 post embryo transfer</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with Biochemical pregnancy per Embryo Transfer</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 5 post embryo transfer</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum progesterone level</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) administration and Day 14+/-3 post embryo transfer</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">130</enrollment>
  <condition>Luteal Hormone Supplementation in In-vitro Fertilization</condition>
  <condition>Embryo Transfer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COL-1620</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>COL-1620</intervention_name>
    <description>COL-1620 vaginal progesterone gel (1.125 grams of progesterone gel containing 90 milligram that is 8% gel) will be administered by the vaginal route once daily, from the day of ovum pick-up (OPU) until Week 12, or until the confirmation of miscarriage or extra-uterine pregnancy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>COL-1620</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) analogue</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will undergo conventional controlled ovarian stimulation (COS) therapy for IVF/ET according to the Investigator's discretion using GnRH analogue (agonist or antagonist) preparation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>COL-1620</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH)</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will undergo conventional COS therapy for IVF/ET according to the Investigator's discretion using FSH containing preparation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>COL-1620</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Human Chorionic Gonadotropin (hCG)</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will undergo conventional COS therapy for IVF/ET according to the Investigator's discretion using hCG preparation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>COL-1620</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Japanese race

          -  Woman with a history of infertility and in whom IVF/ET is indicated

          -  The COS therapy is GnRH analogue (agonist or antagonist) in combination with a
             FSH-containing preparation

          -  Healthy premenopausal woman aged between 20 and 45 years (inclusive) and wishing to
             conceive

          -  Body mass index (BMI) of 17.0 to 25.0 kilogram per square meter (kg/m^2) (inclusive)

          -  A negative pregnancy test (urinary beta-hCG) prior to starting COS

          -  Normal cervical smear result (Papanicolaou [PAP] test: Negative for Intraepithelial
             Lesion or Malignancy [NILM] or [Atypical Squamous Cells of Undetermined Significance
             {ASC-US} and Human Papillomavirus {HPV} negative]) within 12 months prior to the date
             of informed consent. If not available, a cervical smear and HPV test will be
             performed as part of Screening

          -  No clinically significant abnormal findings in the Screening hematology, biochemistry
             and urinalysis parameters

          -  Full comprehension of the study and voluntary written informed consent obtained in
             writing prior to any trial-related activities

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of recurrent pregnancy loss (defined as 3 or more previous spontaneous
             abortions)

          -  History of 3 or more consecutive cancelled or failed (no clinical pregnancy) IVF/ET
             cycles

          -  Abnormal hemorrhage of the reproductive tract of undetermined origin

          -  Any contraindication to being pregnant and/or carrying a pregnancy to term (for
             example, malformations of sexual organs or fibroid tumors of the uterus incompatible
             with pregnancy)

          -  Uterine myoma requiring treatment

          -  Extra-uterine pregnancy within the last 3 months prior to the date of informed
             consent

          -  History or presence of intracranial tumor (for example, hypothalamic or pituitary
             tumor)

          -  Presence of or suspected gonadotropin- or estrogen-dependent malignancy (for example,
             ovarian, uterine or mammary carcinoma)

          -  Ovarian enlargement or cyst of unknown etiology

          -  Breast-feeding or lactation

          -  History of severe Ovarian Hyperstimulation Syndrome (OHSS) (Classification of OHSS
             Severity, as per Japan Reproductive/Endocrine Working Group)

          -  Known Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV)-positive status, or a history of or current
             active infection with Hepatitis B or C

          -  Known allergy or hypersensitivity to progesterone preparations or gonadotropin
             preparations and/or their excipients, or any contraindication to receive medication
             for controlled ovarian stimulation (for example, gonadotropin, GnRH analogues,
             combined oral contraceptive pill, as appropriate)

          -  History of or suspected alcohol or substance abuse within 5 years prior to the date
             of informed consent

          -  Clinically significant systemic disease (for example, insulin-dependent diabetes,
             epilepsy, severe migraine, acute porphyria, hepatic, renal or cardiovascular disease,
             severe corticosteroid-dependent asthma)

          -  Active thrombophlebitis, thromboembolic disorder or cerebral apoplexy, or a history
             of such conditions

          -  Other significant disease that in the Investigator's or Sub-Investigator's opinion
             would exclude the subject from the trial

          -  Participation in another clinical trial within 3 months prior to the date of informed
             consent or simultaneous participation in another clinical trial

          -  Legal incapacity or limited legal capacity
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Merck KGaA Communication Center</last_name>
    <phone>+49 6151 72 5200</phone>
    <email>service@merck.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Infertility</keyword>
  <keyword>COL-1620</keyword>
  <keyword>progesterone gel</keyword>
  <keyword>Fertilization in Vitro</keyword>
  <keyword>Embryo Transfer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Chorionic Gonadotropin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hormones</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Progesterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Follicle Stimulating Hormone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
