<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="72295">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02028442</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ColoAd1-1001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02028442</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase I / II Study of ColoAd1 by Sub-acute Fractionated IV Dosing in Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>EVOLVE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Clinical Study Of ColoAd1 Administered by Sub-Acute Fractionated Intravenous Injection: Dose Escalation in Metastatic Epithelial Solid Tumours and Randomised Controlled Trial in Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PsiOxus Therapeutics Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PsiOxus Therapeutics Ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Federal Agency for Medicines and Health Products, FAMHP</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Agencia Española de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicentre, open-label, Phase I/II study of ColoAd1 in patients with either solid
      tumour of epithelial origin not responding to standard therapy or for whom no standard
      treatment exists (phase I Dose Escalation) or metastatic colorectal cancer not responding to
      standard therapy (Phase I dose Expansion) or metastatic colorectal cancer in stable disease
      or partial response after 3-4 months of first line standard of care chemotherapy (phase II).

      The dose of ColoAd1 will be administered intravenously once daily as 3 consecutive
      injections separated by 48 hours (hrs.) over a period of five days unless an unacceptable
      toxicity occurs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1 - Maximum Tolerated Dose</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 22</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>- Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) / maximum feasible dose (MFD) of ColoAd1 when administered by sub-acute fractionated IV injection (phase I Dose Escalation) and recommended dose for phase II.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">133</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumours of Epithelial Origin</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ColoAd1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ColoAd1</intervention_name>
    <description>Oncolytic virus</description>
    <arm_group_label>ColoAd1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must provide written informed consent

          -  Age ≥ 18 years and the patient must be at least the legal age limit to be able to
             give consent within the jurisdiction the study is taking place.

          -  ECOG performance status 0 or 1 (See Appendix 1) * Predicted life expectancy of 3
             months or more

          -  Ability to comply with study procedures in the Investigator's opinion

          -  Recovered to Grade 1 from the effects (excluding alopecia) of any prior therapy for
             their malignancies.

          -  Adequate renal function:

               -  Creatinine ≤ 1.5 mg/dL or calculated creatinine clearance using the
                  Cockcroft-Gault formula ≥ 60 mL/min, or measured creatinine clearance ≥ 60
                  mL/min,

               -  Absence of clinically  significant haematuria or proteinuria on urinalysis
                  defined as follows:

                    -  Haematuria: dipstick &lt; 2+

                    -  Proteinuria: dipstick &lt; 2+.

          -  Adequate hepatic function:

               -  serum bilirubin &lt; 1.5 mg/dL

               -  AST and ALT ≤ 3 x ULN

          -  Adequate bone marrow function:

               -  ANC ≥  1.5 x 109/L,

               -  platelets ≥ 100 x 109/L,

               -  haemoglobin ≥ 90 g/L

          -  Adequate coagulation tests: INR ≤ 1.5 x ULN;

          -  For females of childbearing potential (defined as &lt;2 years after last menstruation or
             not surgically sterile), a negative serum pregnancy test must be documented within 14
             days prior to first administration of study treatment; -- For women who are not
             postmenopausal (24 months of amenorrhea) or surgically sterile (absence of ovaries
             and/or uterus):  agreement to use two adequate methods of contraception, during the
             treatment period and for at least 3 months after the last dose of study drug;

          -  For men: agreement to use a barrier method of contraception during the treatment
             period and for at least 6 months after the last dose of study drug;

          -  At least 3 weeks since any dose of intravenous systemic chemotherapy and at least two
             weeks since any oral dose of capecitabine at the time of first administration of
             ColoAd1.

          -  Phase I specific inclusion criteria Dose-escalation stage only (except Repeat cycle
             cohort):

               -  Solid tumour of epithelial origin not responding to standard therapy or for whom
                  no standard treatment exists  Dose Expansion Stage and Dose-escalation Stage
                  Repeat cycle cohort

               -  Metastatic colorectal carcinoma not responding to standard therapy

               -  ≤ 3 prior lines of systemic therapy for advanced disease OR ≤ 4 prior lines of
                  systemic therapy for advanced disease if one of the 4 lines was an anti-EGFR
                  therapy given as a single agent or combined to a previously administered
                  chemotherapy regimen;

          -  Phase II specific inclusion criteria:

               -  Metastatic colorectal cancer;

               -  Have received 3 - 4 months of first line chemotherapy with either FOLFOX,
                  FOLFIRI or CAPOX, with or without bevacizumab;

               -  At least one measurable lesion according to RECIST 1.1 criteria ; * Documented
                  partial response or stable disease;

               -  Eligible to receive chemotherapy with FOLFOX or CAPOX after a short chemotherapy
                  interruption (3 to 4 weeks).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding females;

          -  Known history or evidence of significant immunodeficiency due to underlying illness
             (e.g. HIV/AIDS) and/or medication (e.g. systemic corticosteroids, or other
             immunosuppressive medications including cyclosporine, azathioprine, interferons,
             within the past 4 weeks);

          -  Splenectomy;

          -  Prior allogeneic or autologous bone marrow or organ transplantation;

          -  Active infections requiring antibiotics, physician monitoring, or recurrent fevers
             &gt;38.0 degrees centigrade associated with a clinical diagnosis of active infection ;

          -  Active viral disease or known positive serology for HIV, hepatitis B or hepatitis C;

          -  Use of the following anti-viral agents: ribavirin, adefovir, lamivudine or cidofovir
             within 7 days prior to day 1; or PEG-IFN (within 14 days prior to first
             administration of ColoAd1);

          -  Administration of an investigational drug within 28 days prior to first dose of
             ColoAd1;

          -  Major surgery within 4 weeks or radiotherapy within 3 weeks prior to first dose of
             ColoAd1;

          -  Another primary malignancy within the past 3 years (except for non-melanoma skin
             cancer or cervical cancer in situ);

          -  CNS metastasis that is symptomatic and/or requires treatment;

          -  Any condition or illness that, in the opinion of the Investigator or the medical
             monitor, would compromise patient safety or interfere with the evaluation of the
             safety of the drug;

          -  Known allergy to treatment medication or its excipients;

          -  Any other medical or psychological condition that would preclude participation in the
             study or compromise ability to give informed consent. Exclusion criteria for Phase II
             patients only

          -  Progression on first line therapy;

          -  A complete response on first line therapy;

          -  Use of first line therapy for longer than 4 months;

          -  Use of any first line treatment with a chemotherapy regimen other than FOLFOX,
             FOLFIRI or CAPOX (each with or without bevacizumab).

          -  More than 6 weeks since the last administration of 5 FU, capecitabine, oxaliplatin or
             irinotecan.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christine Wilkinson-Blanc, MD</last_name>
    <email>christine.blanc@psioxus.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>John Beadle, MD</last_name>
    <email>john.beadle@psioxus.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cliniques Universitaires St Luc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bruxelles</city>
        <zip>B-1200</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jean-Pascal Machiels, MD</last_name>
      <email>jean-pascal.machiels@uclouvain.be</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean-Pascal Machiels, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ghent University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ghent</city>
        <zip>9000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sylvie Rottey, MD</last_name>
      <email>sylvie.rottey@ugent.be</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sylvie Rottey, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Catala d Oncologica</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08970</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ramon Salazar, MD</last_name>
      <email>ramonsalazar@iconcologica.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ramon Salazar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>START - Hospital Universitario Madrid Sanchinarrio</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28050</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emiliano Calvo, MD</last_name>
      <email>emiliano.calvo@start.stoh.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Emiliano Calvo, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
