<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="127688">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01817075</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACCL1034</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00595</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA095861</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>COG-ACCL1034</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01817075</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chlorhexidine Gluconate Cleansing in Preventing Central Line Associated Bloodstream Infection and Acquisition of Multi-drug Resistant Organisms in Younger Patients With Cancer or Undergoing Donor Stem Cell Transplant</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Cleansing With Chlorhexidine Gluconate (CHG) on Reducing Central Line Associated Bloodstream Infection (CLABSI) and Acquisition of Multi-Drug Resistant Organisms (MDRO) in Children With Cancer or Those Receiving Allogeneic Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation (HCT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Oncology Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Oncology Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized phase III trial studies chlorhexidine gluconate cleansing to see how well it
      works compared to control cleansing in preventing central line associated bloodstream
      infection and acquisition of multi-drug resistant organisms in younger patients with cancer
      or undergoing donor stem cell transplant. Chlorhexidine gluconate may help reduce
      bloodstream infections and bacterial infections associated with the central line
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES: I. To determine whether chlorhexidine gluconate (CHG) cleansing
      decreases central line associated bloodstream infection (CLABSI) in children with cancer or
      those receiving an allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation (HCT).  SECONDARY
      OBJECTIVES: I. To determine whether CHG cleansing decreases acquisition of multi-drug
      resistant organisms [MDRO: vancomycin resistant enterococci (VRE), methicillin resistant
      Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA), etc.] in children with cancer or those receiving allogeneic
      HCT. II. To determine whether CHG cleansing in children with cancer or those receiving
      allogeneic HCT is associated with cutaneous bacterial isolates with reduced susceptibility
      to CHG. III. To determine whether CHG cleansing decreases positive blood cultures in
      children with cancer or those receiving allogeneic HCT.  OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to
      1 of 2 arms.  ARM I: Patients receive CHG cleansing with topical skin wipes once daily (QD)
      for 90 days.  ARM II: Patients receive control cleansing with topical skin wipes QD for 90
      days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of CLABSI events during the at-risk days</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated and compared between the 2 arms by a Poisson regression model adjusting for the randomization stratification factor on treatment/diagnosis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acquisition of MDRO</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Compared between the two arms using logistic regression. Non-linear mixed effects models will also be used to examine the effect of CHG on the proportion of patients acquiring MDRO with adjustment for the treating institution as random effects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Susceptibility to CHG as measured by minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) and minimum bactericidal concentrations (MBCs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Compared between the two arms using logistic regression. Nonlinear mixed models applied to explore the association between CHG cleansing and reduced susceptibility to CHG over the longitudinal assessments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of bacteremia episodes during the at-risk days</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Poisson regression model used for detecting the reduction in the rate of bacteremia at 2-sided alpha level of 0.05.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">450</enrollment>
  <condition>Bacterial Infection</condition>
  <condition>Infection</condition>
  <condition>Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus Aureus Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (CHG cleansing wipe)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive chlorhexidine gluconate cleansing with topical skin wipes QD for 90 days.  Cloths impregnated with 2% CHG.   Once daily.  Wound care management as necessary.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (control)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive control cleansing with topical skin wipes QD for 90 days.    Cloths impregnated with mild soap and moisturizers.  Once Daily.  Wound care management as necessary.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>chlorhexidine gluconate</intervention_name>
    <description>Receive CGH cleansing with cloths impregnated with 2% CHG once daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (CHG cleansing wipe)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Chlorhexidine Gluconate cloth 2%</other_name>
    <other_name>NSC #753971</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>wound care management</intervention_name>
    <description>Receive control cleansing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (CHG cleansing wipe)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (control)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients undergoing planned allogeneic transplant (both malignant and
             non-malignant diagnoses)

          -  Patients with an oncology diagnosis that are on a chemotherapy regimen that will last
             for an additional &gt;= 3 months; patients with an oncology diagnosis that will be on a
             chemotherapy regimen for &gt;= 3 months

          -  Patients must have, or be scheduled to have, an external tunneled central venous
             catheter (CVC) (Broviacs, Hickmans, tunneled percutaneously inserted central catheter
             (PICCs), etc.) that is expected to remain in place for an additional &gt;= 3 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a previous or current line infection are ineligible until 14 days after
             the completion of antibiotics

          -  Subjects who would enroll in the Oncology Patient stratum who are planned to start
             conditioning for HCT within 3 months of enrollment are ineligible

          -  Patients with only non-tunneled CVCs (non-tunneled peripherally inserted central
             catheters [PICCs], temporary CVCs, midline catheters, etc) are ineligible

          -  Patients with only totally implanted CVCs or ports are ineligible

          -  Patients with a known allergy or hypersensitivity to CHG are ineligible

          -  Patients with chronic, severe, generalized skin breakdown (such as generalized
             blistering, burns, severe graft versus host disease [GVHD] with open sores, etc.) are
             ineligible

          -  Patients enrolled on ACCL0934 are ineligible

          -  Patients scheduled to receive broad-spectrum prophylactic antibacterial therapy are
             ineligible

          -  Patients receiving sorafenib at the time of enrollment or as part of a treatment plan
             scheduled to receive sorafenib are ineligible

          -  Patients using prophylactic antimicrobial locks in the CVC at the time of enrollment
             or as part of a treatment plan scheduled to receive prophylactic antimicrobial locks
             in the CVC are ineligible

          -  Patients previously enrolled on this trial are ineligible
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Danielle Zerr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Oncology Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Oncology Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Arcadia</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91006-3776</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Danielle M. Zerr</last_name>
      <phone>206-987-2653</phone>
      <email>danielle.zerr@seattlechildrens.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Danielle M. Zerr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 14, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bacterial Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Staphylococcal Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Chlorhexidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chlorhexidine gluconate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
