<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="107707">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02070263</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>110035</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02070263</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mixed Tree Nut Food Challenges</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mixed Tree Nut Food Challenges</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Arkansas Children's Hospital Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Arkansas Children's Hospital Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this prospective study is twofold: 1) to establish oral tolerance to selected
      tree nuts and to examine potential predictors of oral tolerance and 2) to determine the
      usefulness of mixed tree nut allergen food challenges in more efficiently defining tree nut
      allergy and oral tolerance.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the absence of tree nuts (TN) allergy, referred patients from one of the
      Arkansas Children's Hospital (ACH) Allergy Clinic physicians with current serum
      immunoglobulin E (IgE) to TNs that meet eligibility criteria will be invited to undergo a
      series of open mixed TN food challenges.

      A questionnaire pertaining to their TN allergy will be administered

      A brief physical exam will be performed.

      Skin prick tests using selected nut allergen extracts along with a positive (histamine) and
      a negative (salt-water) control will be performed at the first oral food challenge visit.

      Each food challenges will be performed to 1 to 3 TNs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Oral tolerance to selected tree nuts (TN) to determine potential predictors of oral tolerance.</measure>
    <time_frame>total -20 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This prospective, observational study uses serum IgE to specific TN, skin prick test to TN, and TN oral food challenges to establish oral tolerance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of tree nut (TN) IgE testing to assess the risk of positive food challenges based on  grouped mixed TN food challenges</measure>
    <time_frame>total - 20 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We postulate that by grouping TN that are mixed into one food challenge based on the individual's TN serum IgE will be more efficient in defining TN allergy and tolerance. One to three TNs will be in one food challenge based on TN IgE testing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Food Allergy</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients seen at Arkansas Children's Hospital between 3-21 years of age who have Tree Nut
        food allergies.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Any patient between 3-21 years of age followed by the Allergy and Immunology
             Department at Arkansas Children's Hospital on tree nut avoidance diet.

          -  Has current serum IgE test within the past 12 months to major nuts in question. All
             TN serum IgE are &lt;10

          -  Children must have a stable baseline examination prior to undergoing challenge
             without significant symptoms of atopic dermatitis, allergic rhinoconjunctivitis,
             current urticaria or other allergic symptoms deemed important by the physician.

          -  Children must have stable asthma and no wheezing or repetitive cough prior to
             challenge, nor have been treated with oral steroids for a significant asthma
             exacerbation within 1 month of challenge.  Asthmatics that undergo lung function
             testing.

          -  Children must have no current illness (e.g., fever or viral illness) at time of
             challenge.

          -  The subject will be asked to restrict the use of antihistamines (short acting, 72
             hours: long acting, 5-7 days), (B-agonists (12 hours), theophylline (12 hours), and
             cromolyn (12 hours) prior to the first mixed TN food challenge.  Other medications
             may be continued.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any TN serum IgE ≥10.

          -  Life-threatening reaction (respiratory involvement requiring medications, or shock,
             or gastrointestinal reaction requiring intravenous fluids) to any TN.

          -  History of a reaction in the past year or severe reaction in the past 2 years or a
             history of a severe reaction anytime with a TN serum IgE &gt;5

          -  Unstable asthma, gastrointestinal disease, cardiovascular disease, chronic lung
             disease, beta-blocker use.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stacie M Jones, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences / Arkansas Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arkansas Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Food allergy</keyword>
  <keyword>Tree nuts</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Food Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
