<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="23486">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02050113</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CARPE-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02050113</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Complex Aortic Aneurysm Repair Using Physician Modified Endografts</brief_title>
  <acronym>CARPE</acronym>
  <official_title>Complex Aortic Aneurysm Repair Using Physician Modified Endografts</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of physician modification
      of FDA approved off-the-shelf endovascular grafts in the treatment of patients with complex
      abdominal aortoiliac aneurysms or thoracoabdominal aneurysms who (1) have anatomy not
      suitable for endovascular repair using grafts currently marketed in the United States,(2)
      are deemed unsafe to wait the required time necessary for commercial endograft
      manufacturing, and (3) are at high risk for open surgical repair.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Endovascular repair of complex aortic aneurysms is limited by the need to maintain blood
      flow to the critical organs that receive blood from the aorta, such as the kidneys, liver
      and intestines.  While there are some commercially available devices that may treat some of
      these patients these devices may not be suitable or available for a given patient.  In this
      study we will use off-the-shelf, FDA approved devices and alter them by creating
      fenestrations (holes) in the stent graft that allow additional stents to be inserted into
      the blood vessels that supply blood to these critical organs.  These modified stent grafts
      will be created using advanced imaging techniques that allow the investigator to tailor the
      device to the patient's specific anatomy.

      The finished device is inserted into the body through two small punctures or incisions in
      the groin.  Small stents will be inserted through the stent graft fenestrations into the
      major blood vessels affected by the aneurysm so that blood flow is maintained to these
      organs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The effectiveness of physician modified endovascular grafts will be determined by evaluating the proportion of patients that achieve Treatment Success</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Treatment success is a combination of technical success, and freedom at 12 months from the following: Type 1 and 3 Endoleaks, Stent migration of more than 10 mm, aortic aneurysm enlargement sac enlargement of more than 5 mm, aneurysm rupture and conversion to open repair.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Major Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 30 days of the initial procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Major adverse events include death, myocardial infarction, stroke, respiratory failure, paralysis, bowel ischemia, and procedural blood loss of greater than 1 liter.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Complex Aortic Aneurysms</condition>
  <condition>Thoracoabdominal Aneurysms</condition>
  <condition>Pararenal Aneurysms</condition>
  <condition>Juxtarenal Aneurysms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Endovascular repair</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Endovascular repair of Complex Aortic Aneurysm using a physician modified stent graft</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physician modified stent graft</intervention_name>
    <description>The surgeon will modify commercially available stent grafts to match the anatomy of the patient being treated.  Small fenestrations (holes) will be made in the stent graft so that additional stents can be inserted through the fenestration and into the blood vessels that lead to the kidneys, intestines or liver.  These stents allow blood to flow freely to these organs.  This surgery is done through small incisions in the groin.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Endovascular repair</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A patient may be suitable for inclusion in the study if the patient has at least one
             of the following:

               1. Aortic or aortoiliac aneurysm with diameter ≥5.5 cm

               2. Aortic or aortoiliac aneurysm with a history of growth ≥1.0 cm per year, or
                  clinical indication for aneurysm repair based on symptoms

                  General Inclusion Criteria

               1. Cannot be treated with a currently available non-modified approved device

               2. Symptomatic on presentation and unsafe to wait for the time necessary to obtain
                  a currently available non-modified approved device

               3. At least 18 years of age

               4. Not pregnant or breastfeeding

               5. Willing and able to comply with five years of follow-up

               6. Willing and able to provide informed consent prior to enrollment

               7. No systemic or local infection that may increase the risk of endovascular graft
                  infection

               8. High risk for open surgical repair based on any of the factors below:

                  a. Anatomic i. Previous abdominal surgery ii. Previous left-sided thoracotomy
                  (if the proposed open repair would require dissection of the thoracic aorta)
                  iii. Previous aortic surgery b. Physiologic i. ASA Category III or higher ii.
                  Age &gt;70 years iii. Current tobacco use iv. Previous myocardial infarction,
                  coronary artery disease, or coronary artery stent v. Coronary stress test with a
                  reversible perfusion defect vi. Congestive heart failure vii. COPD

                  Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exclusion Criteria Medical Exclusion Criteria

               1. Baseline creatinine &gt;2.0 mg/dl

               2. Cultural objection to receipt of blood or blood products

               3. Allergy or sensitivity to stainless steel, polyester, polypropylene, solder
                  (tin, silver), gold, or nitinol

               4. Anaphylactic reaction to contrast that cannot be adequately pre-medicated

               5. Uncorrectable coagulopathy

               6. Unstable angina (defined as angina with a progressive increase in symptoms, new
                  onset at rest or nocturnal angina, or onset of prolonged angina)

               7. Patient has a major surgical or interventional procedure planned ≤30 days of the
                  aneurysm repair

               8. Patient has history of connective tissue disease (e.g., Marfan's or
                  Ehler's-Danlos syndrome)

               9. Patient has active malignancy

              10. Patient has life expectancy less than two years

        Anatomical Exclusion Criteria

          1. Significant occlusive disease, tortuosity, or calcification that would prevent
             endovascular access

          2. Proximal neck length ≤25 mm

          3. Proximal neck, measured outer wall to outer wall on a sectional  image (CT)

               1. For use of Zenith Flex:  diameter &gt;32 mm  or &lt;18 mm

               2. For use of Zenith TX2:  diameter &gt;38 mm or &lt;24 mm (for proximal and distal neck
                  diameter)

          4. Proximal neck angulated more than 60 degrees relative to the long axis of the
             aneurysm

          5. Proximal neck diameter change over the length of the proximal seal zone &gt;4 mm

          6. Proximal seal site with a circumferential thrombus/atheroma

          7. Iliac artery diameter, measured inner wall to inner wall on a sectional image (CT)
             &lt;7.0 mm at any point along access length (prior to deployment)

          8. Ipsilateral iliac artery fixation site diameter, measured inner wall on a sectional
             image (CT) &gt;21 mm at distal fixation site

          9. Iliac artery distal fixation site  &lt;10 mm in length

         10. Non-bifurcated segment of any artery to be stented &lt; 15 mm in length

         11. Artery to be stented with a maximum diameter &lt;3 mm or &gt;10 mm at the vessel ostium

         12. Inability to maintain at least one patent hypogastric artery

         13. Bilateral renal artery stenosis &gt;50%

         14. Superior mesenteric artery stenosis &gt;50%
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andres Schanzer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shauneen Valliere, MSN, NP</last_name>
    <phone>508-856-1767</phone>
    <email>shauneen.valliere@umassmed.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Andres Schanzer, MD</last_name>
    <phone>508-856-5599</phone>
    <email>andres.schanzer@umassmemorial.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UMass Memorial Health Care - University Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Worcester</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01655</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shauneen Valliere, MSN, NP</last_name>
      <phone>508-856-1767</phone>
      <email>shauneen.valliere@umassmed.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Andres Schanzer, MD</last_name>
      <phone>508-856-5599</phone>
      <email>andres.schanzer@umassmemorial.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andres Schanzer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 28, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andres Schanzer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Complex Aortic Aneurysms</keyword>
  <keyword>Thoracoabdominal Aneurysms</keyword>
  <keyword>Pararenal Aortic Aneurysms</keyword>
  <keyword>Juxtarenal Renal Aneurysms</keyword>
  <keyword>Endovascular Branch Graft</keyword>
  <keyword>Fenestrated Stent Graft</keyword>
  <keyword>Abdominal Aortic Aneurysm</keyword>
  <keyword>Endovascular</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Aneurysm</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aortic Aneurysm</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
