<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82493">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02141048</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1952 Lester</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02141048</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of The Parent Centre's Positive Parenting Skills Training Course</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of The Parent Centre's Positive Parenting Skills Training Course: Randomised Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Cape Town</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Parent Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Cape Town</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>South Africa: University of Cape Town Research Ethics Committee.</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether The Parent Centre's Positive Parenting
      Skills Training course is effective in improving parenting, child behaviour, a parent's
      sense of competency, the parent-child relationship and child self-esteem.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in poor and positive parenting on The Parenting Scale (PS) at post-assessment (after the parenting programme) and at a one-year follow-up.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Post-assessment (between 1 and 3 weeks after programme completion), One-year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Parenting Scale is a self report measure that can be used to assess dysfunctional discipline practices of parents of young children. It has been validated on a sample of parents who had children between the ages of 5-12 years. The scale is comprised of three factors: verbosity, overreactivity and laxness. It consists of 30 items which can be answered on a 7-point scale. Scale anchors vary per question but are essentially parenting mistakes paired with more effective parenting behaviours (e.g., &quot;I often hold a grudge&quot; vs. &quot;things get back to normal quickly&quot;).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in poor and positive parenting on The Parent Behaviour Inventory (PBI) at post-assessment (after the parenting programme) and at a one-year follow-up.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Post-Assessment (between 1 and 3 weeks after programme completion), One-year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The PBI is a self report measure that is suggested to reflect two dimensions of parenting behaviour: hostile/coercive &quot;behaviour which expresses negative affect or indifference toward the child&quot; and could include using physical punishment, threat or coercion to influence child behaviour; and supportive/engaged parenting which reflects parental acceptance of a child through signs of affection, instrumental and emotional support and shared activities. It is suitable for use with parents of children who are young school-age. The PBI consists of 20 items which can be answered on a 5-point likert-type scale. Scale anchors range from &quot;not at all true&quot; to &quot;very true&quot;.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in poor and positive parenting on The Parenting Young Children Scale (PARYC) - Setting Limits subscale at post-assessment (after the parenting programme) and at a one-year follow-up.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Post-Assessment (between 1 and 3 weeks after programme completion), One-year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The PARCY is a self report measure which assesses the frequency of engagement with particular parenting behaviours towards children on a 7-point Likert scale from &quot;not at all&quot; to &quot;most of the time&quot;. It also determines whether performing this behaviour is seen as a problem for the parent with response options including either &quot;yes&quot; or &quot;no&quot;. This evaluation will only utilise the settling limits subscale which consists of 7 items. The convergent validity of the scale is supported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in child problem behaviour on the Eyberg Child behaviour Inventory (ECBI) at post-assessment (after the parenting programme) and at a one-year follow-up.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Post-Assessment (between 1 and 3 weeks after programme completion), One-year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The ECBI can be used to assess behaviour problems in children from 2 to 16 years old. It is comprised of 36 items. Each item is assessed on two dimensions; how often it occurs (i.e. frequency) and identification of the behaviour as a problem for the parent. Frequency ratings are answered on a 7-point likert-type scale ranging from &quot;never occurs&quot; to &quot;always occurs&quot;. By summing these answers together one is provided with an overall problem behaviour Intensity Score. Parents when identifying whether a behaviour is a problem for them answers either &quot;yes&quot; or &quot;no&quot; when asked about the particular behaviour. These answers can also be summed to create a total Problem Score. 	There is ample evidence for the ECBI to be a psychometrically sound measure, demonstrating its validity and reliability in measuring child problem behaviours.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in child problem behaviour on the Child Behaviour Checklist (CBCL) - Externalising Problem subscale at post-assessment (after the parenting programme) and at a one-year follow-up.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Post-Assessment (between 1 and 3 weeks after programme completion), One-year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Only the  of the CBCL/6-18 school age version will be used in this study. This subscale is made up of35 items which assess aggressive and rule breaking behaviour. The subscale assesses such behaviours on a three-point Likert-type scale with options ranging from 0 &quot;not true&quot;, to 2 &quot;very true&quot;. There is strong support for this scale's psychometric properties.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in parent's sense of competence on the Parenting Sense of Competence Scale (PSOC) at post-assessment (after the parenting programme) and at a one-year follow-up.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Post-Assessment (between 1 and 3 weeks after programme completion), One-year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This measure is a parent self-report. The PSOC's factor structure is composed of two dimensions of parenting self-esteem namely, efficacy and satisfaction. The scale consists of 17 items which can be answered on a 6-point Likert-type scale ranging from &quot;strongly disagree&quot; to &quot;strongly agree.&quot; Some of these items are reverse scored. The scale and its respective subscales have demonstrated high levels of internal consistency. The subscale's convergent and divergent validity are also supported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in the parent-child relationship on the Child Parent Relationship Scale (CPRS) at post-assessment (after the parenting programme) and at a one-year follow-up.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Post-Assessment (between 1 and 3 weeks after programme completion), One-year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The CPRS is a self-report which assesses parent's perceptions of the relationships they have with their children (between 3-12 years). It consists of 15 items, which are answered on a 5-point Likert-type scale. The anchors for this scale range from &quot;does not apply&quot; to &quot;definitely applies&quot;. The measure has two subscales; a conflict subscale assesses the extent to which a parent feels that the relationship with their child is characterised by negativity, and a closeness subscale which measures the degree to which a parent feels that the relationship with their child is characterised by open communication, warmth and affection. The scale has adequate evidence for reliability and validity, suggesting it is psychometrically sound.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in child self-esteem on the Child Health Questionnaire - self-esteem subscale (CHQ-ES) at post-assessment (after the parenting programme) and at a one-year follow-up.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Post-Assessment (between 1 and 3 weeks after programme completion), One-year follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The CHQ-ES is a parent-report. The CHQ measures 14 psychosocial and physical concepts, and is designed and normed for use with children between the ages of 5 and 18 years. Only the self-esteem concept will be used in this evaluation. This concept is comprised of 6 items, which parents can answer on a scale 5-point Likert-type scale ranging from &quot;very satisfied&quot; to &quot;very dissatisfied&quot;. The scale determines how satisfied the parent thinks their child is with aspects of themselves and their lives. Internal consistency reliability in two samples (Australian and USA) was found to be above α= 0.8 for this subscale.This scale also shows high levels of item discriminant validity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Implementation fidelity of each programme session on session-specific check-lists during programme implementation.</measure>
    <time_frame>Programme implementation will be measured over 7 weeks (for duration of the programme)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>All facilitators will complete a self-report check-list after each session which will require them to specify the elements of the programme which they implemented. These checklists are specific to each session and include the core activities mentioned in the programme manual</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Participant exposure, adherence and engagement on attendance registers, session check-lists and in-depth interviews during and post-programme implementation</measure>
    <time_frame>Programme implementation will be measured over 7 weeks (for duration of the programme), Post-assessment (between 1 and 3 weeks after programme completion)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Facilitators will fill in attendance registers for each session - indicating participants' programme exposure and adherence. Programme engagement has been operationalised by using self-report check-lists which participants will take home with them and return to the following sessions. These check-lists will assess the degree to which participants have engaged with the homework practice activities.											Individual in-depth interviews will be utilised to determine what they think about the programme and facilitators and their engagement with the programme lessons in their home environment. The interview schedule will utilise an open-ended approach. Not all participants will be required to complete this aspect of data collection (n= 15). Those that do will be selected at random on the basis that they have completed at least 4 programme sessions. Interviews will be recorded on cellphones.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Positive and Poor Parenting Behaviours</condition>
  <condition>Child Behaviour Problems</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Positive Parenting Skills Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Positive Parenting Skills Training programme's first session provides an overview of the programme. The remaining sessions consider topics including: factors that affect child behaviour, understanding children's feelings, and building children's self-esteem, assertive parenting gaining child-co-operation, effective discipline, and problem solving. The programme is knowledge based and encourages the development of various parenting skills through the inclusion of experiential activities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wait-list control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will also be assigned to a wait-list control group. This control group will receive the Positive Parenting Skills Training programme after the one-year follow-up.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Positive Parenting Skills Training</intervention_name>
    <description>The Positive Parenting Skills Training course primarily targets caregivers of children between the ages of 6-12 years. The programme is universally implemented, i.e. anyone caregiver is able to attend. It consists of seven weekly 3-hour sessions, and is group-based.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Positive Parenting Skills Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Primary caregivers (the person most responsible for the well-being of a child)

          -  Have a child between the ages of 5-12 years

          -  Look after this child for a minimum of four nights a week.

          -  Live in Mitchells Plain in the Western Cape

          -  Never participated in the The Parent Centre's Positive Parenting Skills Training
             course nor the Parenting and Leadership Training course.

        Another adult in the household (if available)

          -  Lives with the index child (selected by the formerly mentioned caregiver) for at
             least four nights a week

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  none
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Soraya N Lester, BA(Hons)</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Cape Town</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Soraya N Lester, BA(Hons)</last_name>
    <phone>021 785 4111</phone>
    <phone_ext>+27</phone_ext>
    <email>rayalester@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Catherine L Ward, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>021 650 3422</phone>
    <phone_ext>+27</phone_ext>
    <email>cathy.ward.sa@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Cape Town</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <state>Western Cape</state>
        <zip>7701</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Soraya N Lester, MPhil</last_name>
      <phone>021 785 4111</phone>
      <phone_ext>+27</phone_ext>
      <email>rayalester@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Catherine I Ward, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>021-650-3422</phone>
      <phone_ext>+27</phone_ext>
      <email>cathy.ward.sa@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Soraya N Lester, BA (Hons)</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>South Africa</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.theparentcentre.org.za</url>
    <description>The Parent Centre's website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kane GA, Wood VA, Barlow J. Parenting programmes: a systematic review and synthesis of qualitative research. Child Care Health Dev. 2007 Nov;33(6):784-93. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17944788</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krug EG, Mercy JA, Dahlberg LL, Zwi AB. [World report on violence and health]. Biomedica. 2002 Dec;22 Suppl 2:327-36. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>12596453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Knerr W, Gardner F, Cluver L. Improving positive parenting skills and reducing harsh and abusive parenting in low- and middle-income countries: a systematic review. Prev Sci. 2013 Aug;14(4):352-63. doi: 10.1007/s11121-012-0314-1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23315023</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaminski JW, Valle LA, Filene JH, Boyle CL. A meta-analytic review of components associated with parent training program effectiveness. J Abnorm Child Psychol. 2008 May;36(4):567-89. doi: 10.1007/s10802-007-9201-9. Epub 2008 Jan 19.</citation>
    <PMID>18205039</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 12, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Cape Town</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Soraya Lester</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parenting programme</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomised controlled trial</keyword>
  <keyword>South Africa</keyword>
  <keyword>Positive parenting</keyword>
  <keyword>Poor parenting</keyword>
  <keyword>Child behaviour problems</keyword>
  <keyword>Parent-child relationship</keyword>
  <keyword>Child self-esteem</keyword>
  <keyword>Parent's sense of competency</keyword>
  <keyword>Implementation fidelity</keyword>
  <keyword>Programme exposure</keyword>
  <keyword>Programme adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>Programme engagement</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
