<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="125938">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01723774</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201301106</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01723774</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PD 0332991 and Anastrozole for Stage 2 or 3 Estrogen Receptor Positive and HER2 Negative Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial of Neoadjuvant PD 0332991, a Cyclin-Dependent Kinase (Cdk) 4/6 Inhibitor, in Combination With Anastrozole in Women With Clinical Stage 2 or 3 Estrogen Receptor Positive and HER2 Negative Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A Phase II study to investigate the potential utility of PD 0332991 in the treatment of
      early stage ER+ Human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)- breast cancer, to
      investigate whether the combination of PD 0332991 and anastrozole is able to: 1) improve the
      pathologic complete response rate when compared to the historical control of single agent
      aromatase inhibitors, 2) result in fewer patients with on therapy Ki67&gt;10% compared to
      historical control.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete cell cycle arrest in women without PIK3CA hotspot mutation</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks (C1D15)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Complete cell cycle arrest is defined as Ki67 &lt; 2.7% following 2 weeks of neoadjuvant PD 0332991</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PEPI 0 score</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days following the last day of study treatment.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical response and radiologic response</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Physical examination: Prior cycle 0 and at the end of each neoadjuvant treatment cycle cycles (that is, at the end of cycles 0-4) the longest axis and the perpendicular axis of the measurable lesion should be measured and recorded in metric notation by tape, ruler or caliper technique on the case report forms.
Radiographic evaluation of tumor size:  Mammogram and ultrasound imaging will be performed prior to cycle 0 and at the end of cycle 4 combination therapy for bidimensional measurement of the tumor.
WHO criteria will be used to assess clinical response:</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ki67 level post 2 weeks of PD 332991</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Following the approach of Dowsett et al., the percent change in the Ki67 level from baseline will be determined on the log scale. A 95% t-confidence interval for the mean percent change in the Ki67 level from baseline will be constructed (if appropriate).
Logistic regression modeling will be used to examine which baseline patient and/or tumor characteristics are associated with the likelihood of a Ki67 being at or below 10%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>concentration of PD 0332991</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood will be drawn for PKs on Cycle 1 Day 15.  At each time point, blood will be drawn prior to drug administration and 90 minutes following drug administration.  This will be done in the first 16 patients in the PIK3CA wild type cohort only.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete cell cycle arrest rate at C1D1 and C1D15</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Compare rate of complete cell cycle (defined as Ki67 &lt; 2.7%) arrest between C1D1 and C1D15</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ki67 level of tumor specimens</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess Ki67 level on serially collected tumor specimens (baseline, C1D1, C1D15, and time of surgery)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathologic complete response (pCR) rate</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>concentration of anastrozole</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood will be drawn for PKs prior to initiation of PD 0332991 but after patients have taken anastrozole alone or in combination with goserelin for at least 2 weeks (this could be done on Cycle 1 Day 1) and again on Cycle 1 Day 15. At each time point, blood will be drawn prior to drug administration and 90 minutes following drug administration. This will be done in the first 16 patients in the PIK3CA wild type cohort only.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of PD 0332991 in combination in anastrozole</measure>
    <time_frame>15 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The maximum grade for each type of adverse event will be recorded for each patient using the NCI-CTCAE v4.0 coding scheme, and frequency tables will be reviewed to determine patterns. Additionally, the relationship of the adverse event(s) to the study treatment will be taken into consideration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete cell cycle arrest in women with PIK3CA hotspot mutation</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks (C1D15)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Complete cell cycle arrest is defined as Ki67 &lt; 2.7% following 2 weeks of neoadjuvant PD 0332991</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">29</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PD0332991+ Anastrozole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PD0332991 125 mg orally Days 1-21 of each 28 day cycle.
Anastrozole 1 mg orally on Days 1-28 of each cycle.
If premenopausal Goserelin 3.6 mg SC on Day 1.
Treatment with PD 0332991 combined with anastrozole (and goserelin if premenopausal) is for a maximum of 4 28-day cycles prior to surgery.
Anastrozole is to be continued until the day of surgery.  The last dose is on the day before surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PD0332991</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>PD0332991+ Anastrozole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anastrozole</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>PD0332991+ Anastrozole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Arimidex®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Goserelin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>PD0332991+ Anastrozole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zoladex®</other_name>
    <other_name>Decapeptide I</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients who were pre-registered to NCI 9170 trial (Phase II Trial of Neoadjuvant MK-2206
        in Combination with either Anastrozole if Postmenopausal or Anastrozole and Goserelin if
        Premenopausal in Women with Clinical Stage 2 or 3 PIK3CA Mutant Estrogen Receptor Positive
        and HER2 Negative Invasive Breast Cancer), started anastrozole (or anastrozole plus
        goserelin if premenopausal) &lt; 6 weeks, and were found negative for PIK3CA hotspot
        mutations are eligible to be screened for the wild type cohort. In institutions without
        NCI9170 open, or after completion of enrollment to NCI9170 in institutions where it is
        open, patients will be pre-registered to this trial and those with PIK3CA mutations will
        be enrolled to the PIK3CA mutant cohort.  Pre-registration is not required for patients to
        be enrolled in the endocrine resistant cohort, as PIK3CA mutation status will not be
        assessed.

        Pre-Registration Inclusion Criteria:

        -Clinical T2-T4c, any N, M0 invasive ER+ (Allred Score of 6-8) and HER2 negative (0 or 1+
        by IHC or FISH negative for amplification) breast cancer, by AJCC 7th edition clinical
        staging, with the goal being surgery to completely excise the tumor in the breast and the
        lymph node.

        Note:  Patients with invasive ER+ (Allred score of 6-8) HER2- breast cancer or DCIS in the
        contralateral breast the patient are eligible

          -  Female ≥18 years of age.

          -  ECOG performance status of 0, 1 or 2.

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 4 months.

          -  If premenopausal, patient must be willing to comply with pregnancy requirements

          -  Adequate organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  leukocytes ≥ 3,000/mcL

               -  absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1,500/mcL

               -  platelets ≥ 100,000/mcL

               -  total bilirubin ≤ upper normal institutional limits

               -  AST(SGOT)/ and ALT(SGPT) ≤ 2.5 X institutional upper limit normal

               -  Creatinine ≤ upper normal institutional limits

          -  Able to understand and willing to sign an IRB-approved written informed consent
             document.

        Pre-Registration Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior treatment of this cancer including:

               -  Surgery

               -  Radiation therapy

               -  Chemotherapy

               -  Biotherapy

               -  Hormonal therapy

               -  Investigational agent prior to study entry.

          -  Receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  Prior therapy with any Cdk4 inhibitor.

          -  Any of the following in the previous 6 months:

               -  myocardial infarction

               -  severe/unstable angina

               -  coronary/peripheral artery bypass graft

               -  symptomatic congestive heart failure

               -  cerebrovascular accident

               -  transient ischemic attack

               -  symptomatic pulmonary embolism.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to:

               -  ongoing or active infection

               -  symptomatic congestive heart failure

               -  unstable angina pectoris

               -  uncontrolled symptomatic cardiac arrhythmia,

               -  psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
                  requirements.

          -  Pregnant/nursing.

          -  Unwilling to employ adequate contraception.

          -  Known HIV-positive on combination antiretroviral therapy.

        NOTE: HIV-positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible because
        of the potential for pharmacokinetic interactions with PD 0332991.  In addition, these
        patients are at increased risk of lethal infections when treated with marrow-suppressive
        therapy.

          -  Evidence of inflammatory cancer (clinical presentation of skin erythema involving
             more than one third of the breast or pathological evidence of dermal lymphatic
             involvement)

          -  Known metastatic disease.

          -  Current use of anticoagulation therapy.

          -  Previous excisional biopsy of the breast cancer or sentinel lymph node biopsy.

          -  Any condition that impairs patient's ability to swallow PD 0332991 tablets (e.g.,
             gastrointestinal tract disease resulting in an inability to take oral medication or a
             requirement for IV alimentation, prior surgical procedures affecting absorption)

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to PD 0332991 or other agents used in the study.

          -  Corrected QT (QTc) interval &gt; 470 msec.

        Registration Inclusion Criteria

        The criteria below must be met for registration onto the study in addition to the
        pre-registration criteria, except treatment with endocrine therapy for this cancer is
        allowed prior to registration.

          -  For the PIK3CA mutant cohort: tumor PIK3CA mutation present

          -  For the PIK3CA wild type cohort: tumor PIK3CA mutation absent.

        Note that if a patient did not have sufficient tissue for PIK3CA sequencing at
        pre-registration or if PIK3CA sequencing result is delayed, she could be registered and
        enrolled on this trial without assigning to a particular cohort at the time of enrollment.
         PIK3CA sequencing will be performed in the future on tumors collected at subsequent time
        points to assign the treatment cohort or when the PIK3CA sequencing data is available.

          -  In premenopausal women, serum estradiol level in postmenopausal range ≤ 7 days prior
             to registration.

          -  For the endocrine resistant cohort: Ki67 &gt; 10% by central testing at Washington
             University AMP laboratory from a tumor biopsy performed after at least 2 weeks on
             neoadjuvant endocrine therapy.

               -  Note that prior neoadjuvant endocrine therapy could include any endocrine
                  therapy (including aromatase inhibitor, tamoxifen, fulvestrant) alone or in
                  combination, or endocrine therapy in combination with any investigational agent
                  that is not a Cdk 4/6 inhibitor.

               -  Patients who had a Day 17 Ki67 &gt; 10% from the NCI9170 trial are eligible for the
                  endocrine resistant cohort.

               -  Note that enrollment to the endocrine resistant cohort will depend on the
                  funding availability.  Please contact the study chair before enrolling patients
                  to this cohort.

        Registration Exclusion Criteria

        The criteria below must be met for registration onto the study in addition to the
        pre-registration criteria.

          -  Receiving medications (within the last 7 days prior to registration) that have the
             potential of prolonging the QT interval.

          -  Current use or anticipated need for food or drugs that are known strong CYP3A4
             inhibitors (i.e. grapefruit juice, verapamil, ketoconazole, miconazole, itraconazole,
             posaconazole, erythromycin, clarithromycin, telithromycin, indinavir, saquinavir,
             ritonavir, nelfinavir, lopinavir, atazanavir, amprenavir, fosamprenavir, nefazodone,
             diltiazem, and delavirdine) or inducers (i.e. dexamethasone, glucocorticoids,
             progesterone, rifampin, phenobarbital, St. John's wort).

          -  Receiving medications that are proton pump inhibitors.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cynthia Ma, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cynthia Ma, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>314-362-9383</phone>
    <email>cma@dom.wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic - Scottsdale</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85259</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Donald W Northfelt, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>480-301-8000</phone>
      <email>northfelt.donald@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donald W Northfelt, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic - Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matthew Goetz, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>507-284-2511</phone>
      <email>goetz.matthew@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthew Goetz, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tina Hieken, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cynthia Ma, M.D., PH.D.</last_name>
      <phone>314-362-9383</phone>
      <email>cma@dom.wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cynthia Ma, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthew Ellis, M.B., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julie Margenthaler, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donald Allred, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Souzan Sanati, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hussam Al-Kateb, M.Sc, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.siteman.wustl.edu</url>
    <description>Alvin J. Siteman Cancer Center at Barnes-Jewish Hospital and Washington University School of Medicine</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 6, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Estrogens</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Goserelin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anastrozole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
