<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="156416">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01934192</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>113445</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01934192</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nutritional Adequacy Therapeutic Enhancement in the Critically Ill. The NUTRIATE Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>NUTRItional Adequacy Therapeutic Enhancement in the Critically Ill: A Randomized Double Blind, Placebo-controlled Trial of the Motilin Receptor Agonist GSK962040. The NUTRIATE Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Australia : Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA)</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, parallel group, placebo-controlled and active-compared, randomized
      study to assess the ability of GSK962040 to enhance the delivery of enteral feed to
      critically ill subjects that are predisposed to developing feeding intolerance (e.g.,
      percentage of goal volume); enhance gastric emptying in this population; and provide
      preliminary evidence of the drug's effect on outcomes of therapy (length of stay in the
      Intensive Care Unit [ICU], time on ventilator, ICU acquired infections, and 60-day
      mortality). Other aims are evaluation of GSK962040 safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetics
      upon repeat dosing in a critically ill population.

      After meeting eligibility criteria, male and female subjects will be randomized to either
      receive GSK962040 (50 milligram [mg]) once daily (OD) via naso-gastric (NG) or orogastric
      (OG) feeding tube (oral solution), or placebo by the same route. If subjects develop
      intolerance to enteral feeding at any point up to Dose 5 of study medication (inclusive),
      study treatments will switch such that those originally receiving GSK962040 will receive
      metoclopramide (10 mg, intravenous [iv], every 6 hours) and those subjects originally
      randomized to receive placebo will receive GSK962040 (50 mg, via NG, OD).  Additionally, if
      subjects develop intolerance prior to any treatment, they will be randomized to receive
      either GSK962040 (50 mg, via NG, OD) or metoclopramide (10 mg, iv, every 6 hours).

      The study will consist of a screening/baseline assessment, a treatment period (up to 7 days
      in duration), and a 4-day post treatment safety follow-up assessment. The duration of each
      subject's participation in the study from screening to follow-up safety assessment will be
      up to approximately 2 weeks. In addition, mortality will be assessed 60 days after admission
      to the ICU.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Daily adequacy of enteral feed delivered via NG tube and average percent goal volume delivered (prior to development of intolerance)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The efficacy of GSK962040 upon the daily volume of enteral feed delivered on each of the dosing days was assessed by measuring the average percent goal volume delivered</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Daily adequacy of enteral feed delivered via NG tube, average per cent goal calories and protein delivered (prior to intolerance)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The effect of GSK962040 was assessed on the daily calories and protein delivered (up to 7 days) to mechanically-ventilated, critically-ill subjects who have conditions which predispose them to delayed gastric emptying.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to delivery of 80% prescribed calories</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The efficacy of GSK962040 was assessed by the time to deliver 80% prescribed calories.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with adverse events as a measure of safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The safety and tolerability of GSK962040 administration was assessed by adverse events (AEs): Only 'unexpected' events (inconsistent with underlying pathophysiology or progression of underlying disease) will be reported as an AE or serious AE (SAE)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trends in and change from baseline in measure of clinical laboratory test values to access safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to 7 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical laboratory tests will include hematology, Hepatitis B and C screen, clinical chemistry and urinalysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trends in and change from baseline for vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to 7 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital sign measurements will include pulse rate, blood pressure, and temperature</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trends in and change from baseline in measure of 12-lead ECG to access safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to 7 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Electrocardiograph (ECG) is a machine that measures the electrical activity of the heart and records changes in the hearts rhythm. All subjects underwent ECG testing to record the effect of GSK962040 on the heart and access its safety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total GRV for each 24h period</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The effect of GSK962040 upon the daily GRV on each of the dosing days while receiving randomized treatment was assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters following repeated doses of GSK962040: Cmax, Tmax, AUC(0-tau), AUC(0-infinity) for single-dose, and, if possible, accumulation ratio (Ro)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 7 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The pharmacokinetics of repeated doses of GSK962040 will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of feeding intolerance (FI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Development of FI as percent of subjects that become intolerant, time to development of FI and gastric emptying assessment within 24 hrs of developing intolerance (prior to being placed on rescue treatment); vomiting, regurgitation, and macroaspiration episodes. The relative incidence of the development of enteral feeding intolerance (two consecutive gastric residual volume [GRV] &gt;=250 mL) in subjects treated with GSK962040 was assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters of acetaminophen C60 min), Tmax, (AUC)0-60 min, AUC(0-120 min), AUC(0-180 min) and AUC(0-360 min) and 3-OMG AUC(0-60 min), C60 min, Cmax and Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 6 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The effect of GSK962040 upon gastric emptying after 2-3 doses of study medication (24h or 48h after Dose #1 of study medication) was measured by the acetaminophen and 3-O-methylglucose (3-OMG) absorption methods. Pharmacokinetic parameters included (Concentration at 60 minutes, (C60 min), Maximum observed concentration (Cmax), time of occurrence of maximum observed concentration (Cmax) (Tmax), Area under the concentration-time curves at different time intervals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastroparesis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Initial randomization: GSK962040 Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in the GSK962040 Arm will receive 50 mg once daily enteral dose administered through NG tube up to 7 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Initial randomization: Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in the placebo arm will receive once daily dose enteral dose administered through NG tube up to 7 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment change due to intolerance: GSK962040 Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects that develop intolerance and that originally received Placebo will receive 50 mg once daily enteral dose administered through NG tube + placebo IV</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment change due to intolerance: Metoclopramide Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects that develop intolerance and that originally received GSK962040 will receive metoclopramide 10 mg IV every 6 h + placebo NG</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK962040 50 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>GSK962040 50 mg will be administered once daily enteral dose through NG tube up to 7 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment change due to intolerance: GSK962040 Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Initial randomization: GSK962040 Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metoclopramide 10 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Metoclopramide will be administered IV every 6 h</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment change due to intolerance: Metoclopramide Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo NG</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo once daily enteral dose will be administered through NG tube up to 7 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Initial randomization: Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment change due to intolerance: Metoclopramide Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo IV</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo will be administered IV every 6 hours</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment change due to intolerance: GSK962040 Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &amp; Gender: Male or female between 18 and 85 years of age inclusive, at the time of
             obtaining the informed consent.

          -  First admitted to participating ICU within the previous 48 hours.

          -  Intubated and invasively mechanically ventilated

          -  Indicated to receive early EN or are already receiving EN (subject must be on EN
             prior to receiving study treatment)

          -  Have at least one of the following

          -  Clinical evidence of cardiovascular dysfunction defined as the need for vasopressor
             agents (e.g. norepinephrine, epinephrine, vasopressin), &gt;5 microgram/kg/min of
             dopamine, or &gt;/= 50 microgram/min phenylephrine) for greater than or equal to 2
             hours;

          -  Poly-trauma with an injury severity score (ISS) &gt;=15 points

          -  Acute traumatic or non-traumatic brain injury Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) &lt;=12, prior to
             the initiation of sedation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who are not expected to be in the ICU and alive for at least 48 hrs from
             point of screening.

          -  Subjects with acute hepatitis (e.g. acute hepatitis B or C) or severe chronic liver
             disease (e.g. Child Pugh class C cirrhosis) will be excluded

          -  Liver function tests: If Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt;=8x upper limit of normal
             (ULN); OR If ALT &gt;5-8x ULN and bilirubin &gt;2&lt;=3 ULN or bilirubin &gt;3x ULN (Include only
             if bilirubin &lt;1.5xULN); OR If ALT &lt;=5xULN and Bilirubin &gt;3xULN (Include only if ALT
             &lt;=3xULN and Bilirubin &gt;2 &lt;=3xULN)

          -  Subjects who have received a gastric prokinetic agent in the previous 12 hours (e.g.,
             erythromycin, azithromycin, metoclopramide, domperidone).

          -  QT duration corrected for heart rate (QTc) &gt;480 ms. QTcF is the recommended
             correction factor for all sites. If QT duration corrected for heart rate by
             Fridericia's formula (QTcF) is not possible to obtain or calculate, QT duration
             corrected for heart rate by Bazett's formula (QTcB) or machine or manual over read,
             may be obtained after consultation with the medical monitor. The QT correction
             formula used to determine inclusion and discontinuation should be the same throughout
             the study.

          -  Use of strong Cyp3A4 inhibitors

          -  Subjects who require renal replacement therapy or with an estimated glomerular
             filtration rate (GFR) of &lt;30 mL/min byCockroft-Gault calculation).

          -  Subjects who have a history of or who have undergone major esophageal or gastric
             surgery on this admission (major lower abdominal surgery will not result in exclusion
             unless this carries a contraindication to enteral feeding).

          -  Subjects with an absolute contraindication to enteral nutrition e.g. subjects with
             ongoing bowel obstruction or perforation.

          -  Subject has a gastric pacemaker

          -  Pregnant or lactating females

          -  History of sensitivity to any of the study medications, or components thereof or a
             history of drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of the investigator or GSK
             Medical Monitor, contraindicates their participation.

          -  Concurrent enrollment in other interventional study involving a novel (i.e.unapproved
             or experimental) chemical or biopharmaceutical entity.

          -  Previous randomization in this study

          -  Subjects for whom the reason for admission to ICU was an overdose (deliberate or
             accidental; medicinal product or not).

          -  Exclusion to re-randomization:

          -  Subjects with an untreated pheochromocytoma.

          -  Subjects with a past history of a seizure disorder (e.g., epilepsy) and is currently
             receiving anti-epileptic treatment for their seizure disorder, ongoing refractory, or
             sustained seizure disorder (prophylactic use for head injury/isolated new seizure
             maintained on anti-seizure meds in ICU acceptable).

          -  Subjects taking drugs likely to cause extrapyramidal reactions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T1Y 6J4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2N 2T9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kingston</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K7L 2V7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sainte-Foy</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>G1V 4G5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sherbrooke</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>J1H 5N4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>tolerability</keyword>
  <keyword>camicinal</keyword>
  <keyword>single dose</keyword>
  <keyword>acetaminophen</keyword>
  <keyword>gastric emptying</keyword>
  <keyword>critically ill</keyword>
  <keyword>GSK962040</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacodynamics</keyword>
  <keyword>gut motility</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gastroparesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Metoclopramide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
