<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="43552">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01915225</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130176</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-C-0176</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01915225</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Obtaining Solid Tumor Tissue From People Having Biopsy or Surgery for Certain Types of Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Tumor, Normal Tissue and Specimens From Patients Undergoing Evaluation or Surgical Resection of Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Recent advances in cancer research have led to new therapies to treat the disease. It is
      important to continue these advances and discover new ones. To do that, researchers need
      tissue samples from solid tumors. This study will collect such samples from people already
      scheduled to have a procedure at the National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (NIHCC).

      Objectives:

      - To collect tissue samples for use in studying new ways to treat tumors.

      Eligibility:

      - Adults 18 years and older, with a precancerous or cancerous solid tumor who are scheduled
      to have surgery or a biopsy at the NIHCC.

      Design:

        -  Before their procedure, participants will have a small blood sample taken.

        -  Some participants will undergo leukapheresis. In this procedure, blood is removed
           through a tube in one arm and circulated through a machine that removes white blood
           cells. The blood, minus the white blood cells, is returned through a tube in the other
           arm. The procedure takes 3   4 hours.

        -  For all participants, during the surgery or biopsy, pieces of the tumor and pieces of
           normal tissue near it will be removed for this study. The rest of the tumor or
           precancerous growth will be sent to a lab for analysis.

        -  Participants will return to the clinic about 6 weeks after the operation for a routine
           checkup. Some may have to return for additional follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

        -  Recent advances and insights into the molecular pathogenesis of cancer have led to the
           development of novel molecular and biologic targeted therapies for the treatment of
           advanced cancer patients. A critical challenge in extending these studies involves the
           identification and validation of new therapeutic targets for future cancer therapies.

        -  As Surgical Oncologists at the NCI, we have an interest in identifying novel molecular
           and biologic targets to facilitate the development of future cancer therapies. In
           addition, we have the primary responsibility for providing surgical consultative
           services to the NIH. As such, we are uniquely positioned to acquire and perform
           important studies on solid tumor tissue to help identify therapeutic targets that may
           have significant clinical ramifications.

      OBJECTIVES:

        -  Primary Objective: To collect biologic samples from patients undergoing diagnostic or
           therapeutic interventions for premalignant, primary or metastatic solid tumors for the
           purpose of identifying novel molecular and biologic therapeutic targets

        -  Secondary Objectives: To collect detailed history, demographic, treatment data, and
           perioperative findings in order to categorize and track the specific procedures and
           outcomes.

      ELIGIBILITY:

        -  Patients greater than or equal to 18 years of age with radiographic evidence of,
           biochemical evidence of, or histologically/cytologically proven solid neoplasms who
           require diagnostic or therapeutic intervention as a part of the diagnosis and /or
           standard of care treatment and/or follow up for their neoplasm

        -  Patients must have laboratory and physical examination parameters within acceptable
           limits by standard of practice guidelines prior to planned intervention

      DESIGN:

        -  A tissue acquisition trial in which tissues will be obtained at the time of
           intervention

        -  Tissue and blood will be processed at the time of collection, stored and then
           transferred to Dr. Rudloff   s laboratory for further processing.

        -  No investigational therapy will be given.

        -  It is anticipated that 1000 patients will be enrolled over a period of 10 years
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Collect biologic samples for premalignant, primary or metastatic solid tumors for the purpose of identifying novel molecular and biologic therapeutic targets</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To collect detailed history, demographic, treatment data, and perioperative findings in order to categorize and track the specific procedures and outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Gastric Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Cholangiocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Bile Duct Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Pancreas Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA

          -  Patients must be greater than or equal to 18 years of age.

          -  Patients who have a premalignant, primary or metastatic solid tumors based upon
             either radiographic or biochemical testing, or histological/cytological analysis that
             requires surgery or biopsy as a part of the standard of care diagnosis, treatment
             and/or follow up

          -  Patients must have laboratory and physical examination parameters within acceptable
             limits by standard of practice guidelines prior to biopsy or surgery.

          -  Patients must be planning to undergo surgery or biopsy as part of their treatment
             plan. Note: Patients will not be enrolled exclusively for the procurement of tissue
             samples.

          -  Patients who agree to undergo leukapheresis must meet the following criteria:

          -  Seronegative for HIV

          -  Seronegative for hepatitis B surface antigen and seronegative for antibody to
             hepatitis C.

          -  CBC within acceptable limits
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marybeth S Hughes, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marybeth S Hughes, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 594-9341</phone>
    <email>hughesm@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact NCI/Surgery Branch Recruitment Center</last_name>
      <phone>866-820-4505</phone>
      <email>ncisbirc@mail.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-C-0176.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson JI, Decker S, Zaharevitz D, Rubinstein LV, Venditti JM, Schepartz S, Kalyandrug S, Christian M, Arbuck S, Hollingshead M, Sausville EA. Relationships between drug activity in NCI preclinical in vitro and in vivo models and early clinical trials. Br J Cancer. 2001 May 18;84(10):1424-31.</citation>
    <PMID>11355958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Philip PA, Mooney M, Jaffe D, Eckhardt G, Moore M, Meropol N, Emens L, O'Reilly E, Korc M, Ellis L, Benedetti J, Rothenberg M, Willett C, Tempero M, Lowy A, Abbruzzese J, Simeone D, Hingorani S, Berlin J, Tepper J. Consensus report of the national cancer institute clinical trials planning meeting on pancreas cancer treatment. J Clin Oncol. 2009 Nov 20;27(33):5660-9. Epub 2009 Oct 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19858397</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubio-Viqueira B, Hidalgo M. Direct in vivo xenograft tumor model for predicting chemotherapeutic drug response in cancer patients. Clin Pharmacol Ther. 2009 Feb;85(2):217-21. Epub 2008 Nov 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19005462</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 31, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tissue Procurement</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastasectomy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomach Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholangiocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bile Duct Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
