<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="109309">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01943864</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>117134</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01943864</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase IIa Study of the MEK Inhibitor Trametinib Monotherapy in the Treatment of Biliary Tract Cancers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase IIa Study of the MEK Inhibitor GSK1120212 Monotherapy in the Treatment of Gemcitabine Refractory Locally Advanced, Recurrent or Metastatic Biliary Tract Cancers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare</authority>
    <authority>Japan: Pharmaceuticals and Medical Devices Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase IIa, open-label, single-arm, multi-center study to evaluate the efficacy and
      safety of orally administered MEK inhibitor trametinib as the second line in subjects with
      advanced or metastatic biliary tract cancers (BTC) in Japanese population. The primary
      endpoint of this study is 12 week non-progressive disease (PD) rate defined as the
      percentage of subjects without progression at Week 12. As a sub-study, pharmacokinetics (PK)
      of four tablets of 0.5 milligram (mg) tablet, or one tablet of 2 mg tablet to achieve 2 mg
      daily regimen will be assessed to evaluate the pharmacokinetics of trametinib in Japanese
      population.

      Eligible subjects will be randomized to receive trametinib at the recommended Phase II dose
      of 2 mg every day as one 2 mg tablet or four 0.5 mg tablets on Day 1. From Day 2 until
      disease progression or withdrawal from the study treatment, all subjects will receive one
      tablet of 2 mg trametinib . Disease assessment will be performed every 8 week. Translational
      research is also planned to evaluate the potential blood or tumor tissue-derived biomarkers
      for biological activity, and sensitivity or resistance to treatment with trametinib .
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-progressive disease rate at Week  12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Day 1) to Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The clinical activity of trametinib will be assessed as per Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1. The 12-week non-PD rate will be calculated as the percentage of subjects without progression as per RECIST 1.1 criteria at Week 12.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with adverse events as a measure of safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Day 1) and up to 30 days following discontinuation of study treatment.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The safety of trametinib administration will be assessed by adverse events (AEs). AE is defined as Any untoward medical occurrence in a participant or clinical investigation participant, temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the medicinal product.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in clinical laboratory measurements to assess safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (Day -21) and up to 7 days after study withdrawal or disease progression</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Any abnormal laboratory test results (haematology, clinical chemistry, or urinalysis)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in vital sign measurements to assess safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (Day -21)  and up to 7 days after study withdrawal or disease progression</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital sign measurements will include systolic and diastolic blood pressure, body temperature, heart rate and oxygen saturation. Blood pressure should be measured after sitting for at least 5 min, and all measurements should use the same cuff size as well as the same arm throughout the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS) in overall population</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (Day -21)  and up to 14 days after study withdrawal or disease progression</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The efficacy of trametinib will be assessed as PFS is defined as the interval between the date of randomization and the earliest date of disease progression or death due to any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS) in overall population up to 1 year from randomization</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (Day -21)  and up to 14 days after study withdrawal or disease progression</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The efficacy of trametinib will be assessed as OS defined as the time from randomization until death due to any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall response rate (ORR) in overall population</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (Day -21)  and up to 14 days after study withdrawal or disease progression</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The efficacy of trametinib will be assessed as ORR defined as the percentage of subjects with a confirmed complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) as per RECIST 1.1 criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response (DR) in overall population</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (Day -21)  and up to 14 days after study withdrawal or disease progression</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The efficacy of trametinib will be assessed as DR defined for the subset of subjects with a confirmed CR or PR, as the time from first documented evidence of CR or PR until first documented disease progression or death due to any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Response (TR) in overall population</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (Day -21)  and up to 14 days after study withdrawal or disease progression</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The efficacy of trametinib will be assessed as TR defined for subjects with a confirmed CR or PR as the time from randomization to the first documented evidence of CR or PR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK profile of GSK1120212</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (pre dose, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 24 hr after first dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected assessment of PK parameters including area under the concentration-time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Trametinib (single tablet)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive, trametinib once daily as a single tablet of 2 mg administered orally with eight ounces of water under fasting conditions either one hour before or 2 hours after a meal.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Trametinib PK study (multiple tablet)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive on Day 1, trametinib as four tablets of 0.5 mg administered orally with eight ounces of water under fasting conditions either one hour before or 2 hours after a meal.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Trametinib PK study (single tablet)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive Day 2 onwards, trametinib once daily as a single tablet of 2 mg administered orally with eight ounces of water under fasting conditions either one hour before or 2 hours after a meal.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trametinib (single tablet)</intervention_name>
    <description>The drug substance is blended with inert</description>
    <arm_group_label>Trametinib PK study (single tablet)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Trametinib (single tablet)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trametinib (Multiple tablet)</intervention_name>
    <description>The drug substance is blended with inert</description>
    <arm_group_label>Trametinib PK study (multiple tablet)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female of age 20 years or older inclusive, at the time of signing the
             informed consent.

          -  Japanese patients with histologically or cytologically confirmed cholangiocarcinoma
             (intra- or extrahepatic) or gallbladder cancer or ampulla of Vater cancer are
             eligible for which all of the following criteria have to be met: Nonresectable,
             recurrent, and/or metastatic disease.

          -  Disease progression after up to two lines of systemic chemotherapies including no
             more than one line of gemcitabine-based chemotherapy. Note: Systemic therapy in
             adjuvant setting is not allowed as prior therapy.

          -  More than 21 days have elapsed since any prior anti-tumor therapy.

          -  At least one of the tumor samples for archived tissue at initial diagnosis or
             archived tissue at recent progression or fresh biopsy at recent progression (collect
             within 21 days from randomization if none of the archived tissues are available) is
             available prior to randomization to provide for translational research.

          -  Measurable disease, i.e. presenting with at least one measurable lesion per the
             RESIST 1.1.

          -  Performance status score of ≤1 according to the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group
             (ECOG) scale.

          -  Estimated life expectancy of at least 12 weeks.

          -  All prior treatment- related toxicities must be common terminology criteria for
             adverse events (CTCAE)  (Version 4.0) ≤ Grade 1 (except alopecia) at the time of
             randomization.

          -  Negative for hepatitis C virus (HCV) test, hepatitis B surface (HBs) antigen,
             hepatitis virus Bc (HBc) antibody, and HBs antibody. HBs antigen-negative subjects
             who test positive for both HBc antibody and HBs antibody or either of them may be
             eligible when their HBV DNA quantification result is negative.

          -  Able to swallow and retain orally administered medication and does not have any
             clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities that may alter absorption such
             as malabsorption syndrome or major resection of the stomach or bowels.

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test within 7
             days prior to the first dose of study treatment and agree to use effective
             contraception throughout the treatment period, and for 4 months after the last dose
             of study treatment.

          -  Adequate baseline organ function for haematological, hepatic, renal, cardiac systems.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of another malignancy.

          -  Any serious and/or unstable pre-existing medical disorder (aside from malignancy
             exception above), psychiatric disorder, or other conditions that could interfere with
             subject's safety, obtaining informed consent or compliance to the study procedures.

          -  Radiotherapy completed within 2 weeks prior to randomization.

          -  History of interstitial lung disease or pneumonitis.

          -  Having a known immediate or delayed hypersensitivity reaction or idiosyncrasy to
             drugs chemically related to study drug, or excipients or to dimethyl sulfoxide
             (DMSO).

          -  Any major surgery, extensive radiotherapy, chemotherapy with delayed toxicity,
             biologic therapy, or immunotherapy within 28 days prior to randomization and/or
             chemotherapy without the potential for delayed toxicity within 21days prior to
             randomization.

          -  Any prior use of any MEK inhibitors (including but not limited to trametinib, AZD6244
             (selumetinib), RDEA119).

          -  Current use of a prohibited medication.

          -  History or current evidence/risk of retinal vein occlusion (RVO) or central serous
             retinopathy (CSR).

          -  Symptomatic or untreated leptomeningeal or brain metastases or spinal cord
             compression.

          -  Known Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) infection. History or evidence of
             cardiovascular risk including a QT interval corrected for heart rate using the
             Bazett's formula (QTcB) interval &gt;480 msec, history or evidence of current clinically
             significant uncontrolled arrhythmias, history of acute coronary syndromes (including
             myocardial infarction and unstable angina), coronary angioplasty, or stenting within
             6 months prior to randomization, history or evidence of current &gt; or = Class II
             congestive heart failure as defined by New York Heart Association, treatment
             refractory hypertension defined as a blood pressure of systolic&gt; 140 mmHg and/or
             diastolic &gt; 90 mmHg which cannot be controlled by anti-hypertensive therapy, subjects
             with intra-cardiac defibrillators or permanent pacemakers.

          -  Known cardiac metastases.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chiba</city>
        <zip>277-8577</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Osaka</city>
        <zip>537-8511</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shizuoka</city>
        <zip>411-8777</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <zip>104-0045</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <zip>181-8611</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>second line monotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>GSK1120212 (trametinib)</keyword>
  <keyword>MEK inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>locally advanced or metastatic biliary tract cancers</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Biliary Tract Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
