<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="164966">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02097797</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P 121104</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02097797</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of the Fecal Flora Transplantation on Crohn's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>IMPACT</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of Fecal transPlantAtion on MiCrobotia and hosT in Crohn's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>French National Institute for Health and Medical Research-French National Agency for Research on AIDS and Viral Hepatitis (Inserm-ANRS)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pierre and Marie Curie University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Afssaps - Agence française de sécurité sanitaire des produits de santé (Saint-Denis)</authority>
    <authority>France: French Data Protection Authority</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Crohn's disease is a chronic and relapsing inflammatory bowel disease. Many data show that
      the intestinal flora is involved in the disease and it has been show that patients with
      Crohn's disease exhibit an abnormal fecal flora that might play a role in inflammation. The
      purpose of this study is to determine the effect of the fecal flora transplantation on
      Crohn's disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction : Crohn's disease (CD) is an relapsing inflammatory bowel disease relatively
      frequent. Its prevalence is about 1 for 700 in France, affecting predominantly young adults.
      Its treatment is based on immunosuppressants that might be associated with potentially
      severe complications such as infection and cancers. Moreover, these treatments are
      expensive. The gut microbiota being involved in the disease pathogenesis, it can be
      considered as a potential therapeutic target.

      CD pathogenesis remains poorly understood but involves an inappropriate immune response
      toward an unbalanced gut microbiota (called dysbiosis) in predisposed hosts. The complete
      replacement of a dysbiotic microbiota by a &quot;healthy&quot; one is thus an attractive strategy.
      Fecal transplantation (FT) has been used with success for a long time in the context of
      Clostridium difficile.

      Hypothesis : Fecal transplantation allow the replacement of a dysbiotic microbiota by a &quot;
      healthy &quot; one with favorable impact on CD evolution.

      Primary endpoint : In CD patient with colonic or ileo-colonic involvement put in remission
      with corticosteroids,  Evaluate if FT can modify a dysbiotic fecal microbiota to be closer
      of the one of a healthy donor.

      Methodology

      For the Receiver :

      Once corticoid-induced remission will be achieved, the patient will be included and
      randomised to receive either FT or sham transplantation during a colonoscopy. The patient
      will be evaluated at week 2, 6, 10, 14, 18 and 24. At week 6, a colonoscopy will be
      performed.

      For the Donor :

      Donors will be recruited by poster advertising. When a receiver will be included, 2 donors
      will be contacted to attend an inclusion visit including physical examination as well as
      blood and stool screening for pathogen. The 2 donors will then come the day of the FT to
      donate their stool.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>FT success defined by : Sorensen's index [receiver 6 weeks after FT vs donor] &gt; Sorensen's index [receiver 6 weeks after FT vs receiver before FT]) with Sorensen's index [receiver 6 weeks after FT vs donor] ≥ 0.6.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after FT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In other words, FT success is reached if the fecal microbiota of the receiver 6 weeks after FT is closer of the fecal microbiota of the donor that of the receiver before FT.
Fecal microbiota composition will be assessed by 454 pyrosequencing (16S RNA) and microbiota comparison will be done using Sorensen's index.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FT feasibility</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after FT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>evaluate the feasibility of the FT procedure (frequency of evaluable patients in each group)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical relapse rate in the 24 weeks following FT procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks following FT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical relapse defined by a Crohn's disease activity index (CDAI) &gt; 220 points, or by a CDAI between 150 and 220 with an increase &gt;70 compared with baseline, or by the need of surgery or to start a medical treatment for CD.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on CRP</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after FT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on CRP level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on Leukocytes level</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after FT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on: Leukocytes level</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on fecal calprotectin</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after FT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on: fecal calprotectin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on Crohn's Disease Endoscopic Index of Severity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after FT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on: Crohn's Disease Endoscopic Index of Severity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on fecal microbiota composition</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after FT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on: fecal microbiota composition</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on lymphocytes population in blood</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after FT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on: lymphocytes population in blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on lymphocytes population in colon</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after FT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on: lymphocytes population in colon.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on colon transcriptomics</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after FT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Effect of FT compared to sham transplantation on: colon transcriptomics.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Crohn's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fecal Transplantation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients receiving the fecal transplant (fecal microbiota from a healthy donor)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Transplantation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients receiving the vehicle (Physiological serum)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fecal Transplantation</intervention_name>
    <description>Fecal microbiota (50-100g of stool from donor resuspended in 250-350ml of physiological serum and filtered) given by infusion in coecum during colonoscopy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fecal Transplantation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham Transplantation</intervention_name>
    <description>250-350ml of physiological serum given by infusion in coecum during colonoscopy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Transplantation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Receiver

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt; 18 years and  &lt; 70 years

          -  Crohn's disease with colonic or ileo-colonic involvement

          -  Active disease at screening defined by a Harvey Bradshaw Index &gt;4

          -  Clinical remission (Harvey Bradshaw Index &lt;5) in the 3 weeks following corticosteroid
             onset

          -  Patient with health insurance

          -  Written consent obtained

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Fistulizing disease

          -  Anoperineal or abdominal abscess

          -  Complication requiring surgical treatment

          -  Treatment with anti-TNFa (ongoing or stopped in the 3 months preceding randomization)

          -  Immunosuppressant treatment started or stopped  in the 3 months preceding
             randomization

          -  Non-steroidal anti inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) intake in the 4 weeks preceding
             randomization

          -  Antibiotics or antifungic treatment in the 4 weeks preceding colonoscopy

          -  Probiotics intake in the 4 weeks preceding colonoscopy

          -  Clostridium difficile infection in the 10 days preceding randomization

          -  contraindication to colonoscopy or anesthesia

          -  Pregnancy

        Donor

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt; 20 years and  &lt; 50 years

          -  27kg/m² &gt; BMI &gt; 17 kg/m²

          -  Regular bowel movement with usually one bowel movement in the morning

          -  Subject with health insurance

          -  Written consent obtained

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Infection risk:

               -  Known infection by human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), Human T Leukemia Virus
                  (HTLV), Hepatitis B or C virus.

               -  At risk behavior: Travel (in the preceding 3 months,  excepting in Euro area,
                  United Kingdom, Denmark, Norway, Sweden, Swiss, USA or Canada), at risk sexual
                  activity (intercourse without protection with a new partner) in the preceding 6
                  months, blood transfusion, piercing or tattoo in the preceding 6 months.

               -  Positive result at one of the screening tests for infectious disease. : HIV,
                  HCV, HBV, HTLV, syphilis, Enteric viruses (Rotavirus,  HEV, Adenovirus,
                  Norovirus, Enterovirus, HAV, Poliovirus, Astrovirus), parasites in stool
                  (Cyclospora, Isospora, Cryptosporidium, Microsporidium, Strongyloides
                  stercoralis, Entamoeba histolitica,  Giardia intestinalis, Dientamoeba
                  fragilis), pathogenic bacteria in stool (Clostridium difficile, Shigella,
                  Campylobacter, Yersinia, Salmonella, Listeria monocytogenes, Vibrio
                  cholerae/parahemolyticus)

               -  Anal lesions suggesting viral infection or positive test for HSV anal.

               -  Positive test for multidrug resistant bacteria

               -  If receiver is EBV negative, EBV positive donor will be excluded

               -  If receiver is CMV negative, CMV positive donor will be excluded.

               -  Known transmissible infectious disease

               -  Infection (or possible infection) in the 7 days preceding screening

               -  Risk factors for Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease

          -  Gastrointestinal comorbidity

               -  Personal history or first degree relative :

                    -  Inflammatory bowel disease

                    -  Coeliac disease

               -  Personal history of irritable bowel syndrome, chronic constipation, chronic
                  diarrhea

               -  Personal history of gastrointestinal neoplasia or polyposis

               -  First degree relative with gastrointestinal neoplasia or polyposis before 60
                  years old

               -  Gastrointestinal infection in the 3 preceding months (defined by the occurrence
                  of an acute diarrhea that last less than a week)

          -  Factors possibly affecting the composition of the microbiota:

               -  Antibiotics or antifungic intake  in the 3 preceding months before FT

               -  Non-steroidal anti inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) intake in the 4 weeks preceding
                  FT

               -  Specific diet (exclusion diet, vegetarian diet)

               -  Pregnancy

               -  Immunosuppressant intake (corticosteroids, calcineurin inhibitors, biologics,
                  etc)

               -  Anti neoplastic chemotherapy

               -  Hemorrhoid disease

          -  Other Factors :

               -  Known chronic disease

               -  Abnormality at initial biological check up: blood cells count, fasting,
                  glycaemia, kidney function, liver tests, haemostasis, calprotectin

          -  between screening and FT :

               -  At risk behavior (Travel, at risk sexual activity, blood transfusion, piercing
                  tattoo)

               -  Infection or possible infection

               -  Occurrence of gastro-intestinal symptoms

               -  Medicine intake in the 48 hours preceding FT (except contraceptive)

               -  In case of woman: menstruation in the 48 hours preceding FT
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Harry Sokol, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Harry SOKOL, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+ 33 1 49 28 31 62</phone>
    <email>harry.sokol@sat.aphp.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Laurent Beaugerie, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+33 (0)1 49 28 31 62</phone>
    <email>laurent.beaugerie@sat.aphp.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gastroenterology department, Saint Antoine Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75571</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Harry Sokol, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+ 33 1 49 28 31 62</phone>
      <email>harry.sokol@sat.aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Laurent Beaugerie, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+33 (0)1 49 28 31 62</phone>
      <email>laurent.beaugerie@sat.aphp.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 26, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Inflammatory bowel disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Crohn's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>microbiota</keyword>
  <keyword>fecal transplantation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Crohn Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
