<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="129262">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01680276</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10/104/13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01680276</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical and Cost Effectiveness of Positive Behaviour Support: a Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>PBS community</acronym>
  <official_title>Clinical and Cost Effectiveness of Staff Training in Positive Behaviour Support (PBS) for Treating Challenging Behaviour in People With Intellectual Disability: A Cluster Randomised Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University College, London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University College, London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: National Institute for Health Research</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Many people with intellectual disability have challenging behaviour which often has serious
      consequences such as the prescription of long term medication, in-patient admissions and
      disruption of normal daily activities.  Community intellectual disability services may have
      difficulties in helping people with challenging behaviour.  Available research suggests that
      Positive Behaviour Support (PBS), a training system that teaches staff how to manage these
      situations, can benefit  service users who may show improvements in challenging behaviour
      and quality of life.  Previous researchers have published small studies on its effectiveness
      but these studies have methodological problems.  The investigators do not know of any study
      so far that has examined the clinical and cost effectiveness of PBS that is provided by
      staff in routine clinical practice in community intellectual disability services.  If PBS
      proved to be better than treatment as usual, it would have important implications for the
      management of a very vulnerable group of service users. In this trial, health staff will
      receive accredited training in PBS available in a manual written by experts in PBS.  It will
      give details of how to understand challenging behaviour and develop a management plan and
      how to implement it and monitor whether it has achieved its goals.   Twenty community
      intellectual disability services and 260 service users with mild to severe intellectual
      disability and challenging behaviour will be invited to take part in the study.   The sample
      size calculations are based on our pilot study and allow for non participation of 10% and
      inflation due to the number of community intellectual disability teams and staff that will
      take part. The teams will be randomly allocated into one of two conditions.  Half will be in
      the PBS arm (but will also have treatment as usual) and half will be in the treatment as
      usual only group. The investigators will carry out assessments of challenging behaviour, use
      of services, quality of life, mental health, aggression and family and paid carer burden at
      six and 12 months.  The investigators will monitor treatment fidelity and the investigators
      will talk to a sample of paid and family carers, service users, staff and managers about
      what they think of the treatment and how best the investigators can deliver it in routine
      care.  The main outcome is reduction in challenging behaviour at one year after the
      randomisation.  The investigators will also carry out a health economic evaluation to
      examine the costs and consequences of staff training in PBS.   The study will last for four
      years and the investigators will run it in community intellectual disability services in
      England.  The investigators will follow the research and clinical governance guidance and
      seek ethical approval before the study starts.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Challenging Behaviour</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Reduction in challenging behaviour as measured by the Aberrant Behaviour Checklist (ABC)and change from baseline and 6 months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Challenging Behaviour</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Reduction in challenging behaviour as measured by the Aberrant Behaviour Checklist</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Improvement in Quality of Life measured by the Quality of Life Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mental health status</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Improvement in mental health measured by the mini-PASADD.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Family carer burden</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Reduction in family carer burden measured by the Uplift/Burden Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Paid carer burden</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Reduction in burden measured by Caregiving Difficulty Scale—Intellectual Disability</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Family Carer Psychiatric Morbidity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Reduction in Psychiatric morbidity measured by the General Health Questionnaire (12 item version)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cost effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Service use will be measured over the trial period at three month intervals using the Client Service Receipt Inventory adapted specifically for the study</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Community participation</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Improvement measured by change in Guernsey Community Participation and Leisure Activity Scale (GCPLAS)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Community participation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Positive change from 6 months as measured with the GCPLAS</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">260</enrollment>
  <condition>Treatment of Challenging Behaviour in Intellectual and Developmental Disability</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PBS based staff training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The training, which will be supported by a treatment manual will comprise the following sections:
Functional Behavioural Assessment and formulation skills
• Brief Behavioural Assessment Tool for brief functional analyses
Primary Prevention
Secondary Prevention and Reactive Strategies
Periodic Service Review and Problem Solving
Developing individualised periodic service reviews
Trouble shooting</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Most community intellectual disability services provide a range of health interventions that include but are not limited to psychiatric assessment and management, nursing support, psychology, speech and language therapy, occupational therapy and counselling.  There may be some variation in resources but service users with challenging behaviour are likely to receive a range of broadly defined behavioural management and pharmacological interventions.  Staff is routinely supervised by their clinical managers weekly.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PBS based staff training</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>PBS based staff training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment as Usual</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Service users:  Eligible to receive care from intellectual disability services; mild
             to severe intellectual disability; aged 18 years and over; total ABC score of at
             least 15 (indicates a degree of challenging behaviour occurring at least weekly
             including verbal or physical aggression, hyperactivity, refusal to attend activities,
             non responsiveness that requires professional input).

          -  Service:  Willing to participate; availability of at least two staff members willing
             to train; written agreement by the service manager to participate.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Service users:  primary clinical diagnosis of personality disorder or substance
             misuse; relapse in pre-existing mental disorder; decision by clinical team that a
             referral to the study would be inappropriate, e.g. there is an open complaint
             investigation

          -  Service:  there are no team members willing to train; the service has already
             received and implements accredited PBS for their service users.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andre Strydom, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>UCL</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ian Hall, MBBS MPhil</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>East London Foundation Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael King, FRCGP PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>UCL</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rumana Omar</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>UCL Statistics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rachael Hunter</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Health Economist</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vivien Cooper</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Challenging Behaviour Foundation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Angela Hassiotis, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+442079743788</phone>
    <email>a.hassiotis@ucl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leicestershire Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leicester</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Asit Biswas</last_name>
      <email>asitbiswas@yahoo.co.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South London and St George's Mental Health Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>William Howie, MBBS MRCPsych</last_name>
      <email>William.Howie@swlstg-tr.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Camden &amp; Islington Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Angela Hassiotis</last_name>
      <email>a.hassiotis@ucl.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jason Crabtree</last_name>
      <email>jason.grabtree@islington.gov.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 3, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 28, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>intellectual disability</keyword>
  <keyword>developmental disability</keyword>
  <keyword>challenging behaviour</keyword>
  <keyword>behavioural intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>training</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Developmental Disabilities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Retardation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
