<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="156562">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02127892</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CCI-06-00243</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02127892</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SCID Bu/Flu/ATG Study With T Cell Depletion</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/II Trial of Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant (HSCT) for Children With Severe Combined Immune Deficiency (SCID) and Without an HLA-Matched Sibling Donor</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Neena Kapoor, M.D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot clinical trial of hematopoietic stem cell transplantation for patients with
      a diagnosis of Severe Combined Immune Deficiency (SCID) who do not have an HLA-matched
      sibling donor. The stem cells will be derived from a 1) matched unrelated donor (MUD), 2)
      unrelated cord blood donor, or 3) a haplo-identical (parental) donor (in descending order of
      preference).Patients will receive a novel conditioning regimen with Busulfan, Fludarabine
      and Anti-thymocyte globulin (ATG) followed by an unrelated donor hematopoietic stem cell
      transplant (HSCT) with T-cell depletion using the CliniMACS device.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is being conducted to assess the following:

        -  overall survival

        -  event-free survival (events are defined as: death,non-engraftment/2nd transplant,
           immune reconstitution failure)

        -  acute toxicity of the conditioning regimen

        -  engraftment frequency immune reconstitution frequency and tempo acute and chronic
           graft-versus-host disease (GVHD), frequency and severity.

      The outcome from this protocol will be compared to the retrospective cohort consisting of
      all patients who have undergone haplo-identical HSCT for SCID at CHLA from 1984-2006 based
      on the assessment of the above-listed endpoints.

      The CliniMACS device will be used for CD34+ selection in place of the Isolex 300i. The
      CliniMACS CD34 Reagent System is an investigational medical device that has not yet been
      approved by the FDA. This device is used in vitro to select and enrich specific cell
      populations. When using the CliniMACS CD34 Reagent, the system selects CD34+ cells from
      heterogenous hematological cell populations for transplantation in cases where this is
      clinically indicated. Based on the gathered data, CliniMACS has not been a contributing
      factor in the toxicity of patients, although, may have a potential of eliciting &quot;antibody&quot;
      reactions in some patients, the process has been of significant life-saving benefit as
      compared to the potential risks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Engraftment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Engraftment is defined as recovery of blood counts (neutrophil and platelet engraftment) with cells of donor origin, documented by either bone marrow or peripheral blood chimerism assays after hematopoietic stem cell transplant.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T lymphocyte recovery to assess immune function</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Absolute number of donor-derived CD3+ T lymphocytes &gt;/= 100/mm3</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Veno-occlusive Disease</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Graft versus host disease</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Combined Immunodeficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>unrelated BM with T cell depletion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Acceptable matching for matched unrelated donor (MUD) bone marrow will be genotypic matches at 10 of 10 HLA alleles (HLA-A, B, C, DR and DQ) or 9 of 10 HLA alleles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>unrelated cord blood</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Acceptable matching for unrelated cord blood will be a genotypic match at 6 of 6 alleles (HLA A, B and DR) or 5 of 6 alleles, but not with mismatches at both alleles of a single locus (e.g. not mismatched for both HLA A alleles).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>haplo BM with T cell depletion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>If there is no unrelated donor available meeting the matching criteria for unrelated bone marrow or unrelated cord blood donors.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>unrelated PBSC with T cell depletion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The preferred source will be bone marrow, however, if a donor is unable or unwilling to donate bone marrow, peripheral blood stem cells (PBSC) will be allowed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>unrelated BM with T cell depletion</intervention_name>
    <description>Remaining unmanipulated bone marrow will be processed to isolate CD34+ cells (T cell depleted).</description>
    <arm_group_label>unrelated BM with T cell depletion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CD34+ selection using CliniMACS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>unrelated cord blood</intervention_name>
    <description>Cord blood will be thawed (and processed if ABO incompatibility) per institutional SOP.</description>
    <arm_group_label>unrelated cord blood</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>umbilical cord blood</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>haplo BM with T cell depletion</intervention_name>
    <description>haplo-identical (parental) bone marrow will be processed for CD34+ cell isolation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>haplo BM with T cell depletion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CD34+ selection with CliniMACS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>unrelated PBSC with T cell depletion</intervention_name>
    <description>peripheral blood stem cell  will be processed for CD34+ cell isolation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>unrelated PBSC with T cell depletion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CD34+ selection using CliniMACS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients with SCID who lack a histocompatible sibling or HLA-matched related
             donor will be considered as candidates for this study protocol.

          -  Eligible patients must have adequate physical function to tolerate the chemotherapy
             conditioning regimen and the HSCT, as measure by:

               1. Renal: creatinine clearance or GFR ≥50 ml/min/1.73m2, and not requiring dialysis

               2. Pulmonary: Because patients with SCID frequently present with infectious
                  pneumonia causing ventilatory failure, patients will be considered for
                  enrollment in the study even if respiratory failure requiring mechanical
                  ventilatory support is present. In patients recently diagnosed with pneumonia,
                  efforts to stabilize the respiratory status will be made prior to enrollment in
                  the study.

               3. Infectious disease status. The presence of infection per se will not be a reason
                  for exclusion from the study. Patients with SCID are frequently infected with
                  both routine pathogens as well as opportunistic infections. Antibiotic,
                  antifungal and antiviral prophylaxis and therapy will be instituted as
                  clinically indicated. Despite the use of antimicrobial therapy, the ability to
                  control infections will not be achieved unless HSCT is performed. Therefore,
                  subjects may be enrolled in the study, even though infection is present, because
                  control of infection may depend on engraftment of a donor immune system.

               4. Patients will be 0-21 years of age.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with histocompatible sibling or other related donor

          -  End-organ failure that precludes the ability to tolerate the transplant procedure,
             including conditioning.

          -  Renal failure requiring dialysis

          -  Congenital heart disease resulting in congestive heart failure

          -  Severe CNS disease, e.g., coma or intractable seizures

          -  Ventilatory failure due to non-infectious etiology

          -  Major congenital anomalies that adversely affect survival, eg CNS malformations

          -  Metabolic diseases that would affect transplant survival, eg urea cycle disorders

          -  HIV infection

        Since the only chance of survival for patients with SCID is successful transplantation,
        all patients with SCID will be considered to be potential subjects for the study,
        regardless of end-organ dysfunction.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Neena Kapoor, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Los Angeles, University of Southern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 19, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Neena Kapoor, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Pediatrics, Keck School of Medicine; Division Head, Division of Research Immunology/BMT</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Severe Combined Immune Deficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>SCID</keyword>
  <keyword>HLA-matched unrelated donor</keyword>
  <keyword>unrelated</keyword>
  <keyword>MUD</keyword>
  <keyword>bone marrow</keyword>
  <keyword>cord blood</keyword>
  <keyword>haplo-identical</keyword>
  <keyword>peripheral blood</keyword>
  <keyword>CD34+ selection</keyword>
  <keyword>T cell depletion</keyword>
  <keyword>HSCT</keyword>
  <keyword>BMT</keyword>
  <keyword>CliniMACS</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Severe Combined Immunodeficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
