<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="18456">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02079610</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-013-00</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02079610</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Amygdala Neurofeedback on Depressive Symptoms and Processing Biases</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Amygdala Neurofeedback on Depressive Symptoms and Processing Biases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Laureate Institute for Brain Research, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Laureate Institute for Brain Research, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether upregulating the left amygdala during
      positive autobiographical memory recall via real time functional magnetic resonance imaging
      neurofeedback will lead to an improvement in clinician administered ratings of depressive
      symptoms. The investigators predict that patients with major depressive disorder receiving
      left amygdala neurofeedback will increase their amygdala response during positive
      autobiographical memory recall compared to those receiving control feedback from a region
      not involved in emotional processing and that this ability will be associated with
      clinically significant improvement.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Major depressive disorder (MDD) is the leading cause of years lived with disability
      worldwide. Traditional pharmacological and/or psychological interventions are ineffective in
      up to one-half of patients, and treatments (such as electroconvulsive therapy, vagus nerve
      stimulation, and deep brain stimulation) available for severely ill patients who do not
      respond to standard interventions are invasive, and associated with potentially significant
      side effects. Therefore, there is a need to explore and develop novel non-invasive
      treatments.

      One such non-invasive method is real-time functional magnetic resonance imaging
      neurofeedback (rtfMRI-nf), which allows a person to see and regulate the fMRI signal from
      his or her own brain. Emerging evidence suggests rtfMRI-nf has clinical utility in reducing
      symptoms of chronic pain, tinnitus, and Parkinson's disease. The goal of the current study
      is to leverage recent advances in rtfMRI-nf to determine whether this procedure can be
      adapted as treatment for MDD. While amygdala activity is exaggerated in response to negative
      stimuli in MDD, evidence further suggests that the amygdala response to positive stimuli is
      attenuated in MDD and normalizes with remission. Therefore, the target for our rtfMRI-nf
      procedure is the left amygdala. Participants will be randomly assigned to receive rtfMRI-nf
      from either the left amygdala or the left horizontal segment of the intraparietal sulcus
      (HIPS; a region not involved in emotional processing) and to increase the activity within
      that region to a target level by thinking of positive autobiographical memories. This
      neurofeedback condition will alternate with periods of rest and counting backwards in order
      to allow participants to disengage from memory contemplation. A final run without
      neurofeedback information will be included to determine whether participants can maintain
      the learned amygdala elevation during positive memory recall in the absence of
      neurofeedback. Participants will complete two sessions within a one-week period. Clinical
      ratings will be taken at the time of each scan to determine whether the amygdala rtfMRI-nf
      procedure results in improvement of depression symptoms, and changes within the emotional
      regulation network that occur with successful amygdala regulation will be examined.
      Furthermore, the investigators aim to determine whether the rtfMRI-nf procedure will alter
      assessments of emotional processing conducted within three days prior to, and following
      completion of, the rtfMRI-nf procedure.

      Specific Aim 1: In individuals with MDD, determine the degree to which rtfMRI-nf enhances
      voluntary control over neural activity in the amygdala, co-modulates other brain regions
      within the emotion regulation circuitry, and alters depressive symptom severity ratings.

        -  Hypothesis 1.1: MDD participants receiving rtfMRI-nf regarding blood oxygen-level
           dependent (BOLD) activity within their amygdala can learn to voluntarily regulate this
           activity in response to positive stimuli. MDD participants receiving rtfMRI-nf
           regarding left amygdala activity will demonstrate greater activity in this region while
           contemplating positive autobiographical memories (AMs) than MDD participants receiving
           rtfMRI-nf regarding BOLD activity in the left HIPS, a region not involved in emotion.

        -  Hypothesis 1.2: The investigators hypothesize enhancing control over the amygdala via
           rtfMRI-nf will increase connectivity strengths between the amygdala and prefrontal
           regions involved in modulating emotional behavior including the pregenual anterior
           cingulate cortex and ventromedial prefrontal cortex.

        -  Hypothesis 1.3: The investigators hypothesize participants showing the greatest
           enhancement of amygdala activity in response to rtfMRI-nf also will show the greatest
           improvement in depressive symptom severity ratings at the end of the study.

      Specific Aim 2: In MDD patients, determine the degree to which rtfMRI-nf from the amygdala
      restores a normative mood-congruent processing bias during the processing of emotionally
      valenced stimuli.

        -  Hypothesis 2.1:  During the performance of a backward masking task in which emotional
           faces are presented below conscious awareness, the investigators hypothesize MDD
           participants will initially show a processing bias toward negative stimuli in the
           amygdala that will reverse to a processing bias toward positive stimuli in participants
           receiving active vs HIPS rtfMRI-nf

        -  Hypothesis 2.2: The investigators hypothesize that MDD patients will initially show a
           mood-congruent processing bias toward negative stimuli on the P1Vital Emotional Test
           Battery that will reverse to a bias toward positive stimuli following amygdala (vs
           HIPS) rtfMRI-nf.

      Results from this project will lead to new insights into the plastic neurobiological
      mechanisms that govern recovery from MDD and promote novel, non-invasive approaches to MDD
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale at 2 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Depression symptom severity rating scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Beck Depression Inventory at 2 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Depression symptom severity rating scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression at 2 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Depression symptom severity rating scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Profile of Mood States at 2 hours (following 1 rtfMRI-nf session)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 2 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Transient mood states rating scale</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline State-Trait Anxiety Inventory at 2 hours (following 1 rtfMRI-nf session)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 2 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>rating scale to measure transient and characteristic anxiety levels</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>real-time fMRI neurofeedback: Amygdala</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Amygdala neurofeedback - attempt to upregulate the left amygdala during positive autobiographical memory recall via real time fMRI neurofeedback from the amygdala. Two sessions will be performed one week apart.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>real-time fMRI neurofeedback: HIPS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>HIPS neurofeedback - attempt to upregulate the left horizontal segment of the intraparietal sulcus (HIPS), a region not involved in emotional processing, during positive autobiographical memory recall via real time fMRI neurofeedback from the HIPS. Two sessions will be performed one week apart.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>real-time fMRI neurofeedback: Amygdala</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants are shown activity from their left amygdala in real time and are instructed to increase the level of activity in that region by thinking of positive autobiographical memories.</description>
    <arm_group_label>real-time fMRI neurofeedback: Amygdala</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>real-time fMRI neurofeedback: HIPS</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants are shown activity from their left horizontal segment of the intraparietal sulcus in real time and are instructed to increase the level of activity in that region by thinking of positive autobiographical memories.</description>
    <arm_group_label>real-time fMRI neurofeedback: HIPS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  clinical diagnosis of major depressive disorder

          -  right handed

          -  adult aged 18-55

          -  currently depressed

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  clinically significant or unstable cardiovascular, pulmonary, endocrine,
             neurological, gastrointestinal illness or unstable medical disorder

          -  met Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-IV) criteria for
             alcohol and/or substance abuse or substance dependence (other than nicotine) within
             12 months prior to screening

          -  endorse suicidal intent or have made a suicide attempt within the preceding three
             months

          -  history of traumatic brain injury

          -  inability to complete MRI scan due to claustrophobia or general MRI exclusions (e.g.,
             shrapnel inside body)

          -  current pregnancy or breast feeding

          -  a primary language other than English

          -  received psychotropic drugs for at least 3 weeks (8 weeks for fluoxetine) prior to
             scanning (Effective medications will not be discontinued for the purposes of the
             study)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kymberly D Young, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Laureate Institute for Brain Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kymberly D Young, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>918-502-5107</phone>
    <email>kyoung@laureateinstitute.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Laureate Institute for Brain Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tulsa</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>74136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Young</last_name>
      <email>kyoung@laureateinstitute.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kymberly D Young, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jerzy Bodurka, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zotev V, Phillips R, Young KD, Drevets WC, Bodurka J. Prefrontal control of the amygdala during real-time fMRI neurofeedback training of emotion regulation. PLoS One. 2013 Nov 6;8(11):e79184. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0079184. eCollection 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>24223175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zotev V, Krueger F, Phillips R, Alvarez RP, Simmons WK, Bellgowan P, Drevets WC, Bodurka J. Self-regulation of amygdala activation using real-time FMRI neurofeedback. PLoS One. 2011;6(9):e24522. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0024522. Epub 2011 Sep 8.</citation>
    <PMID>21931738</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young KD, Zotev V, Phillips R, Misaki M, Yuan H, Drevets WC, Bodurka J. Real-time FMRI neurofeedback training of amygdala activity in patients with major depressive disorder. PLoS One. 2014 Feb 11;9(2):e88785. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0088785. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24523939</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 4, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurofeedback</keyword>
  <keyword>Amygdala</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
