<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="124204">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01668173</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-076</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01668173</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>HSP90 Inhibitor, AUY922, in Patients With Primary Myelofibrosis (PMF), Post-Polycythemia Vera Myelofibrosis (Post-PV MF), Post-Essential Thrombocythemia Myelofibrosis (Post-ET MF), and Refractory PV/ET</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of the HSP90 Inhibitor, AUY922, in Patients With Primary Myelofibrosis (PMF), Post-Polycythemia Vera Myelofibrosis (Post-PV MF), Post-Essential Thrombocythemia Myelofibrosis (Post-ET MF), and Refractory PV/ET</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test a new drug called AUY922. AUY922 is not FDA-approved.
      AUY922 is a new kind of drug that attacks a protein called HSP90. HSP90 is found in both
      normal and cancer cells, but the investigators think it is more important in cancer cells.

      This study will see if AUY922 helps people with myelofibrosis, essential thrombocythemia and
      polycythemia vera. This study will also see if AUY922 is safe in people with myelofibrosis,
      essential thrombocythemia and polycythemia vera. It will find out what effects, good and/or
      bad, AUY922 has on the patient and the disease. The researchers hope that this study will
      help them to find better treatments for primary myelofibrosis, essential thrombocythemia and
      polycythemia vera.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint is overall response rate defined as the rate of complete response, partial response and clinical improvement by six months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>safety</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>and tolerability of AUY922 in patients with myeloproliferative neoplasms. Adverse events will be assessed according to the Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.02.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pharmacodynamics of AUY922</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>via measurement of Hsp90, downstream targets of JAK2 (P-STAT3, P-STAT5, P-MAPK), client proteins of Hsp90 (AKT, Raf-1, EGFR, and HER2) by Western blot and flow cytometry. These will be serially compared from the evaluation at baseline. Peripheral blood and bone marrow aspirate samples from pretreatment and post-treatment will be assessed for the above proteins to assess the on-target effect of the AUY922.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Myeloproliferative Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AUY922</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is an open-label phase II trial to assess the efficacy of the HSP90 inhibitor, AUY922, in patients with PMF, post-PV MF, post-ET MF, and with PV/ET who are refractory to hydroxyurea, phlebotomy or anagrelide.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AUY922</intervention_name>
    <description>AUY922 will be administered as an intravenous infusion over 60 minutes, on a once weekly schedule. A cycle on study will be defined as 28 days. The dose to be studied are 70 mg/m2 and 55 mg/m2 if DLTs are identified in the first 3-6 patients. The same schedule of administration will be used for all patients in this trial.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AUY922</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Eligible patients must have myeloproliferative neoplasms, specifically, primary
             myelofibrosis (PMF), post polycythemia vera myelofibrosis (post-PV MF), post
             essential thrombocythemia myelofibrosis (post-ET MF), and PV/ET that are refractory
             to hydroxyurea, phlebotomy and anagrelide or not a candidate for standard therapies.

          -  ≥ 18 years of age

          -  ECOG performance status of 0-2

          -  Acceptable pre-study organ function during screening as defined as:

        Hematologic:

          -  Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) ≥1.5x109/L

          -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) ≥ 8 g/dl (may be supported with transfusion)

          -  Platelets (plt) ≥50x10^9/L

        Biochemistry:

          -  Potassium within normal limits

          -  Total calcium (corrected for serum albumin) and phosphorus within normal limits

          -  Magnesium above LLN or correctable with supplements Liver and Kidney Functions

          -  AST/SGOT and ALT/SGPT ≤ 1.5 x Upper Limit of Normal (ULN) if AP &gt; 2.5 ULN

          -  Serum bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x ULN

          -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN or 24-hour clearance ≥ 50 ml/min

          -  Negative serum pregnancy test. The serum pregnancy test must be obtained prior to the
             first administration of AUY922 (≤ 72 hours prior to dosing) in all pre-menopausal
             women and women &lt;2 years after the onset of menopause

          -  Patients who previously received JAK2 inhibitors will be eligible as long as they
             have been off the drug for more than 4 weeks.

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Requiring ongoing therapy with either G- or GM-CSF, or long-acting versions of these
             molecules

          -  Active medical condition such as infection or cancer that is actively requiring
             treatment.

          -  Unresolved diarrhea ≥ CTCAE (v4.02) grade 1

          -  Prior anti-neoplastic treatment with any HSP90 or HDAC inhibitor compound

          -  Patients who have undergone any major surgery ≤ 2 weeks prior to starting study drug
             or have not recovered from the side effects of such therapy.

          -  Patient must be ≥ 4 weeks since last chemotherapy or treatment with another systemic
             anticancer agent with the exception of hydroxyurea. Hydroxyurea must be discontinued
             at least 48 hours prior to the initiation of AUY922. Patients must have recovered
             (CTC ≤ 1) from acute toxicities of any previous therapy (with the exception of
             alopecia).

          -  Active anticoagulation with warfarin.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women

          -  Fertile women of childbearing potential (WCBP) not using double-barrier methods of
             contraception (abstinence, oral contraceptives, intrauterine device or barrier method
             of contraception in conjunction with spermicidal jelly, or surgically sterile). Male
             patients whose partners are WCBP not using double-barrier methods of contraception.

        Impaired cardiac function, including any one of the following:

          -  History (or family history) of long QT syndrome

          -  Mean QTc ≥ 450 msec on baseline ECG

          -  History of clinically manifested ischemic heart disease (including myocardial
             infarction, stable or unstable angina pectoris, coronary arteriography or cardiac
             stress testing/imaging with findings consistent with infarction or clinically
             significant coronary occlusion) ≤ 6 months prior to study start

          -  History of heart failure or left ventricular (LV) dysfunction (LVEF ≤ 45%) by MUGA or
             ECHO

          -  Clinically significant ECG abnormalities including 1 or more of the following: left
             bundle branch block (LBBB), right bundle branch block (RBBB) with left anterior
             hemiblock (LAHB). ST segment elevation or depression &gt; 1mm, or 2nd (Mobitz II), or
             3rd degree AV block.

        History or presence of atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter or ventricular arrhythmias
        including ventricular tachycardia or Torsades de Pointes

          -  Other clinically significant heart disease (e.g. congestive heart failure,
             uncontrolled hypertension, history of labile hypertension, or history of poor
             compliance with an antihypertensive regimen)

          -  Clinically significant resting bradycardia (&lt; 50 beats per minute)

          -  Patients who are currently receiving treatment with any medication which has a
             relative risk of prolonging the QTcF interval or inducing Torsades de Pointes and
             cannot be switched or discontinued to an alternative drug prior to commencing AUY922.

          -  Obligate use of a cardiac pacemaker
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raajit Rampal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Raajit Rampal, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-2194</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ross Levine, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-888-2767</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Raajit Rampal, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-2194</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ross Levine, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-2767</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 13, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HSP90 Inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>AUY922</keyword>
  <keyword>12-076</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Primary Myelofibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myeloproliferative Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polycythemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polycythemia Vera</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombocythemia, Essential</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombocytosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
