<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="147928">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01830387</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00041869</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01830387</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparative Study of Polymetric Clips (Hem-o-Lok) Versus Historical Endoscopic Staplers for Laparoscopic Appendectomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparative Study of Polymetric Clips (Hem-o-Lok) Versus Historical Endoscopic Staplers for Laparoscopic Appendectomy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the outcomes of appendectomy performed with
      polymetric clips (Hem-o-lok速) versus endoscopic staplers. The hypothesis is that the use of
      polymetric clips for ligation of the appendix will result in decreased operative cost with
      no change in morbidity when compared to endoscopic staplers. Eligibility will include all
      patients 18 years or older that are scheduled for laparoscopic appendectomy because of a
      diagnosis of appendicitis. In conducted trials the risks associated with the use of
      Hem-o-lok速 for ligation of the appendix is negligible compared to other standard ligation
      techniques including endoscopic staplers and endoloop. The study team does not perceive any
      additional risk to study participants beyond the risks associated with laparoscopic
      appendectomy. The average length of the operation is one and a half hours. Categorical
      variables will be compared using a Chi-square analysis, while continuous variables will be
      analyzed using Student's t-test. A statistician with the department has reviewed and
      approved the &quot;Data Analysis &amp; Statistical Considerations.&quot;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Subjects will be followed for the duration of their hopsital stay, an expected average of 2-3 days.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Charts will be reviewed to calculate the number of days the subject was in the hospital. Clinical and financial outcomes of subjects enrolled for laparoscopic appendectomy using Hem-o-Lok will be compared to a historical (retrospective) cohort of patients who underwent appendectomy using endoscopic staplers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total Hospital Charges</measure>
    <time_frame>Financial data will be gathered for the duration of the subjects hospital stay, an expected average of 2-3 days.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Data will be gathered on the expense of the subjects hospital stay from admission, surgery, to discharge. Clinical and financial outcomes of subjects enrolled for laparoscopic appendectomy using Hem-o-Lok will be compared to a historical (retrospective) cohort of patients who underwent appendectomy using endoscopic staplers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Operative time</measure>
    <time_frame>Length of operation is approximately one and a half hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subject's chart will be reviewed to gather operative start and stop times. Clinical and financial outcomes of subjects enrolled for laparoscopic appendectomy using Hem-o-Lok will be compared to a historical (retrospective) cohort of patients who underwent appendectomy using endoscopic staplers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of Surgical Outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediatly Postoperative to 30 days postoperative</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measures of surgical outcomes will be compared between the two procedures including rates of postoperative appendiceal stump dehiscence, hemorrhage, pneumonia, urinary tract infection, myocardial infarction, pulmonary embolism, deep vein thrombosis, and death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Appendicitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Polymetric clips</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study team will prospectively enroll subjects with a diagnosis of appendicitis who are scheduled for laparoscopic appendectomy to have Hem-o-Lok速 clips used for closure of the appendiceal stump. All subjects enrolled in the study will have their medical chart reviewed from consent to 30 days post operatively.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Endoscopic Staplers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study team will retrospectively identify patients who have undergone laparoscopic appendectomy during a one year time span by performing a database search. The operative notes will be reviewed for these patients to select patients who underwent ligation of the appendix with an endoscopic stapler.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Polymetric clips</intervention_name>
    <description>The study team will prospectively enroll subjects with a diagnosis of appendicitis who are scheduled for laparoscopic appendectomy to have Hem-o-Lok速 clips used for closure of the appendiceal stump.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Polymetric clips</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endoscopic Staplers</intervention_name>
    <description>The study team will retrospectively identify patients who have undergone laparoscopic appendectomy by performing a database search. The operative notes will be reviewed for these patients to select patients who underwent ligation of the appendix with an endoscopic stapler.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Endoscopic Staplers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 18 years of age or older

          2. scheduled to undergo a laparoscopic appendectomy because of a diagnosis of
             appendicitis based on clinical history or radiographic imaging.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Less than 18 years of age

          2. Signs of appendiceal rupture or abcess on preoperative imaging studies (CT or
             ultrasound)

          3. Inability to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chan Park, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke Center for Metabolic and Weight Loss Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27704</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 16, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 3, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Polymetric Clips (Hem-o-Lok)</keyword>
  <keyword>Laparoscopic Appendectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Endoscopic Staplers</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Appendicitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
