<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="79113">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02139046</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FEB-XR_301</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1152-4040</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02139046</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety of Extended Release and Immediate Release Febuxostat in Participants With Gout</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 3, Randomized, Double Blind, Multicenter, Placebo Controlled Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Febuxostat 40 mg XR, 80 mg XR, 40 mg IR and 80 mg IR in Subjects With Gout</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy and safety of febuxostat 40 mg
      extended release (XR) and 80 mg XR in comparison with febuxostat 40 mg immediate release
      (IR) and 80 mg IR, respectively, in participants with gout.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The drug being tested in this study is called febuxostat. Febuxostat is being tested to
      decrease and maintain serum urate in people who have gout. This study will look at serum
      urate levels in people who take febuxostat extended release (XR) capsules compared to
      febuxostat immediate release (IR) capsules and placebo.

      The study will enroll approximately 1750 patients. Participants will be randomly assigned
      (by chance) to one of the five treatment groups—which will remain undisclosed to the patient
      and study doctor during the study (unless there is an urgent medical need):

        -  Febuxostat 40 mg XR

        -  Febuxostat 80 mg XR

        -  Febuxostat 40 mg IR

        -  Febuxostat 80 mg IR

        -  Placebo (dummy inactive pill) - this is a tablet that looks like the study drug but has
           no active ingredient.

      All participants will be asked to take one capsule at the same time each day throughout the
      study, and will be asked to call an interactive voice response system any time they are
      having a gout flare up. In addition to study medication, participants will also take 0.6 mg
      of colchicine every day or every other day, or naproxen 250 mg twice a day and lansoprazole
      15 mg once a day to prevent gout flare ups.

      This multi-centre trial will be conducted in the United States. The overall time to
      participate in this study is up to approximately 4 months and participants will make up to 7
      visits to the clinic.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Serum Urate &lt;5.0 mg/dL at Month 3</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with at Least One Gout Flare Requiring Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Month 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Serum Urate &lt;6.0 mg/dL at Month 3</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1750</enrollment>
  <condition>Gout</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 40 mg IR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Febuxostat 40 mg Immediate Release (IR) over-encapsulated tablet, orally, once daily, and colchicine 0.6 mg tablet, orally, every day (for participants with estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) ≥ 60 mL/min) or every other day (if eGFR ≥ 15 - ≤ 59 mL/min), or, alternatively, if colchicine is not tolerated and the subject's eGFR is ≥ 50 mL/min, naproxen 250 mg tablets, orally, twice a day and lansoprazole 15 mg capsule, orally once daily, for 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 80 mg IR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Febuxostat 80 mg IR over-encapsulated tablet, orally, once daily, and colchicine 0.6 mg tablet, orally, every day or every other day, or, alternatively, if colchicine is not tolerated and the subject's eGFR is ≥ 50 mL/min, naproxen 250 mg tablets, orally, twice a day and lansoprazole 15 mg capsule, orally once daily, for 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 40 mg XR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Febuxostat 40 mg Extended Release (XR) over-encapsulated capsule, orally, once daily, and colchicine 0.6 mg tablet, orally, every day or every other day, or, alternatively, if colchicine is not tolerated and the subject's eGFR is ≥ 50 mL/min, naproxen 250 mg tablets, orally, twice a day and lansoprazole 15 mg capsule, orally once daily, for 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 80 mg XR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Febuxostat 80 mg XR over-encapsulated capsule, orally, once daily, and colchicine 0.6 mg tablet, orally, every day or every other day, or,  alternatively, if colchicine is not tolerated and the subject's eGFR is ≥ 50 mL/min,naproxen 250 mg tablets, orally, twice a day and lansoprazole 15 mg capsule, orally once daily, for 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Febuxostat placebo-matching capsule, orally, once daily, and colchicine 0.6 mg tablet, orally, every day or every other day, or, alternatively, if colchicine is not tolerated and the subject's eGFR is ≥ 50 mL/min, naproxen 250 mg tablets, orally, twice a day and lansoprazole 15 mg capsule, orally once daily, for 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Febuxostat IR</intervention_name>
    <description>Febuxostat IR over-encapsulated tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 40 mg IR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 80 mg IR</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Uloric</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Febuxostat XR</intervention_name>
    <description>Febuxostat XR over-encapsulated capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 40 mg XR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 80 mg XR</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Uloric</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Febuxostat placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Febuxostat placebo-matching capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Colchicine</intervention_name>
    <description>Colchicine tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 40 mg IR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 80 mg IR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 40 mg XR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 80 mg XR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Naproxen</intervention_name>
    <description>Naproxen tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 40 mg IR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 80 mg IR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 40 mg XR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 80 mg XR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lansoprazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Lansoprazole capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 40 mg IR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 80 mg IR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 40 mg XR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Febuxostat 80 mg XR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. In the opinion of the investigator, the participant is capable of understanding and
             complying with protocol requirements.

          2. The participant or, when applicable, the participant's legally acceptable
             representative signs and dates a written, informed consent form and any required
             privacy authorization prior to the initiation of any study procedure.

          3. Has a history or presence of gout defined as having one or more of the American
             Rheumatism Association (ARA) criteria for the diagnosis of gout:

               1. A tophus proven to contain urate crystals by chemical or polarized light
                  microscopic means, AND/OR;

               2. Characteristic urate crystals in the joint fluid, AND/OR;

               3. History of at least 6 of the following clinical, laboratory, and x-ray
                  phenomena:

             i. more than one attack of acute arthritis, ii. maximum inflammation developed within
             1 day, iii. monoarticular arthritis, iv. redness observed over joints, v. first
             metatarsophalangeal joint painful or swollen, vi. unilateral first
             metatarsophalangeal joint attack, vii. unilateral tarsal joint attack, viii. tophus
             (proven or suspected), ix. Hyperuricemia, x. asymmetric swelling within a joint on
             x-ray, xi. subcortical cysts without erosions on x-ray, xii. joint fluid culture
             negative for organisms during attack.

          4. Is male or female at least 18 years of age, inclusive.

          5. A female participant of childbearing potential who is sexually active with a
             nonsterilized male partner agrees to use routinely adequate contraception from
             signing of informed consent throughout the duration of the study.

          6. Have a serum urate (sUA) level ≥8.0 mg/dL at the Day -4 Visit or at the retest visit.

          7. Has an estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate (eGRF) ≥15 mL/min using the Modification
             of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) formula at the Screening visit (Day -21 for
             participants on urate lowering therapy (ULT) and Day -4 for participants not on ULT)
             or at the retest visit.

          8. Has at least one gout flare within 12 months prior to Screening visit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has received any investigational compound within 30 days prior to Screening.

          2. Is an immediate family member, study site employee, or is in a dependant relationship
             with a study site employee who is involved in conduct of this study (eg, spouse,
             parent, child, sibling) or may consent under duress.

          3. Is breastfeeding or pregnant.

          4. Has secondary hyperuricemia (eg, due to myeloproliferative disorder).

          5. Has a history of xanthinuria.

          6. Has received ULT (ie, allopurinol, probenecid, etc.) within 20 days prior to Day
             1/Randomization Visit.

          7. Has a known hypersensitivity to febuxostat or any components of their formulation;
             has a known hypersensitivity to naproxen, any other nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory
             drug (NSAID), aspirin, lansoprazole, colchicine or any components in their
             formulation.

          8. Has active peptic ulcer disease.

          9. Has a history of cancer (other than basal cell carcinoma of the skin) within 5 years
             prior to the Screening Visit.

         10. Has alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) values &gt;2 x
             the upper limit of normal (ULN).

         11. Has rheumatoid arthritis which requires treatment.

         12. Has a significant medical condition and/or conditions that would interfere with the
             treatment, safety, or compliance with the protocol.

         13. Has experienced a myocardial infarction (MI), stroke, hospitalized unstable angina,
             cardiac or cerebrovascular revascularization procedure or hospitalized transient
             ischemic attack (TIA) - except in participants who have severe renal impairment.

         14. Participants with severe renal impairment had a MI or stroke within 90 days prior to
             initial screening visit or has a MI or stroke during the screening period prior to
             Day 1/Randomization Visit.

         15. Participant consumes &gt;14 alcoholic beverages/week. Has a history of alcoholism or
             illicit drug abuse within 5 years.

         16. Has participated in another investigational study within the 30 days prior to the
             Screening Visit.

         17. Has a known history of infection with hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or human
             immunodeficiency virus.

         18. Is required to take excluded medications.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director Clinical Science</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Takeda Study Registration Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>800-778-2860</phone>
    <email>medicalinformation@tpna.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 13, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gout</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Naproxen</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colchicine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Febuxostat</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lansoprazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
