<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40339">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02097823</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1401283326</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02097823</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study of Olanzapine and Aprepitant to Prevent Nausea and Vomiting in Children Receiving Chemotherapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study Comparing Olanzapine and Aprepitant for the Prevention of Chemotherapy Induced Nausea and Vomiting in Pediatric Patients Receiving Highly Emetogenic Chemotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the feasibility of a larger trial comparing
      olanzapine and aprepitant and to obtain preliminary data on the effectiveness of these two
      medications to treat nausea and vomiting in children receiving chemotherapy.  Children
      receiving 2 cycles of chemotherapy with a high risk of causing nausea and vomiting will
      receive olanzapine in one cycle and aprepitant in another cycle.  Children will be
      randomized to see which medicine they receive first.  The investigators will record the
      number of extra medications used for nausea, the number of times a child vomits, and the
      amount of nausea the child feels each day.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a pilot study, designed as a randomized, crossover study comparing olanzapine
      and aprepitant in pediatric oncology patients receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy
      (HEC).  The primary objective is to determine the feasibility of recruitment and data
      collection for conducting a larger trial aimed at comparing olanzapine and aprepitant as
      antiemetic regimens and establishing efficacy of this regimens for pediatric patients
      receiving HEC.  Secondary objectives are to obtain preliminary data regarding the
      effectiveness of olanzapine and aprepitant as well as the tolerability of olanzapine in the
      pediatric oncology population.

      Each patient must be planned to undergo at least 2 cycles of the same cycle of HEC.  Each
      patient will be randomized to receive olanzapine or aprepitant in the first cycle of
      chemotherapy, and then will receive the other agent in a second cycle of chemotherapy.
      Patients will also receive ondansetron and dexamethasone with each cycle.  Patients with CNS
      tumors will not receive dexamethasone.  Response will be measured objectively recording
      number of emesis and use of breakthrough medications.  The medications chosen for
      breakthrough medications will be at the treating physicians discretion.  A complete response
      will be no episodes of emesis or use of breakthrough medications.  A partial response is one
      or less episodes of emesis and one or less use of breakthrough medications.  Nausea will be
      measured based on parent and patient scales and will be a separate measure, not included in
      the compete or partial response.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of recruitment and data collection.</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year after study opens, at the conclusion of data collection.  Participants will be followed during 2 cycles of chemotherapy, an expected average of 6 weeks.  Data will be collected over 5 days during each cycle.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Primary objective of this study is to determine the feasibility of recruitment and data collection for conducting a larger trial.  Recruitment and data collection will be feasible if at least 20 subjects can be recruited in 1 year and there is a 90% form completion rate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete Response in Overall Phase</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed during 2 cycles of chemotherapy, an expected average of 6 weeks.  Data will be collected over 5 days during each cycle.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This will measure what percentage of patients have a complete response (no emesis or use of breakthrough medications) in the overall phase (0-120 hours).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete Response in Acute Phase</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed during 2 cycles of chemotherapy, an expected average of 6 weeks.  Data will be collected over 5 days during each cycle.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This will measure what percentage of patients have a complete response (no emesis or use of breakthrough medications) in the acute phase (0-24 hours).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete Response in Delayed Phase</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed during 2 cycles of chemotherapy, an expected average of 6 weeks.  Data will be collected over 5 days during each cycle.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This will measure what percentage of patients have a complete response (no emesis or use of breakthrough medications) in the delayed phase (25-120 hours).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Good control of nausea</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed during 2 cycles of chemotherapy, an expected average of 6 weeks.  Data will be collected over 5 days during each cycle.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Good control of nausea will be ratings &lt;25 on visual analog scale by parents and &lt;2 on baxter retching faces scale by patients.  Will look at the proportions of patients with good control of nausea.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing, throughout the study.  Will be fully evaluated in approximately 1 year, at the conclusion of data collection.  Each patient will be followed during 2 cycles of chemotherapy, an expected average of 6 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Olanzapine will be considered tolerable if less than 10% of patients experience a grade III or IV adverse event attributable to olanzapine.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Oral intake of patients during chemotherapy cycles</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed during 2 cycles of chemotherapy, an expected average of 6 weeks.  Data will be collected over 5 days during each cycle.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will record total oral intake of patients receiving chemotherapy while inpatient.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients requiring IV fluid hydration at home</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed during 2 cycles of chemotherapy, an expected average of 6 weeks.  Data will be collected over 5 days during each cycle.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Chemotherapy Induced Nausea and Vomiting</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aprepitant First, Olanzapine Second</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Will receive aprepitant (weight based dose, see below) in first cycle of chemotherapy and olanzapine (weight based dose, see below) in the second cycle of chemotherapy.  All doses will be given starting 30 minutes before chemotherapy on day 1.
Olanzapine dosing:
&gt;60kg - 10mg orally daily for 4 doses 40-59.9kg - 5mg orally daily for 4 doses 20-39.9kg - 2.5mg orally daily for 4 doses &lt;20kg - 1.25mg orally daily for 4 doses
Aprepitant dosing:
&gt;40kg - 125mg orally on day 1, then 80mg orally daily on days 2,3 35-39.9kg - 80mg orally daily for 3 doses 20-34.9kg - 40mg orally daily for 3 doses &lt;20kg - 1.5-2mg/kg orally daily for 3 doses</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Olanzapine First, Aprepitant Second</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Will receive olanzapine (weight based dose, see below) in first cycle of chemotherapy and aprepitant (weight based dose, see below) in the second cycle of chemotherapy.  All doses will be given starting 30 minutes before chemotherapy on day 1.
Olanzapine dosing:
&gt;60kg - 10mg orally daily for 4 doses 40-59.9kg - 5mg orally daily for 4 doses 20-39.9kg - 2.5mg orally daily for 4 doses &lt;20kg - 1.25mg orally daily for 4 doses
Aprepitant dosing:
&gt;40kg - 125mg orally on day 1, then 80mg orally daily on days 2,3 35-39.9kg - 80mg orally daily for 3 doses 20-34.9kg - 40mg orally daily for 3 doses &lt;20kg - 1.5-2mg/kg orally daily for 3 doses</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Olanzapine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Aprepitant First, Olanzapine Second</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Olanzapine First, Aprepitant Second</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>zyprexa</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aprepitant</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Aprepitant First, Olanzapine Second</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Olanzapine First, Aprepitant Second</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>emend</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age greater than 4 years and less than 21 years

          -  patient will receive at least two cycles of the same regimen of highly emetogenic
             chemotherapy

          -  adequate liver function - defined as total bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 times
             the upper limit of normal for age and AST/ALT less than or equal to upper limit of
             normal for age

          -  adequate kidney function - defined as creatinine clearance or GFR greater than or
             equal to 70mL/min/1.73m2 or a serum creatinine based on age/gender as follows:
             Maximum serum creatinine

               -  2- &lt;6 years:       Male &amp; Female   0.8

               -  6- &lt;10 years:     Male &amp; Female   1

               -  10- &lt;13 years:   Male &amp; Female  1.2

               -  13- &lt;16 years:   Male 1.5   Female 1.4

               -  &gt;16 years:          Male 1.7    Female 1.4

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  known QTc prolongation or other cardiac arrhythmia

          -  current treatment with another antipsychotic (for example: risperidone, quetiapine,
             clozapine)

          -  prior adverse reaction to either olanzapine or aprepitant

          -  the planned two cycles of chemotherapy include ifosfamide (a patient may receive
             ifosfamide as a part of his/her overall treatment plan but not during study cycles)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Holly Knoderer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Catherine Long, MD</last_name>
    <phone>317-944-8784</phone>
    <email>cathlong@iupui.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Riley Hospital for Children at Indiana University Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Catherine Long, MD</last_name>
      <phone>317-944-8784</phone>
      <email>cathlong@iupui.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Catherine Long, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 21, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>olanzapine</keyword>
  <keyword>Nausea and vomiting</keyword>
  <keyword>aprepitant</keyword>
  <keyword>pediatrics</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Nausea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vomiting</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Olanzapine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aprepitant</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
