<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="122530">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01687972</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00043795</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01687972</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>INSORB Versus Subcuticular Sutures at Cesarean Section</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial of Skin Closure at Cesarean Section: INSORB Absorbable Staples Versus Subcuticular Sutures</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Office of Human Subjects Research</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study is a randomized controlled trial with two arms.  All patients admitted to
      Labor and Delivery at Johns Hopkins Hospital for delivery will be approached and offered
      entry into our study.  Once the patient is enrolled, and if she undergoes a cesarean
      section, the patient will be randomized at time of cesarean section to receive skin closure
      by either the INSORB™ absorbable staples or subcuticular closure using Biosyn™ suture as is
      the standard practice.  Both an observer scar assessment score (OSAS) and patient scar
      assessment score (PSAS) will be obtained during this visit.  The patient will then be
      contacted by telephone by a study member 3 months after her surgery for a brief survey (same
      PSAS survey) assessing her satisfaction with the resulting scar.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study is a randomized controlled trial with two arms.  All patients admitted to
      Labor and Delivery at Johns Hopkins Hospital for delivery will be approached and offered
      entry into our study during the routine consent process which includes consent for cesarean
      section that occurs with each patient.  Once the patient is enrolled, and if she undergoes a
      cesarean section, the patient will be randomized at time of cesarean section to receive skin
      closure by either the INSORB™ absorbable staples or subcuticular closure using  Biosyn™
      suture as is the standard practice. The size of the suture (3-0 vs. 4-0) and type of needle
      used to sew is at the discretion of the surgeon.  The indications for and performance of the
      cesarean section will remain standard care by the Obstetrical team and the patient's
      participation in this study will have no impact whatsoever on the obstetrical course of the
      patient.  The only additional procedure that will be asked of the obstetrical team
      performing the cesarean section is to measure and close the subcutaneous tissue if the depth
      from the skin edge to the transversalis fascia is greater than 2cm as this has been shown to
      decrease subsequent seroma formation and wound disruption.  The dressing will be
      standardized as follows: a folded ABD pad will be placed in a sterile fashion directly over
      the incision and foam tape will be applied to provide a &quot;pressure dressing.&quot;  The dressing
      will be removed on post-operative day #2.

      The patient's postoperative course will remain unchanged and her discharge will be at the
      discretion of her obstetrical providers.  On post-operative day #3, a picture of the
      incision will be taken with the patient's identifying number adjacent to the picture and the
      patient will be asked to complete a brief survey asking about post-operative pain and scars
      (see included PSAS survey).  The patients will follow-up with her Obstetrician for her
      normal post-partum visit where another picture of the incision will be taken.  Both an
      observer scar assessment score (OSAS) and patient scar assessment score (PSAS) will be
      obtained during this visit.  The patient will then be contacted by telephone by a study
      member 3 months after her surgery for a brief survey (same PSAS survey) assessing her
      satisfaction with the resulting scar.  At this point, the patient's participation in the
      study will end.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite wound complication rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Wound separation, seroma or hematoma requiring wound opening or antibiotics, wound infection requiring antibiotics or opening of incision, unexpected visits to doctor or hospital for wound issues</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction with scar</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessed using the Patient scar assessment score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient pain scale</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective scar score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>assessed using the Objective scare score scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Closure time</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">450</enrollment>
  <condition>Cesarean Section</condition>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sutures</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Insorb Staples</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Insorb absorbable staples</intervention_name>
    <description>Placement of Insorb absorbable staples at cesarean section</description>
    <arm_group_label>Insorb Staples</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Absorbable sutures</intervention_name>
    <description>placement of absorbable sutures at cesarean section</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sutures</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  cesarean section via transverse skin incision informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  vertical skin incision
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christopher P Wayock, MD</last_name>
    <phone>5167178904</phone>
    <email>cwayock1@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20794</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christopher P Wayock</last_name>
      <phone>516-717-8904</phone>
      <email>cwayock1@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Janice Henderson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher P Wayock, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chelmow D, Rodriguez EJ, Sabatini MM. Suture closure of subcutaneous fat and wound disruption after cesarean delivery: a meta-analysis. Obstet Gynecol. 2004 May;103(5 Pt 1):974-80.</citation>
    <PMID>15121573</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basha SL, Rochon ML, Quiñones JN, Coassolo KM, Rust OA, Smulian JC. Randomized controlled trial of wound complication rates of subcuticular suture vs staples for skin closure at cesarean delivery. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2010 Sep;203(3):285.e1-8.</citation>
    <PMID>20816153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cromi A, Ghezzi F, Gottardi A, Cherubino M, Uccella S, Valdatta L. Cosmetic outcomes of various skin closure methods following cesarean delivery: a randomized trial. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2010 Jul;203(1):36.e1-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2010.02.001. Epub 2010 Apr 24.</citation>
    <PMID>20417924</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gaertner I, Burkhardt T, Beinder E. Scar appearance of different skin and subcutaneous tissue closure techniques in caesarean section: a randomized study. Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol. 2008 May;138(1):29-33. Epub 2007 Sep 6.</citation>
    <PMID>17825472</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Couto RC, Pedrosa TM, Nogueira JM, Gomes DL, Neto MF, Rezende NA. Post-discharge surveillance and infection rates in obstetric patients. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 1998 Jun;61(3):227-31.</citation>
    <PMID>9688482</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Menacker F, Hamilton BE. Recent trends in cesarean delivery in the United States. NCHS Data Brief. 2010 Mar;(35):1-8.</citation>
    <PMID>20334736</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 14, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 9, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Janice Henderson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cesarean section</keyword>
  <keyword>insorb staples</keyword>
  <keyword>absorbable staples</keyword>
  <keyword>transverse skin incision</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
