<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="104404">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02151461</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NS-0100-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02151461</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose Comparisons of Leucine-Metformin Combinations on Blood Glucose Levels In Type 2 Diabetic Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Active-Controlled Study to Evaluate the Effect of Various Fixed-Dose Leucine and Metformin Combinations (NS-0100) Versus Standard Metformin Monotherapy on Glycemic Control in Subjects With Type 2 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NuSirt Biopharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NuSirt Biopharma</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to demonstrate that leucine in combination with a low does of
      metformin can serve as an adjunct to diet and exercise to improve blood glucose levels in
      type 2 diabetic subjects.  This study will compare three doses of a leucine-metformin
      combination to the standard metformin dose in controlling blood glucose levels in type 2
      diabetic patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, 4-week, active-controlled, double-blind study to evaluate the effect
      of various fixed-dose combinations of leucine and metformin compared to standard metformin
      monotherapy on glycemic control.  In this study, standard metformin therapy will be defined
      as 1000 g/day for Day 1 to Day 14 and then escalated to 1700 g/day for Day 15 to Day 28.
      Subjects meeting all inclusion criteria and no exclusion criteria will be randomized to one
      of four treatment arms.

      The primary objective of the study is to evaluate the change in fasting plasma glucose from
      Baseline (Day 1) to Week 4 (Day 28) in subjects receiving various fixed-dose combinations of
      leucine and metformin compared to standard metformin monotherapy.  Secondary objectives will
      also assess changes in baseline-corrected plasma glucose and insulin area under the
      concentration curves from baseline to day 28 and changes in insulin secretory rates as
      assessed during a 3-hour meal tolerance test.  Finally the effects of gastrointestinal
      symptoms will be assessed by subject questionnaires.

      The study will include a total of 3 periods: screening or washout of current diabetic
      monotherapy, a pre-treatment period to ensure subjects will be compliant, and a treatment
      period of 4 weeks, with the first dosing of medication on day 1 of the study.  Each day
      blood glucose readings will be measured and recorded by patients.  Three-hour standardized
      meal tests will be performed at Baseline (Day 1) and at Study Termination (Day 28).  In
      addition, two, 7-day continuous glucose assessments will be conducted, as well as two seven
      point glucose profiles.  Patients will also be asked about any gastrointestinal side effects
      they experience.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change In Fasting Plasma Glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Fasting plasma glucose levels will be measured in a variety of ways including; Standard fasting plasma glucose lab readings, seven point glucose profiles, and through continuous glucose monitoring.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gastrointestinal Effects</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Effects on gastrointestinal symptoms patients experienced by questions answered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Baseline-Corrected Plasma Glucose and Insulin Area Under The Concentration Curves</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Plasma blood glucose levels will be accessed through continuous glucose monitoring and through standard 3 hour meal tolerance tests.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Insulin Secretory Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Insulin secretory rates will be tested using standard 3 hour meal tolerance testing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Fasting Plasma Lipids</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Fasting plasmid lipids will be tested by standard lipid chemistry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in HbA1c</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>HbA1c will be examined through standard chemistry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in HOMA-IR</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>HOMA-IR will be evaluated through standard chemistry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change In 7-Point Glucose Profiles</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 7, Day 21, Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>7 point glucose profiles will be examined by obtaining plasma glucose levels at 7 different time points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change In Serial Blood Glucose Concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline,Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessed by continuous glucose monitoring</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will be monitored and asked about any adverse events or problems they encounter as a result of the study drug</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">102</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low Metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 capsules BID with each capsule containing 366.7 mg L-Leucine and 41.7 mg of metformin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mid Metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 capsules BID with each capsule containing 366.7 mg L-Leucine and 83.3 mg of metformin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High Metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 capsules BID with each capsule containing 366.7 mg L-Leucine and 166.7 mg of metformin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metformin Monotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 Capsules BID each containing 166.7 mg of metformin with dose escalation to 283.3 mg capsules BID (1,700 mg/Day) at Day 14.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>1100 mg L Leucine in combination with 125 mg of Metformin BID</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low Metformin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Metformin</other_name>
    <other_name>Leucine</other_name>
    <other_name>L-Leucine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>500 mg metformin BID until day 14 with dose escalation at day 14 to 850 mg metformin BID</description>
    <arm_group_label>Metformin Monotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Metformin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mid Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>1100 mg of Leucine in combination with 250 mg Metformin BID</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mid Metformin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Metformin</other_name>
    <other_name>Leucine</other_name>
    <other_name>L-Leucine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>1100 mg of Leucine in combination with 500 mg Metformin BID</description>
    <arm_group_label>High Metformin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Metformin</other_name>
    <other_name>Leucine</other_name>
    <other_name>L-Leucine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Over age 18 at study entry.

          -  Male, or female, if female, meets all of the following criteria:

          -  Not breastfeeding

          -  Post-menopausal or negative pregnancy test result (human chorionic gonadotropin, beta
             subunit [β- hCG]) at Screening (Visit 1) (not required for hysterectomized females)

          -  If of childbearing potential and sexually active, must practice and be willing to
             continue to practice appropriate birth control

          -  Is diagnosed with type 2 diabetes mellitus and either not adequately controlled by:
             diet and exercise alone or diet and exercise plus a single, first line treatment for
             type 2 diabetes.

          -  If treated with an oral anti-diabetes agent, be willing and able to withdraw from
             therapy for 4 weeks after the screening visit and prior to initiating study mediation
             at Baseline (Day 1/Visit 4).

          -  Be willing to avoid acetaminophen use for intervals up to 10 days as required for
             study procedures (see Section 4.6)

          -  Has a fasting plasma glucose ≥126 mg/dL to ≤220 mg/dL at Screening

          -  Has an HbA1c ≥7% to ≤8.5% at Screening

          -  Has a BMI ≤40 kg/m2

          -  Clinical laboratory tests (hematology, clinical chemistry, and urinalysis) either
             normal or abnormal but consistent with type 2 diabetes mellitus.

          -  Is able to read, understand, and sign the informed consent forms (ICF) and if
             applicable, an authorization to use and disclose protected health information form
             (consistent with health insurance portability and accountability act of 1996 [HIPAA]
             legislation), communicate with the investigator, and understand and comply with
             protocol requirements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinically significant renal dysfunction

          -  If using any of the following medications, has not been on a stable treatment regimen
             for a minimum of 4 weeks prior to screening:

        Lipid-lowering agents Anti-hypertensive medications Thyroid replacement therapy
        Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents

          -  Unable to perform self-blood glucose monitoring employing a glucose meter.

          -  History of active cardio- or cerebro-vascular disease with an event within the
             previous 6 months

          -  Gastrointestinal disorders

          -  Endocrine disorders other than type 2 diabetes

          -  Chronic infection

          -  Hepatic disease

          -  Neurological or psychiatric diseases

          -  History of other psychiatric disorders

          -  Has been treated (within the last month), is currently treated, or is expected to
             require or undergo treatment with; any anti-diabetes medications (other than as
             allowed by the inclusion criteria), oral or parenteral steroids.

          -  Participation in a weight loss program within the past 3 months.

          -  Weight change by more than 10 pounds during the past month.

          -  History of alcohol or substance abuse in the past 3 months or a positive screen for
             alcohol or drugs of abuse at screening.

          -  Has received any investigational drug within 3 months of Screening.

          -  Has donated blood within 3 months before Screening or is planning to donate blood
             during the study.

          -  Has known allergies or hypersensitivity to metformin or leucine

          -  Is employed, contracted or has an immediate family member directly affiliated with
             NuSirt Biopharma.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Orville G Kolterman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>NuSirt Biopharma</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Streling Research Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthew D Wenker, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Research South</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29407</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donald P Hurley, DO</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Diabetes, Endocrinology, and Metabolism</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kevin D Niswender, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Meharry Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37208</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John J Murray, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 28, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Type 2 Diabetes</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
