<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="28328">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01790516</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2010-439</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01790516</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Use of Pharmacogenetics to Select Erbitux or Cisplatin to Treat Head and Neck Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Prospective Clinical Trial to Use Pharmacogenetics (PGx) to Select Erbitux or Cisplatin to Treat Head and Neck Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Georgetown University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Georgetown University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is for patients with newly diagnosed head and neck cancer that cannot be removed
      by surgery.

      The purpose of this study is to determine the feasibility of using genetic variations in
      patients to select the right drug to treat head and neck cancer. Cisplatin and cetuximab
      (Erbitux)are both approved by the FDA to treat head and neck cancer in combination with
      radiation therapy. In this study the investigators will test whether genetic differences
      between patients can be used to pick which of these two drugs a patient should receive. All
      patients will have a blood sample drawn that will be tested for genetic differences. If
      patients have genetic differences that correlate with a better outcome from cisplatin they
      will receive cisplatin with radiation. If patients have genetic differences that do not
      correlate with a better outcome from cisplatin they will receive cetuximab with their
      radiation therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Treatment-naive patients with locally advanced, non-metastatic (Stage III to IVB) squamous
      cell carcinoma of the head and neck who are candidates for concurrent chemoradiotherapy as
      primary therapy with curative intent will be enrolled. Patients will be genotyped for
      germline variations at four SNP loci in three genes involved in DNA nucleotide excision
      repair (ERCC1, ERCC2, and XRCC1). Patients with 3 to 8 variants will receive cisplatin (Arm
      A). Patients with 2 or fewer variants will receive cetuximab (Arm B).

      The hypothesis of the study is that prospectively testing patients for variations in DNA
      repair enzymes to determine whether to use cisplatin or cetuximab in locally advanced head
      and neck squamous cell cancer is feasible.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    low accruals--2 patients were enrolled in over a year so study would never have been completed
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>May 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Feasibility is defined as follows:
Patients' genetic test results are returned within 72 hours for at least 16 patients
Genetic testing delays treatment initiation for less than 2 patients
Fewer than 2 patients withdraw from study after enrollment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2</enrollment>
  <condition>Head and Neck Squamous Cell Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cisplatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intensity modulated radiation with concurrent cisplatin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cetuximab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intensity modulated radiation therapy with concurrent cetuximab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>platinum plus radiation</intervention_name>
    <description>Cisplatin 100 mg/m2 during weeks 1,4, and 7 of radiation therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cisplatin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cispaltin</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinum</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cetuximab plus radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Cetuximab beginning at a dose of 400 mg/m2 the week before radiation commences and then 250 mg/m2 weekly during weeks 1 and 7 of radiation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cetuximab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Erbitux</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Biopsy proven squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck, including the oral
             cavity, oropharynx, hypopharynx, or larynx, but not including primary tumors of the
             nasopharynx, sinuses, or salivary glands.

          -  Locally advanced, Stage III to IVB disease, and a candidate for primary therapy using
             chemotherapy and radiation therapy with curative intent.

          -  Patients with a diagnosis of 'unknown primary' will be eligible if chemoradiotherapy
             is the primary modality of treatment

          -  No previous chemotherapy, radiation, or surgery for their diagnosis of head and neck
             cancer

          -  ECOG performance status &lt;/= 1

          -  Women of child-bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test within 30 hours
             before initiation of study drug dosing. Female subjects of reproductive potential
             must agree to avoid pregnancy throughout the study and for up to 3 months following
             discontinuation of study drug. Male subjects must agree to avoid conceiving a child
             throughout the study and for up to 3 months following discontinuation of study drug;

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;/= 8.0 gm/dL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;/= 1500

          -  Platelet count &gt;/= 100,000

          -  GFR &gt; 50 mL/min calculated by the Cockcroft-Gault equation

          -  Total bilirubin &lt;/= 2.0 times the upper limit of normal unless the patient has
             Gilbert's syndrome

          -  AST and ALT &lt;/= 2.5 times the upper limit of normal

          -  No other current malignancy, other than basal cell skin cancer, squamous cell skin
             cancer, in situ cervical cancer, ductal or lobular in situ of the breast. Patients
             with other malignancies are eligible if they have been continuously disease-free for
             &gt;/= 3 years prior to screening for this protocol.

          -  Age of 18 or older

          -  Ability and willingness to give informed consent

          -  Subjects must in the opinion of the Investigator be capable of complying with this
             protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute treatment for an infection or other serious medical illness within 14 days
             prior to study entry

          -  Major surgery within 3 weeks prior to study entry

          -  Known hypersensitivity to cisplatin or cetuximab

          -  Patients who have any severe or uncontrolled medical conditions or other conditions
             that could affect their participation in this study, including: unstable angina,
             serious uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia, active acute or uncontrolled infectious
             disorder, or myocardial infarction &lt;/= 6 months prior to study entry.

          -  Female patients who are pregnant or breast feeding, or adults who are of reproductive
             potential and are unwilling to refrain from conceiving a child during study
             treatment.

          -  Patients unwilling to comply with the protocol, or provide informed consent

          -  Psychiatric illness that would limit compliance with study requirements
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John F Deeken, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Georgetown University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Georgetown Lombardi Comprhensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20007</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 29, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 21, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Head and neck cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>genetic testing</keyword>
  <keyword>cisplatin</keyword>
  <keyword>erbitux</keyword>
  <keyword>radiation therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cetuximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
