<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8279">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01833104</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ReSource</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01833104</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Plasticity of the Compassionate Brain</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Longitudinal Study on the Trainability of Socio-affective and Cognitive Functions and Abilities.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Max Planck Institute for Human Cognitive and Brain Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Research Council (ERC)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Max Planck Institute for Human Cognitive and Brain Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to look at the long term effects of a complex socio-affective
      mental training program on a neuroscientific-, hormonal-, behavioral-, biological, and
      subjective measures-level. The training protocol consists of a variety of meditation and
      other mental health techniques, which are trained over the period of 11 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The ReSource Project is a unique, large-scale study on the effects of mental training
      techniques. Over a period of eleven months, participants practice a wide range of mental
      exercises that are designed to enhance attentional control, body- and self-awareness,
      emotion regulation, self-care, compassion, empathy, and perspective taking. Overall, the aim
      of the training is to improve mental health and social skills. It may reduce stress, improve
      mental clarity, increase life satisfaction, and lead to a better understanding of others'
      views, values and actions.

      The ReSource Project is a secular program developed by a team of experienced meditation
      teachers, scientists, and psychotherapists.

      Over the last decades, isolation, stress, and psychological tensions have been steadily
      increasing in our society. Mental training can alter stress responses, physical health,
      resilience, attention, perception, emotional experience, and social behavior. Evidence for
      these results is based on previous studies showing behavioral changes, as well as observed
      changes in brain function and structure. Moreover, health factors, such as peripheral
      autonomic responses, stress hormones, and immune parameters were significantly changed after
      training.

      In contrast to most previous studies of just a few months, the ReSource Project will be
      conducted over a period of one year for each experimental group (2 groups with shifted
      design), and will cover a wide range of practices intended to enhance cognitive and
      socio-affective skills.

      The ReSource Project consists of three consecutive modules: called &quot;Presence&quot;,
      &quot;Perspective&quot;, and &quot;Affect&quot;. The Presence module trains mindful attention to internal mental
      and physical processes. The Perspective module focuses on socio-cognitive abilities, such as
      insight into the nature of the mind and self, and also the ability to assume the perspective
      of others. The Affect module focuses on constructive ways of dealing with difficult
      emotions, and works to cultivate prosocial motivations and positive emotions such as
      compassion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in structural MRI measures</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Each structural MRI session has 20min of scan time. Investigation of long-lasting changes in cortical and sub-cortical networks after training. How do psychological traits and certain brain structures predict individual differences in training effects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in dynamic MRI measures in emotion generation and regulation paradigms</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The measure is part of the 2h 20min MRI session and lasts for 25 min. Goal is the Investigation of dynamic changes of functional MRI signals during affective and cognitive tasks in order to test the correlation of functional and structural network changes after training. How do psychological traits and certain brain structures predict individual differences in training effects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in MRI measures in resting state measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The measure is part of the 2h 20min MRI session and lasts for 7 min. Goal is the Investigation of dynamic changes of functional MRI signals during resting state in order to test the correlation of functional and structural network changes after training. How do psychological traits and certain brain structures predict individual differences in training effects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in dynamic MRI measures in an emotional reactivity paradigm</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The measure is part of the 2h 20min MRI session and lasts 15 min. Goal is the Investigation of dynamic changes of functional MRI signals during affective tasks in order to test the correlation of functional and structural network changes after training. How do psychological traits and certain brain structures predict individual differences in training effects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in dynamic MRI measures in a pain anticipation and perception paradigm</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The measure is part of the 2h 20min MRI session and lasts 23 min. Goal is the Investigation of dynamic changes of functional MRI signals during a pain perception task in order to test the correlation of functional and structural network changes after training. How do psychological traits and certain brain structures predict individual differences in training effects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in dynamic MRI measures in an attention and orienting task</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The measure is part of the 2h 20min MRI session and lasts 15 min. Goal is the Investigation of dynamic changes of functional MRI signals during an attention and orienting task in order to test the correlation of functional and structural network changes after training. How do psychological traits and certain brain structures predict individual differences in training effects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in dynamic MRI measures in a theory of mind and social cognition task</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The measure is part of the 2h 20min MRI session and lasts 15 min. Goal is the Investigation of dynamic changes of functional MRI signals during a theory of mind and social cognition task in order to test the correlation of functional and structural network changes after training. How do psychological traits and certain brain structures predict individual differences in training effects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in &quot;subjective experience sampling by smartphones or by means of an internet platform&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>weekly questions via online platform, concerning: actual affective condition, actual activity, actual thoughts, social closeness, quality of sleep (administered once a week via short questions online, duration 4 min.).
questions via online platform before and after a voluntary training exercise at home, 3-7 times a week; duration is 4 min, concerning: actual effects and experiences after daily mental training practice.
experience- sampling via smartphones, concerning: valance and arousal of current emotional state using &quot;single item affect grid&quot; method. Current activity and situation. Current thoughts. Amount of significant or stressful events since last sampling and how positive or negative or stressful was this event. How did you cope with this event. How was your body and mind awareness. (7 times for 3 consecutive days for each T0-T4).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in stress physiology: &quot;diurnal cortisol profile&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Examination of the diurnal cortisol profile (awakening, day timeline): on two non- consecutive week days, subjects collect saliva samples during the day (7 timepoints, each 5 min). This will be coordinated with the experience-sampling via the smartphones.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in autonomic functions: vagal tone (4 Min.)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>People sit quietly; no specific task given.
We will use &quot;Biopac MP150 Bionomadix&quot; or &quot;Nexus 10&quot; systems for measurement of the vagal tone by measuring heart rate at 3-point ECG in the chest area.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in attention and change detection in a virtual reality environment.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In a series of virtual worlds, we will look at attention and change detection in an unknown environment with emotional stimuli. Each subject will spend ~40 min. in a virtual environment. With preparation time, it will be 1 h altogether. It will happen on the same days as the MRT measurements and will be measured by counting the amount of changes of the virtual environment that could be detected.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in social distance in a virtual reality environment.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In a series of virtual worlds, we will look at changes in social distance. Each subject will spend ~40 min. in a virtual environment. With preparation time, it will be 1 h altogether. It will happen on the same days as the MRT measurements and will be measured by detecting the preferred proximity to avatars within the virtual worlds.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in exploratory behavior in a virtual reality environment.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In a series of virtual worlds, we will look at changes in exploratory behavior. Each subject will spend ~40 min. in a virtual environment. With preparation time, it will be 1 h altogether. It will happen on the same days as the MRT measurements and will be measured by detecting the amount of exploratory behavior (approaching, examining objects or avatars).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in affective preferences in a virtual reality environment.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In a series of virtual worlds, we will look at changes in approach and avoidance behavior in terms of affective preferences of available affective stimuli. Each subject will spend ~40 min. in a virtual environment. With preparation time, it will be 1 h altogether. It will happen on the same days as the MRT measurements.
We will use &quot;Biopac MP150 Bionomadix&quot; or &quot;Nexus 10&quot; systems for measurement of the following parameters for assessing affective reactions:
Temperature (finger clip)
EMG
respiration frequency (belt in the chest / abdominal area)
heart rate  (3-point ECG in the chest area)
EDA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in acute stress reactions in a virtual reality environment.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In a series of virtual worlds, we will look at changes in acute stress reactions to aversive affective stimuli (ground shaking, bugs, sudden loud noise, angry avatars). Each subject will spend ~40 min. in a virtual environment. With preparation time, it will be 1 h altogether. It will happen on the same days as the MRT measurements. We will use &quot;Biopac MP150 Bionomadix&quot; or &quot;Nexus 10&quot; systems for measurement of the following parameters for assessing stress reactions:
Temperature (finger clip)
EMG
respiration frequency (belt in the chest / abdominal area)
heart rate  (3-point ECG in the chest area)
EDA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the perceptional sensitivity and meta-cognition task (20 min., PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In this task, two stimuli are presented consecutively (e.g. a pattern with horizontal lines). The two stimuli differ slightly and the participants are asked to identify the differences (e.g. length or direction of the lines). The difference between the two stimuli gradually decreases with each round. The point, at which the participants cannot distinguish between the two stimuli is called the perceptional sensitivity. After each round, the participants are asked to assess their level of certainty regarding their answers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the inhibition and alerting task (stop-signal-reaction time task) (10 min., PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In this task, participants are asked to differentiate between two visual stimuli. The reaction time is measured. In some rounds, a stop-signal is presented after the presentation of the stimuli. The participants are supposed to inhibit pushing a button when this stop-signal is presented. Ability to inhibit a response is measured.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in working memory and meta-cognition (20 min., PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The participants are presented with 4, 6 or 8 letters, which they have to remember over a short period of time (about 2 seconds). Then they are presented with another letter and are asked to state whether or not that letter was part of the set of letters presented beforehand. After each round, the participants are asked to assess their level of certainty regarding their answers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the task switching paradigm (30 min, PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The cognitive and affective flexibility is measured in this task. Participants are asked to complete comparable cognitive and affective task-switching tasks of 15 min respectively. We use a task-cueing paradigm in which participants have to judge different stimuli. These stimuli are cognitive or affective in nature. The dependent variable is reaction time and accuracy in so-called &quot;shift&quot; or &quot;no-shift&quot; rounds, i.e. rounds which either have the same task as the round before (&quot;no-shift&quot;) or rounds, which consist of a new task (&quot;shift&quot;).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the emotional complexity task (15-20 min, PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants are asked to judge the similarity of a number of adjectives which describe emotional states. Using network analysis and multi-dimensional scaling, the data regarding the proximity of the adjectives are transformed in a depiction of the emotional-concept networks of the participant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the socio-affective video task (15 min, PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants watch a number of short clips (max. 15 sec) of news programs or documentaries. These clips have either neutral or emotional (negative) content. After watching a clip participants report on their emotional state and on how much compassion they feel.
Additionally, we will use &quot;Biopac MP150 Bionomadix&quot; or &quot;Nexus 10&quot; systems for measurement of the following parameters during the task:
Temperature (finger clip)
EMG
respiration frequency (belt in the chest / abdominal area)
heart rate  (3-point ECG in the chest area)
EDA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the Samson´s test (25 min, PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In this computer-based task, participants see a person standing in a room, in which oval-shaped objects can be seen on the walls. The participants are asked to report on how many of these objects can be seen from their own perspective and how many objects the person in the room is able to see.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the &quot;attentional blink paradigm&quot; (30 min, PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In this task, a number of visual stimuli are presented consecutively for short periods of time (about 100ms). The relevant stimuli are embedded in a number of distractor-stimuli. The participants are asked to report on the number of perceived relevant stimuli. They are also supposed to identify them.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the Zurich Prosocial Game (20 min, PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In this computer-based game, participants have to find their way through a labyrinth and solve little tasks on their way. They are under the impression, that there is another participant playing with them. The participant's readiness to share resources, necessary to complete the game, is measured.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the &quot;Trust Game&quot; (5 min, PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This game measures the participant's readiness to entrust another player with money. The participants are asked to say how much money they are ready to entrust the other player. This amount is then tripled and the other player can then decide how much money she is giving back. Before the first player is told how much money she is given back she is asked to estimate the amount.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the &quot;Punishing Game&quot; (10 min, PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>There are two parts to this game: 2nd person punishing and 3rd person punishing. In the 2nd person punishing game, there are two players. One Player (player A) has a larger amount of money at her disposal, than the other player (player B). The player with the larger amount of money can decide how she wants to split the money between herself and the other player. Then player B can decide whether he wants to punish player A by taking money from player A while using his own money (for each unit of money she spends three three units are taken from the other player). After two rounds, the tasks of the players are reversed. In the 3rd person punishing game, the participants watch the interaction of anonymous players A and B. After each round, the participant can decide whether or not to punish the player, who split the money.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the &quot;Dictator Game&quot; (5 min, PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In this game, participants can decide how they split a set amount of money between themselves and an anonymous player.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the &quot;Self-complexity Task&quot; (15 min, PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In this task, participants receive 44 cards with adjectives written on them describing personal traits. These can be either negative or positive. After thinking for a while about aspects and roles in their own life, the participants are asked to arrange the cards into an arbitrary amount of piles. The amount of piles is measured.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>&quot;Self-reference Task&quot; (15 min, PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Between subjects at two measurement points: 1. at TO; 2. at T2 (=T0 + 26 weeks).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In the first part of this task, participants are asked to judge adjectives regarding a) whether they apply to themselves, b) whether they apply to a famous person (e.g. Angela Merkel), or c) whether they meet linguistic criteria (e.g. whether they are written in capital letters). In the second part, participants are asked to identify the adjectives, which had been presented in the first part.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the &quot;amount of mind wandering task&quot; (25 min, PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Aim of this measure is to access the amount and content of spontaneously generated cognition. Main focus is &quot;day dreaming&quot; or &quot;mind wandering&quot; that occurs, when our minds drift off, while working on a task.
In this measure, subjects are asked to work on two little, rather boring PC-based exercises (1. CRT, choice reaction time task; 2. WM, working memory task). During selective queries, they are then asked for the content and valence of their thoughts (&quot;thought probe&quot;).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in autonomic functions: heart rate detection (6 min.)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects are asked to count their heart beats.
We will use &quot;Biopac MP150 Bionomadix&quot; or &quot;Nexus 10&quot; systems for measurement of heart rate at 3-point ECG in the chest area.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in autonomic functions: biofeedback and auto-regulation task (8 min.)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Respiratory sinus arrythmia (RSA) is reported to the subjects. They observe a ball on a computer screen, which ascends in accordance with their RSA. Goal is to make the ball rise. RSA is computed through ECG and respiration.
Before the start, subjects are warned that there will be a load noise approximately during the middle of the experiment. They are asked to stay calm despite of the noise. After the sound for another 4 Minutes, the amount of arousal and the ability to regulate it will be assessed.
We will use &quot;Biopac MP150 Bionomadix&quot; or &quot;Nexus 10&quot; systems for measurement of respiration frequency (belt in the chest / abdominal area).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Amount of stress response in the &quot;Trier social stress test&quot; (TSST, 110 min.)</measure>
    <time_frame>The TSST can only be done once, so each 40 subjects will participate at T0, 50 at T1 (T0+13 weeks), 50 at T2 (T1+13 weeks), and 50 at T3 (T2+13 weeks) in a between-subjects design.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>TSST: a standardized stress test, that induces stress in the laboratory. Here, the cortisol levels, alpha-amylase as well as immunoglobulin A (lgA9 levels are examined via saliva samples, with heart rate variability (HRV), EDA, hear rate, blood pressure and finger temperature as adjunct measurement.
Additionally, each 10 ml blood samples are drawn before and after the test. They are then used to assess levels of oxytocin as well as the inflammatory markers cytokine IL-6, TNF-alpha and C-reactive protein (CRP).
The measurement will also include qualitative interviewer reports.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;adult temperament questionnaire (ATQ) effortful control subscale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an attention questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;ADHS-SB&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an ADHD self assessment questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;FFA Freiburg Mindfulness Questionnaire&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a mindfulness self assessment questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Five Factor Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a mindfulness self assessment questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Multidimensional Assessment of Interoceptive Awareness (Mehling MAIA)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an interoceptive self assessment questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Kristin Neff - Self-Compassion Scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a self-compassion self assessment questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;SAIS - short affect intensity scale (pos. emotion intensity, serenity)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an emotion questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Kristin Neff - Compassion for other scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an compassion questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Interpersonal Reactivity Index IRI - Davis&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a empathy questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Gilbert: 2 types of positive affect&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an emotion / compassion questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Gilbert: Fear of Compassion Scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an emotion / compassion questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Borderline Personality Questionnaire (BPQ)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a borderline questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Narcissistic Personality Inventory (NPI-40)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a narcissism questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;CERQ Cognitive emotion regulation questionnaire&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an emotion regulation questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;brief COPE inventory&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a coping strategy questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Berkeley Expressivity Questionnaire BEQ&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an emotional expressivity questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Range and Differentiation of Emotion Scale (RDEES)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an emotional complexity questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;van Lange Prosocial Scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an social value orientation questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;EROS-Emotion Regulation of Others and Self&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an emotion regulation questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Jennifer Crocker: Friendship, Compassionate and Self-Image Goals Scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an goal approach style questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Reed and Aquino: Self Importance of Moral Identity Scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an moral identity questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;SDPT /ODPT Self &amp; Other Perspective Taking Scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an perspective taking questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Singelis: Self Questionnaire (Self Construal)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an self construal questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Caprara: Prosocialness Scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a prosocialness questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Twenty Statement Test (TST)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a self statement questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;The Machiavellianism Scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a leadership and interpersonal style questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;NEO FFI&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a personality questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Pain Catastrophizing Questionnaire (PCS)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a pain questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;intolerance of uncertainty scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a clinical questionnaire on insecurity tolerance via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Trier Inventory for Chronic Stress (TICS)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a stress questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Perceived Stress Scale (PSS)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a stress questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Parental Bonding Inventory (PBI)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a bonding questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Freiburger Beschwerdeliste (FBL)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a symptoms check list via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Pittsburgh Sleep Inventory (PSQI)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a sleep questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Multi Motive Grid (MMG)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a achievement, affiliation and power motives questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Mental Health Continuum short form (MHC-SF)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a mental health questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Diener Satisfaction with Life Scale SWLS&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a satisfaction with life questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;BDI-2, Becks Depression Inventory&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a depression questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Ego Resiliency (ER-89)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a resiliency questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;experiences in close relationships - revised&quot;(ECR-R)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a questionnaire on close relationships via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;UCLA Lonliness Scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a lonliness questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;PANAS&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a positive and negative affect scale via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;MDES, acute feelings&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months). Questionnaire is administered once a week in each block.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a acute feelings scale via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;social closeness scale&quot; (a subscale of the UCLA lonliness scale).</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months). Questionnaire is administered once a week in each block.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a social closeness scale via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>questionnaire score &quot;POMS Profile of Mood States&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Together with the TSST, POMS is only done once for each subject: so each 10 subjects will do the POMS at T0, 50 subjects at T1 (T0+13 weeks), 50 subjects at T2 (T1+13 weeks), and 50 at T3 (T2+13 weeks) in a between-subjects design.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a paper &amp; pencil version of the POMS mood scale, for each subject on that day, when they do the TSST stress test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>questionnaire score &quot;STAI state&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Together with the TSST, STAI state is only done once for each subject: so each 10 subjects will do the POMS at T0, 50 subjects at T1 (T0+13 weeks), 50 subjects at T2 (T1+13 weeks), and 50 at T3 (T2+13 weeks) in a between-subjects design.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a paper &amp; pencil version of the STAI state scale on anxiety, for each subject on that day, when they do the TSST stress test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in &quot;Subjective Sensory Sensitivity questionnaire&quot; following Fox et al. (2012)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T1(T0 +13 weeks) to T2 (T1+13 weeks).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a paper &amp; pencil version of a measure for the visualisation of body sensations following Fox et al. (2012).
The measure will be administered at the start and the end of the first training block, the &quot;presence block&quot;. The start of the presence block for arm one will be: Aug. 19th 2013 till Sept. 19th 2013. The start of the presence block for arm two will be: Okt. 7th 2013 till Okt. 30th 2013.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;private body consciousness scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a body consciousness questionnaire via online webplatform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;perceived responsiveness scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a responsiveness questionnaire via online webplatform. The scale is answered by selected close friends of the subjects (&quot;observer&quot;), rating their relationship to the subject (with their consent).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Perceived responses to capitalization attempts (PRCA)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of a questionnaire looking at perceived responses of their partners to own capitalization attempts via online webplatform. The scale is answered by selected close friends of the subjects (&quot;observer&quot;), rating their relationship to the subject (with their consent).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Dyadic Adjustment Scale (DAS)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The DAS scale is a self-report measure of relationship adjustment. It will be provided via online webplatform. The scale is answered by selected close friends of the subjects (&quot;observer&quot;), rating their impression of the subject (with their consent).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Brief COPE scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Brief Cope is an abbreviated version of the COPE Inventory. It will be provided via online webplatform. The scale is answered by selected close friends of the subjects (&quot;observer&quot;), rating their impression of the subject (with their consent).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Satisfaction With Life Scale (SWLS)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The SWLS is a short 5-item instrument designed to measure global cognitive judgments of satisfaction with one's life. It will be provided via online webplatform. The scale is answered by selected close friends of the subjects (&quot;observer&quot;), rating their impression of the subject (with their consent).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;FFMQ&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The FFMQ is a mindfulness questionnaire. It will be provided via online webplatform. The scale is answered by selected close friends of the subjects (&quot;observer&quot;), rating their impression of the subject (with their consent).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in &quot;TIPI-10&quot; personality scale.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Tipi-10 is a personality scale. It will be provided via online webplatform. The scale is answered by selected close friends of the subjects (&quot;observer&quot;), rating their impression of the subject (with their consent).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in &quot;Caprara: Prosocialness Scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>It will be provided via online webplatform. The scale is answered by selected close friends of the subjects (&quot;observer&quot;), rating their impression of the subject (with their consent).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in &quot;Interpersonal Reactivity Index IRI - Davis&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>It will be provided via online webplatform. The scale is answered by selected close friends of the subjects (&quot;observer&quot;), rating their impression of the subject (with their consent).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in questionnaire score &quot;Behavior Rating Inventory of Executive Function (BRIEF®)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The BRIEF scale has eight clinical scales (Inhibit, Shift, Emotional Control, Initiate, Working Memory, Plan/Organize, Organization of Materials, Monitor) and two validity scales (Inconsistency and Negativity) and gives the clinician a well-rounded picture of the behavior of the adolescent being rated.
It will be provided via online webplatform. The scale is answered by selected close friends of the subjects (&quot;observer&quot;), rating their impression of the subject (with their consent).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in stress physiology: &quot;cortisol analyses of hair samples&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>During each measurement time point, the subjects are asked for hair samples from the back of their head, as close as possible to the scalp. It will be sent to a cooperating lab in Dresden to assess the amount of cortisol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in telomer length</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>During each measurement time point, 4 ml blood samples in EDTA-tubs are collected from each subject and stored  at - 80 degrees celsius. To analyze, if the training leads to reduced shortening of the telomers, the probes are sent to the Blackburn lab of UCLA in San Francisco, USA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in willingness to make donations in the economic game &quot;donation paradigm&quot; (10 min, PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This economic game assesses the participant's willingness to donate to selected charity groups. In this game, they receive a certain amount of money and can decide, if and how much they would like to contribute.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in self concept and self complexity (20 min., PC based)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks), to T4 (T3 + 4,5 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In a first step, participants are asked to cluster 30 positive or negative personality traits around their depicted self in such a way, that the spatial closeness or distance reflects, how much they identify with the trait.
In a second step, they are asked to choose selected items and pile them. The height of the stack then is thought to reflect the complexity of the self. concept.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of gene variants / polymorphisms</measure>
    <time_frame>on the first day of T0 (starting 4/22/13 for controls; 5/13/13 for group 1; 7/1/13 for group 2)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>During the first day of T0, 12 ml blood samples in EDTA-tubs are collected from each subject and stored  at -80 degrees celsius. Aim is to analyze the connection between gen variants, personality traits, behavior &amp; brain activation. Furthermore, it is possible to assess if the training effects interact with certain gene variants.
The following are explored:
arginine-vasopressin-receptor gene (AVPR1A) at chromosome 12q
oxytocin-receptor gene (OXTR) at chromosome 3p25
catechol-O-methyltransferase (COMT) (Val158Met polymorphism)
serotonin-transporter 5HTTPLR (SCL6A4 and rs25531)
monoamine-oxidase A (MAOA; rs6323)
mu-opioid-receptor gene
neuropeptide Y (NPY)
tryptophan hydroxylase-2 gene (TPH2, rs4570625)
CACNA1C gene (SNP rs1006737)
CHRNA4 gene (rs1044396)
ADRA2B gene (&quot;deletion&quot;)
cannabinoid-receptor 1 gene (CNR1)
dopamine D4 Receptor gene (DRD4)
dicarboxylate/amino acid cation sodium transporter (DAT1)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in (immune) activity and changes in amount of inflammatory markers (blood samples)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>At all four measurement points, 10 ml blood samples are drawn altogether, centrifuged, and stored at -20 degrees celsius.
They are sent to the &quot;First Dept of Pediatrics, Director, Division of Endocrinology, Metabolism and Diabetes, University of Athens Medical School, Aghia Sophia Children's Hospital, Athens, Greece&quot; for analysis.
Blood levels of cytokines IL-6, TNF-alpha and C-reactive protein (CRP) are assessed there.
Additionally, a complete blood count is drawn. Not aiming in diagnostic directions, the goal is to assess the status of neutrophils, lymphocytes and monocytes in the probes. These are thought to be general markers of immune activity and are inspected in relation to telomer length.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Training induced short term changes in oxytocin blood level.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes before and after a single &quot;perspective&quot; or &quot;affective&quot; training session between T2 and T3 (i.e. for arm one: between 11/21/13 - 12/23/13 or 3/3/14 - 4/5/14; for arm two: between 1/20/14 - 2/20/14 or 5/2/14 - 5/24/14).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Once during the training for each subject, before and directly after a 2h &quot;perspective&quot; or &quot;affective&quot; training session, a 10 ml blood sample is drawn and stored at -80 degrees celsius. To analyse blood levels of oxytocin, probes are sent to the Max-Planck-Institut für Psychiatrie, Munich, Germany (Department of Prof. Rainer Landgraf).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in autonomic functions: &quot;measurement of autonomic functions and kinesic behavior during meditation training&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from T0 to T1 (TO + 13 weeks), to T2 (T1 + 13 weeks), to T3 (T2 + 13 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Heart rate, kinesic behavior,respiratory frequency and heart rate variability are being measured during two meditation session in each training block.
We use the non-invasive &quot;Zephyr BioHarness 3 multi-sensor-device&quot;, which comes with a belly belt.
After the meditation session, subjects are asked to answer a 5 item questionnaire (2 Min.)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>questionnaire score &quot;psychopathology in the family&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months before T0 and during initial proband screening phase of the project, each subject fills out this questionnaire at the online recruiting webpage via secure connection.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Information on relevant potential psychopathology in the family system of the participants.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>score of &quot;d2&quot; attention task.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months before T0 and during initial proband screening phase of the project, each subject takes the d2 test in paper &amp; pencil version..</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The d2 Test is a timed test of selective attention. In response to the discrimination of similar visual stimuli, the test measures processing speed, rule compliance, and quality of performance, allowing estimation of individual attention and concentration performance.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>score of &quot;TIPI-10&quot; personality test.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months before T0 and during initial proband screening phase of the project, each subject fills out this questionnaire at the online recruiting webpage via secure connection.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The TIPI was designed to assess the constellation of traits defined by the Five Factor Theory of Personality.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>score of &quot;Freiburger Beschwerdeliste FBL&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months before T0 and during initial proband screening phase of the project, each subject fills out this questionnaire at the online recruiting webpage via secure connection.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The FBL is a standardized list to assess physical discomforts.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>score of &quot;Mental Health Continuum short form (MHC-SF)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months before T0 and during initial proband screening phase of the project, each subject fills out this questionnaire at the online recruiting webpage via secure connection.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A questionnaire measuring emotional well-being.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>score of &quot;Interpersonal Reactivity Index IRI - Davis&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months before T0 and during initial proband screening phase of the project, each subject fills out this questionnaire at the online recruiting webpage via secure connection.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A questionnaire measuring empathy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>score of &quot;Kristin Neff - Compassion for other scale &amp; compassion for self scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months before T0 and during initial proband screening phase of the project, each subject fills out this questionnaire at the online recruiting webpage via secure connection.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A questionnaire measuring compassion.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>score of &quot;Perceived Stress Scale&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months before T0 and during initial proband screening phase of the project, each subject fills out this questionnaire at the online recruiting webpage via secure connection.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A questionnaire measuring stress levels.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>score of &quot;Five Factor Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ)&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months before T0 and during initial proband screening phase of the project, each subject fills out this questionnaire at the online recruiting webpage via secure connection.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A questionnaire measuring self report of mindfulness.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>score of &quot;Multidimensional Assessment of Interoceptive Awareness, MAIA&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months before T0 and during initial proband screening phase of the project, each subject fills out this questionnaire at the online recruiting webpage via secure connection.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of an interoceptive self assessment questionnaire.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>score of &quot;RAVEN IQ test&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months before T0 and during initial proband screening phase of the project, each subject fills out this questionnaire at the online recruiting webpage via secure connection.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Administration of the raven IQ test.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative interviews (1 h)</measure>
    <time_frame>voluntarily, possible during each block of meditation training</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>on a voluntary basis and with written consent, we would like to conduct qualitative interviews with some of the participants, where they are able to describe the subjective experience of the whole training. The interviews will be video-taped with the consent of the participants.
We will be using depth-interview techniques that assess not only what the subjects experience but also how they process it.
Interviews will be done by a interview specialist with a degree in Psychology and Philosophy.
The data will be treated in accordance with data protection laws. In further publications, all statements of the subjects will be anonymized, the tapes will be erased after transcription. In case they agreed to be video-taped, the material will potentially be used for a video documentation of the whole ReSource project.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">330</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Subjects</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Training group I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>(n=80) in the order &quot;Presence - Perspective - Affective&quot;</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Training group II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>(n=80) in the order &quot;Presence - Affective - Perspective&quot;</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Retest-control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>(up to n = 30) this is a non-intervention control group to access measurement effects and will be tested at each timepoint.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>(n=80) here, the &quot;Affective only&quot; intervention is administered</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Presence - Perspective - Affective.</intervention_name>
    <description>PRESENCE:
Goal is to cultivate attentional skills and interoceptive body awareness through meditation on breath and the so-called &quot;body scan&quot;.
PERSPECTIVE:
It focuses on the cognitive aspects of compassion; learn to take perspectives on thoughts, on their sense of self, and on other people; observe more macroscopic dynamics within oneself, that is, your inner &quot;parts&quot;, &quot;roles&quot;, or &quot;self-aspects&quot;; do not fully identify with them and remaining aware of their transiency; strengthen the ability to detach from one's own perspective and take the perspectives of other people, trying to understand their thoughts, motives, and feelings.
AFFECTIVE:
Cultivate emotional and motivational aspects of compassion; cultivate a sense of benevolence, love, and care, &quot;opening the heart&quot; for oneself and others; work with obstacles, such as fear, anger or sadness (&quot;emotion acceptance&quot;); pro-social motivations as an alley towards loving and benevolent feelings and as a consequence of them.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Training group I</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Presence - Affective - Perspective.</intervention_name>
    <description>As specified above the order is interchanged between two groups.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Training group II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Affective only</intervention_name>
    <description>AFFECTIVE:
Cultivate emotional and motivational aspects of compassion; cultivate a sense of benevolence, love, and care, &quot;opening the heart&quot; for oneself and others; work with obstacles, such as fear, anger or sadness (&quot;emotion acceptance&quot;); pro-social motivations as an alley towards loving and benevolent feelings and as a consequence of them.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  is a healthy, normal subject

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  can not participate in the kick-off retreats

          -  does not have a PC with internet connection at home

          -  does not speak and understand German fluently

          -  has studied or is studying Psychology

          -  has a daily meditation practice

          -  attended a meditation retreat within the last 2 years

          -  exceeds normal BDI

          -  not right handed (or re-educated right handed)

          -  not able to lie still in MRT scanner for 1,5 h

          -  is pregnant or in lactation or plans to become pregnant

          -  has had a larger surgery or plans to have one during the next year

          -  has metal parts in the body (due to MRT scanning)

          -  has a cardiac pacemaker

          -  carries an insulin or medicine pump

          -  carries a shunt

          -  has a heart valve

          -  has an inner ear implant

          -  carries piercings or electronics on / in the body, that cannot be removed

          -  has a tattoo in the head / throat area

          -  works in the field of metal processing (if that leads to small metal parts on the
             body, that cannot be removed)

          -  has dyslexia or ametropia

          -  has claustrophobia (MRT scanner)

          -  has severe hearing problems

          -  has limitations with motor functions

          -  has or had a severe injury in the head area

          -  has or had a neurological disease (meningitis, cerebral hemorrhage, cerebral infarct,
             brain trauma, coma etc.)

          -  has or had epilepsy

          -  has a severe disease targeting the musculoskeletal system

          -  has a heart disease

          -  has a (peripheral) vascular disease, circulatory disorder, Raynaud´s disease

          -  has a liver disease

          -  has a respiratory disease

          -  has an affected kidney

          -  has an advanced multiple sclerosis

          -  has an infection (e.g. HIV)

          -  is in treatment due to chronic pain

          -  has a thyroid disease, which leads to massive intake of thyroid hormones

          -  is on medication that effects the central nervous system (psychotropic drugs) during
             the last three months

          -  has been diagnosed with a mental health disease and is in treatment at the moment or
             within the last 2 years

          -  reaches clinical scores in the following questionnaires: TAS-20, MDI, STAI-trait,
             PHQ;

          -  reaches clinical scores following DSM-IV as determined by a SKID I and SKID II
             clinical interview
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tania Singer, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Max Planck Institute for Human Cognitive and Brain Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Max Planck Institute for Human Cognitive and Brain Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leipzig</city>
        <state>Sachsen</state>
        <zip>04103</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Max Planck Institute, Humboldt University, Campus Nord, Haus 5</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10099</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.resource-project.org</url>
    <description>Homepage of the ReSource Project Webpage</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 18, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 1, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthy subjects</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
