<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="63843">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02014337</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C1073-500</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02014337</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mifepristone and Eribulin in Patients With Metastatic Triple Negative Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Study of Mifepristone in Combination With Eribulin in Patients With Locally Advanced/Metastatic Breast Cancer With a Dose Expansion Cohort in Patients With Triple Negative Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Corcept Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Corcept Therapeutics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a study to assess the safety and preliminary efficacy of the combination of
      mifepristone and eribulin in patients with metastatic or locally advanced unresectable
      Triple Negative Breast Cancer.  The structure for the study is a single arm, non-randomized,
      open-label, multicenter trial with no control group.  The study will be conducted at up to 8
      sites, with up to 40 evaluable patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There will be two parts to the study: Part 1, a dose escalation phase, in which the Maximum
      Tolerated Dose (MTD) and Recommended Phase II Dose (RP2D) will be determined in up to 20
      patients; and Part 2, a dose expansion phase in which a preliminary estimate of efficacy
      will be made in an expansion group of up to 20 patients at the RP2D.

      Treatment will be administered in 21-day cycles, with the exception of the first cycle,
      which will be of 28 days duration with a lead-in of 7 days dosing of mifepristone.

      Cycle 1 (28-day cycle): Mifepristone administered orally (PO) with food once daily for 28
      days. Eribulin will be administered intravenously (IV) over 2 to 5 minutes on days 8 and 15.

      Cycle 2 and beyond (21-day cycle): Mifepristone administered orally (PO) with food once
      daily for 21 days. Eribulin will be administered intravenously (IV) over 2 to 5 minutes on
      days 1 and 8. Enrolment in Part 2 of the study (dose expansion) will occur once the RP2D has
      been determined. Patients in the dose expansion study must have disease that is
      glucocorticoid (GR) receptor positive (by immunohistochemistry [IHC]). Patients will be
      treated in repeated 21 day cycles until progression or another withdrawal criterion is met.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics/Dynamics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of the combination of mifepristone and eribulin in patients with metastatic or locally advanced unresectable triple negative breast cancer (TNBC).</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>In the dose escalation phase: MTD time frame is within 28 days of first dose (Cycle 1)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mifepristone and Eribulin in combination</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single Arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mifepristone and Eribulin in combination</intervention_name>
    <description>Single Arm, Two Parts Part 1: Dose Escalation Phase to determine MTD and RP2D in up to 20 patients Part 2: Dose Expansion Phase at RP2D in 20 patients</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mifepristone and Eribulin in combination</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Korlym</other_name>
    <other_name>Halaven</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥ 18 years old

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of breast cancer

          -  For dose escalation: Locally advanced or metastatic breast cancer

          -  For dose expansion:  Triple-negative for ER, progesterone receptor, and HER2 (&lt; 1%
             cells positive for ER/progesterone receptor, and HER2 IHC score of 0-,or 1, or FISH
             HER2+ ratio of 1.8); patients with low ER IHC  (&gt; 1% but &lt; 10% cells positive), but
             negative by genomic assay are eligible.

          -  Inoperable metastatic or locally advanced unresectable disease

          -  For dose escalation, patients may have evaluable or measurable disease.

          -  For dose expansion, patients must have measurable disease as defined by Response
             Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST v1.1) in at least one lesion not
             previously irradiated unless there is documented evidence of progression.

          -  Part 1, dose escalation:  patients should have received a minimum of two, and up to
             four prior chemotherapy treatments for metastatic or locally advanced disease.

          -  In Part 2, dose expansion: TNBC tumor must be positive for the glucocorticoid
             receptor (as defined by at least 10% positive cells by IHC assay).  Patients should
             have received a minimum of two, and up to four, prior  chemotherapeutic regimens
             metastatic or locally advanced disease.

          -  Disease-free period of &gt; 3 years from any previous malignancies, excluding curatively
             treated basal cell carcinoma, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, or carcinoma in
             situ of the cervix.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0 or 1

          -  Patients must have adequate bone marrow and renal/hepatic function at the screening
             visit

          -  Patients who are women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy
             test.   Sexually active patients of reproductive potential must be willing to use
             non-hormonal contraception

          -  Able to take oral medications

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had recent systemic cytotoxic therapies or radiotherapy within 14
             days prior to day 1 of cycle 1

          -  Patients who have had any major surgery within 4 weeks prior to day 1 of cycle 1, or
             minor surgery within 2 weeks prior to day 1 of cycle 1

          -  For two weeks prior to first day of study drug treatment, administration of a strong
             cytochrome P450 3A (CYP3A) inducer or inhibitors

          -  Patients who are taking simvastatin or lovastatin.  Patients should be switched to
             alternative therapies a minimum of 2 weeks before starting study drug.

          -  Patients who have been treated with an investigational agent within 21 days prior to
             day 1 of cycle 1

          -  Concomitant use of biological agents including growth factors

          -  Patients who require treatment with systemic corticosteroids for serious medical
             conditions or illnesses (e.g. immunosuppression after organ transplantation)

          -  Chronic liver disease

          -  History of significant cardiac disease.

          -  Pregnant or lactating

          -  Any other significant co-morbid conditions that in the opinion of the investigator
             would impair study participation or cooperation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rita Nanda, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rita Nanda, MD</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rita Nanda, MD</last_name>
      <phone>773-834-2756</phone>
      <email>rnanda@medicine.bsd.uchicago.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rita Nanda, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Oncology-Baylor Charles A. Sammons Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75246</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carlos Becerra, MD</last_name>
      <phone>214-370-1179</phone>
      <email>carlos.becerra@usoncology.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carlos Becerra, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Cancer Specialist</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fairfax</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22031</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexander Spira, MD</last_name>
      <phone>703-208-3173</phone>
      <email>Alexander.spira@usoncology.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alexander Spira, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 4, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mifepristone</keyword>
  <keyword>Eribulin Mesylate</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mifepristone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
