<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="141255">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01865383</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-1111</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01MH098690-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01865383</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Microfinance and Health Intervention Trial for Youth in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania</brief_title>
  <official_title>Microfinance and Health Intervention Trial for Youth in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Tanzania: National Institute for Medical Research</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Young men who are members of the camps randomized to receive a microfinance and health
      leadership intervention will have a lower incidence of sexually transmitted infections
      (Neisseria gonorrhea (NG), Chlamydia trachomatis (CT) and Trichomonas vaginalis (TV) and
      report perpetrating less physical or sexual violence against sexual partners as compared to
      young men who are members of camps not randomized to receive the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Finding effective strategies to reach out to young men and mobilize them to reduce their HIV
      risk is critical, given men's control over the terms and conditions of most sexual
      partnerships. Unequal power distribution in relationships has a devastating impact on women,
      leading to HIV prevalence among young women in some sub-Saharan African countries four to
      seven times higher than among young men the same age. Gender power differentials have
      negative consequences for men as well, leading to increased risk of physical and mental
      health problems, substance use, and low uptake of health-related services. We need
      innovative approaches to address the structural and social determinant of young men's risk.
      Lack of economic opportunity is a key structural determinant of risk that has negative
      consequences for men, and has been linked to poor health outcomes. The influence of social
      network members is a social determinant of risk for both HIV and gender-based violence that
      can be addressed through interventions designed to change network norms. For the past 12
      years our group has conducted research in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania on HIV and gender-based
      violence. With support from the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH) we identified
      networks of young men who socialize in what are called &quot;camps&quot; and we successfully piloted a
      microfinance and health leadership intervention with men in camps like the one proposed in
      this application (R21 MH080577). Camps are enduring social groups of mostly men that have
      elected leadership, paid membership fees, and physical space to meet. The equivalent of a
      camp in US culture may be a cross between a club and a gang.  Camps appear to be an urban
      phenomenon in Tanzania and our group is the first to have published data describing them.
      Men in camps engage in HIV risk behavior and in gender-based violence that put them and
      their partners at risk for HIV.  Research suggests that microfinance combined with health
      promotion can lead to improvement in health outcomes, including reductions in HIV risk and
      gender-based violence. However, few, if any well designed evaluations of microfinance and
      health programs with young men have been reported.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of New Sexually Transmitted Infections</measure>
    <time_frame>at 30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Men Reporting Perpetration of Physical, Sexual, or Psychological Partner Violence</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Men Reporting Perpetration of Physical, Sexual, or Psychological Partner Violence</measure>
    <time_frame>at 30 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2623</enrollment>
  <condition>Sexually Transmitted Infections</condition>
  <condition>Gender Based Violence Perpetration</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Microfinance and Health Leadership</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Microfinance and Health Leadership:  Participants will receive small loans and business training as part of the microfinance component.  Camp leaders will receive health leadership training and then pass on knowledge to camp members.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Microfinance and Health Leadership</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Microfinance and Health Leadership</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must be registered camp member for at least the last 3 months

          -  Must be at least 15 years old

          -  Must plan to reside in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania for the next 30 months

          -  Must visit primary camp at least 1 time per week

          -  Must provide contact information of friend or family member

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unwilling to provide locator information

          -  Unable to participate due to psychological disturbance, cognitive impairment or
             threatening behavior.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Suzanne Maman, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UNC Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lusajo Kajula-Maonga, MA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Muhimbilit University of Health and Allied Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Suzanne Maman, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>919-966-3901</phone>
    <email>maman@email.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Suzanne Maman</last_name>
      <email>maman@email.unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Suzanne Maman, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 24, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sexually Transmitted Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
