<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="23304">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01809613</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-009020</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01809613</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) During Deep Brain Stimulation (DBS) to Treat Parkinson's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) During Deep Brain Stimulation (DBS) to Treat Parkinson's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is investigating the usefulness of using functional magnetic resonance imaging
      (fMRI) to monitor brain activation during deep brain stimulation for Parkinson's Disease.
      The study may determine the relationship between patterns of brain activation and
      therapeutic outcome and/or side effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Deep brain stimulation (DBS) of the subthalamic nucleus (STN) within the thalamocortical
      basal ganglion (BG) complex is an effective neurosurgical approach for treating motor
      symptoms of Parkinson's disease (PD). However, because the nature of its underlying
      mechanisms and clinical effects are not fully understood, precision targeting, decreasing
      adverse effects, and improving clinical outcomes represent major clinical and scientific
      challenges in PD and other disorders treated by DBS. Our goal is to investigate the
      inter-relationships between site-specific neural activation and clinical outcomes during STN
      DBS. To do so, we will perform non-invasive functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) to
      investigate DBS-mediated activation of thalamocortical BG network circuitry. Our proposed
      protocol involves the addition of intraoperative fMRI to the standard DBS protocol in order
      to determine the major sites of activation in the thalamocortical BG complex during
      application of clinically effective DBS to the dorsal and ventral regions of the STN (dSTN
      and ventral subthalamic nucleus (vSTN), respectively). Patients will undergo clinical
      assessment using the Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS) to determine the
      relative efficacy of dSTN and vSTN DBS, applied during the fMRI and at every standard follow
      visit post-surgery. Our Specific Aims are to: (1) Identify fMRI-activated brain regions by
      vSTN and dSTN DBS in PD patients and (2) correlate fMRI activation with clinical outcomes
      (UPDRS) and side effects. With the goal of improving DBS electrode targeting for optimal and
      reproducible clinical outcomes, these experiments will be the first attempt to relate
      site-specific DBS with functional in vivo imaging data and quantitative longitudinal
      clinical outcome measures in PD patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Score on Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after Deep Brain Stimulation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The UPDRS is a rating scale used to follow the longitudinal course of Parkinson's disease. The version of the scale used in this study has a total of 14 items; each of these item has a scale of 0-4, with 0 being no impairment, and 4 being severe impairment. All of the parts are combined to give a numeric score: 0 indicating no sign of disease, and 56, the highest score indicating severely incapacitated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stimulation-evoked blood-oxygen-level dependence (BOLD) signal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) will be performed to determine the areas of BOLD signal modulation with DBS.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI)</intervention_name>
    <description>During the deep brain stimulation (DBS) surgery of the subthalamic nucleus within the thalamocortical basal ganglion, an additional lead extendor will be connected to the DBS electrode to allow externalization of the lead. Following confirmation of electrode location with MRI, a series of fMRI scans will be run. Total scanning time will be limited to 35 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stimulation-evoked blood-oxygen-level dependence (BOLD) signal</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult Patients with medically intractable Parkinson's Disease who have been approved
             for DBS surgery by the interdisciplinary Mayo DBS committee.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant patients, prisoners, children (age less than 18), and any patients
             identified as unsuitable for this protocol by the Mayo DBS committee.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Su Youne Chang, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emily Knight</last_name>
    <phone>507-293-0512</phone>
    <email>knight.emily@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Su Youne Chang, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>507-255-6443</phone>
    <email>chang.suyoune@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emily Knight</last_name>
      <phone>507-293-0512</phone>
      <email>knight.emily@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Su-youne Chang, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kendall Lee, M.D. Phd</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 16, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 11, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Su-Youne Chang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PI</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parkinson disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Deep Brain Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
