<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="87318">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01871051</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-4414</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01871051</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Risk Factors For Postoperative Respiratory Complications After Anesthesia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Risk Factors For Postoperative Respiratory Complications After Anesthesia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project was aimed to identify the risk factors associated with the occurrence of
      respiratory complications in post anesthesia care unit. The primary outcome was the
      composite measure of occurrence of complications in PACU. The components were apnea or
      hypopnea, laryngospasm, bronchospasm and prolonged oxygen requirement.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a retrospective project. Data will be used from Quality Improvement database for
      publication purpose. Data was collected from a prospectively collected database that was
      done as a Quality Improvement Project. The study sites included post anesthesia care units
      (PACU) of the main and ambulatory campuses of our hospital. The data was collected from
      surgical and radiology PACU's. Data was collected each quarter for 2 weeks in the surgical
      PACU, and for 1 month in Radiology PACU, from Sep 2007 through Mar 2012. Trained
      perioperative nurses and Certified Registered Nurse Anesthesiologist did data collection.
      This ensured a sample representative of at least 10% of patients anesthetized for surgical
      and radiological procedures. The independent variables (risk factors) collected included
      age, American Society of Anesthesiology (ASA) physical status, obesity, preexisting airway
      or lung disease, preexisting neuromuscular disease or hypotonia, morbid obesity,
      intraoperative bronchospasm and intraoperative laryngospasm. The primary outcome variables
      collected were Apnea or hypopnea, Laryngospasm, Bronchospasm, and prolonged Oxygen
      requirement. Apnea or hypopnea was defined by the need for bag mask ventilation,
      Laryngospasm by the requirement of a positive pressure ventilation of &gt; 20 cmH2O or
      administration of succinylcholine, Bronchospasm by use of albuterol, and Oxygen requirement
      by continued oxygen administration to maintain SpO2&gt;92% for 2 hours postoperatively.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Retrospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of complications in PACU</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This project was aimed to identify the risk factors associated with the occurrence of respiratory complications in post anesthesia care unit. The primary outcome was the composite measure of occurrence of complications in PACU. The components were apnea or hypopnea, laryngospasm, bronchospasm and prolonged oxygen requirement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improve the quality of care for children undergoing anesthesia</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To improve the quality of care for children undergoing anesthesia in the United States by identifying preventable causes of anesthesia and surgery-related adverse events.
To use root cause analysis to investigate significant adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16000</enrollment>
  <condition>Anesthesia</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients who receive an anesthetic in participating institutions who are under 18
        years of age and where an anesthetic record is generated will be included in the overall
        statistics for each center
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        1) All patients who receive an anesthetic in participating institutions who are under 18
        years of age and where an anesthetic record is generated will be included in the overall
        statistics for each center  -

        Exclusion Criteria:

        1) Patients older than 18 years of age.-
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 4, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 4, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
