<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="104364">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02122861</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ID-LV305-2013-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02122861</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 1 Safety Study of Intradermal ID-LV305 in Patients With Locally Advanced, Relapsed or Metastatic Cancer Expressing NY-ESO-1</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Open-Label Clinical Trial Evaluating the Safety, Tolerability and Immunogenicity of Intradermally Administered ID-LV305 in Patients With Locally Advanced, Relapsed, or Metastatic Cancer Expressing NY-ESO-1</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Immune Design</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Immune Design</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1 multi-center study to evaluate the clinical safety and immune response of
      ID-LV305 when injected intradermally in patients with advanced cancer. ID-LV305 is a novel
      immunotherapy agent designed to target dendritic cells and stimulate the body's immune
      system to fight the spread and growth of cancer for patients whose tumors express the
      NY-ESO-1 protein. Patients with melanoma, sarcoma, ovarian cancer, breast cancer or
      non-small cell lung cancer that express NY-ESO-1 may be considered for the trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ID-LV305 is an agent designed to specifically target dendritic cells within the patient and
      induce them to stimulate and generate cytotoxic T cell responses against the NY-ESO-1
      protein, a molecule which is often expressed in certain types of cancer cells.  This is a
      first-in-human study of ID-LV305.  The primary purpose of the study is to determine what
      dose of ID-LV305 can be given safely to patients with advanced cancers that express NY-ESO-1
      protein.  ID-LV305 will be administered by intradermal injection every three weeks times
      three doses.  The study will have two phases.  In Part 1 Dose Escalation, three sequentially
      enrolled cohorts of patients will be treated at one of three dose levels of ID-LV305 using a
      standard escalation design.  Once the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) is established, Part 2
      Patient Expansion will begin using the highest safe dose level and the same treatment
      regimen.  Three cancer indications will be expanded to include at least six patients each to
      further examine safety and immunogenicity of the study agent.  This program was reviewed by
      the NIH Recombinant DNA Advisory Committee and received a recommendation that the Phase 1
      trial could proceed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years since first study injection</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of multiple ascending doses of intradermally (i.d.) administered ID-LV305 by assessing the number of participants experiencing AEs</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the cellular and humoral immunogenicity of multiple ascending doses of i.d. administered ID-LV305 by assessing the frequency of inducing or increasing responses in participants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Sarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ID-LV305</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose escalation and Expansion cohorts</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ID-LV305</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>ID-LV305</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Locally advanced, relapsed, and/or metastatic cancer with low or minimal tumor burden

          -  Tumor histology consistent with one of the following: breast cancer, melanoma,
             non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC), ovarian cancer or sarcoma

          -  Tumor specimen positive for NY-ESO-1 expression by IHC and/or RT-PCR

          -  If ovarian cancer, cancer antigen 125 (CA-125) must be ≥ 40 U/mL, or if melanoma, LDH
             must be ≤ ULN

          -  Inadequate response, relapse, and/or unacceptable toxicity with one or more prior
             systemic, surgical, or radiation cancer therapies, except patients with NSCLC and
             breast cancer who must have experienced either an inadequate response and/or
             unacceptable toxicity with two or more prior systemic, surgical, or radiation cancer
             therapies

          -  ≥ 18 years of age

          -  Life expectancy of ≥ 6 months per the investigator

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1

          -  ECG without evidence of clinically significant arrhythmia or ischemia

          -  If female of childbearing potential (FCBP), willing to undergo pregnancy testing and
             agrees to use at least one highly effective or two effective contraceptive methods
             during the dosing period and for three months after last ID-LV305 injection

          -  If male and sexually active with a FCBP, must agree to use highly effective
             contraception such as latex condom during the dosing period and for three months
             after last ID-LV305 injection

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Investigational therapy within 3 weeks prior to ID-LV305 dosing

          -  Prior administration of other NY-ESO-1-targeting immunotherapeutics

          -  Significant immunosuppression from:

               1. Concurrent, recent (≤ 4 weeks ago) or anticipated treatment with systemic
                  corticosteroids at any dose, or

               2. Other immunosuppressive medications such as methotrexate, cyclosporine,
                  azathioprine (antihistamines, non-steroidal anti- inflammatory drugs and aspirin
                  permitted) or conditions such as common variable hypogammaglobulinemia or
                  exposures such as large field radiotherapy

          -  Cancer therapies, including chemotherapy, radiation, biologics or kinase inhibitors,
             G-CSF or GM-CSF within 3 weeks prior to the first scheduled ID-LV305 dosing

          -  Psychiatric, other medical illness or other condition that in the opinion of the PI
             prevents compliance with study procedures or ability to provide valid informed
             consent

          -  Significant autoimmune disease with the exception of alopecia, vitiligo,
             hypothyroidism or other conditions that have never been clinically active and require
             no ongoing therapy

          -  Myocardial infarction within 6 months of study initiation, active cardiac ischemia or
             New York Heart Association (NYHA) Grade III or IV heart failure

          -  Inadequate organ function including:

               1. Marrow: Peripheral blood leukocyte count (WBC) &lt; 3000/mm3, absolute neutrophils
                  count ≤ 1500/mm3, platelets &lt; 75000/mm3, or hemoglobin &lt; 10 gm/dL

               2. Hepatic: alanine aminotransferase (ALT), and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt;
                  2.5 x ULN, total serum bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x ULN (patients with Gilbert's Disease
                  may be included if their total bilirubin is ≤ 3.0 mg/dL)

               3. Renal: Creatinine &gt; 1.5x ULN

               4. Other: INR (prothrombin time ratio) or partial thromboplastin time (PTT) &gt;1.5 x
                  ULN

          -  History of other cancer within 3 years (except non-melanoma cutaneous malignancies
             and cervical carcinoma in situ)

          -  Active tuberculosis or recent (&lt; 2 week ago) clinically significant infection or
             evidence of active hepatitis B, hepatitis C or HIV infection

          -  Uveal melanoma

          -  Brain metastases considered unstable as:

               1. Without confirmed stability over 60 days in patients previously treated with
                  prior surgery or radiation; OR

               2. Associated with symptoms and/or findings; OR

               3. Requiring corticosteroids or anticonvulsants in the prior 60 days

          -  Pregnancy or nursing
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Immune Design</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Immune Design</last_name>
    <phone>650-887-6703</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTrials@immunedesign.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06520</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana Farber Harvard Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nikki Weaver, RN</last_name>
      <phone>713-563-0509</phone>
      <email>ncweaver@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Diane Gravel, RN</last_name>
      <phone>713-563-6702</phone>
      <email>dgravel@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seattle Cancer Care Alliance</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Erica Peters</last_name>
      <phone>206-288-7551</phone>
      <email>phase1@uw.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 22, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
