<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="53819">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02127931</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCT01711372B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02127931</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Predictive Executive Functioning Models Using Interactive Tangible-Graphical Interface Devices in Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>Predictive Executive Functioning Models Using Interactive Tangible-Graphical Interface Devices in Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>CogCubed, Corp</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>CogCubed, Corp</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Current diagnostic aids used in treating ADHD are currently expensive, time intensive, and
      provide little information about accessory movements in response to a stimulus.

      Tests such as the Conners' Rating Scale require subjective responses from parents and
      teachers, making coordination difficult. The computerized Conners' Continuous Performance
      Test (CPT) provides objective data in regards to inattention and impulsive patterns of
      response. However, it does not provide data regarding accessory movements such as
      restlessness, hyperactivity, and other inappropriate movements. If the subject taking the
      exam has a reading disorder, it will impair his or her ability to respond accurately and it
      will increase response time. The T.O.V.A. is another computer based test used as a
      diagnostic aid for ADHD, which uses a microswitch to record responses. It does utilize
      auditory and visual stimuli, which removes the reading level limitation. However, it is
      unable to measure to measure accessory movements that may be contributing to reaction time
      and errors of omission and commission.

      Because of these limitations, a new company called CogCubed has created a new game based on
      the Sifteo Cube (http://www.sifteo.com) platform. These new hands-on digitized cubes are
      unique, motion-sensitive wireless blocks that contain multiple sensors that can interact
      with one another. CogCubed is providing the data for this study. The game will be played in
      a 30 minute sessions by subjects aged 18 and over. Subjects recruited to play the game will
      be those with ADHD and those without, matched by gender. Those with comorbidities of
      developmental delay, mental retardation, psychosis, schizophrenia, bipolar disorder and
      substance use disorders will be excluded, as well as any physiological disability that
      affects upper limb movement and/or coordination. Informed consent will be obtained from
      participant prior to administering the game.

      The hypothesis is that by analyzing data generated from this new gaming platform named
      Sifteo for which a game was created, which uses auditory and visual stimuli and distracters,
      the investigators expect that they will be able to provide a more accurate profile of
      impulsivity and inattention. The investigators expect that inattention will have more errors
      of omission and less tilt movements than control and impulsivity will be represented as more
      commission and greater tilting movements than control.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This trial builds on the previous results of our phase 1 trials in children ages 6-17 used
      to create the predictive algorithms to analyze the data and predict the likelihood of ADHD
      diagnosis based on patterns of game play behavior. Participants in this study will fill out
      the Toronto Alexithymia Scale (TAS), Interpersonal Reactivity Index (IRI), and the DSM IV
      Adult ADHD Checklist.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Omissions</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of visit, day one</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>No response by subject of hitting correct stimulus with another cube</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Commission</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of visit, day one</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Stimulus, wrong response exhibited by subject hitting an incorrect stimulus when the correct stimulus is being presented on another game cube</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hit Reaction Time Standard Deviation</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of visit, day one</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure of response speed consistency, calculated as standard deviation of reaction time that is measured in 1/5th's of a second</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Accuracy</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of visit, day one</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of correct responses to the pre-identified correct stimulus</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Detectability</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of visit, day one</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference between signal and noise disturbances measured as reaction time in 1/5th's of seconds</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Preservations</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of visit, day one</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Any reaction time less than 100ms is a perseverative response: a slow response to a preceding stimuli, random response, or response repeated without consideration for stimuli</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Response Style</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of visit, day one</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pattern of response such as is the pattern or response hesitant in general (lack of commissions). High on this indicates person avoids commissions. (Degree of tilt and pauses in tilt pattern to hit a cube measured as change in movement in cube in x, y and z axis measured in degree of change from zero).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Attention</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of visit, day one</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description># of responses to target stimulus (good responses) (ability to detect, evaluate and respond correctly).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hyperactivity</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of visit, day one</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tilt and length of time in tilt for any stimulus (correct or not). Tilt is measured as degree of change in x, y and z axis from zero.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Impulsivity</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of visit, day one</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description># responses to non-target stimulus (groundskeeper and grass) (responding without evaluating the stimulus).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Reaction Time</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of visit, day one</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Length of time has reaction to any stimulus measured in 1/5th's of a second.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Incorrect Reaction Time</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of visit, day one</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Average speed of incorrect response to identified stimulus, measured in 1/5th's of seconds</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Excess Movements</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of visit, day one</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Flips of cubes measured in tilt, clicks of the cube face): measure of hyperactivity- severity and length of time doing excess movements</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Video Game Diagnostic Tool</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Groundskeeper, a Video Game Diagnostic Tool for ADHD is administer to probands with ADHD and age, gender matched controls without ADHD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Groundskeeper</intervention_name>
    <description>Groundskeeper, a Video Game Diagnostic Tool for ADHD is administered to probands with ADHD and age, gender matched controls without ADHD.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Video Game Diagnostic Tool</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18+, males and females

          -  Individuals with ADHD

          -  Individuals without ADHD

          -  Depressive Disorders

          -  Anxiety Disorders

          -  High functioning Autism Spectrum Disorders

          -  Mood Disorders

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Under the age of 18
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Monika Heller, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CogCubed, Corp</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Macalester College</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Paul</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 28, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>CogCubed, Corp</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Monika Roots</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
