<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="23501">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02067013</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ML28894s</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02067013</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Analysis of Aqueous and Vitreous Humor</brief_title>
  <acronym>ARK</acronym>
  <official_title>Analysis of Vitreous and Aqueous Humor for Ocular Growth Factors, Cytokines, Chemokines, and Ranibizumab Pharmacokinetics Associated With Various Retinal Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>California Retina Consultants</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>California Retina Consultants</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Clinical Retina research studies often collect aqueous samples in hopes of estimating levels
      of drug or cytokines in the vitreous. Little is known about how well vitreous and aqueous
      correlate. This study will collect vitreous and aqueous samples at the same time to evaluate
      and compare drug and cytokine levels.

      The overall objective of this study is to evaluate the molecular concentration of growth
      factors, cytokines and chemokines in human aqueous humor and vitreous samples collected from
      individuals undergoing pars plana vitrectomy for tractional retinal detachment secondary to
      proliferative diabetic retinopathy, exudative or tractional retinal detachment secondary to
      macular degeneration, macular hole or neovascular glaucoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label, pilot study of intravitreally administered ranibizumab in subjects
      undergoing pars plana vitrectomy (PPV) to repair tractional retinal detachment secondary to
      proliferative diabetic retinopathy, exudative serous retinal detachment, macular hole or
      neovascular glaucoma.

      Consented, enrolled subjects will be eligible to receive a single open-label intravitreal
      injection of 0.5 mg ranibizumab administered prior to undergoing PPV if in the Retinal
      Specialists opinion there could be a benefit to the disease or procedure from ranibizumab
      therapy.

      The proposed study will analyze aqueous humor and vitreous samples drawn at the same time
      during vitrectomy to evaluate the levels of growth factors, cytokines and chemokines from
      patients undergoing planned pars plana vitrectomy as part of their retinal care. For
      patients receiving ranibizumab, serum samples will also be collected to assess PK. Patients
      will be split into three groups based on diagnosis: Group 1: (potential ranibizumab)
      proliferative diabetic retinopathy (tractional retinal detachment); Group 2: (potential
      ranibizumab) macular degeneration with exudative or tractional retinal detachment; and Group
      3: (no drug control) macular hole or neovascular glaucoma. Group 1 and Group 2 may receive
      one injection of intravitreal ranibizumab 0.5mg prior to vitrectomy.  The injection will be
      administered at least 1-14 days prior to vitrectomy. Group 3 will serve as the control group
      and will not receive intravitreal ranibizumab prior to surgery.

      Aqueous humor, vitreous and serum samples will be obtained to measure and compare growth
      factor, cytokine, chemokine levels and ranibizumab levels (if received).  Undiluted core
      vitreous biopsies will be taken at the start of victrectomy.  Aproximately 1 mL of undiluted
      vitreous fluid will be obtained with a closed infusion line and by manual aspiration with
      cutting on through the vitrectomy probe into a 2.5 mL syringe connected along the aspiration
      line.  The sample will be frozen immediately and stored at -80°C.

      Approximately 100 microliters of aqueous humor will be collected prior to the start of
      vitrectomy through anterior chamber paracentesis in the peripheral clear cornea using a 27
      gauge needle on a tuberculin microsyringe from the central papillary area.  Aqueous is
      transferred to a vial and placed in liquid nitrogen upon removal from the anterior chamber.
      Aqueous humor samples are immediately frozen at -80°C within 2 hours of collection until
      transferred to outside laboratories for further analysis.

      Serum samples will be obtained from patients in Group 1 and Group 2 at baseline (Day 0)
      prior to treatment with intravitreal ranibizumab and on the day of surgery prior to the
      start of vitrectomy. Serum samples will be processed according to Genentech standard
      operating procedures and samples will be frozen immediately at -80C until analysis is ready
      to begin.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cytokine Levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Collected at Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Growth factor, cytokine, chemokine , and ranibizumab  (if applicable) concentration in aqueous and vitreous samples collected during pars plana vitrectomy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Pharmacokinetics</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 14</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Serum pharmacokinetic levels following a single intravitreal ranibizumab injection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Proliferative Diabetic Retinopathy</condition>
  <condition>Macular Degeneration</condition>
  <condition>Macular Hole</condition>
  <condition>Neovascular Glaucoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ranibizumab</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ability to provide written informed consent and comply with study assessments for the
             full duration of the study

          -  Age &gt; 18 years

          -  Subjects with a diagnosis of tractional retinal detachment secondary to proliferative
             diabetic retinopathy, age-related macular degeneration with tractional or exudative
             retinal detachment, macular hole, epiretinal membrane, or neovascular glaucoma
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert L Avery, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>California Retina Consultants</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mel D Rabena, BS</last_name>
    <phone>805-963-1648</phone>
    <phone_ext>31</phone_ext>
    <email>mdrabena@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>California Retina Consultants - Santa Barbara Office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santa Barbara</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>93103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mel D Rabena, BS</last_name>
      <phone>805-963-1648</phone>
      <phone_ext>31</phone_ext>
      <email>mdrabena@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert L Avery, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ma'an A Nasir, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dante J Pieramici, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alessandro A Castellarin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert F See, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen S Couvillion, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nathan C Steinle, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dilsher S Dhoot, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 17, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>California Retina Consultants</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Robert Avery</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tractional retinal detachment</keyword>
  <keyword>Exudative retinal detachment</keyword>
  <keyword>Macular hole</keyword>
  <keyword>Neovascular glaucoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Retinopathy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma, Neovascular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Macular Degeneration</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinal Perforations</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinal Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
