<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="126137">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02007174</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CC-002-2011</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02007174</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bevacizumab Injection for Recurrent Pterygium</brief_title>
  <official_title>Triple Subconjunctival Bevacizumab Injection for Early Recurrent Pterygium. One Year Follow-up</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Instituto de Oftalmología Fundación Conde de Valenciana</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Council of Science and Technology, Mexico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Instituto de Oftalmología Fundación Conde de Valenciana</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Mexico: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Blockade of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) with bevacizumab has been used to
      treat abnormal vascular conditions of the anterior segment of the eye. In pterygium,
      anti-VEGF agents have been recently proposed as primary treatments, such as perioperative
      adjuvants, as well as treatments for pterygia recurrences after surgery. The aim of the
      present study was to prospectively evaluate the effect of three subconjunctival bevacizumab
      injections in patients with an early pterygium recurrence. Materials and Methods: The
      current study was a non-randomized single central trial. The method of ensuring allocation
      concealment was sequentially numbered. Patients with an early pterygium recurrence were
      selected and invited to participate in the study. Recurrence was defined as the presence of
      corneal vessels with concomitant conjunctival hyperemia within the first trimester after
      primary pterygium removal, and only patients with primary pterygium recurrence were
      included. Patient related factors such as pregnancy, women seeking to become pregnant, and
      lactating women were excluded from the study. All patients received three subconjunctival
      bevacizumab (2.5 mg/0.05 ml) injections (basal, 2 and 4 weeks) in the recurrence area of the
      pterygium, and were photographed at the third, sixth and twelfth months after the last
      bevacizumab injection. Photographic analyses were performed taking into account two
      pterygium areas: the first measure included only the vessel area in the corneal surface,
      while the second measure included, both, conjunctival and corneal vessel area
      (corneal-conjunctival area of hyperemia). Neovascularization area of each pterygium was
      determined using digital slit lam pictures, which were analyzed using Photoshop CS4, in
      order to get pixels measurements of the lesion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pterygium recurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evidence of vessel growth on both, corneal and conjunctival area after bevacizumab treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">38</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Pterygium</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bevacizumab injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Three subconjunctival intralesional injections of bevacizumab. Bevacizumab injections were 2.5 mg/0.05 ml, subconjunctivally applied near to the pterygium recurrence. Application of bevacizumab was performed three times: basal, 2 and 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bevacizumab</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Bevacizumab injection</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Avastin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with an early pterygium recurrence were selected and invited to participate
             in the study. Recurrence was defined as the presence of corneal vessels with
             concomitant conjunctival hyperemia within the first trimester after primary pterygium
             removal, and only patients with primary pterygium recurrence were included

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient related factors such as pregnancy, women seeking to become pregnant, and
             lactating women.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Angel Nava-Castañeda, MD, Msc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Ophthalmology, Conde de Valenciana Foundation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yonathan O Garfias, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Ophthalmology, Conde de Valenciana Foundation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Ophthalmology, Conde de Valenciana Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mexico, City</city>
        <state>Mexico City</state>
        <zip>06800</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 2, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>recurrent pterygium</keyword>
  <keyword>bevacizumab</keyword>
  <keyword>triple dose</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pterygium</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bevacizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
