<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="102407">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01770860</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ABDWDP0005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01770860</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Test of Different Kinds of Bandages on Healing of Wounds</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Assessment of QuiltVent™ Pad Technology on the Healing of Induced Dermabrasion Wounds</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johnson &amp; Johnson Consumer Products Company Division of Johnson &amp; Johnson Consumer Companies, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johnson &amp; Johnson Consumer and Personal Products Worldwide</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This two-week study will compare the healing of minor wounds when no bandage is applied
      against four different types of bandages.

      The study doctors will make five small wounds similar to scrapes (about a half-inch square)
      on the back of subjects who qualify to participate in the trial and have given informed
      consent.  Four of the wounds will be covered by different bandages and one will be left
      uncovered.  Participants will visit the clinic every day for 2 weeks or until all the wounds
      are healed (whichever comes first).  At the clinic, the bandages will be removed, the doctor
      will score the wounds, a picture will be taken of the wounds, and new bandages will be
      applied.

      It is expected that some pain and itching will be experienced, because they are part of the
      normal wound healing process.  Subjects will be asked about adverse events at each visit and
      will have the opportunity to discuss issues or concerns with the investigator or the doctor
      during the course of the trial.  It is expected that the wounds will be completely healed
      within 14 days, but if not, the participant will need to return to the clinic for follow-up
      treatment until the wounds are completely healed.

      We will see if the different bandages help with the healing of the wounds during the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is evaluating the performance of various bandages on facilitating the healing of
      induced dermabrasion wounds.  To qualify for this study, subjects must meet the
      inclusion/exclusion criteria within the protocol-specified parameters at both the screening
      and baseline visits.  Once a subject is qualified, five dermabrasion wounds will be created
      on each subject's back by a licensed physician.  Four of the wounds will be covered with
      four different commercially-available bandages and one wound will be left open to the air to
      serve as a no treatment control.  Treatments and control will be randomized to application
      site.  During this 14-day clinical study, subjects will return to the site for daily
      evaluations; study bandages will also be replaced daily by study personnel.  Adverse events
      will be observed and collected by querying each subject at each visit, and during any
      follow-up period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Healing (days)</measure>
    <time_frame>within 14 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Wound epithelialization will be recorded daily for each wound (until healed) by the doctor on a scale of 0-5, where 0= No presence of epithelialization (no sign of healing), a bandage is necessary and 5=Wound is 100% epithelialized (healed), no bandage necessary.  Time to healing is defined as the time from wounding to 12:00 pm of the day the wound is 100% epithelialized (receives a score of 5), and the median from the estimated survival curve will be calculated for each test product.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Appearance</measure>
    <time_frame>within 14 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The doctor will rank the overall appearance of all five wounds in relation to each other on a daily basis until all five are healed on a scale of 1 to 5, where 1= Worst and 5=Best</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Erythema</measure>
    <time_frame>within 14 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Until healed, erythema of each wound bed and surrounding skin will be scored daily on a scale of 0-10, where 0=None and 10=Most severe</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Edema</measure>
    <time_frame>within 14 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Until healed, edema of each wound bed and surrounding skin will be scored daily on a scale of 0-10, where 0=None and 10=Most severe</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maceration</measure>
    <time_frame>within 14 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Until healed, maceration (a slight whitening of the skin around the wound compared to the surrounding unbandaged area) will be scored as P=Present or A=Absent</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective Assessment of Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>within 14 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Until healed, pain assessments by the participant will be recorded daily for each wound site as either Present (P) or Absent (A)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective Assessment of Itch</measure>
    <time_frame>within 14 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Until healed, itch assessments by the participant will be recorded daily for each wound site as either Present (P) or Absent (A)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective Assessment of Wound Healing</measure>
    <time_frame>within 14 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Until healed, subjects will be shown photographs of each wound they have not previously classified as healed at each daily visit, and asked to determine if the wound is healed.  Yes or No responses will be recorded, along with text entries of the reasons for the response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Wound Healing</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is a single-arm trial.  Five dermabrasion wounds will be created on each subject's back by a licensed physician. Four of the wounds will be covered with four different commercially-available bandages (6660, 4314, 8336, and 4840),  and one wound will be left open to the air to serve as a no treatment control (0000).  Treatments and control will be randomized to application site.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>6660</intervention_name>
    <description>At each daily visit, designated study personnel will replace the specific test product on the assigned wound site.</description>
    <arm_group_label>All Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sheer Strips</other_name>
    <other_name>BAND-AID® with Quiltvent™ Pad Technology</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>4314</intervention_name>
    <description>At each daily visit, designated study personnel will replace the specific test product on the assigned wound site.</description>
    <arm_group_label>All Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Flexible Fabric</other_name>
    <other_name>BAND-AID® with Quiltvent™ Pad Technology</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>8336</intervention_name>
    <description>At each daily visit, designated study personnel will replace the specific test product on the assigned wound site.</description>
    <arm_group_label>All Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tough Strips® Waterproof</other_name>
    <other_name>BAND-AID® with Quiltvent™ Pad Technology</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>4840</intervention_name>
    <description>At each daily visit, designated study personnel will replace the specific test product on the assigned wound site.</description>
    <arm_group_label>All Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Flat Pad</other_name>
    <other_name>BAND-AID® Dora the Explorer™</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>0000</intervention_name>
    <description>At each daily visit, designated study personnel will cut out the center pad of the bandage and apply only the adhesive tabs around the assigned wound site.</description>
    <arm_group_label>All Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sheer Strips</other_name>
    <other_name>BAND-AID® with Quiltvent™ Pad Technology</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must be able to read and understand English enough to understand the nature,
             risk and relevance of the study, read and sign the informed consent document, and
             follow study instructions

          -  After being completely informed about the study and being given a chance to have all
             questions answered,  the subject has signed an informed consent document agreeing to:

          -  comply with lifestyle instructions, including:  limiting bandage exposure to water or
             sunlight, the use of lotions, creams, cosmetics or sunscreens during the study, to
             allow at least 2 hours between showers and scheduled visits, and the use of
             contraception

          -  return to the clinical site for follow-up visits if the wounds are not healed by Day
             14

          -  Subject is determined to be an appropriate participant according to protocol-defined
             conditions, including among other things, Body Weight and Fitzpatrick Skin Type
             between I (Always burns easily, never tans) and III (Burns moderately, tans
             gradually)

          -  In the opinion of the Investigator, participation in the trial will not compromise
             the subject's safety or the interpretation of study results

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medical condition or history, or use of drugs or treatments that could possibly
             compromise the safety of the research subject or the interpretation of results, per
             protocol or in the opinion of the investigator

          -  Known allergies or hypersensitivity to LATEX, anesthetics, adhesive bandages, wound
             treatment products or any component present in the test bandages

          -  Current participation in any other clinical trial or past participation in other
             clinical trials described in the protocol

          -  Body mass index (BMI) above 35, and/or Fitzpatrick Skin Type above III

          -  Pregnant, nursing or planning a pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clare Kendall</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Johnson &amp; Johnson Consumer Products Company Division of Johnson &amp; Johnson Consumer Companies, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hill Top Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Petersburg</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 15, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 16, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adhesive Bandages</keyword>
  <keyword>Dermabrasion Wounds</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
