<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="89114">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02003352</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CBC11013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02003352</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of PTSD in Military Veterans Who Have Suffered Traumatic Brain Injuries</brief_title>
  <acronym>PTSD-TBI</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Prospective Clinical Trial of PTSD in Military Veterans Who Have Suffered Traumatic Brain Injuries</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Carrick Institute for Graduate Studies</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Carrick Institute for Graduate Studies</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Treatment for veterans who have had a traumatic brain injury (TBI) and who are suffering
      from post traumatic stress syndrome (PTSD) is varied with varied outcomes.  Investigators
      will study PTSD treatment in military Veterans who have suffered traumatic brain injuries.
      Investigators will use 2 independent specialty treatment centers that utilize different
      methodology of PTSD treatments and study the clinical outcomes of  veterans who have
      suffered a TBI with associated post-concussive symptoms and other comorbidities such as
      PTSD.  Investigators hypothesize that the treatment of PTSD will have a better outcome with
      neurological physical and vestibular rehabilitation when compared to psychological or
      psychiatric therapy.  This study will use gold standard measurement scales and compare
      changes in the scales after treatment to evaluate the treatments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Department of Defense and the Defense and Veteran's Brain Injury Center estimate that
      22% of all combat casualties from conflicts in Iraq and Afghanistan are brain injuries.
      Patients with TBI often meet criteria for PTSD on screening instruments for TBI and vice
      versa.  No screening instruments available can reliably make the diagnosis of PTSD and the
      gold standard remains an interview by a skilled clinician using the Clinician-Administered
      PTSD Scale (CAPS) a 30-item structured interview that corresponds to the Diagnostic and
      Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders IV (DSM-IV) criteria for PTSD. Treatment for veterans
      who have had a TBI and who are suffering from PTSD is varied with varied outcomes.
      Investigators propose a Randomized Prospective Clinical Trial of PTSD treatment in military
      Veterans that have suffered traumatic brain injuries.  Investigators will use 2 independent
      specialty treatment centers that utilize different methodology of PTSD treatments and study
      the clinical outcomes of  veterans who have suffered a TBI with associated post-concussive
      symptoms and other comorbidities such as PTSD.  This study will use a baseline CAPS
      assessment and investigators will establish cut points and randomize from within those to
      establish a stratified randomization within groups.  Subjects will undergo treatments and an
      outcome CAPS score will be obtained at the end of treatment as the primary outcome to
      calculate if there is a change in score that is statistically or clinically significant.
      Investigators also will utilize secondary outcomes to measure any changes in the scores
      obtained by these instruments.  These instruments and measures such as the Minnesota
      Multiphasic Personality Inventory-2 (MMPI-2), Primary Care Post Traumatic Stress Syndrome
      Screen (PC-PTSD), Beck Depression Inventory and Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression,
      Computerized Dynamic Posturography and video electronystagmography and saccadometry will be
      obtained before the initiation of treatment and when treatment is terminated to measure a
      change in score.  All instruments will be used to measure changes in function that are
      related to changes in PTSD symptomatology and neurological function
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders IV Clinician-Administered PTSD Scale DSM IV-(CAPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>CAPS (a 30-item structured interview that corresponds to the DSM-IV criteria for PTSD).  Considered the Gold Standard for PTSD classification/diagnosis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Minnesota Multiphasic Personality Inventory-2 (MMPI-2)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Validated test that has the CAPS imbedded</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Primary Care Post Traumatic Stress Syndrome Screen (PC-PTSD)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A validated self administered scale that the subject can complete without an examiner.  Shows good relationship to CAPS-DSM IV outcome measures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A validated scale to measure depression (common in PTSD)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Computerized Dynamic Posturography</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A validated measure of whole body response to perturbation.  A standardized measure of brain body reflexogenic action</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Saccadometry</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurements of eye movements to laser targets</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>PTSD</condition>
  <condition>TBI</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Psychological Counselling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard neuropsychological batteries common in PTSD treatment administered by qualified practitioners</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Functional Neurological Rehabilitation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Functional Neurological and physical/vestibular rehabilitation strategies</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Functional Neurological Rehabilitation</intervention_name>
    <description>Functional Neurological Rehabilitation Includes vestibular rehabilitation and physical rehabilitation. Vestibular rehabilitation utilizes strategies that  involves movement of the head and eyes  at various speeds and directions  while the subject looks at a target. Physical rehabilitation involves exercises to increase mobility and increase strength.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Functional Neurological Rehabilitation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychological Counselling</intervention_name>
    <description>Psychological counselling Involves the interaction of the subject with a licensed psychologist/psychiatrist. A variety of techniques are utilized to empower the subject to be able to minimize conflict and maximize performance. This is a nonpharmaceutical intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Psychological Counselling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of PTSD

          -  History of Traumatic Brain Injury

          -  Military veteran of conflict in war zone

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Criminal history of violence
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Frederick R Carrick, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Carrick IGS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Frederick R Carrick, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>214-771-8885</phone>
    <email>drfrcarrick@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Carrick Brain Centers</name>
      <address>
        <city>Irving</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75062</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Frederick R Carrick, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joel B Brock, RN, MSN, DC</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cagen Randall, DC, DACNB</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jacob Shores, DC, DACNB</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andre Fredieu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 2, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Carrick Institute for Graduate Studies</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Frederick Carrick, PhD, FACCN</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TBI</keyword>
  <keyword>PTSD</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional Neurology</keyword>
  <keyword>Vestibular Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Dynamic Computerized Posturography</keyword>
  <keyword>Saccadometry</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
