<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="131301">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02129777</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>M1-1188_203</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1146-1219</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-002806-30</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02129777</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety of Namilumab (MT203) for Plaque Psoriasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multi-Centre, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Dose-Finding and Proof of Concept Study, to Assess the Efficacy, Safety and Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Namilumab/MT203 At 4 Different Subcutaneous Doses in Subjects With Moderate to Severe Chronic Plaque Psoriasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Canada: Biologics and Genetic Therapies Directorate, Health Canada</authority>
    <authority>Denmark: Danish Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Vaccines and Biomedicines</authority>
    <authority>Latvia: State Agency of Medicines</authority>
    <authority>Poland: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to establish proof of efficacy of namilumab in moderate to
      severe plaque psoriasis, measured as Psoriasis Area and Severity Index (PASI)75 response
      rate at week 12.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The drug being tested in this study is called namilumab. Namilumab is being tested to prove
      its effectiveness in treating moderate to severe chronic plaque psoriasis. This study will
      look at improvement of plaque psoriasis in people who take namilumab.

      The study will enroll approximately 100 patients. Participants will be randomly assigned (by
      chance, like flipping a coin) to one of the five treatment groups—which will remain
      undisclosed to the patient and study doctor during the study (unless there is an urgent
      medical need):

        -  Namilumab subcutaneous injection 300 mg Day 1, 150 mg Days 15, 43 and 71

        -  Namilumab subcutaneous injection 160 mg Day 1, 80 mg Days 15, 43 and 71

        -  Namilumab subcutaneous injection 100 mg Day 1, 50 mg Days 15, 43 and 71

        -  Namilumab subcutaneous injection 40 mg Day 1, 20 mg Days 15, 43 and 71

        -  Placebo (dummy inactive subcutaneous injection) - this is a liquid solution that looks
           like the study drug but has no active ingredient Days 1, 15, 43 and 71.

      This multi-centre trial will be conducted in North America and Europe. The overall time to
      participate in this study is up to 32 weeks. Participants will make 1 screening period
      visit, 6 treatment period visits, and 4 follow-up visits to the clinic.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants achieving an improvement in Psoriasis Area and Severity Index (PASI) score (reduction by ≥ 75%)  from Baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PASI is an index used to express the severity of psoriasis: it combines estimates on the severity of three features (erythema, induration and desquamation) and affected area of skin in each of four regions of the body (head/neck, arms/hands, chest/abdomen/back and buttocks/legs). Within each body region the area of skin involved is attributed a score from 0 - 6 (increasing involvement), and severity of the three clinical features rated on a scale from 0 to 4 (none to maximum) respectively. The total score ranges from 0 to 74 with higher scores indicating higher levels of disease. PASI75 denotes a 75% reduction of the PASI score from Baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants achieving an improvement in Psoriasis Area and Severity Index (PASI) scores ≥ 75% at each week assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 2, 4, 6, 10, 14, 18, 22, 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PASI is an index used to express the severity of psoriasis: it combines estimates on the severity of three features (erythema, induration and desquamation) and affected area of skin in each of four regions of the body (head/neck, arms/hands, chest/abdomen/back and buttocks/legs). Within each body region the area of skin involved is attributed a score from 0 - 6 (increasing involvement), and severity of the three clinical features rated on a scale from 0 to 4 (none to maximum) respectively. The total score ranges from 0 to 74, with higher scores indicating higher disease levels. PASI75 denotes a 75% reduction of the PASI score from Baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in PASI score at each week assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 2, 4, 6, 10, 12, 14, 18, 22, 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PASI is an index used to express the severity of psoriasis: it combines estimates on the severity of three features (erythema, induration and desquamation) and affected area of skin in each of four regions of the body (head/neck, arms/hands, chest/abdomen/back and buttocks/legs). Within each body region the area of skin involved is attributed a score from 0 - 6 (increasing involvement), and severity of the three clinical features rated on a scale from 0 to 4 (none to maximum) respectively. The total score ranges from 0 to 74, with higher scores indicating higher disease levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants achieving ≥ 2 point improvement in sPGA score, assessed (using a 6-point rating scale with range 0 = Clear to 5 = very severe) at all applicable post-baseline clinic visits</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 2, 4, 6, 10, 12, 14, 18, 22, 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>sPGA scoring determines psoriasis severity at a single point in time (based on erythema, plaque elevation and skin scaling for all lesions), assessed using a 6-point rating scale ranging from 0 = clear to 5 = very severe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants achieving static Physicians Global Assessment (sPGA) of clear or almost clear/minimal at each week assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 2, 4, 6, 10, 12, 14, 18, 22, 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>sPGA scoring determines psoriasis severity at a single point in time (based on erythema, plaque elevation and skin scaling for all lesions), assessed using a 6-point rating scale ranging from 0 = clear to 5 = very severe. A score of 0 or 1 indicates clear or almost clear/minimal.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants achieving an improvement in Psoriasis Area and Severity Index (PASI) scores ≥ 50% at each week assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 2, 4, 6, 10, 12, 14, 18, 22, 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PASI is an index used to express the severity of psoriasis: it combines estimates on the severity of three features (erythema, induration and desquamation) and affected area of skin in each of four regions of the body (head/neck, arms/hands, chest/abdomen/back and buttocks/legs). Within each body region the area of skin involved is attributed a score from 0 - 6 (increasing involvement), and severity of the three clinical features rated on a scale from 0 to 4 (none to maximum) respectively. The total score ranges from 0 to 74 with higher scores indicating higher disease activity. PASI50 denotes a 50% reduction of the PASI score from Baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants achieving an improvement in Psoriasis Area and Severity Index (PASI) scores ≥ 90% at each week assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 2, 4, 6, 10, 12, 14, 18, 22, 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PASI is an index used to express the severity of psoriasis: it combines estimates on the severity of three features (erythema, induration and desquamation) and affected area of skin in each of four regions of the body (head/neck, arms/hands, chest/abdomen/back and buttocks/legs). Within each body region the area of skin involved is attributed a score from 0 - 6 (increasing involvement), and severity of the three clinical features rated on a scale from 0 to 4 (none to maximum) respectively. The total score ranges form 0 to 74 with higher scores indicating higher levels of disease. PASI90 denotes a 90% reduction of the PASI score from Baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in affected body surface area (BSA) at each week assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 2, 4, 6, 10, 12, 14, 18, 22, 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) Dermal Itching at each week assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 2, 4, 6, 10, 12, 14, 18, 22, 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change between itch intensity measured at Baseline and at each week assessed. Participants will be asked to indicate their level of itching by making a mark on a line from 0 mm on the left (indicating no itching) to 100 mm on the right (indicating unbearable itching).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in VAS joint pain at each week assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 2, 4, 6, 10, 12, 14, 18, 22, 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change between joint pain intensity measured at each week assessed and joint pain intensity at baseline. Participants will be asked to indicate their level of joint pain by making a mark on a line from 0 mm on the left (indicating no joint pain) to 100 mm on the right (indicating unbearable joint pain).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in VAS morning stiffness at each week assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 2, 4, 6, 10, 12, 14, 18, 22, 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change between morning stiffness measured at each week assessed and morning stiffness intensity at baseline. Participants will be asked to indicate their level of morning stiffness by making a mark on a line from 0 mm on the left (indicating no morning stiffness) to 100 mm on the right (indicating unbearable morning stiffness).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 12 and 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The DQLI is a 10 item questionnaire to assess quality of life in patients with skin diseases. The scoring of each question is as follows: 3=Very much; 2=A lot; 1=A little; 0=Not at all. The DLQI is calculated by summing the score of each question resulting in a maximum of 30 and a minimum of 0. The higher the score, the more quality of life is impaired.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in score from Baseline in Short Form 36 Health Survey (SF-36)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12 and 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The SF-36 measures the impact of disease on overall quality of life and consists of 36 questions in eight domains (physical function, pain, general and mental health, vitality, social function, physical and emotional health). The individual domain scores are calculated and transformed to range from 0 to 100, with higher scores indicating a better level of functioning. A positive change from baseline score indicates an improvement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in score from Baseline in EuroQoL Health Questionnaire (EQ-5D)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 12 and 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The EuroQoL Questionnaire-5 Dimension (EQ-5D) is a generic, multidimensional, health-related, quality-of-life instrument. The profile allows participants to rate their health state in 5 health domains: mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and mood. The score ranges 0-100. The higher score indicates a better health state perceived by the participant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline for Nail Psoriasis Severity Index (NAPSI) at each week assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Weeks 2, 4, 6, 10, 12, 14, 18, 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The nails are graded for nail matrix psoriasis and nail bed psoriasis. The sum of these two scores is the total score for that nail. Per nail, the NAPSI score ranges from 0 (no nail psoriasis) to 4 (most severe nail psoriasis).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Plaque Psoriasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Namilumab 300 mg + namilumab 150 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Namilumab 300 mg (2 separate injections of 150 mg), subcutaneous injection, on Day 1, followed by namilumab 150 mg subcutaneous injection, on Days 15, 43 and 71.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Namilumab 160 mg + namilumab 80 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Namilumab 160 mg (2 separate injections of 80 mg), subcutaneous injection, on Day 1, followed by namilumab 80 mg subcutaneous injection, on Days 15, 43 and 71.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Namilumab 100 mg + namilumab 50 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Namilumab 100 mg (2 separate injections of 50 mg), subcutaneous injection, on Day 1, followed by namilumab 50 mg subcutaneous injection, on Days 15, 43 and 71.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Namilumab 40 mg + namilumab 20 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Namilumab 40 mg (2 separate injections of 20 mg), subcutaneous injection, on Day 1, followed by namilumab 20 mg subcutaneous injection, on Days 15, 43 and 71.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo (2 separate injections), subcutaneous injection, on Day 1, followed by placebo, subcutaneous injection, on Days 15, 43 and 71.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Namilumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Namilumab subcutaneous injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Namilumab 300 mg + namilumab 150 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Namilumab 160 mg + namilumab 80 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Namilumab 100 mg + namilumab 50 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Namilumab 40 mg + namilumab 20 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MT203</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo subcutaneous injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Is male or female aged 18 to 70 years, inclusive.

          2. Is suffering from active but clinically stable plaque psoriasis (for at least 12
             months) involving ≥10% of their body surface area, Psoriasis Area and Severity Index
             (PASI) score ≥12, and a minimum score of 3 with the 6-point static Physician's Global
             Assessment  (sPGA) rating scale used in this study.

          3. Must have been a candidate for, or have received, ≥1 phototherapy or systemic
             psoriasis therapy.

          4. A male participant who is non-sterilized and sexually active with a female partner of
             childbearing potential agrees to use adequate contraception from signing of the
             informed consent throughout the duration of the study and for 12 weeks after last
             dose of study medication.

          5. A female participant of childbearing potential who is sexually active with a
             non-sterilized male partner agrees to routinely use adequate contraception from
             signing of the informed consent throughout the duration of the study and for 12 weeks
             after last dose of study medication.

          6. In the opinion of the investigator, is capable of understanding and complying with
             protocol requirements.

          7. The participant or, when applicable, the participant's legally acceptable
             representative signs and dates a written informed consent form and any required
             privacy authorization prior to the initiation of any study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has received any investigational agent during an interval equivalent to 5 half- lives
             for that agent prior to the study Baseline clinic visit, or is participating / plans
             to participate in any other clinical trial during this study.

          2. Has received namilumab, any other Granulocyte-Macrophage Colony-Stimulating Factor
             (GM-CSF) / GM-CSF receptor or granulocyte stimulating factor (G-GSF) signaling
             inhibitor either in a previous clinical study or as a therapeutic agent.

          3. Is required to take excluded medications.

          4. Has a history of hypersensitivity or allergies to namilumab or any of the contents of
             the formulation.

          5. Has other forms of psoriasis (eg drug-induced psoriasis, pustular, erythrodermic,
             exfoliative, inverse and/or guttate psoriasis).

          6. Evidence of skin conditions other than psoriasis (eg, eczema) at the time of the
             Screening clinic visit, or between the Screening visit and study drug initiation,
             that would interfere with evaluations of the effect of investigational product on
             psoriasis.

          7. Has a history or evidence of a clinically significant disorder (including but not
             limited to cardiopulmonary, oncologic, renal, metabolic, hematologic or psychiatric),
             condition or disease that, in the opinion of the investigator and Takeda physician
             would pose a risk to participant safety or interfere with the study evaluation,
             procedures or completion.

          8. Has a clinically relevant decrease in partial pressure of oxygen in the blood (PaO2)
             &lt; 90% saturation at Screening - as measured by pulse oximetry at rest.

          9. Has findings consistent with pulmonary disease on chest X-ray, including sarcoidosis,
             up to three months prior to Screening.

         10. History of clinically significant interstitial lung disease - eg chronic or recurrent
             pulmonary infection where macrophages are important for the clearance of the
             infection (such as pneumocystis carinii pneumonia, allergic bronchopulmonary
             aspergillosis, nocardia infections, Actinomyces infection).

         11. Presence or history of active tuberculosis (TB) or latent TB infection, where no
             anti-TB treatment has been given or where successful completion of an appropriate
             course of anti-TB therapy cannot be documented.

         12. A positive QuantiFERON-TB Gold test and / or evidence of active or latent TB by chest
             X- ray, not accompanied by initiation of an approved regimen of anti-TB therapy at
             least 12 weeks prior to the Baseline clinic visit.

         13. Has a history of severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and / or history
             of severe COPD exacerbation(s), or a history of asthma with exacerbations requiring
             hospitalization, within the last 12 months prior to the Screening visit.

         14. History of methotrexate treatment-associated lung toxicity.

         15. Has a history of cancer within the last 5 years except for adequately managed basal
             cell or squamous cell carcinomas of the skin.

         16. Has a history of treatment with anti-cancer chemotherapy (e.g. alkylating agents,
             anti-metabolites, purine analogues) and/or monoclonal antibodies, or has received
             GM-CSF / G-CSF treatment associated with chemotherapy within the last 5 years.

         17. Has an underlying condition that predisposes to infections (eg immunodeficiency,
             history of poorly controlled diabetes, splenectomy).

         18. Has any clinically significant illness within 4 weeks prior to the first dose of
             study medication or during the study - including acute or chronic infectious disease,
             which may influence the outcome of the study.

         19. Has a known history of infection with hepatitis B virus, hepatitis C virus, or human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV), or has serological findings at the Screening visit
             which indicate active or latent hepatitis B, hepatitis C or HIV infection.

         20. Has, in the judgment of the investigator, clinically significant abnormal clinical
             laboratory parameters at Screening.

         21. Has a history of drug abuse (defined as any illicit drug use), or a history of
             alcohol abuse within 2 years prior to the Screening visit.

         22. Any other condition that, in the judgment of the investigator, might cause this study
             to be detrimental to the participant's health.

         23. If female, is (a) pregnant / lactating / intending to become pregnant before or
             within the period of 12 weeks immediately after receiving the last dose of study
             medication; (b) intending to donate ova during this time period.

         24. Intends to donate sperm during the course of this study or within a period of 12
             weeks after receiving the last dose of study medication.

         25. Is an immediate family member, study site employee, or is in a dependent relationship
             with a study site employee involved in conduct of this study (eg, spouse, parent,
             child, sibling), or may consent under duress.

             -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director, Clinical Science</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Takeda Study Registration Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>800-778-2860</phone>
    <email>medicalinformation@tpna.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
