<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="132674">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01731678</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E-24656</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01731678</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation for Adolescent Depression</brief_title>
  <acronym>TMSAD</acronym>
  <official_title>Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation for Adolescent Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Calgary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Calgary</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Major depression (or MDD) in adolescents is a major public health problem. MDD affects
      approximately 15% of adolescents; it is associated with impairment in social, family, and
      academic functioning, and it is a major risk factor for suicide - a leading cause of death
      in adolescents . Unfortunately, there is a paucity of treatment options for this age group.
      Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) are the only class of medications approved
      for treating MDD in adolescents, but rates of remission following treatment with SSRIs are
      only 30 to 45 percent. Cognitive behavior therapy is associated with similar remission rates
      and access is limited. Most adolescents will require more than one therapeutic intervention
      in order to achieve full symptom control. Collectively, there is overwhelming evidence that
      additional treatment options are urgently needed to improve outcomes for teens with MDD. One
      novel treatment for adolescent MDD is repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS).
      Studies in children have been limited (a total of 23 cases). This is surprising given the
      evidence suggesting younger adult subjects with MDD respond better to rTMS (56% response
      rate) than older subjects. This limited experience with rTMS for adolescent MDD represents a
      substantial gap in the knowledge, recently recognized in publications calling for further
      study of rTMS in adolescent depression. Most importantly, the mechanism of action of rTMS in
      adolescent MDD is not well understood. The objective of this application is to develop an
      understanding of the brain alterations associated with the positive clinical changes that
      occur with rTMS in adolescent MDD. Such knowledge will provide the basis for pursuing rTMS
      for adolescent MDD as a rational therapeutic technique.

      Specific Aim: To compare the effect of rTMS on DLPFC glutamate concentration in adolescent
      MDD. The investigators hypothesize an increase (normalization to controls) in DLPFC
      glutamate after three weeks of rTMS. Furthermore, the change in glutamate concentration will
      correlate with a change in MDD symptoms.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hamilton Depression Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Three weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A reduction of Hamilton Depression Rating Scale score of 50% is considered positive response</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Interim Analysis - rTMS tolerability scale</measure>
    <time_frame>After the first 10 patients are completed</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>There will be an interim analysis to review safety, tolerability (as measured by our rTMS tolerability scale) after the first 10 rTMS patients. Should there be significant concerns, the team will terminate the study. Ten was selected as it is close to previous reports and should be informative.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Interim Analysis - Ham-D</measure>
    <time_frame>After the first 10 patients are completed</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>There will be an interim analysis to review response (Ham-D) after the first 10 rTMS patients. Should there be significant concerns, the team will terminate the study. Ten was selected as it is close to previous reports and should be informative.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The standardized treatment location will be the left DLPFC. Anatomical T1 images from the pre-intervention MRI will be loaded into our Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS) lab neuronavigation software (Brainsight2, Rogue Research, Montreal). Following 3D co-registration of the TMS coil with the patient's MRI images and head, the coil will be placed over the left DLPFC (tangential to scalp, angle of 45 degrees to midline). Interventional repetitive TMS (rTMS) (Magstim Rapid2, Wales, UK) will consist of 40 suprathreshold (120% RMT) pulses over 4 seconds (10 Hz) with an inter-train interval of 26 seconds. Treatment sessions will last 37.5 minutes (75 trains/3000 pulses). Treatments will occur on each weekday for three weeks (15 days total).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>The standardized treatment location will be the left DLPFC. Anatomical T1 images from the pre-intervention MRI will be loaded into our Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS) lab neuronavigation software (Brainsight2, Rogue Research, Montreal). Following 3D co-registration of the TMS coil with the patient's MRI images and head, the coil will be placed over the left DLPFC (tangential to scalp, angle of 45 degrees to midline). Interventional repetitive TMS (rTMS) (Magstim Rapid2, Wales, UK) will consist of 40 suprathreshold (120% RMT) pulses over 4 seconds (10 Hz) with an inter-train interval of 26 seconds. Treatment sessions will last 37.5 minutes (75 trains/3000 pulses). Treatments will occur on each weekday for three weeks (15 days total).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age (12-22 years),

          -  MDD failing to respond to at least one SSRI trial (minimum 8 weeks treatment at an
             adequate dose; determined retrospectively), and

          -  informed consent. Healthy controls with no psychiatric history (who do not receive
             rTMS) will undergo MRI scans to allow for comparison with MDD patients.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  previous seizures or epilepsy,

          -  hypertension,

          -  additional neurological or psychiatric diagnoses (specifically: bipolar disorder,
             psychosis, pervasive developmental disorder, eating disorders, and post-traumatic
             stress disorder).

        As 3T MRI will be used, pregnancy is exclusionary.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Frank P MacMaster, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Calgary</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Frank P MacMaster, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>403-955-2784</phone>
    <email>fmacmast@ucalgary.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alberta Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T3B 6A8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Frank P MacMaster, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>403-955-2784</phone>
      <email>fmacmast@ucalgary.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 21, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 3, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Calgary</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Frank MacMaster, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Cuthbertson and Fischer Chair in Paediatric Mental Health</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
