<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="52021">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01960530</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Infacort 002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01960530</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Investigational Study of Hydrocortisone</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single Centre, Open Label, Partially Randomised, Single Dose, Crossover Study to Build a Model of Hydrocortisone Metabolism and Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics, Oral Bioavailability and Relationship to Metabolic Parameters of Hydrocortisone and Infacort® in Healthy Adult Male Volunteers.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Diurnal Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Simbec Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Diurnal Limited</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will investigate a new drug called Infacort®; a newly-developed immediate release
      formulation of a well-established drug called hydrocortisone. Hydrocortisone is used as a
      replacement treatment for people whose adrenal glands are not producing enough natural
      cortisol - a condition known as adrenal insufficiency.  The study will assess how Infacort®
      acts once inside the body, by measuring cortisol and other hormone levels in the body,
      compared to already marketed hydrocortisone tablet and hydrocortisone intravenous (through
      the vein) injection.

      The population who are eligible to take part in the study are healthy male volunteers, aged
      between 18 and 60 years of age.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will evaluate the normal physiology, PK and metabolism of cortisol, investigate
      the PK and bioavailability of cortisol from the test Infacort® Granules (hydrocortisone) and
      the reference hydrocortisone tablets and i.v injection in healthy adult male volunteers and
      explore the role of cortisol in the regulation of metabolic pathways.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the absolute bioavailability of cortisol from Infacort® Granules and Hydrocortisone Tablets using Intra-Venous (i.v) Hydrocortisone as the reference Injection.</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples on Day 1 and/or Day 2 of each Study Period</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Derived PK for Serum Cortisol:
Non-compartmental Analysis - All Study Periods: Maximum serum concentration (Cmax), time to Cmax (tmax), elimination rate constant (λz), terminal elimination half life (t½), area under the concentration-time curve (AUC) from the time of dosing to the time of the last observed concentration (AUC0-t last) and extrapolated to infinity (AUC0-inf), area under the first moment curve (AUMC), clearance (CL/F), mean residence time (MRT) and mean absorption time (MAT)
Compartmental Analysis - i.v Hydrocortisone Injection: beta t½, AUC, CL/F, MRT, volume of distribution (Vd) at steady state (Vss/Vdss), of the central compartment (Vc) and during the elimination phase (Vz/Vd area).
Compartmental Analysis - Infacort® Granules &amp; Hydrocortisone Tablets: Cmax, tmax, t½, AUC, MRT, AUMC, and MAT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the comparative bioavailability of cortisol from Infacort® Granules with the reference Hydrocortisone Tablets.</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples on Day 1 and/or Day 2 of each Study Period</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Following logarithmic transformation of Cmax, AUC0-t and AUC0-∞ cortisol values, data from periods 3, 4 and 5 data will be subjected to a mixed effects analysis of variance (ANOVA) including a fixed effect for treatment and a random effect for subject. Point estimates and 90% confidence intervals will be constructed for the contrasts between treatments using the residual mean square error obtained from the ANOVA. The point and interval estimates will then be back-transformed to give estimates of the ratios of the geometric least squares means and corresponding 90% confidence intervals. In addition, estimated geometric means and will be produced for each treatment group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the safety and tolerability of Infacort Granules and hydrocortisone throughout the study.</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1-2 during each Study Period</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse events (AEs), routine laboratory assessments (haematology, biochemistry and urinalysis), vital signs (systolic and diastolic blood pressure, pulse rate, respiratory rate and oral body temperature) and 12-lead ECG (heart rate, PR interval, QRS duration, QT interval and QTcB interval).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the concentrations of cortisol binding protein and its relationship to calculated free cortisol and cortisol plasma/saliva ratios under physiological conditions and after the administration of dexamethasone and hydrocortisone.</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples on Day 1 and/or Day 2 of each Study Period</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Cortisol Protein Binding: Serum ALB, CBG and Free cortisol.
Free Cortisol Index:  The measurement of serum cortisol will also be used to calculate the free cortisol index (FCI).  This will be calculated as:
Total Cortisol = CFree + CALB + CCBG
Where CFree = free cortisol, CALB = cortisol bound to ALB and CCBG = cortisol bound to CBG.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the normal physiology of cortisol and the relationship between cortisol and insulin sensitivity under physiological conditions and after administration of dexamethasone and Infacort®, Hydrocortisone Tablets and i.v Hydrocortisone.</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples on Day 1 and/or Day 2 of each Study Period</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A standardised mixed meal elevates blood glucose and provides a reproducible stimulation of insulin release. Assessment of the response will be determined by calculation of Cmax and AUC0-4 of glucose and insulin in the 4 hours following ingestion of the mixed meal. Comparison will be made of both the Cmax as well as AUC across the differing interventions. Lower levels of insulin secretion, whilst maintaining normoglycaemia would indicate enhanced insulin sensitivity and glucose disposal; higher insulin levels will reflect insulin resistance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the pharmacokinetics (PK) and metabolism of cortisol under physiological conditions and after administration of dexamethasone and Infacort® Granules, Hydrocortisone Tablets and i.v Hydrocortisone Injection.</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood, urine &amp; saliva samples on Day 1 and/or Day 2 of each Study Period</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood: Serum cortisol (same data as collected for derived PK calculations), cortisone.
Saliva: Salivary cortisol Urine: Urinary steroid metabolites.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To explore the role of cortisol in regulation of metabolic pathways.</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples on Day 1 and/or Day 2 of each Study Period</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Exploratory Investigation: Plasma metabolome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Adrenal Insufficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Endogenous Cortisol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No Study medication will be given during this study period, however various blood, urine and saliva samples will be taken in order to measure normal levels of hormones and other chemicals at several time-points.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>1mg Dexamethasone will be administered at 22:00 on Day 1 and at 06:00 and 12:00 on Day 2. Various blood, urine and saliva samples will be taken in order to measure normal levels of hormones and other chemicals at several time-points.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Infacort®</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>20mg Infacort® will be administered on Day 2 at 07:00. Dexamethasone is a challenge agent and will be taken to suppress endogenous Adrenocorticotropic Hormone(ACTH)and Cortisol. 1mg Dexamethasone will be administered at 22:00 on Day 1 and 06:00 and 12:00 on Day 2. Various blood, urine and saliva samples will be taken in order to measure normal levels of hormones and other chemicals at several time-points.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hydrocortisone Tablet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>20mg Hydrocortisone Tablet will be administered on Day 2 at 07:00. Dexamethasone is a challenge agent and will be taken to suppress endogenous ACTH and Cortisol. 1mg Dexamethasone will be administered at 22:00 on Day 1 and 06:00 and 12:00 on Day 2. Various blood, urine and saliva samples will be taken in order to measure normal levels of hormones and other chemicals at several time-points.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>i.v Hydrocortisone Injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>20mg i.v. Hydrocortisone Injection will be administered on Day 2 at 07:00.  Dexamethasone is a challenge agent and will be taken to suppress endogenous ACTH and Cortisol. 1mg Dexamethasone will be administered at 22:00 on Day 1 and 06:00 and 12:00 on Day 2. Various blood, urine and saliva samples will be taken in order to measure normal levels of hormones and other chemicals at several time-points.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Infacort</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Infacort®</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydrocortisone Tablet</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Hydrocortisone Tablet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>i.v. Hydrocortisone Injection</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>i.v Hydrocortisone Injection</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy male volunteers between 18 and 60 years of age, inclusive (at screening).

          -  Subjects with a Body Mass Index (BMI) of 21-28. Body Mass Index = Body weight (kg) /
             (Height (m)2.

          -  Subjects with no clinically significant abnormal serum biochemistry, haematology and
             urinalysis values within 14 days prior to Day 1 of Study Period 1.

          -  Subjects with a negative urinary drugs of abuse screen, determined within 14 days
             prior to Day 1 of Study Period 1. A positive alcohol test may be repeated at the
             discretion of the Investigator.

          -  Subjects with negative HIV and Hepatitis B and C results.

          -  Subjects with no clinically significant abnormalities in 12-lead electrocardiogram
             (ECG) determined within 14 days prior to Day 1 of Study Period 1.

          -  Subjects with no clinically-significant deviation outside the normal ranges for blood
             pressure and pulse measurements.

          -  Subjects (unless anatomically sterile or where abstaining from sexual intercourse is
             in line with the preferred and usual lifestyle of the subject) and sexual partners
             must use effective contraception methods during the trial and for 3 months after the
             last dose, for example:

               -  Oral contraceptive + condom

               -  Intra-uterine device (IUD) + condom

               -  Diaphragm with spermicide + condom

          -  Subjects must be available to complete the study.

          -  Subjects must satisfy a medical examiner about their fitness to participate in the
             study.

          -  Subjects must provide written informed consent to participate in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A clinically significant history of gastrointestinal disorder likely to influence
             drug absorption.

          -  Receipt of regular medication within 14 days prior to Day 1 of Study Period 1
             (including high dose vitamins, dietary supplements or herbal remedies).

          -  Receipt of any vaccination within 14 days prior to Day 1 of Study Period 1.

          -  Evidence of renal, hepatic, central nervous system, respiratory, cardiovascular or
             metabolic dysfunction.

          -  Presence of clinically significant infections (systemic fungal and viral infections,
             acute bacterial infections).

          -  Current or previous history of tuberculosis.

          -  A clinically significant history of previous allergy / sensitivity to Hydrocortisone
             and/or Dexamethasone.

          -  A clinically significant history or family history of psychiatric
             disorders/illnesses.

          -  A clinically significant history of drug or alcohol abuse.

          -  Inability to communicate well with the Investigator (i.e., language problem, poor
             mental development or impaired cerebral function).

          -  Participation in a New Chemical Entity clinical study within the previous 4 months or
             a marketed drug clinical study within the previous 3 months.  (N.B.  The  washout
             period between trials is defined as the period of time elapsed between the last dose
             of the previous study and the first dose of the next study)

          -  Subjects who have consumed more than 2 units of alcohol per day within seven (7) days
             prior to Day 1 of Study Period 1or have consumed any alcohol within the 48 hour
             period prior to Day 1 of Study Period 1.

          -  Donation of 450ml or more of blood within the previous 3 months.

          -  Subjects who smoke (or ex-smokers who have smoked within 6 months prior to Day 1 of
             Study Period 1).

          -  Subjects who work shifts (i.e. regularly alternate between days, afternoons and
             nights).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Simbec Research Limited</name>
      <address>
        <city>Merthyr Tydfil</city>
        <zip>CF48 4DR</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.simbec.com/volunteers</url>
    <description>Volunteer Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adrenal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Addison Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cortisol succinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone 17-butyrate 21-propionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone 21-phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone-17-butyrate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
