<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="114431">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02066467</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Rally X4-10-2013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02066467</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Maximizing CRT Delivery by Using MultipolAr Coronary Sinus Lead FamiLy ACUITY® X4 - RALLY X4 Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>RallyX4</acronym>
  <official_title>Maximizing CRT Delivery by Using Multipolar Coronary Sinus Lead Family ACUITY® X4</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Guidant Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aptiv Solutions</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Guidant Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Ethikkommission / Medizinische Fakultät/ Otto-von-Guericke-Universität/ Magdeburg</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to collect clinical data on safety and performance of ACUITY
      X4® leads when used in a standard clinical setting.

      It is a prospective, non-randomized, observational multicenter study evaluating standard of
      care.

      For Post Market Clinical Follow up (PMCF) purposes the 3 month implant success rate, adverse
      events and basic parameters of the lead will be assessed. The cohort of subjects included in
      this evaluation will be the first 200 subjects which are indicated for PMCF in Rally X4 to
      receive an ACUITY X4® lead implant.

      Study endpoints:

      Phrenic Nerve Stimulation (PNS) related CFR through 6 months post-implant (Defined as: rate
      of freedom from loss of function or operative system revision due to unacceptable PNS
      threshold) Lead-related Complication-Free Rate (CFR) from Implant through 3 months
      post-implant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Clinic visits will occur at:

        -  Enrollment and Consenting Clinic Visit (≤ 30 days prior to implant procedure)

        -  Implant Procedure (Day 0; all future follow ups based on this date)

        -  Pre-Discharge Clinic Visit (≤ 7 days post implant procedure) (Required)

        -  One to 6 Month Clinic Visit (20 to 180 days post implant procedure) (Required)

        -  Interim Visit(s) (Any time between the 1 to 6 Month Clinic Visit and Close-out Clinic
           Visit) (Following study center specific standard of care) (Device follow up optional)
           AE - reporting required

        -  Close-out Clinic Visit (30 months ± 90 days,  OR 180 days ± 90 days after the study is
           closed to enrollment, whichever comes first) (Required)

        -  During the trial all AEs, deaths, and changes in the device system must be reported

        -  Devices of subjects who have received a Latitude device will be followed by the Boston
           Scientific (BSC) Latitude team. Device Data as defined in the Clinical Investigation
           Plan (CIP), device alerts, and diagnostic data from the standard Latitude database may
           be collected and entered into the study database at any time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>12 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phrenic Nerve Complication Free Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>median follow up 12 month, a minimum of 6 month and a maximum of 30 month depending of point of enrolment.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PNS related CFR through 6 months post-implant is greater than the pre-specified performance goal of 94%.
• The PNS related CFR will be calculated as the proportion of implanted subjects with no PNS related complications reported through follow-up. The null hypothesis will be rejected and the endpoint considered met if the lower 95% confidence bound for the proportion of subjects with no PNS related complication is greater than 94%.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3 month Lead-related Complication-Free Rate (CFR)</measure>
    <time_frame>After last patient compleated 1 - 6 month follow up visit window post implant.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Lead-related Complication-Free Rate (CFR) from implant through 3 months post-implant is greater than the pre-specified performance goal of 86%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>3 month Implant success rate for indicated subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>Analysis of first 200 data sets of indicated patients which compleated a 3 month follow up(+/- 30 day) window</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Post Market Clinical Follow-up of the ACUITY X4® lead will be evaluated in this study.  The outcome of interest will be the 3 month implant success rate. The cohort of subjects included in this evaluation will be the first 200 subjects to receive an ACUITY X4® lead implant and meet the PMCF eligibility criteria outlined below. The outcomes of interest for the PMCF supplemental analysis will be the percent of subjects successfully implanted with an ACUITY X4® lead.
Implant success - is defined as the ability of the ACUITY X4® lead to be implanted and deliver CRT therapy. Subjects who have multiple lead implant attempts during the procedure, but are eventually successfully implanted with the ACUITY X4® lead and receive CRT therapy will be classified as a successful implant.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Heartfailure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Heart failure patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects with art failure who receive stable optimal pharmacologic therapy
Moderate to severe heart failure (NYHA Class III-IV) with ejection fraction (EF) ≤ 35% and QRS duration ≥ 120 ms
Left bundle branch block (LBBB) with QRS duration ≥ 130 ms, EF ≤ 30%, and mild (NYHA Class II) ischemic or non-ischemic heart failure or asymptomatic (NYHA Class I) ischemic heart failure.
The study is collecting observational data on regular CRT-D device implants with special focus on the left ventricular ACUITY X4® Lead Family' .</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Left Ventricular lead implant: ACUITY X4® Lead Family</intervention_name>
    <description>Implantation of (cardiac re-synchronization therapy with defibrillator) CRT-D devices for heartfailure treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Heart failure patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Autogen™X4 CRT-D G179-200 G177-200</other_name>
    <other_name>Dynagen™ X4 CRT-D G158-200 G156-200</other_name>
    <other_name>Inogen™ X4 CRT-D G148-200 G146-200</other_name>
    <other_name>Origen™ X4 CRT-D G058-200 G056-200</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The BSC Cardiac Resynchronization Therapy Defibrillators (CRT-Ds) are indicated for
        subjects with art failure who receive stable optimal pharmacologic therapy (OPT) for heart
        failure and who meet any one of the following classifications:

          -  Moderate to severe heart failure (New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III-IV)
             with ejection fraction (EF) ≤ 35% and QRS duration ≥ 120 ms

          -  Left bundle branch block (LBBB) with QRS duration ≥ 130 ms, EF ≤ 30%, and mild (NYHA
             Class II) ischemic or non-ischemic heart failure or asymptomatic (NYHA Class I)
             ischemic heart failure BSCCRT-Ds are also intended to provide ventricular
             antitachycardia pacing and ventricular defibrillation for automated treatment of
             life-threatening ventricular arrhythmias.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject is willing and capable of providing informed consent

          2. Subject is planned to be implanted with an ACUITY X4® lead  for left-ventricular
             pacing and sensing via the coronary venous system in conjunction with a compatible
             BSC pulse generator

          3. Subject is willing and capable of participating in all visits associated with this
             study at an approved clinical study center and at the intervals defined by this CIP

          4. Subject is age 18 or above, or of legal age to give informed consent specific to
             state and national law

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects with a hypersensitivity to a maximum single dose of 0.51 mg dexamethasone
             acetate

          2. Subject is enrolled in any other concurrent study without prior written approval from
             BSC, with the exception of local mandatory governmental registries and observational
             studies/registries that are not in conflict and do not affect the following:

               -  Schedule of procedures for the RALLY X4 Study (i.e. should not cause additional
                  or missed visits);

               -  RALLY X4 Study outcome (i.e. involve medications that could affect the heart
                  rate of the subject);

               -  Conduct of the RALLY X4 Study per GCP/ ISO 14155:2011/ local regulations as
                  applicable

          3. Per the implanting physician's discretion, the subject is not a suitable candidate to
             receive the study device as determined during the implant procedure

          4. Women of childbearing potential who are or might be pregnant at the time of study
             enrollment or ACUITY X4® lead implant.

          5. Subject is unwilling or unable to participate in all scheduled study follow up visits
             at an approved study center

          6. Subject does not anticipate being a resident of the area for the scheduled duration
             of the trial

          7. Subject's physician does not allow participation

             -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Torsten Kayser, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Guidant Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Guidant Europe SA / NV a Boston Scientific Company</name>
      <address>
        <city>Diegem</city>
        <zip>1831</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Torsten Kayser, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+32-473-877020</phone>
      <email>torsten.kayser@bsci.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Michal Berlinski, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+48 22 594 44 76</phone>
      <email>Michal.Berlinski@aptivsolutions.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Haran Burri, Prof</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 17, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 7, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Phrenic Nerve Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Heartfailure treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>CRT-D therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Quadripolar lead</keyword>
  <keyword>Lead related complication free rate</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
