<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="122852">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02094872</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-184</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-00670</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>WIRB Pro #20140190</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>WO #1-822810-1</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>Invest #161467</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>Study #1144561</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-184</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA022453</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02094872</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Molecularly Targeted Therapy in Treating Patients With Melanoma That is Metastatic or Cannot be Removed by Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Stand Up to Cancer Consortium Genomics-Enabled Medicine for Melanoma (G.E.M.M.): Using Molecularly-Guided Therapy for Patients With BRAF Wild-Type (BRAFwt) Metastatic Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized phase II trial studies how well molecularly targeted therapy works in
      treating patients with melanoma that has spread to other parts of the body or cannot be
      removed by surgery. Targeted therapy is a type of treatment that uses drugs or other
      substances to identify and attack specific types of cancer cells with less harm to normal
      cells. Molecularly targeted therapy works by treating patients with substances that kill
      cancer cells by targeting key molecules involved in cancer cell growth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the difference in best overall response rate (BORR) between patients treated
      with personalized targeted treatment vs. those treated with physician's choice of standard
      therapy.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the safety of performing individualized drug therapy (including novel agents
      and commercially-available agents) in the context of a personalized medicine clinical trial.

      II. To continually assess the process of enrolling and treating patients to a personalized
      medicine clinical trial by acquiring blood and tissue, genetically characterizing v-raf
      murine sarcoma viral oncogene homolog B (BRAF) wild type (wt) metastatic melanoma tumors,
      identifying a list of potential driver mutations, and treating each patient within a 5-week
      time frame.

      III. To determine the difference in progression free survival (PFS) between patients treated
      with personalized targeted treatment vs. those treated with physician's choice therapy.

      IV. To determine the BORR in specific target-drug matchings (those more frequent).

      V. To iteratively refine and standardize a set of statistical and informatics methodologies
      for matching treatments to the patient's tumor, based on their molecular profile.

      OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms.

      ARM I: Patients undergo collection of tissue and blood samples for deoxyribonucleic acid
      (DNA) and ribonucleic acid (RNA) analysis via sequencing. Based on the results of the DNA
      and RNA analysis, patients receive molecularly targeted therapy. Treatment continues in the
      absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM II: Patients undergo collection of tissue and blood samples for DNA and RNA analysis via
      sequencing. Patients receive physician's choice standard of care therapy. Treatment
      continues in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 1 year.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>BORR</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of treatment to time of progression or death, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A log rank test will be performed for the comparison between the two groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (molecularly targeted therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo collection of tissue and blood samples for DNA and RNA analysis via sequencing. Based on the results of the DNA and RNA analysis, patients receive molecularly targeted therapy. Treatment continues in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (standard of care therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo collection of tissue and blood samples for DNA and RNA analysis via sequencing. Patients receive physician's choice standard of care therapy. Treatment continues in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cytology specimen collection procedure</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo collection of tissue and blood samples</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (molecularly targeted therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (standard of care therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>cytologic sampling</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>molecularly targeted therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>molecularly targeted therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (molecularly targeted therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Doxorubicin</other_name>
    <other_name>Rubex ®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>therapeutic procedure</intervention_name>
    <description>Receive standard of care therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (standard of care therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Therapeutic Interventions</other_name>
    <other_name>Therapeutic Method</other_name>
    <other_name>Therapeutic Technique</other_name>
    <other_name>Therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>TX</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (molecularly targeted therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (standard of care therapy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>quality-of-life assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (molecularly targeted therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (standard of care therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>quality of life assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pts. with metastatic or locally advanced and unresectable BRAF wild-type melanoma who
             have either progressed following previous Rx (Rx) with ipilimumab and/or
             interleukin-2, or are not eligible for interleukin-2 or ipilimumab; ineligibility for
             interleukin-2 would include pts. with underlying cardiac disease (DZ), abnormal
             pulmonary function, or known hypersensitivity to IL-2 or any component of its
             formulation; pts. are not eligible for ipilimumab if they have known autoimmune DZ;
             for others, an open discussion between the physician and pt. must have occurred, and
             a mutual decision must have been reached that the pt. would not receive either of
             these agents; pts. are defined as &quot;BRAF wild-type&quot; if they test negative for V600
             mutations based on a Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA) certified
             assay

          -  Pts. must have tumor accessible by interventional radiology or surgical intervention
             and suitable for biopsy (BX) with 5-6 passes of a 16 or 18 gauge needle for core BX
             (defined as at least 1 cm^3 tumor/50 mg accessible for BX), and must agree to undergo
             up to two surgical resections/biopsies to collect tumor for research purposes; the
             first of these biopsies will occur at the beginning of the study, prior to genetic
             analysis and Rx; the second BX will be performed at the time of DZ progression/end of
             study should funding be available

          -  Pts. must have measurable DZ (per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors
             [RECIST] version 1.1 [v1.1] criteria), defined as at least one lesion that can be
             accurately measured in at least one dimension (longest diameter to be recorded for
             non-nodal lesions and short axis for nodal lesions) as &gt;= 20 mm with conventional
             techniques or as &gt;= 10 mm with spiral computed tomography (CT) scan, magnetic
             resonance imaging (MRI), or a subcutaneous or superficial lesion that can be measured
             with calipers by clinical exam; for lymph nodes, the short axis must be &gt;= 15 mm

          -  Previous therapies: prior radiation therapies, immunotherapies, and investigational
             therapies are allowed as follows.

               -  Radiation: prior radiation therapy (RT) is allowed with the following
                  conditions:

                    -  Pts. who have received minimal RT (=&lt; 5% of their total marrow volume) must
                       have completed it &gt;= 2 weeks prior to the initiation of study Rx

                    -  Pts. who have received RT that constituted &gt; 5% but &lt; 50% of their total
                       marrow volume must have completed it &gt;= 4 weeks prior to the initiation of
                       study Rx

                    -  Pts. who have received prior radiation to 50% or more of their total marrow
                       volume will be excluded

                    -  Pts. may be biopsied while undergoing RT as long as BX site is not in the
                       radiation portal; however, they still have to wait the required amount of
                       time from radiation to Rx even though the tumor board may have already
                       occurred and a Rx plan assigned

               -  Other therapies: prior investigational or targeted therapies and immunotherapies
                  may be allowed following discussion with the PI (PI); if the PI deems the prior
                  Rx acceptable, pts. must not have received these therapies for 28 days or five
                  half-lives of the drug (whichever is lesser) prior to the initiation of study Rx
                  and must have full recovery from any acute effects of these therapies; prior
                  therapy with mitogen-activated protein kinase (MEK) inhibitors will not be
                  allowed

          -  Pts. with chronic grade 1 or 2 toxicity may be eligible at the discretion of the PI
             if the condition has been stable, and not worsening, for at least 30 days; pts. with
             ongoing alopecia of any grade will be eligible

          -  Pt. must have a life expectancy of &gt;= 3 months, as estimated by the treating
             oncologist

          -  Pt. must have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 2

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9 g/dL

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3,000/microliter (mcL)

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets (PLT) &gt;= 100,000/mcL

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) =&lt; 2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN); if liver
             metastases are present, =&lt; 5 x ULN

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x ULN; if liver metastases are present, =&lt; 5 x
             ULN

          -  Alkaline phosphatase =&lt; 2.0 x ULN; if bone or liver metastases are present, =&lt; 5 x
             ULN

          -  Bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x ULN

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 1.5 x ULN OR calculated or measured creatinine clearance &gt;= 50
             mL/min/1.73 m^2 for pts. with creatinine above institutional normal

          -  If available, pt. must agree to provide archival tissue for research purposes (either
             archival paraffin tissue block or 10 unstained slides of a primary or metastatic
             melanoma lesion) prior to enrollment; samples should be shipped within 1 month after
             enrollment

          -  Pt. agrees to having a blood sample (a minimum of 10 mL, with 20 mL preferred) drawn
             and analyzed to compare their normal genetic profile to that of their tumor sample

          -  Pt. must be able to tolerate oral medication

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use 2 forms of adequate
             contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) for the
             duration of study participation, and for four months following completion of study
             therapy; should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while
             participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately;
             women who become pregnant must immediately discontinue Rx with any study therapy;
             male pts. should avoid impregnating a female partner; male pts., even if surgically
             sterilized, (i.e. post-vasectomy) must agree to one of the following: practice
             effective barrier contraception during the entire study Rx period and through 4
             months after the last dose of study drug, or completely abstain from sexual
             intercourse

          -  Pt. must have the ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written
             informed consent document

          -  Pt. must be willing and able to comply with the protocol for the duration of the
             study, including attending scheduled visits, examinations, the BX procedure, and
             having their tumor and blood molecularly characterized

          -  Pt. understands if he or she is randomized to receive molecularly guided Rx, they
             must meet all inclusion and exclusion criteria in the drug specific appendix for
             which they were randomized

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pt. has had prior cytotoxic chemotherapy for the Rx of metastatic melanoma; however,
             pts. who are randomized to the physician's choice arm and treated with cytotoxic
             chemotherapy as part of this study will be allowed to cross over to receive their
             assigned molecularly guided therapy should DZ progression occur and they meet the
             specific eligibility requirements of the molecularly guided agent

          -  Pts. with peripheral neuropathy &gt;= grade 2 are not permitted unless discussed with
             the PI and only in unique circumstances (i.e. unilateral neuropathy due to trauma)

          -  Pt. has DZ that tests positive for BRAF V600 mutations based on the results of a CLIA
             certified assay

          -  Pts. with active infection at time of BX

          -  Pts. with any evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic DZ(s) including known cases
             of hepatitis B or C or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV); screening for chronic
             conditions is not required, although pts. known to have such conditions at screening
             should not be included

          -  Any pt. requiring chronic maintenance of red blood cell, white blood cell or
             granulocyte counts through the use of blood transfusions or growth factor support
             (e.g. Neulasta®, Neupogen®)

          -  Pts. with a prior history of seizures within the past year unrelated to brain
             metastases

          -  Pts. with known active progressive brain metastases; pts. with prior treated brain
             metastases are allowed, providing that they were not accompanied by seizures within
             the past year and that a baseline brain MRI scan prior to study entry demonstrates no
             current evidence of active brain metastases; all pts. with prior treated brain
             metastases must be stable for &gt; 1 months after Rx and off steroid Rx prior to study
             enrollment

          -  Pts. receiving any other anti-cancer therapy (cytotoxic, biologic, radiation, or
             hormonal other than for replacement) except for medications that are prescribed for
             supportive care but may potentially have an anti-cancer effect (i.e. megestrol
             acetate, bisphosphonates); these medications must have been started &gt;= month prior to
             enrollment on this study; pts. may be on low molecular weight heparin or direct
             factor Xa inhibitors

          -  Pts. with any clinically significant medical condition which, in the opinion of the
             investigator, makes it undesirable for the pt. to participate in the study or which
             could jeopardize compliance with protocol requirements including, but not limited to:
             ongoing or active infection, significant uncontrolled hypertension, or severe
             psychiatric illness/social situations

          -  Pts. with preexisting cardiac conditions, including uncontrolled or symptomatic
             angina, arrhythmias, or congestive heart failure will not be eligible

          -  Pts. with left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; 45% will not be eligible

          -  Pts. with either of the following within 6 months before the first dose of study Rx:

               -  Stroke (including transient ischemic attack [TIA], or other ischemic event)

               -  Myocardial infarction

          -  Pts. with acute gastrointestinal bleeding within 1 month of study entry

          -  Pts. who have, at screening, corrected QT interval using Fridericia's formula (QTcF)
             &gt;= 450 msec for males and QTcF &gt;= 470 for females

          -  Pts. with a co-morbid condition(s) that, in the opinion of the investigator, prevents
             safe surgery/BX procedure

          -  Pts. with malabsorption syndrome or other condition that would interfere with
             intestinal absorption or ability to swallow oral medication

          -  Pregnant or nursing women; breastfeeding must be discontinued prior to Rx

          -  Pts. who have received organ transplant

          -  Pts. who have had major surgery within 14 days of study enrollment

          -  Pts. diagnosed or treated for another malignancy within 3 years of enrollment, with
             the exception of complete resection of basal cell carcinoma or squamous cell
             carcinoma of the skin, or an in situ malignancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patricia LoRusso, D.O.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Clarice Zuccaro, BA, CCRP</last_name>
    <phone>313-576-9375</phone>
    <email>zuccaroc@karmanos.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Karen Forman, BA, CCRP</last_name>
    <phone>313-576-8096</phone>
    <email>formank@karmanos.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic Scottsdale-Phoenix</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85259</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alan H. Bryce</last_name>
      <phone>480-301-8335</phone>
      <email>Bryce.Alan@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alan H. Bryce</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia G Piper Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85258</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Samuel Ejadi</last_name>
      <phone>480-323-1350</phone>
      <email>sejadi@shc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Samuel Ejadi</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32224-9980</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard W. Joseph</last_name>
      <phone>904-953-7188</phone>
      <email>joseph.richard@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard W. Joseph</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Leslie A. Fecher</last_name>
      <phone>317-948-7576</phone>
      <email>lafecher@iupui.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leslie A. Fecher</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109-0944</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christopher D. Lao</last_name>
      <phone>734-615-4762</phone>
      <email>clao@umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher D. Lao</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen Forman, BA, CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>313-576-8096</phone>
      <email>formank@karmanos.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Clarice Zuccaro, BA, CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>313-576-9375</phone>
      <email>zuccaroc@karmanos.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patricia M. LoRusso, D.O.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lawrence Flaherty, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Muaiad Kittaneh, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Svetomir N. Markovic</last_name>
      <phone>507-284-2511</phone>
      <email>markovic.svetomir@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Svetomir N. Markovic</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gary K. Schwartz</last_name>
      <phone>212-305-8602</phone>
      <email>gks2123@cumc.columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gary K. Schwartz</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul B. Chapman</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-2378</phone>
      <email>chapmanp@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul B. Chapman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UPMC Cancer Center - Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15241</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hussein A. Tawbi</last_name>
      <phone>412-648-6466</phone>
      <email>tawbih@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hussein A. Tawbi</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37240</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeffrey A. Sosman</last_name>
      <phone>615-322-4967</phone>
      <email>jeff.sosman@vanderbilt.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey A. Sosman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor Sammons Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75246</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Charles L. Cowey</last_name>
      <phone>214-370-1800</phone>
      <email>Lance.Cowey@USONCOLOGY.COM</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charles L. Cowey</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 18, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Patricia LoRusso</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
