<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="139533">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01883882</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>43641-B</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R34DA033384</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01883882</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Trial of Opioid Taper Support</brief_title>
  <acronym>POTS</acronym>
  <official_title>Pilot Randomized Trial of Opioid Taper Support</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed research will develop, demonstrate the feasibility of, and pilot test in a
      randomized controlled trial a prescription opioid taper support intervention. This
      intervention aims to prevent opioid misuse and adverse events among patients receiving
      chronic opioid therapy for chronic non-cancer pain without evidence of current substance
      abuse.

      The project will yield information essential to planning a future, larger-scale RCT designed
      to evaluate: 1) the efficacy of the intervention in preventing prescription opioid abuse,
      misuse, overdose and other adverse events among patients receiving chronic opioid therapy
      for chronic non-cancer pain, 2) the effects of the intervention on opioid use, pain,
      painrelated activity interference, and mood. Participants in our pilot study will be limited
      to those without current opioid abuse or other substance abuse, but past substance abuse
      will be allowed. This will provide a sample of patients at risk for opioid abuse, misuse and
      overdose, but who may be able to taper their opioids successfully. Hypothesis: Patients
      receiving chronic opioid therapy for chronic non-cancer painwho are randomized to the opioid
      taper support intervention, as compared with patients randomized to usual opioid prescribing
      care, will have lower opioid average daily doses at 22 and 34 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mean daily opioid dose over past week</measure>
    <time_frame>week 22 after randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>mean daily opioid dose over past week as calculated in morphine equivalent dose</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>prescription opioid difficulties</measure>
    <time_frame>week 22 after randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Prescription opioid difficulties subscale scores on: psychosocial problems and opioid control concerns</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Non-cancer Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>taper support</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Weekly visits with pharmacological and psychological support for opioid taper at 10% of original dose per week</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care for chronic pain. All care allowed except buprenorphine.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>opioid taper support</intervention_name>
    <description>Weekly visits with physician's assistant (supervised by pain physician/psychiatrist and pain psychologist) who provides pharmacological and psychological support for opioid taper at 10% per week</description>
    <arm_group_label>taper support</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age 18-80 years;

          -  UW CPR patient with plans to continue CPR care for at least6 months;

          -  CNCP, defined as pain on more than half the days in the past six months, where
             indicated diagnostic workup is complete and treatment is focused on pain;

          -  currently on COT, defined as self-report of prescribed oral opioid medication use on
             a daily or near-daily (&gt;90% of days) basis for 90 days or more;

          -  mean daily opioid dose in the past 30 days of 50 mg MED or greater;

          -  willing to participate in the study arm to which they are randomly assigned
             (including opioid taper in-person sessions if randomized to that group);

          -  willing, if randomized to opioid taper, to aim for at least a 50% reduction from
             baseline opioid dose or for 120mg MED (whichever is less) by the end of an 22-week
             period;

          -  able to read, speak, and write English.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  currently receiving treatment for cancer (other than non-melanoma skin cancer);

          -  medical comorbidity with life expectancy less than a year (based on medical record
             review by the PI);

          -  recent use (past month) of parenteral, transdermal, or transmucosal opioids,

          -  currently residing in nursing home;

          -  currently using intrathecal pump for pain control;

          -  any current substance abuse according to the Comprehensive International Diagnostic
             Interview- Substance Abuse Module (CIDI-SAM) (nicotine and marijuana will be allowed
             since Washington State allows medical marijuana for pain control);

          -  presence of illicit drug metabolite in baseline urine drug test,

          -  psychotic symptoms, psychiatric hospitalization or suicide attempts in the past 10
             years;

          -  current suicidal ideation with specific plan or intent;

          -  significant cognitive impairment (on 6-item screener Scale).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark D Sullivan, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>206-685-3184</phone>
    <email>sullimar@uw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Angela Roof, PA</last_name>
    <phone>206-598-4283</phone>
    <email>roofa@uw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington Center for Pain Relief</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Angela Roof, PA</last_name>
      <phone>206-598-4282</phone>
      <email>roofa@uw.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark D Sullivan, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 20, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Washington</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mark Sullivan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prinicipal Study Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic non-cancer pain</keyword>
  <keyword>opioid taper</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic pain self-management</keyword>
  <keyword>motivational interviewing</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Analgesics, Opioid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
