<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="31928">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02091518</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-239</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02091518</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development and Evaluation of Magnetic Resonance Imaging Acquisition and Analysis Methods</brief_title>
  <official_title>Development and Evaluation of Magnetic Resonance Imaging Acquisition and Analysis Methods</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is a diagnostic imaging method with constant progress and
      improvement in the way the MRI images are obtained. Many of these advances involve changes
      to MRI software and hardware. The goal of this study is to find out the possible benefits of
      new MRI techniques. This will allow us to use the new MRI methods in research and patient
      care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>feasibility of new MRI applications</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This protocol will provide pilot data to determine the feasibility of development and optimization of new MRI acquisition and analysis method.including sequence development, optimization, and workflow and analysis/visualization tools. An investigator will view the conventional images, as well as the additional research sequences. The radiologist will then complete data forms for each image and quantitative values, as listed in the evaluation form will be recorded. After all images have been read, the radiologist will review the clinical images together with the research images, and determine whether the research sequences had any effect on their diagnostic confidence.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MRI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will include patients who are scheduled for a routine clinical MRI who meet the eligibility requirements for this protocol. Protocol participation will consist of an &quot;add-on&quot; research. MRI scan not to exceed 20 minutes, which will be performed at the conclusion of the routine clinical MRI scan.
Volunteers will be subjects expressing interest in participation and who meet the eligibility requirements for this protocol. No contrast enhanced research MRIs including gadolinium-based or other contrast agents will be performed in volunteers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MR Screening Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>All participants will complete the MR Screening Questionnaire before the MRI exam. During the MRI exam, all participants will be observed through the window from the operator console. Verbal communication will be kept with the participant throughout the exam via a speaker system.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MRI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Magnetic Resonance Imaging Acquisition and Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>MRI Studies: The MRI scans will be performed on a 1.5T or 3T MRI scanner. Conventional MRI studies will be performed using the standard clinical sequences. The new research sequences will be performed following the standard pulse sequences. Total additional imaging time will be 10-20 minutes for add-on research patients, and 30-45 minutes for volunteers.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MRI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women age 18 or older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Anyone who would be normally excluded from undergoing an MRI examination as per
             Memorial Hospital for Cancer and Allied Diseases Screening Questionnaire for MRI

          -  Patients/volunteers with a pacemaker, aneurysm clip or any other condition that would
             warrant avoidance of a strong magnetic field

          -  Female patients/ volunteers who are pregnant or nursing

          -  Patients/ volunteers who are unable to comply or complete the MRI exam due to
             claustrophobia or high levels of anxiety

          -  Patients/ volunteers from the vulnerable population, as defined by 45 CFR 46.

          -  Patients at higher risk due to age, frailty, or the emergent nature of their
             condition
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Oguz Akin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>13-239</keyword>
  <keyword>volunteers</keyword>
  <keyword>patients</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
