<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="141433">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02142283</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>T4024</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02142283</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trevo and Medical Management Versus Medical Management Alone in Wake Up and Late Presenting Strokes</brief_title>
  <acronym>DAWN</acronym>
  <official_title>Diffusion Weighted Imaging (DWI) or Computerized Tomography Perfusion (CTP) Assessment With Clinical Mismatch in the Triage of Wake Up and Late Presenting Strokes Undergoing Neurointervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stryker Neurovascular</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stryker Neurovascular</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to evaluate the hypothesis that Trevo thrombectomy plus medical
      management leads to superior clinical outcomes at 90 days as compared to medical management
      alone in appropriately selected subjects experiencing an acute ischemic stroke when
      treatment is initiated within 6-24 hours after last seen well.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is a prospective, randomized, multi-center, Phase II/III (feasibility/pivotal),
      adaptive, controlled trial, designed to demonstrate that mechanical thrombectomy using the
      Trevo Retriever with medical management is superior to medical management alone in improving
      clinical outcomes at 90 days in appropriately selected wake up and late presenting acute
      ischemic stroke subjects.

      The intent of this study is to support the use of the Trevo Retriever beyond the currently
      labeled 8 hour indicated time limit in wake up, unclear onset, and late presenting ischemic
      stroke subjects, who currently have no other option besides medical management of their
      symptoms.

      Patients with wake-up strokes, strokes with unclear onset time, and witnessed late
      presenting strokes may potentially benefit from intra-arterial reperfusion therapy. However,
      an important indicator of whether subjects will benefit or not during this later time window
      is the confirmation of a large vessel occlusion (LVO), and assessment of the core infarct
      volume relative to the volume of salvageable penumbra. Therefore, standardized imaging
      selection of subjects is required for inclusion into the study.

      This trial has been designed with subject safety in mind, as a seamless Phase II
      (feasibility) / Phase III (pivotal) adaptive design, in order to address the concerns around
      potential unknown harms to enrolled subjects. This study will help to answer the question of
      whether carefully selecting subjects by using Clinical Imaging Mismatch will allow acute
      ischemic stroke patients who present at or beyond 6 hours from Time Last Seen Well (TLSW) to
      be considered for intra-arterial intervention. If Trevo thrombectomy plus medical management
      leads to better clinical outcomes over medical management alone, more patients in the future
      could receive endovascular treatment (either in addition to or in lieu of IV tPA).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Weighted modified Rankin Scale (mRS) score</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke-related mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Good functional outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of subjects with a good functional outcome at 90 days, defined as mRS 0-2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early response</measure>
    <time_frame>5-7 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of subjects with &quot;early response&quot; at Day 5-7/Discharge (whichever is earlier), defined as a National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale (NIHSS) drop of ≥10 from baseline or NIHSS score 0 or 1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median final infarct size</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The median final infarct size at 24 hours from randomization, by MRI T2/Flair or CT.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Revascularization rates</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Revascularization rates at 24 hours from randomization, by CT-MR core lab assessment of vessel patency on CTA/MRA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vessel reperfusion rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after device usage and at the end of the thrombectomy procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vessel reperfusion rates (percentages) post device and post procedure, by angiography core lab measurement of modified TICI ≥ 2b (Treatment arm only).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptomatic intracranial hemorrhage</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Symptomatic intracranial hemorrhage, by ECASS III definition, within 24 hours post randomization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurological deterioration from baseline NIHSS score</measure>
    <time_frame>5-7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Neurological deterioration from baseline NIHSS score through Day 5-7/discharge (whichever is earlier) post randomization. Neurological deterioration is defined as ≥ 4 point increase in the NIHSS score from the baseline score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Procedure-related and device-related SAEs</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Procedure-related and device-related serious adverse events (SAEs) through 24 hours post randomization (Treatment arm only).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Ischemic Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Trevo Thrombectomy Procedure</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Trevo Thrombectomy Procedure and Medical Management</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Medical Management</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Medical Management</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trevo Thrombectomy Procedure</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Trevo Thrombectomy Procedure</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Trevo ProVue Retriever</other_name>
    <other_name>Trevo XP ProVue Retriever</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Medical Management</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Trevo Thrombectomy Procedure</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Medical Management</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Medical Management per each institution's standard of care</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        General Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Clinical signs and symptoms consistent with the diagnosis of an acute ischemic
             stroke, and subject belongs to one of the following subgroups:

               1. Subject has failed IV t-PA therapy (defined as a confirmed persistent occlusion
                  60 min after administration)

               2. Subject is contraindicated for IV t-PA administration

          2. Age ≥18

          3. Baseline NIHSS ≥10 (assessed within one hour prior to measuring core infarct volume)

          4. Subject can be randomized between with 6 to 24 hours after time last known well

          5. No significant pre-stroke disability (pre-stroke mRS must be 0 or 1)

          6. Anticipated life expectancy of at least 6 months

          7. Subject willing/able to return for protocol required follow up visits

          8. Subject or subject's Legally Authorized Representative (LAR) has signed the study
             Informed Consent form*

        Imaging Inclusion Criteria:

          1. &lt; 1/3 MCA territory involved, as evidenced by CT or MRI

          2. Occlusion of the intracranial ICA and/or MCA-M1 as evidenced by MRA or CTA

          3. Clinical Imaging Mismatch (CIM) defined as one of the following on RAPID MR-DWI or
             CTP-rCBF maps:

               1. 0-20 cc core infarct and NIHSS ≥ 10 (and age ≥ 80 years old)

               2. 0-30 cc core infarct and NIHSS ≥ 10 (and age &lt; 80 years old)

               3. 31 cc to &lt; 50 cc core infarct and NIHSS ≥ 20 (and age &lt; 80 years old)

        General Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of severe head injury within past 90 days with residual neurological deficit,
             as determined by medical history

          2. Rapid improvement in neurological status  to an NIHSS &lt;10  or evidence of vessel
             recanalization prior to randomization

          3. Pre-existing neurological or psychiatric disease that would confound the neurological
             or functional evaluations, e.g. dementia with prescribed anti-cholinesterase
             inhibitor (e.g. Aricept)

          4. Seizures at stroke onset if it makes the diagnosis of stroke doubtful and precludes
             obtaining an accurate baseline NIHSS assessment

          5. Baseline blood glucose of &lt;50mg/dL (2.78 mmol) or &gt;400mg/dL (22.20 mmol)

          6. Renal failure as defined by a serum  creatinine &gt;3.0 mg/dL (264 µmol/L) NOTE:
             subjects on renal dialysis may be treated regardless of serum creatinine  levels

          7. Known hemorrhagic diathesis, coagulation factor deficiency, or on anticoagulant
             therapy with INR &gt; 3.0 or PTT &gt; 3 times normal; If factor Xa inhibitor (e.g.
             apixaban) &lt; 24 hrs ago must have normal ecarin clotting time and if 24-48 hrs ago
             must have normal PTT.

          8. Any active or recent hemorrhage within the past 30 days

          9. Baseline platelet count &lt; 50,000/uL

         10. History of severe allergy (more than rash)  to contrast medium

         11. Severe, sustained hypertension (Systolic Blood Pressure &gt;185 mmHg or Diastolic Blood
             Pressure &gt;110 mmHg) NOTE: If the blood pressure can be successfully reduced and
             maintained at the acceptable level using medication the subject can be enrolled

         12. Female who is pregnant or lactating at time of admission

         13. Current participation in another investigational drug or device study or registry

         14. Presumed septic embolus, or suspicion of bacterial endocarditis

         15. Treatment with any cleared thrombectomy devices or other intra-arterial
             (neurovascular) therapies prior to randomization

        Imaging Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Evidence of intracranial hemorrhage on CT/MRI

          2. Evidence of internal carotid artery flow limiting dissection on CTA/MRA

          3. Severe proximal extra-cranial carotid artery stenosis, or occlusion of any etiology,
             where concurrent vessel angioplasty or stenting is expected to be necessary and the
             procedure cannot be delayed until after the 24 (-6/+24) hours assessments have been
             completed

          4. Excessive tortuosity of cervical vessels on CTA/MRA that would likely preclude device
             delivery/deployment

          5. Suspected cerebral vasculitis based on medical history and CTA/MRA

          6. Suspected aortic dissection based on medical history and CTA/MRA

          7. Intracranial stent implanted in the same vascular territory that would preclude the
             safe deployment/removal of the Trevo device

          8. Occlusions in multiple vascular territories (e.g., bilateral anterior circulation, or
             anterior/posterior circulation) as confirmed on CTA/MRA, or clinical evidence of
             bilateral strokes or strokes in multiple territories

          9. Significant mass effect with midline shift as confirmed on CT/MRI

         10. Evidence of intracranial tumor (except small meningioma) as confirmed on CT/MRI
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tudor G Jovin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburg Medical Center Stroke Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raul Nogueira, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Marcus Stroke &amp; Neuroscience Center, Grady Memorial Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Julie Moore, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>510-413-2701</phone>
    <email>julie.moore@stryker.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Amelia Saliba, BA</last_name>
    <phone>510-413-2634</phone>
    <email>amelia.saliba@stryker.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 15, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mechanical thrombectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute ischemic stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Wake up stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Late presenting stroke</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
