<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="166521">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01937598</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>120-0569-DZBL-2012</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-001764-35</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01937598</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Antidiabetic Effects of Adding a DPP-4 Inhibitor (Sitagliptin) to Pre-Existing Treatment With an Incretin Mimetic (Liraglutide) in Patients With Type 2 Diabetes Treated With Metformin</brief_title>
  <official_title>Antidiabetic Effects of Adding a DPP-4 Inhibitor (Sitagliptin) to Pre-Existing Treatment With an Incretin Mimetic (Liraglutide) in Patients With Type 2 Diabetes Treated With Metformin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Michael A. Nauck</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Diabeteszentrum Bad Lauterberg im Harz</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objectives: To quantify differences in control of glycemia (primary objective) and the
      secretion of endogenous incretin hormones (secondary objective) comparing sitagliptin or
      placebo added to pre-existing therapy with liraglutide and metformin
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a double blind, controlled, cross-over comparison of adding sitagliptin (or placebo)
      to pre-existing metformin+liraglutide therapy. Patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM)
      on pre-existing treatment with metformin (≥ 1500 mg/d) monotherapy or metformin plus
      liraglutide (1.2 mg/d) will be studied. Patients on metformin monotherapy will, after
      screening and randomization, enter a run-in period of 2 weeks with the additional treatment
      of liraglutide (0.6 mg/d for 1 week followed by 1.2 mg/d for another week).  At the end of
      this 2 weeks therapy, a mixed meal challenge will take place, with the assessment of glucose
      and hormone responses (insulin, C-peptide, glucagon, GLP-1, GIP) and gastric emptying as
      measured by 13C-octanoate breath tests. Prior to the meal tests, liraglutide will be
      administered at a dose of 1.2 mg per injection, which is the recommended dose for treatment.
      Sitagliptin will be used at a dose of 100 mg, which is recommended for clinical use.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incremental area under the plasma glucose (BG) concentration-time profile (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 6 weeks (range 9 - 60 days / 8.5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Incremental area under the plasma glucose (BG) concentration-time profile (AUC) immediately before to 300 min after a mixed meal test. In addition, the time course of BG values will be analysed with an ANCOVA model for repeated measurements with placebo baseline values as covariate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC plasma glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 6 weeks (range 9 - 60 days / 8.5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Incremental AUC from 0 to 300 min</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 6 weeks (range 9 - 60 days / 8.5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC C-peptide</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 6 weeks (range 9 - 60 days / 8.5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC glucagon</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 6 weeks (range 9 - 60 days / 8.5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC total GLP-1</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 6 weeks (range 9 - 60 days / 8.5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC total GIP</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 6 weeks (range 9 - 60 days / 8.5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC active GLP-1</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 6 weeks (range 9 - 60 days / 8.5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC active GIP</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 6 weeks (range 9 - 60 days / 8.5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Velocity of gastric emptying</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 6 weeks (range 9 - 60 days / 8.5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>velocity of gastric emptying as determined through 13C-breath test with t½, lag time, gastric emptying coefficient and time course as main outcome parameters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>plasma glucose concentration 120 min after starting the meal;</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 6 weeks (range 9 - 60 days / 8.5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sitagliptin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Substance:			Sitagliptin phosphate 1H2O Pharmaceutical form:		tablets Source:			MSD SHARP &amp; DOHME GMBH, Doses:				100 mg, Route of administration:	p.o. as a tablet</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Substance:			Placebo (sitagliptin) Pharmaceutical form:		tablets Source:	MSD SHARP &amp; DOHME GMBH Doses:				- Route of administration:	p.o. as tablets</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sitagliptin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Sitagliptin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mixed meal test</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be instructed to consume the mixed meal test within 20 minutes. The exact start and stop time of the mixed meal test consumption will be recorded in the CRF. The mixed meal test procedures will be identical for all subjects randomised in the study. To detect the plasma glucose excursion after mixed meal test, plasma glucose will be closely monitored</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sitagliptin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Liraglutide</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients on metformin monotherapy will, after screening and randomization, enter a run-in period of 2 weeks with the additional treatment of liraglutide (0.6 mg/d for 1 week followed by 1.2 mg/d for another week) that will be continued for the entire duration of the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sitagliptin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Liraglutide</other_name>
    <other_name>(Source Victoza Prescribing Information, issued April 6, 2012, Version 3)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Signed and dated written informed consent obtained before any study-related
             activities

          2. Male and female subjects with a diagnosis of type 2 diabetes mellitus according to
             ADA criteria at least 4 months prior to screening

          3. Medical history without major pathology (with the exception of type 2 diabetes) as
             judged by the investigator

          4. On a stable regimen of metformin for at least 1 month and liraglutide 1.2 mg for at
             least 1 week at the time-point of randomisation.

          5. Aged between 25 and 75 years, both inclusive

          6. Body mass index (BMI) between 22 and 40kg/m2, both inclusive

          7. HbA1c ≥ 6.5 and ≤ 8.5% (≥ 7.0 and ≤ 8.5% for patients without previous liraglutide
             treatment)

          8. Female must be post-menopausal, surgically sterilized or practicing an effective
             birth control

        Exclusion criteria

          1. Subjects with type 1 diabetes, maturity onset diabetes of the young (MODY) or
             secondary forms of diabetes such as due to pancreatitis

          2. Current or previous treatment with insulin therapy (except for treatment at diabetes'
             diagnosis, within a clinical trial, for surgical procedures or during an acute
             illness, and no insulin administration within the 6 months before screening)

          3. Treatment with any hypoglycaemic medication other than metformin and liraglutide
             within one month prior to screening

          4. Subjects with known diabetic gastroparesis and / or prokinetic therapy

          5. Subjects that underwent surgery of the upper gastrointestinal tract

          6. Women who are pregnant, intending to become pregnant during the study period,
             currently lactating females, or women of child-bearing potential not using highly
             effective, medically approved birth control methods

          7. Subjects with any severe medical or surgical history of conditions likely to confound
             study assessments or study endpoints, for example but not limited to
             haemoglobinopathies, inflammatory bowel disease, cystic fibrosis, bariatric surgery
             and/or any surgery shortening the intestine, history of lactose intolerance,
             lactose- or glucose-galactose-malabsorption

          8. Subjects with a suspicion of medullary thyroid cancer or a multiple endocrine
             neoplasia

          9. Subjects with a personal or family history of medullar thyroid cancer or a multiple
             endocrine neoplasia

         10. Serious and/or unstable coronary heart disease (unstable angina, myocardial
             infarction within the preceding 6 months), congestive heart failure of New York Heart
             Association Class III or worse (severe limitation of physical activity; physical
             activity of low intensity resulting in fatigue, palpitation, or dyspnoea),
             second/third degree heart block, superior vena cava syndrome, uncontrolled
             hypertension, history of congenital QT-syndrome within family, history of stroke
             (within the preceding 6 months) or serious peripheral vascular disease

         11. History of arrhythmia (multifocal premature ventricular contractions, bigeminy,
             trigeminy, ventricular tachycardia, or uncontrolled atrial fibrillation) that is
             symptomatic or requires treatment (grade 3), left bundle branch block, or
             asymptomatic sustained ventricular tachycardia are not allowed

         12. Marked diabetic complications: severe autonomic or sensory neuropathy including
             previously diagnosed gastroparesis; proliferative retinopathy

         13. Any respiratory disease leading to respiratory insufficiency and/or depression
             including but not limited to clinically significant: bronchial asthma, chronic
             obstructive pulmonary disease, that might impact to the breath test, as judged by the
             investigator

         14. Clinically significant vital signs including known bradycardia with pulse rate &lt;
             50/min or 12-lead ECG findings including QTc &gt; 450 msec for males or QTc &gt; 470 msec
             for women

         15. Clinically significant abnormal haematology, biochemistry, lipids, or urinalysis or
             coagulation screening tests, as judged by the Investigator

         16. Moderate or severe renal dysfunction defined as an estimated creatinine clearance
             (MDRD equation) GFR &lt;50 ml/min.

         17. Clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic dysfunction or disease; laboratory
             evidence defined as any of the following parameters: alkaline  phosphatase, ALT, AST
             or bilirubin &gt; 3x ULN. Isolated mild rise in bilirubin considered to be due to
             Gilbert's condition is allowed

         18. Uncontrolled high blood pressure (DBP &gt; 95 mmHg and/or SBP &gt; 160 mmHg), unless
             clearly documented to be white-coat hypertension

         19. History of any psychiatric condition that might impair the subject's ability to
             understand or to comply with the requirements of the study or to provide informed
             consent

         20. History of relevant drug and/or food allergies or a history of severe anaphylactic
             reaction

         21. Currently active or history of alcohol abuse (defined as an intake of more than 24
             units of alcohol per week; one unit of alcohol equals approximately 250 mL of beer,
             100 mL of wine or 35 mL of spirits) or drug addiction (including soft drugs like
             cannabis products)

         22. Use of concomitant medication which would be likely to interact with metformin,
             sitagliptin or liraglutide (according to the subject information leaflet).
             Participation in another clinical trial within the 3 months preceding screening or
             5-half-lives of drug studied, whichever is longer, prior to study medication
             administration

         23. Malignancy within 5 years of study start, except for successfully treated local basal
             cell carcinomas

         24. Subjects known to be positive for Hepatitis B surface antigen or Hepatitis C
             antibodies (or diagnosed with active hepatitis according to local practice)

         25. Subject who has donated or lost more than 500 mL blood within 3 months prior to
             screening and has an Hb &lt; 14 g/dl at screening

         26. History of hypersensitivity to the study medication or any of the excipients or to
             medicinal products with similar chemical structures

         27. Veins unsuitable for repeated venipuncture
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael A. Nauck, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Diabeteszentrum Bad Lauterberg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael A. Nauck, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <email>nauck@diabeteszentrum.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diabeteszentrum Bad Lauterberg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bad Lauterberg</city>
        <zip>37431</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael A. Nauck</last_name>
      <email>nauck@diabeteszentrum.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Oleg Baranov</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 4, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 27, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Diabeteszentrum Bad Lauterberg im Harz</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael A. Nauck</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr. med.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Incretin, DPP-4 inhibitor</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sitagliptin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypoglycemic Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucagon-Like Peptide 1</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Incretins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dipeptidyl-Peptidase IV Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
