<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="58847">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02094534</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ORA-D-010</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02094534</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Prospective, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo Controlled Study to Assess the Impact of ORMD-0801 (Insulin Capsules) on the Exogenous Insulin Requirements of Type 1 Diabetics</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo Controlled Study to Assess the Impact of ORMD-0801 (Insulin Capsules) on the Exogenous Insulin Requirements of Type 1 Diabetics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oramed, Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Integrium</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oramed, Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This will be a prospective, randomized, double-blind, placebo controlled study. Patients
      with established Type 1 diabetes will be eligible for entry into the study. Eligible
      patients will be screened and those who fulfill all inclusion/exclusion criteria will be
      admitted to the inpatient unit no fewer than 2 days and no more than 7 days after Screening.
      Patients will report to the inpatient unit at 6 a.m. and outfitted with a continuous glucose
      monitoring (CGM) device. Patients will be given standardized meals and snacks for the
      duration of their inpatient visit.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For the first 3 days, patients will be dosed with placebo 45 minutes prior to each of the
      day's 3 meals to establish baseline insulin requirements. Patients will be dosed with
      exogenous insulin according to their normal sliding scale and each patient's daily insulin
      requirement will be documented. The average daily insulin requirements during the 3 day
      run-in period will constitute the patient's baseline insulin level.

      Following the 3 day run-in, the CGM device will be detached, its data download, and the
      patient refitted with the CGM with a fresh cannula for continued monitoring during the 7-day
      treatment period.

      Patients will be randomized 2:1 to receive ORMD-0801 or placebo for the 7-day double-blind
      treatment period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in exogenous insulin requirements  (Basal, Bolus and Total)</measure>
    <time_frame>treatment (day 1 to day 7), at-home self- monitoring (day 8 to day 14),  endo of study visit (day 15)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in exogenous insulin requirements  (Basal, Bolus and Total) in patients treated with ORMD-0801, compared to the change from baseline for patients treated with placebo</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in mean nighttime, daytime and fasting glucose levels</measure>
    <time_frame>day 1 day 2 day 3 day 4 day 5 day 6  and day 7</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the change from baseline in mean nighttime, daytime and fasting glucose levels (by continuous glucose monitoring) in Type 1 diabetes patients treated with ORMD-0801, compared to the change from baseline for patients treated with placebo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus Type 1</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ORMD-0801</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>API (recombinant human insulin USP), in Oramed's proprietary formulation in capsules, ORMD-0801</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fish oil in capsules, identical in appearance to ORMD-0801</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ORMD-0801 capsules</intervention_name>
    <description>API (recombinant human insulin USP), in Oramed's proprietary formulation in capsules.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ORMD-0801</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Oral Insulin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and Females age 18 to 55 years old, inclusive.

          -  Patients must be willing and able to sign informed consent.

          -  Documented history of Type 1 Diabetes for at least 6 months

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test at
             screening and a negative urinary screening test following admission to the inpatient
             unit

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of any clinically significant endocrine disease according to the
             Investigator (euthyroid patients on replacement therapy will be included if the
             dosage of thyroxine is stable for at least six weeks prior to Screening)

          -  Fasting plasma glucose &gt;260 mg/dL at the end of run-in

          -  Evidence of unawareness of hypoglycemia with a documented plasma glucose ≤50 mg/dL in
             the absence of symptoms of hypoglycemia

          -  Presence of any clinically significant condition that might interfere with the
             evaluation of study medication (i.e., significant renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal
             (GI), cardiovascular (CV), immune disease).

          -  Presence or history of cancer within the past five years with the exception of
             adequately-treated localized basal cell skin cancer or in situ uterine cervical
             cancer

          -  Laboratory abnormalities at screening including:

          -  Positive pregnancy test in females of childbearing potential (at screening and Day -3
             of Visit 2)

          -  Abnormal serum thyrotropin (TSH) levels &gt;1.5X upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Positive test for hepatitis B surface antigen and/or hepatitis C antibody

          -  Positive test for HIV

          -  Any relevant abnormality interfering with the efficacy or the safety assessments
             during study drug administration

          -  Use of the following medications:

             o History of use of aprotinin at any time prior to the screening visit (e.g.,
             Trasylol, any type or dose)

          -  Administration of thiazolidinedione [e.g., (Actos (pioglitazone) and Avandia
             (rosiglitazone)] treatment within 3 months prior to randomization.

          -  Administration of thyroid preparations or thyroxine (except in patients on stable
             replacement therapy) within 6 weeks prior to screening visit

          -  Administration of systemic long-acting corticosteroids within two months or prolonged
             use (more than one week) of other systemic corticosteroids or inhaled corticosteroids
             (if daily dosage is &gt; 1,000 μg equivalent beclomethasone) within 30 days prior to
             screening visit

          -  Use of medications known to modify glucose metabolism or to decrease the ability to
             recover from hypoglycemia such as oral, parenteral, and inhaled steroids (as
             discussed above), beta blockers (with the exception of beta blocker ophthalmic
             solutions for glaucoma or ocular hypertension), and immunosuppressive or
             immunomodulating agents

          -  History of severe or multiple allergies, or known allergy to soy or aprotinin.

          -  History of tobacco or nicotine use within 10 weeks prior to screening

          -  Patient is on a weight loss program and is not in the maintenance phase, or patient
             that started weight loss medication (e.g., orlistat or sibutramine) within 8 weeks
             prior to screening

          -  Pregnancy or breast-feeding

          -  Patient has a screening visit systolic blood pressure of ≥165 mmHg or diastolic
             blood pressure of ≥100 mmHg.

          -  Patient is, at the time of consent, a user of recreational or illicit drugs or has
             had a recent history (within the last year) of drug or alcohol abuse or dependence.
             (Note: Alcohol abuse includes heavy alcohol intake as defined by &gt;3 drinks per day or
             &gt;14 drinks per week, or binge drinking)

          -  Elevated liver enzymes (alanine transaminase (ALT), alanine aminotransferase (AST),
             alkaline phosphatase) greater than 2 times the upper limit of normal (ULN) at
             Screening

          -  Very high triglyceride level (&gt;600 mg/dL) at Screening

          -  Any clinically significant electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormality at screening or
             cardiovascular disease. Clinically significant cardiovascular disease will include:

          -  history of stroke, transient ischemic attack, or myocardial infarction within 6
             months prior to screening,

          -  history of or currently have New York Heart Associate Class II-IV heart failure prior
             to screening, or

          -  uncontrolled hypertension defined as (duplicate seated reading) blood pressure ≥165
             mmHg (systolic) or ≥100 mmHg (diastolic) at screening or at Visit 2.

          -  History of gastrointestinal disorders (e.g. hypochlorhydria) with the potential to
             interfere with drug absorption

          -  At the Principal Investigator's discretion, any condition or other factor that is
             deemed unsuitable for patient enrollment into the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orange County Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tustin</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92780</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joel M Neutel, M. D.</last_name>
      <phone>714-541-5591</phone>
      <email>jmneutel@aol.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joel M Neutel, M. D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 20, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 20, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes type 1</keyword>
  <keyword>Oral Insulin</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Tolerability</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase 2a</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized</keyword>
  <keyword>Blinded</keyword>
  <keyword>Parallel</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
