<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="146439">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02088086</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-07-4472</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL120666</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02088086</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BMI Screening and Reporting in Schools: The Fit Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Trial of BMI Screening: Effects on Obesity, Disparities, and Body Satisfaction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Berkeley</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Berkeley</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Fit Study is a three-year, cluster-randomized controlled trial that will evaluate the
      impact of school-based body mass index (BMI) screening and reporting on childhood obesity in
      California. Seventy-five schools across California will be randomized to one of three
      groups: 1) BMI screening and reporting, 2) BMI screening, and 3) no BMI screening or
      reporting (control). Schools randomized to Groups 1 and 2 will conduct height and weight
      measurements annually with their 3rd-8th grade students, and Group 1 schools will mail a
      report home to parents with their student's BMI results. Schools randomized to Group 3 will
      not conduct height and weight measurements with their students for two school years.
      Investigators will assess the impact of sending a BMI report home to parents on students'
      BMI trajectories over 3 years. Investigators will also assess the impact of having height
      and weight measurements taken at school on weight-based teasing, feelings of stigmatization,
      and weight-control behaviors over 3 years, as measured by a student survey.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Fit Study is a three-year, cluster-randomized controlled trial that will evaluate the
      impact of school-based body mass index (BMI) screening and reporting on childhood obesity in
      California. This study will take place during the 2014-15, 2015-16, and 2016-17 school
      years. Seventy-five schools across California will be randomized to one of three groups: 1)
      BMI screening and reporting, 2) BMI screening, and 3) no BMI screening or reporting
      (control). Schools randomized to Groups 1 and 2 will conduct height and weight measurements
      annually with their 3rd-8th grade students. Group 1 and 2 schools will also administer the
      five fitness assessments from the FITNESSGRAM test annually with their 5th-8th grade
      students. These assessments will take place in the spring to coincide with the annual
      FITNESSGRAM assessment that is required for 5th, 7th, and 9th grade students by California
      state law. In the fall of Years 2 and 3, Group 1 schools will mail a report home to parents
      with their student's BMI results from the previous spring. Investigators will randomize the
      parents of 6th-8th grade students (who were 5th-7th grade students during the previous
      school year) to receive one of two report types: 1) a report that only provides BMI results,
      or 2) a report that provides BMI results with results from the five fitness assessments.
      Schools randomized to Group 3 will not conduct height and weight measurements with their
      students during Years 1 and 2. During these years, 5th and 7th grade students from Group 3
      schools will participate in the five fitness assessments of the FITNESSGRAM test. The
      California Department of Education will grant these schools as exemption from collecting
      height and weight data on their 5th and 7th grade students, which is normally required as
      part of the FITNESSGRAM.

      In the fall of Year 1, investigators will conduct a baseline survey with students from all
      schools. This survey will assess weight-based teasing and stigmatization, weight-control
      behaviors, and general nutrition and physical activity behaviors. The student survey will
      also ask questions about students' experiences having height and weight measurements
      conducted at school. After students complete the baseline survey, investigators will
      randomize schools to study groups. Investigators will repeat the student survey in the fall
      of Years 2 and 3 to assess change in the aforementioned constructs. In addition to the
      student survey, investigators will survey a sample of parents in Years 1 and 3. The parent
      survey will assess parent behaviors related to their child's physical activity and nutrition
      and parent reactions to the BMI report.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in body mass index (BMI) z-score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators will assess change in BMI z-score over 3 years between students in Group 1 (BMI screening + reporting) and students in Group 2 (BMI screening only). Primary analyses will be limited to students who were overweight (BMI ≥ 85th percentile) at baseline (Spring 2015). Investigators will also compare change in BMI z-score over 3 years between Group 1 students whose parents received the BMI-only report and Group 1 students whose parents received the BMI + fitness report. In both sets of analyses, ethnicity will be used as an effect modifier.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in weight-control behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators will compare change in weight-control behaviors (assessed via a survey) between students in Group 3, who did not have their heights and weights measured for 2 school years, and students in Groups 1 and 2, who had their heights and weights measured during those years.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in weight-based teasing</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators will compare change in experiences of weight-based teasing (assessed via a survey) between students in Group 3, who did not have their heights and weights measured for 2 school years, and students in Groups 1 and 2, who had their heights and weights measured during those years.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in body satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators will compare change in body satisfaction  (assessed via a survey) between students in Group 3, who did not have their heights and weights measured for 2 school years, and students in Groups 1 and 2, who had their heights and weights measured during those years.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">38830</enrollment>
  <condition>Pediatric Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BMI screening and reporting (Group 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For 3 school years, 3rd-8th grade students will have their heights and weights measured once annually. Additionally, 5th-8th grade students will participate in 5 fitness assessments. Schools will send BMI reports home to parents.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BMI screening only (Group 2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>For 3 school years, 3rd-8th grade students will have their heights and weights measured once annually. Additionally, 5th-8th grade students will participate in 5 fitness assessments. Schools will NOT send height and weight reports home to parents.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No BMI screening or reporting (Group 3)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>For 2 school years, 3rd-8th grade students will NOT have their heights and weights measured at school.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BMI screening</intervention_name>
    <description>Students in grades 3-8 will have their heights and weights measured annually at school and their BMIs calculated.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BMI screening and reporting (Group 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BMI screening only (Group 2)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BMI reporting</intervention_name>
    <description>Schools will send a report home to parents that provides their child's height, weight, and BMI results.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BMI screening and reporting (Group 1)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fitness testing</intervention_name>
    <description>Students in grades 5-8 will participate in 5 fitness assessments (curl-ups, sit-ups, push-ups, sit-and-reach, and the PACER test) annually at school.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BMI screening and reporting (Group 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BMI screening only (Group 2)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Inclusion criteria for school districts:

          1. District does not report BMI results to caregivers and has no history of doing so

          2. District has at least eight schools that meet all of the school-level eligibility
             criteria

        Inclusion criteria for schools:

          1. School does not report BMI results to caregivers and has no history of doing so

          2. School has an enrollment of 30% to 70% Latino students

          3. School has an enrollment of at least 30 students in grades 3 through 8

        Inclusion criteria for students: Student is enrolled in 3rd-8th grade

        Inclusion criteria for parents: Parent has a child who is enrolled in study

        Inclusion criteria for teachers: Teacher measures the heights and weights of students for
        the study

        Exclusion Criteria:   None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kristine A Madsen, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Berkeley</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer K Linchey, BA</last_name>
    <phone>(925) 788-2210</phone>
    <email>jlinchey@berkeley.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UC Berkeley School of Public Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berkeley</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94720</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer K Linchey, BA</last_name>
      <phone>925-788-2210</phone>
      <email>jlinchey@berkeley.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 7, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pediatric obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Overweight</keyword>
  <keyword>Body mass index</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary schools</keyword>
  <keyword>Secondary schools</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
