<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1383">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01768000</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>173/2012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01768000</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Family Cognitive Adaptation Training Manual: A Test of Effectiveness</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Family CAT (Cognitive Adaptation Training Manual): A Test of Effectiveness</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to examine the effectiveness of family cognitive adaptation
      training, including its impact on functioning and caregiver burden.  Families that receive
      the manual will be compared with a control group of families that will not receive the
      manual. The larger goal is to add to the tools family members have access to better support
      their family members with schizophrenia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Efforts to address the cognitive impacts of schizophrenia can be broadly defined as falling
      into either compensatory or restorative categories. Restorative interventions, such as
      cognitive remediation, have shown promise in reducing cognitive deficits and improving
      functional outcomes (McGurk et al., 2007). In contrast, compensatory approaches such as
      Cognitive Adaptation Training work around cognitive deficits by changing the client's
      natural environment to support improved functioning. These compensatory strategies serve to
      bypass cognitive deficits and negative symptoms by organizing belongings and creating
      reminders and environmental cues to support specific adaptive behaviors. An example includes
      the individual packaging of clothes to be worn by day, to simplify the process of choosing
      what to wear and decrease the likelihood of clients impulsively putting on too many clothes
      or otherwise dressing in a manner that is not a good fit for the climate or social settings
      (Draper et al., 2009; Maples &amp; Velligan, 2008).

      Cognitive Adaptation Training (CAT) is a manualized intervention that was developed to help
      individuals compensate for the cognitive deficits associated with schizophrenia. CAT
      interventions commence with a neuropsychological assessment of clients to determine the best
      profile of strategies to be implemented for the specific cognitive classification within
      which the person is placed. Interventions are based on two dimensions 1) level of executive
      functioning (as determined by scores on a set of neurocognitive tests) and 2) whether the
      behaviour of the individual is characterized more by apathy (poverty of speech and movement
      and difficulty initiating behaviours), disinhibition (distractibility and impulsivity) or a
      combination of the two. Clinicians then develop and implement an individualized set of
      strategies that address key domains such as hygiene, safety, dress, and medication. These
      strategies are then altered for strengths or weaknesses in the areas of attention, memory,
      and fine motor skills. For example, for someone with poor attention, the colour of signs can
      be changed regularly or florescent colours can be used to capture attention. For someone
      with memory problems (particularly those with good auditory attention) audiotapes can be
      used to sequence behaviour.

      CAT interventions are established and maintained in the home during monthly to weekly visits
      from a CAT therapist/trainer with the intervention typically lasting 9 months in most of the
      trials that have taken place to date

      Outcomes of randomized trials of CAT have been promising. Compared to control conditions,
      clients receiving CAT have lower levels of symptomatology, lower relapse rates, higher
      levels of adaptive functioning, better quality of life, and better medication adherence
      (Velligan et al., 2000; 2002; 2007; 2008a; 2008b). In general, CAT has been shown to be
      beneficial for individuals with schizophrenia who vary both in degree and type of functional
      impairment.

      The support and involvement of family in the care of individuals with schizophrenia is both
      one of the most important contributors to wellness and recovery and is also, unfortunately,
      one of the least acknowledged components of the recovery process. A high proportion of
      persons with severe mental illness stay in touch with family and the involvement of family
      in care has been associated with better clinical outcomes, improved quality of life, and
      less use of hospitalization (e.g., Fischer et al., 2008). Despite evidence of the importance
      of family in the recovery process, the contribution of family is often not adequately
      appreciated by treatment providers, and contact with providers is often limited. Similarly
      under-developed are evidence-based tools to assist families in their efforts to support the
      recovery of their loved ones.

      It is within this context that the development of a family member version of CAT is a very
      promising avenue to explore. While some elements of CAT require or are otherwise optimized
      by administration by a mental health professional (e.g., neuropsychological testing;
      targeting interventions based upon ongoing clinical evaluation), there are many standard
      components of CAT that can be readily implemented by a family member or other key support.
      Examples include CAT interventions such as visual reminders regarding medication, arranging
      cleaning supplies in the kitchen to reinforce cleaning routines, and assisting in the use of
      a calendar for scheduling. We have developed a tool that facilitates family members
      implementing CAT components that do not require professional administration.

      The initial 'beta' version of Family CAT was developed in close collaboration between Dr.
      Velligan's team at the University of Texas, the group implementing CAT at the CAMH site led
      by Dr. Kidd, and CAMH Social Workers. This 'beta' version is currently in the process of
      having its content reviewed by 6 families to obtain feedback regarding how readily it can be
      understood. Based on this feedback, we will make edits and produce the final version to be
      used in the trial proposed in this protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Multnomah Community Ability Scale (MCAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months following baseline assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Multnomah Community Ability Scale (MCAS; Barker et al., 1994) is a 17-item scale assessing domains of functionality including interference with functioning, adjustment to living, social competence, and behavioral problems. Ratings are made on the basis of an interview with the patient and their family member. The MCAS generates a total score and scores for each of the five domains listed above.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Adherence Rating Scale (BARS)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months following baseline assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Brief Adherence Rating Scale (BARS; Byerly et al., 2008) is a 4-item, valid, reliable, sensitive, measure with which to obtain specific estimates of antipsychotic medication adherence of outpatients with schizophrenia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with Life Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months following baseline assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>8 out of 18 items from the Satisfaction With Life Scale (Test et al., 2005) will measure the perceived quality of life of the individual with schizophrenia by tapping into global satisfaction in domains relevant to CAT (e.g., How satisfied are you with yourself on the whole? - 5 point scale, not at all - great deal). This scale is well-validated with a schizophrenia population and is being shortened as not all items are relevant to CAT nor expected to be sensitive to change in a 4 month period, and there is a need to abbreviate the battery to reduce the risk of fatigue in a lengthy phone interview.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Involvement Evaluation Questionnaire (IES)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months following baseline assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The 31-item Involvement Evaluation Questionnaire (IEQ; Van Wijngaarden et al., 2000) measures caregiver burden. It has been validated for caregivers of individuals with schizophrenia, covers a broad domain of caregiving consequences and refers to burden experienced within the past 4 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Demographics</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Demographic profile for the individuals with schizophrenia and their family members will include age, ethnicity, gender, length of illness (for individual with schizophrenia), amount of family involvement in care, socioeconomic status, employment status, education, housing, history of hospitalization, and support networks including service providers.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of admissions into psychiatric hospital</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Hospitalization will be tracked by self-report of the individual with schizophrenia and as corroborated by the participating family member(s).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Use and Utility of Family CAT</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months following baseline assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessed through the frequency and type of CAT-oriented contacts, and semi-structured interviews with family members about what was or wasn't helpful.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Psychosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Family Cognitive Adaptation Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this group will receive the Family CAT manual and DVD</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this arm will support their family members as usual, and will not receive the Family CAT manual and DVD provided to those in the experimental arm of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Family Cognitive Adaptation Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Family CAT is a 4 month manualised intervention designed to be administered by families independent of clinician support. A self scoring checklist is provided to assess and tailor Family CAT to the individual, along with descriptions of strategies for bathing, dressing, dental hygiene, make-up, toileting, housekeeping/care of living quarters, laundry, grocery shopping, transportation, management of money and consumables, medication management, social skills, communication and telephone use, leisure skills, work skills, and orientation.  Family members will watch the DVD to gain insight into how the strategies can be implemented in real world settings. Having identified the areas of need, family members will administer the interventions and evaluate their effectiveness for the individual.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Family Cognitive Adaptation Training</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Family CAT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  the key family member/support is actively involved in the support of the individual
             with schizophrenia and regularly visits them (i.e., once a week or more frequently)
             in their home environment

          -  the individual being supported is identified (self-identified and identified by the
             family member) as having a primary diagnosis of schizophrenia

          -  the individual with schizophrenia is not in crisis or experiencing other forms of
             instability (e.g., imminent loss of housing) per verbal report that would threaten
             the implementation of the manual strategies

          -  proficiency in English

        Exclusion criteria:

        - none
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sean Kidd, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sean Kidd, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>416-535-8501</phone>
    <phone_ext>6295</phone_ext>
    <email>sean.kidd@camh.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gursharan Virdee, M.Sc</last_name>
    <phone>416-535-8501</phone>
    <phone_ext>4065</phone_ext>
    <email>gursharan.virdee@camh.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sean Kidd, Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>416-535-8501</phone>
      <phone_ext>4065</phone_ext>
      <email>sean.kidd@camh.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>April Collins</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kwame McKenzie, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Debbie Ernest, MSW</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yarissa Herman, Ph.D</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.camh.ca/en/research/Pages/research.aspx</url>
    <description>Information about research at the Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alphs LD, Summerfelt A, Lann H, Muller RJ. The negative symptom assessment: a new instrument to assess negative symptoms of schizophrenia. Psychopharmacol Bull. 1989;25(2):159-63.</citation>
    <PMID>2602512</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Byerly MJ, Nakonezny PA, Rush AJ. The Brief Adherence Rating Scale (BARS) validated against electronic monitoring in assessing the antipsychotic medication adherence of outpatients with schizophrenia and schizoaffective disorder. Schizophr Res. 2008 Mar;100(1-3):60-9. doi: 10.1016/j.schres.2007.12.470. Epub 2008 Feb 5.</citation>
    <PMID>18255269</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Draper ML, Stutes DS, Maples NJ, Velligan DI. Cognitive adaptation training for outpatients with schizophrenia. J Clin Psychol. 2009 Aug;65(8):842-53. doi: 10.1002/jclp.20612.</citation>
    <PMID>19521972</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fischer EP, McSweeney JC, Pyne JM, Williams DK, Naylor AJ, Blow FC, Owen RR. Influence of family involvement and substance use on sustained utilization of services for schizophrenia. Psychiatr Serv. 2008 Aug;59(8):902-8. doi: 10.1176/appi.ps.59.8.902.</citation>
    <PMID>18678688</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hsieh HF, Shannon SE. Three approaches to qualitative content analysis. Qual Health Res. 2005 Nov;15(9):1277-88.</citation>
    <PMID>16204405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McGurk SR, Mueser KT. Cognitive functioning, symptoms, and work in supported employment: a review and heuristic model. Schizophr Res. 2004 Oct 1;70(2-3):147-73. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15329293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McGurk SR, Twamley EW, Sitzer DI, McHugo GJ, Mueser KT. A meta-analysis of cognitive remediation in schizophrenia. Am J Psychiatry. 2007 Dec;164(12):1791-802.</citation>
    <PMID>18056233</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reichenberg A, Harvey PD. Neuropsychological impairments in schizophrenia: Integration of performance-based and brain imaging findings. Psychol Bull. 2007 Sep;133(5):833-58. Review. Erratum in: Psychol Bull. 2008 May;134(3):382.</citation>
    <PMID>17723032</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Test MA, Greenberg JS, Long JD, Brekke JS, Burke SS. Construct validity of a measure of subjective satisfaction with life of adults with serious mental illness. Psychiatr Serv. 2005 Mar;56(3):292-300.</citation>
    <PMID>15746503</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Wijngaarden B, Schene AH, Koeter M, Vázquez-Barquero JL, Knudsen HC, Lasalvia A, McCrone P. Caregiving in schizophrenia: development, internal consistency and reliability of the Involvement Evaluation Questionnaire--European Version. EPSILON Study 4. European Psychiatric Services: Inputs Linked to Outcome Domains and Needs. Br J Psychiatry Suppl. 2000;(39):s21-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10945074</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Velligan DI, Bow-Thomas CC, Huntzinger C, Ritch J, Ledbetter N, Prihoda TJ, Miller AL. Randomized controlled trial of the use of compensatory strategies to enhance adaptive functioning in outpatients with schizophrenia. Am J Psychiatry. 2000 Aug;157(8):1317-23.</citation>
    <PMID>10910797</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Velligan DI, Prihoda TJ, Ritch JL, Maples N, Bow-Thomas CC, Dassori A. A randomized single-blind pilot study of compensatory strategies in schizophrenia outpatients. Schizophr Bull. 2002;28(2):283-92.</citation>
    <PMID>12693434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Velligan DI, Lam F, Ereshefsky L, Miller AL. Psychopharmacology: Perspectives on medication adherence and atypical antipsychotic medications. Psychiatr Serv. 2003 May;54(5):665-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12719495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Velligan DI, Diamond PM, Mintz J, Maples N, Li X, Zeber J, Ereshefsky L, Lam YW, Castillo D, Miller AL. The use of individually tailored environmental supports to improve medication adherence and outcomes in schizophrenia. Schizophr Bull. 2008 May;34(3):483-93. Epub 2007 Oct 10.</citation>
    <PMID>17932089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Velligan DI, Diamond PM, Maples NJ, Mintz J, Li X, Glahn DC, Miller AL. Comparing the efficacy of interventions that use environmental supports to improve outcomes in patients with schizophrenia. Schizophr Res. 2008 Jul;102(1-3):312-9. doi: 10.1016/j.schres.2008.02.005. Epub 2008 Apr 18.</citation>
    <PMID>18374542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sean Kidd</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Independent Clinician Scientist and Head Psychology Service</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Psychosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychosis NOS</keyword>
  <keyword>Schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Schizoaffective Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Bipolar Disorder</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
