<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="60413">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01931735</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E0924-R</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1I01RX000924-01A2</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01931735</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Trial of Arthroscopic Meniscectomy for Degenerative Meniscus Tears</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Trial of Arthroscopic Meniscectomy for Degenerative Meniscus Tears</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Arthroscopic meniscectomy is among the most commonly performed orthopedic surgical
      procedures in the VA system.  There remains substantial uncertainty, however, regarding the
      short term benefits and the long term consequences of arthroscopic meniscectomy in patients
      with degenerative meniscus tears.  Of major concern is the fact that degenerative meniscus
      tears are associated with osteoarthritis, and it is known that within two years of surgery,
      arthroscopic debridement for osteoarthritis is no better than placebo in relieving pain and
      restoring function.  Longer term, meniscectomy has been shown to be associated with elevated
      risk of osteoarthritis development, raising the concern that meniscectomy can actually be
      harmful.  The purpose of this study is to determine whether meniscectomy in the setting of a
      degenerative meniscus tear is of any clinical value.  Determining this would either justify
      the expenses associated with arthroscopic meniscectomy on a large number of patients, or
      would identify an area of significant potential cost savings.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The overall goal of this project is to determine whether arthroscopic meniscectomy in
      degenerative meniscal tears is beneficial from a clinical and scientific viewpoint relative
      to a non-meniscectomy arthroscopy control.  Arthroscopic meniscectomy is among the most
      commonly performed orthopedic surgical procedures in the VA system and nationally.  In our
      practice at the VA Palo Alto Healthcare System over the last year, 80% of patients having
      knee arthroscopy for meniscus tears have been in the 45-70 years age group and 53% of these
      patients had degenerative meniscal tears without a large unstable flap.  these data are
      comparable to arthroscopic meniscectomy data drawn in other settings.  While meniscectomy is
      a common procedure there remains substantial uncertainty regarding the short term benefits
      and the long term consequences of arthroscopic meniscectomy in patients with degenerative
      meniscus tears.  Of major concern is the fact that degenerative meniscus tears are
      associated with osteoarthritis, and it is known that within two years of surgery,
      arthroscopic debridement for osteoarthritis is no better than placebo in relieving pain and
      restoring function.  Longer term, meniscectomy has been shown to be associated with elevated
      risk of osteoarthritis development, raising the concern that meniscectomy can actually be
      harmful.  It has also been shown by our group that patients with clinically successful
      arthroscopic posterior medial meniscectomy have significant change in the rotational motion
      of the knee during walking.  Rotational changes at the knee follow soft tissue damage and
      have been implicated in the causes for cartilage degeneration.

      Thus, there are critical unanswered questions regarding the clinical benefit as well as the
      scientific basis for arthroscopic meniscectomy for degenerative meniscal tear.  To address
      these questions, this project will conduct a prospective, randomized, blinded, and
      controlled study of arthroscopic meniscectomy in patients between the ages of 45 and 70 with
      stable degenerative meniscus tears.  In this study, the control group will be a group of
      patients having arthroscopic lavage of the joint, but no debridement of the stable
      degenerative meniscus tear.   The aims will address clinical (self-reported) and scientific
      (functional) outcomes of arthroscopic meniscectomy in the time frame lasting up to two years
      after surgery.

      Aim 1:  Test the clinical benefit of arthroscopic meniscectomy in the setting of a stable
      degenerative meniscus tear.

      Hypothesis 1a:  There will be a significant differences in WOMAC scores between the
      meniscectomy and the non-meniscectomy/lavage groups at 12 months following surgery.

      Hypothesis 1b:  The WOMAC scores of the non-meniscectomy/lavage group will not be inferior
      to the WOMAC scores of the meniscectomy group at 12 months after surgery.

      Aim 2:  To test the functional effect of arthroscopic meniscectomy in the setting of a
      degenerative meniscus tear.

      Hypothesis 2:  Subjects randomized to arthroscopy and meniscectomy will have greater changes
      in tibio-femoral rotation, knee adduction moment, and knee flexion moment at 12 months
      following surgery when compared to subjects randomized to arthroscopy and lavage.

      In addition to the above principal aims of the study, we will also pursue other exploratory
      aims:

        1. Understand whether arthroscopic meniscectomy for degenerative tear results in
           accelerated radiographic progression of osteoarthritis (KL score) and regional
           cartilage thinning (3D MRI thickness maps) relative to a control group.

        2. Understand whether tibio-femoral position changes measured in our gait analysis relate
           to radiographic progression of osteoarthritis and regional cartilage thinning relative
           to the control group.

        3. Understand whether meniscal tears are associated with activation of the complement
           system and alteration of gene expression in the synovial lining of the knee, and
           whether elevated complement activity relates to radiographic OA progression following
           surgery.

        4. Understand whether serum biomarkers are affected in degenerative meniscus tears and
           whether they will relate to radiographic OA progression or MRI changes following
           surgery.

        5. Investigate whether articular cartilage matrix changes that are measured by advanced MR
           techniques such as T1rho, sodium, or diffusion MRI can be identified and related to
           radiographic OA progression or MRI changes following surgery.

      This prospective clinical trial with coordinated, multi-disciplinary approach will provide
      an important clinical and scientific assessment of arthroscopic meniscectomy.  It will
      identify whether surgical treatment is efficacious, an important issue given the costs and
      risks of surgery.  It will also provide new insight into incipient arthritis, yielding
      information that will impact future patient care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>WOMAC score</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Arthritis Index is a standardized and validated survey used to evaluate the pain and function of patients with lower extremity arthritis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">82</enrollment>
  <condition>Meniscus Tear</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Meniscectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will have a partial meniscectomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lavage</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will have arthroscopy and lavage</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meniscectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>Arthroscopic meniscectomy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Meniscectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Arthroscopic Lavage</intervention_name>
    <description>Arthroscopic Lavage</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lavage</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Veteran

          -  Age between 45 and 70 years

          -  Degenerative meniscus tear as seen on standard clinical MRI scan

          -  Complaint of &quot;mechanical symptoms&quot; which would include popping, catching, or locking
             of the knee

          -  Persistent symptoms for a minimum of three months despite conservative management

          -  Patient is enrolled for arthroscopic meniscectomy

          -  Subject agrees to the study follow-up schedule and signs informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Radiographic osteoarthritis of the knee in any compartment greater than KL grade 2

          -  Prior knee arthroscopy within two years of study enrollment

          -  Unable to have an MRI scan

          -  Does not agree to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicholas J. Giori, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Palo Alto Health Care System, Palo Alto, CA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nicholas J Giori, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(650) 493-5000</phone>
    <phone_ext>64765</phone_ext>
    <email>Nicholas.Giori@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shannon Edd, MS</last_name>
    <phone>(864) 650-6564</phone>
    <email>snedd@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Palo Alto Health Care System, Palo Alto, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304-1290</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Philip S Tsao, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>650-493-5000</phone>
      <phone_ext>66339</phone_ext>
      <email>philip.tsao@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lawrence L Leung, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(650) 493-5000</phone>
      <phone_ext>65742</phone_ext>
      <email>Lawrence.Leung@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nicholas J. Giori, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>menisci</keyword>
  <keyword>tibial</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
