<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="48434">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01705028</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2007C0048/OSU-07042</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21CA156945-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01705028</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Amide-Proton-Transfer MRI in Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of Amide-Proton-Transfer MRI in Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Michael Knopp</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Of cancer related deaths in American men, prostate cancer continues to be the second most
      common cause. The limitations of prostate imaging technology affect its contribution to
      clinical assessment and treatment management of prostate cancer. The high tumor cell
      proliferation rate and cellular density of prostate cancer leads to overall elevated mobile
      protein and peptide levels. The protein levels in the prostate can be non-invasively
      detected by a new molecular imaging technique called amide-proton-transfer magnetic
      resonance imaging (APT-MRI). APT-MRI will provide efficient measurement for improving our
      ability to better regionally localize prostate cancer and predict tumor stages. The overall
      goal of this trial is to evaluate the capability of the APT imaging technique for detection
      and characterization of prostate cancer. APT-MRI could be an important quantitative marker
      to better delineate and detect malignant regions of the prostate in the management of
      prostate cancer patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this trial is to evaluate the capability of the amide-proton-transfer magnetic
      resonance imaging (APT-MRI) technique for detection and characterization of prostate cancer.
      Prostate cancer typically shows a high tumor cell proliferation rate and cellular density
      that leads to overall elevated mobile protein and peptide levels. An imaging method that can
      non-invasively measure these mobile protein levels may considerably improve our ability to
      better regionally localize prostate cancer and predict the degree of malignancies. APT-MRI
      has recently emerged as a new molecular MRI technique to measure endogenous cellular mobile
      protein and peptide levels non-invasively, which cannot otherwise be provided by current
      prostate imaging techniques [Zhou J, Tryggestad E, Wen Z, et al. Differentiation between
      glioma and radiation necrosis using molecular magnetic resonance imaging of endogenous
      proteins and peptides. Nat Med 2011; 17:130-134]. The preliminary data from 12 prostate
      cancer patients reveals that the increased APT-MRI signal of mobile proteins and peptides in
      cancerous regions of the prostate and in higher stage tumors [Jia G, Abaza R, Williams JD,
      et al. Amide proton transfer MR imaging of prostate cancer: a preliminary study. J Magn
      Reson Imaging 2011; 33:647-654], indicates that the APT-MRI signal is sensitive to the
      elevated mobile protein and peptide levels in such malignant regions. These initial
      observations are the basis for a rigorous validation trial.

      The trial is be implemented within a well-established ongoing collaboration at the James
      Cancer Hospital and Solove Research Institute (NCI-designated CCC) at the Ohio State
      University Medical Center. Patients with biopsy-proven prostate cancer will be referred and
      enrolled by urologists performing robotic prostatectomy. A comprehensive imaging scan
      including APT-MRI will be implemented by radiologists, MR physicists and technologists with
      a phased array surface coil in order to image the prostate in its natural shape. Our
      protocol will include micro-MRI of the prostate specimen prior to pathologic evaluation
      using an ultra-high-field MRI scanner. The prostate specimen will subsequently be cut in a
      way that allows direct correlation of the specimen to micro-MRI. A dedicated pathology team
      will delineate the extent of malignant infiltration in the prostate on pathologic slides,
      which will be co-registered with the clinical and APT-MRI images to allow a targeted
      assessment with a radiologic-pathologic correlation. The data analysis will be done by the
      study team and the statistics evaluated by an experienced biostatistician in the subject
      matter at hand.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of the APT-MRI signal in different prostatic zones</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pathology analysis. Region of Interest (ROI) will be placed on digitized pathologic slides by two experienced uro-pathologists. APTR of the ROIs will be used to evaluate the difference of mobile protein and peptide levels by co-registering digitized pathologic slides with APT-MRI.
Radiology Read. The APT-MRI signal maps of mobile proteins and peptides will be color-coded and reviewed by two experienced radiologists. Tumor location and local extent will be recorded based on conventional MRI without and with the APT-MRI signal maps.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">208</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3 T MRI of the prostate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 T MRI of the prostate using amide-proton-transfer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MR Imaging of the prostate using Amide-Proton-Transfer</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>3 T MRI of the prostate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CEST MRI of APT of the prostate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with known or suspected prostate disease based on clinical data will be
             included in the study.

          -  Patients with intermediate to high grade prostate cancer (Gleason's score &gt;/=7 and
             PSA of &gt;10ng/dl) will be referred from the outpatient clinics after evaluation by the
             treating physicians.

          -  Male

          -  Patients must have an estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate of  ≥ 30 mL/min/1.73m2
             within six weeks of the MRI to be included in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with any type of bioimplant activated by mechanical, electronic, or magnetic
             means (e.g., cochlear implants, pacemakers, neurostimulators

          -  Subjects with any type of ferromagnetic bioimplant that could potentially be
             displaced or damaged.

          -  Subjects that have vascular or aneurysm clips, or metallic staples from a surgical
             procedure.

          -  Subjects with permanent tattoo eye liner (may contain metallic coloring).

          -  Subjects that may have shrapnel imbedded in their bodies, such as from war wounds,
             metal workers and machinists (metallic fragments in or near eyes), severe auto
             accident victims.

          -  Subjects that exhibit noticeable anxiety and/or claustrophobia.

          -  Subjects who cannot adhere to the experimental protocols for any reason, or have an
             inability to communicate with the researcher.

          -  Subjects who have cardiac or known circulatory impairment, and/or the inability to
             perspire (poor thermoregulatory function).

          -  Subjects with an estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate of &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73m2 within
             six weeks of the MRI.

          -  Acute or chronic severe renal insufficiency (estimated Glomerular Filtration

          -  Acute renal dysfunction due to the hepato-renal syndrome or in the perioperative
             liver transplantation period
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael V Knopp, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ohio State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Guang Jia, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>614-366-7937</phone>
    <email>jia.11@osu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Carley Hartings</last_name>
    <phone>614-293-3174</phone>
    <email>carley.hartings@osumc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Martha Morehouse Medical Plaza - Wright Center of Innovation in Biomedical Imaging</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43221</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melanie Hughes</last_name>
      <phone>614-293-9998</phone>
      <email>office@wcibmi.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 26, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Ohio State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Knopp</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor and Vice Chair Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tesla MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Prostate cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Amide proton transfer MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>chemical exchange</keyword>
  <keyword>Saturation transfer</keyword>
  <keyword>Mobile protein level</keyword>
  <keyword>Molecular imaging</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
