<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="132727">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01799278</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1210013164</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01799278</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase II Trial of MLN8237 in Patients With Metastatic Castrate Resistant and Neuroendocrine Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial of the Aurora Kinase A Inhibitor MLN8237 in Patients With Metastatic Castrate Resistant and Neuroendocrine Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the response rate of MLN8237 in patients with histologically
      confirmed or clinically suspected metastatic neuroendocrine prostate cancer (NEPC). MLN8237
      is an orally administered Aurora kinase A inhibitor that has demonstrated broad antitumor
      activity in vitro and in vivo. In preclinical models, aurora kinase inhibition resulted in
      dramatic and preferential anti-tumor activity in NEPC with suppression of neuroendocrine
      marker expression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-institutional single-arm, open-label Phase 2 trial evaluating MLN8237 in
      patients with histologically confirmed or clinically suspected metastatic neuroendocrine
      prostate cancer. Subjects will be treated with MLN8237 at 50 mg twice daily for 7 days
      repeated every 21 days. Individual dose reductions will be made on the basis of the AEs
      observed. Therapy will continue until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity as a result
      of MLN8237, or withdrawal of patient consent. Patients will be followed with history,
      physical, and blood tests at each visit to monitor for toxicity. Response and progression
      will be evaluated by CT/MRI scan and bone scan after every 3 cycles and determined using
      RECIST v1.1. PSA and serum chromogranin A and NSE will be followed every cycle. CTC counts
      by CellSearch will be performed at baseline, at 4-6 weeks, and upon progression. Patients
      will be followed for survival endpoints following completion of this study until death.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate, as assessed by CT/MRI and bone scan, of treatment with MLN8237 for patients with neuroendocrine prostate cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the objective response rate of MLN8237 for patients with neuroendocrine prostate cancer with CT/MRI and bone scan every three cycles. Response will be based on Recist criteria 1.1.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival in response to therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will be followed for survival endpoints following completion of this study until death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival in response to therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will be followed for survival endpoints following completion of this study until death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prostate-Specific Antigen (PSA) test response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PSA to be followed every cycle to determine response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating Tumor Cell (CTC) response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>CTC counts by CellSearch will be performed at baseline, at 4-6 weeks, and upon progression to determine response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Small Cell Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Neuroendocrine Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Prostate Adenocarcinoma Plus &gt; 50% Immunohistochemical Staining for Neuroendocrine Markers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MLN8237 at 50 mg twice daily for 7 days repeated every 21 days. Therapy will continue until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity as a result of MLN8237, or withdrawal of patient consent.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MLN8237</intervention_name>
    <description>MLN8237 will be administered orally. The study drug will be administered on an empty stomach with the patient remaining nothing by mouth (NPO), except for water and prescribed medications, for 2 hours before and 1 hour after each dose. Patients will be instructed to take each oral dose of MLN8237 with 8 ounces (1 cup, 240 mL) of water.</description>
    <arm_group_label>All Patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Alisertib</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Metastatic prostate carcinoma and at least one of the following:

               -  Histologic diagnosis of small cell or neuroendocrine prostate cancer

               -  Histologic diagnosis of prostate adenocarcinoma plus &gt; 50% immunohistochemical
                  staining for neuroendocrine markers (chromogranin, synaptophysin or neuron
                  specific enolase)

               -  Development of liver metastases in the absence of PSA progression as defined by
                  PCWG2

          -  Serum chromogranin A level &gt;5 x upper limit of normal and/or serum neuron specific
             enolase (NSE) &gt;2x upper limit of normal

          -  Measurable disease by RECIST 1.1 with PCWG2 modifications

          -  Patients with pure small cell neuroendocrine carcinoma on histology are not required
             to have received prior androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) or castrate levels of
             testosterone, but their testosterone state should be maintained for the duration of
             the study. Other patients are required to have surgical or ongoing chemical
             castration, with baseline testosterone level &lt;50ng/dL.

          -  Patients capable of fathering children must agree to use an effective method of
             contraception for the duration of the trial and should continue use for 4 months
             after last dose of study drug

          -  Subjects must be able to take oral medication and to maintain a fast as required for
             2 hours before and 1 hour after MLN8237 administration.

          -  ANC &gt; 1500/mm³, platelets &gt; 100,000/mm³, Hgb &gt; 9 g/dL. Values must be obtained
             without need for myeloid growth factor or platelet transfusion support within 14
             days, however, erythrocyte growth factor is allowed as per published ASCO guidelines.

          -  Total bilirubin ≤ ULN, SGOT (AST) and SGPT (ALT)&lt; 1.5 x ULN. AST and/or ALT may be up
             to 5X ULN if with known liver metastases provided bilirubin is normal.

          -  Adequate renal function as defined by serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN. If creatinine
             &gt;1.5 x ULN, calculated or measured creatinine clearance must be ≥ 40 mL/minute
             (Cockcroft-Gault).

          -  ECOG performance status 0-2

          -  Estimated life expectancy &gt; 3 months

          -  Voluntary written informed consent before performance of any study-related procedure
             not part of normal medical care, with the understanding that consent may be withdrawn
             by the subject at any time without prejudice to future medical care.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Radiation therapy to 25% of bone marrow within 2 weeks of first dose

          -  Residual &gt; Grade 2 toxicity from prior treatment must have resolved with the
             exception of those explicitly described elsewhere in entry criteria

          -  Known history of uncontrolled sleep apnea syndrome and other conditions that could
             result in excessive daytime sleepiness, such as severe chronic obstructive pulmonary
             disease; requirement for supplemental oxygen.

          -  Requirement for constant administration of proton pump inhibitor, H2 antagonist, or
             pancreatic enzymes. Intermittent uses of antacids or H2 antagonists are allowed (see
             section 5.5)

          -  Severe or uncontrolled systemic infection

          -  Myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to enrollment or has New York Heart
             Association (NYHA) Class III or IV heart failure, uncontrolled angina, severe
             uncontrolled ventricular arrhythmias, or electrocardiographic evidence of acute
             ischemia or active conduction system abnormalities. Prior to study entry, any ECG
             abnormality at Screening has to be documented by the investigator as not medically
             relevant.

          -  Patient has received other investigational drugs with 14 days before enrollment

          -  Serious medical or psychiatric illness likely to interfere with participation in this
             clinical study.

          -  Other severe acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition, including
             uncontrolled diabetes, malabsorption, resection of the pancreas or upper small bowel,
             requirement for pancreatic enzymes, any condition that would modify small bowel
             absorption of oral medications, or laboratory abnormality that may increase the risk
             associated with study participation or investigational product administration or may
             interfere with the interpretation of study results and, in the judgment of the
             investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for enrollment in this study.

          -  Currently active other malignancy excluding controlled non-melanoma skin cancer.
             Patients are considered NOT to have &quot;currently active&quot; malignancy if they have
             completed any necessary therapy and are considered by their physician to be at less
             than 30% risk of relapse.

          -  Treatment with the enzyme-inducing antiepileptic drugs phenytoin, carbamazepine or
             phenobarbital, or rifampin, rifabutin, rifapentine or St. John's wort within 14 days
             prior to the first dose of MLN8237 and during the study

          -  Known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection, hepatitis B, or
             hepatitis C. Testing is not required in the absence of clinical findings or
             suspicion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Himisha Beltran, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Renee Kahn, RN</last_name>
    <phone>212-746-1851</phone>
    <email>Rek9015@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Cornell Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Renne Kahn, RN</last_name>
      <phone>212-746-1851</phone>
      <email>rek9015@med.cornell.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alice Mercado, RN</last_name>
      <phone>212-746-5430</phone>
      <email>alm2051@med.cornell.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 25, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Metastatic prostate carcinoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
