<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="61972">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01767636</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MC1152</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-02027</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01767636</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pazopanib in Treating Patients With Metastatic Non-Clear Cell Kidney Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Efficacy Trial of Pazopanib in Non-Clear Cell Metastatic Renal Cell Cancer (mRCC) PINCR</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well pazopanib hydrochloride works in treating patients with
      metastatic kidney cancer. Pazopanib hydrochloride may stop the growth of tumor cells by
      blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Pazopanib hydrochloride may also stop
      the growth of kidney cancer by blocking blood flow to the tumor
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the efficacy of pazopanib (pazopanib hydrochloride) in non clear cell
      metastatic renal cell cancer patients as assessed by the overall survival rate at 12 months.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the rates of best tumor response at the end of the first two treatment
      cycles of pazopanib in non clear cell metastatic renal cell cancer patients.

      II. To determine the benefit of pazopanib in increasing progression free survival time.

      III. To describe toxicity profile of pazopanib in non clear cell metastatic renal cell
      cancer patients.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive pazopanib hydrochloride orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days 1-28. Courses
      repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A &quot;12-month overall survivor&quot; will be considered synonymous with &quot;success&quot;. The proportion of successes will be estimated by the number of successes divided by the total number of evaluable patients. Confidence intervals for the true success proportion will be calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor response rate, according to the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) v1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A tumor response is defined to be a complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) noted as the objective status on 2 consecutive evaluations at least 8 weeks apart.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From registration to the earliest date documentation of disease progression or death, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Kaplan-Meier curve will be used to estimate progression-free survival time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse event rate, graded according to the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) v4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The maximum grade for each type of adverse event will be recorded for each patient, and frequency tables will be reviewed to determine patterns.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">39</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Renal Cell Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Renal Cell Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Type 1 Papillary Renal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Type 2 Papillary Renal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pazopanib hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive pazopanib hydrochloride PO QD on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pazopanib hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pazopanib hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GW786034B</other_name>
    <other_name>Votrient</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histological confirmation of non-clear cell renal cancer (including chromophilic
             [papillary], chromophobic, oncocytic, sarcomatoid, collecting duct [Bellini's duct])
             or medullary renal cell carcinoma

          -  Up to one prior treatment for metastatic non clear cell carcinoma is allowed prior to
             registration as long as the agent used to treat was not pazopanib

          -  Measurable or non-measurable metastatic disease

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (PS) 0, 1 or 2

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1500

          -  Platelets (PLT) &gt;= 100,000

          -  Hemoglobin (HgB) &gt; 9.0 g/dL; NOTE: Subjects may not have had a transfusion within 7
             days of registration)

          -  Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) =&lt; 2.5 X ULN;
             NOTE: Concomitant elevations in bilirubin and ALT/AST above 1.0 x ULN is not
             permitted

          -  Urine protein to creatinine ratio (UPC) &lt; 1; NOTE: If UPC &gt;= 1, then a 24-hour urine
             protein must be assessed; subjects must have a 24-hour urine protein value &lt; 1 g to
             be eligible

          -  Prothrombin time (PT) or international normalized ratio (INR) =&lt; 1.2 X ULN; NOTE:
             Subjects receiving anticoagulant therapy are eligible if their INR is stable and
             within the recommended range for the desired level of anticoagulation

          -  Calculated creatinine clearance must be &gt;= 45 ml/min using the Cockcroft-Gault
             formula

          -  A female is eligible to enter and participate in this study if she is of:

               -  Non-childbearing potential (i.e., physiologically incapable of becoming
                  pregnant), including any female who has had:

                    -  A hysterectomy

                    -  A bilateral oophorectomy (ovariectomy)

                    -  A bilateral tubal ligation

                    -  Is post-menopausal

                    -  Subjects not using hormone replacement therapy (HRT) must have experienced
                       total cessation of menses for &gt;= 1 year and be greater than 45 years in
                       age, OR, in questionable cases, have a follicle stimulating hormone (FSH)
                       value &gt; 40 mIU/mL and an estradiol value &lt; 40 pg/mL (&lt; 140 pmol/L)

                    -  Subjects using HRT must have experienced total cessation of menses for &gt;= 1
                       year and be greater than 45 years of age OR have had documented evidence of
                       menopause based on FSH and estradiol concentrations prior to initiation of
                       HRT

               -  Childbearing potential, including any female who has had a negative serum
                  pregnancy test, =&lt; 7 days prior to registration

               -  Agrees to use adequate contraception; acceptable contraceptive methods, when
                  used consistently and in accordance with both the product label and the
                  instructions of the physician, are as follows:

                    -  Complete abstinence from sexual intercourse for 14 days before exposure to
                       investigational product, through the dosing period, and for at least 21
                       days after the last dose of investigational product

                    -  Oral contraceptive, either combined or progestogen alone

                    -  Intrauterine device (IUD) or intrauterine system (IUS) with a documented
                       failure rate of less than 1% per year

                    -  Male partner sterilization (vasectomy with documentation of azoospermia)
                       prior to the female subject's entry into the study, and this male is the
                       sole partner for that subject

                    -  Double barrier method: condom and an occlusive cap (diaphragm or
                       cervical/vault caps) with a vaginal spermicidal agent
                       (foam/gel/film/cream/suppository)

          -  Subjects must provide written informed consent prior to performance of study-specific
             procedures or assessments, and must be willing to comply with treatment and
             follow-up; procedures conducted as part of the subject's routine clinical management
             (e.g., blood count, imaging study) and obtained prior to signing of informed consent
             may be utilized for screening or baseline purposes provided these procedures are
             conducted as specified in the protocol

          -  Willing to return to Mayo Clinic enrolling institution for follow-up

          -  Willing to provide, blood, tissue and urine samples for mandatory future unspecified
             correlative research purposes

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any of the following because this study involves an investigational agent whose
             genotoxic, mutagenic and teratogenic effects on the developing fetus and newborn are
             unknown:

               -  Nursing women

               -  Pregnant women

               -  Men or women of childbearing potential who are unwilling to employ adequate
                  contraception

          -  Co-morbid systemic illnesses or other severe concurrent disease which, in the
             judgment of the investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for entry into
             this study or interfere significantly with the proper assessment of safety and
             toxicity of the prescribed regimens

          -  Immunocompromised patients (other than that related to the use of corticosteroids)
             including patients known to be human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive

          -  Prior history of receiving pazopanib treatments

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to:

               -  Ongoing or active infection

               -  Symptomatic anemia, uncontrolled hypertension (defined as systolic blood
                  pressure [SBP] of &gt;= 140 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure [DBP] of &gt;= 90mmHg)

               -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure as defined by the New York Heart
                  Association (NYHA); does not exclude class III congestive heart failure (CHF)

               -  Previously treated with therapies that are known to negatively impact cardiac
                  function (e.g. prior treatment with anthracyclines)

               -  Unstable angina pectoris

               -  Cardiac arrhythmia

               -  Evidence of active bleeding or bleeding diathesis

               -  Psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
                  requirements

               -  Or any other serious uncontrolled medical disorders in the opinion of the
                  investigator

          -  History of cerebrovascular accident including transient ischemic attack (TIA),
             myocardial infarction, pulmonary embolism or untreated deep venous thrombosis (DVT),
             coronary artery bypass graft surgery within 6 months prior to registration; Note:
             Subjects with recent DVT who have been treated with therapeutic anti-coagulating
             agents for at least 6 weeks are eligible

          -  Receiving any other investigational agent which would be considered as a treatment
             for the primary neoplasm

          -  Other active malignancy =&lt; 5 years prior to registration; EXCEPTIONS: Non-melanotic
             skin cancer or carcinoma-in-situ of the cervix; NOTE: If there is a history or prior
             malignancy, they must not be receiving other specific treatment for their cancer

          -  History or clinical evidence of central nervous system (CNS) metastases or
             leptomeningeal carcinomatosis, except for individuals who have previously-treated CNS
             metastases, are asymptomatic, and have had no requirement for steroids or
             anti-seizure medication for 6 months prior to first dose of study drug; screening
             with CNS imaging studies (computed tomography [CT] or magnetic resonance imaging
             [MRI]) is required only if clinically indicated or if the subject has a history of
             CNS metastases

          -  Clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities that may increase the risk for
             gastrointestinal bleeding including, but not limited to:

               -  Active peptic ulcer disease

               -  Known intraluminal metastatic lesion/s with risk of bleeding

               -  Inflammatory bowel disease (e.g. ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease), or other
                  gastrointestinal conditions with increased risk of perforation

               -  History of abdominal fistula, gastrointestinal perforation, or intra-abdominal
                  abscess =&lt; 28 days prior to registration

               -  Clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities that may affect absorption
                  of investigational product including, but not limited to:

                    -  Malabsorption syndrome

                    -  Major resection of the stomach or small bowel

          -  Corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt; 480 msecs using Bazett's formula

          -  Receiving any medications or substances with risk of torsades de pointes; Note:
             medications or substances on the list &quot;Drugs with Risk of Torsades de Pointes&quot; are
             prohibited; medications or substances on the list &quot;Drugs with Possible or Conditional
             Risk of Torsades de Pointes&quot; may be used while on study with extreme caution and
             careful monitoring

          -  Known endobronchial lesions and/or lesions infiltrating major pulmonary vessels
             and/or hemoptysis in excess of 2.5 mL (or one half teaspoon) =&lt; 8 weeks of
             registration

          -  Treatment with any of the following anti-cancer therapies: radiation therapy, surgery
             or tumor embolization, chemotherapy, immunotherapy, biologic therapy, investigational
             therapy or hormonal therapy =&lt; 14 days prior to registration

          -  Prior autologous or allogeneic organ or tissue transplantation

          -  Elective or planned major surgery to be performed during the course of the trial

          -  Receiving any medications or substances that are strong or moderate inhibitors of
             cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4); use of the strong or moderate inhibitors are prohibited
             =&lt; 7 days prior to registration

          -  Receiving any medications or substances that are inducers of CYP3A4; use of inducers
             are prohibited =&lt; 7 days prior to registration
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian A. Costello, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mayo Clinic Clinical Trials Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>507-538-7623</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Brian A. Costello, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 10, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
