<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="129615">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02136576</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11184</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>New Investigator Grant</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02136576</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Caries Prevention Products &amp; Dentinal Hypersensitivity</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparing Three Caries Prevention Products on Dentinal Hypersensitivity - A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tufts University School of Dental Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tufts University School of Dental Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this pilot research project is to compare the clinical effect on dentinal
      hypersensitivity of three products: Casein Phosphopeptide-Amorphous Calcium Phosphate
      (CPP-ACP) paste with fluoride, 5000 Sodium Fluoride (NaF) dentifrice containing Tri-Calcium
      Phosphate (TCP), and a dentifrice containing Potassium Nitrate.

      The hypothesis of this study is that CPP-ACP with fluoride and 5000ppm NaF with TCP will
      exhibit a greater reduction in dentinal hypersensitivity compared to the control (dentifrice
      containing Potassium Nitrate).

      The results of this pilot study will validate or negate the need for a larger clinical study
      that may provide generalizable results for using caries-prevention products with the
      additional benefit of minimizing dentinal hypersensitivity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Dentinal hypersensitivity commonly occurs in patients with gingival recession, resulting
      from a reduced periodontium or in patients who have undergone non-surgical and surgical
      periodontal therapy. When the gingiva recede, the root surfaces of the teeth are exposed. In
      addition, after a non-surgical or surgical periodontal procedure, the cementum of the root
      surface is removed as a result of scaling and root planing.  This leaves dentin exposed on
      the root surface with open dentinal tubules.  In addition, dentin is less mineralized than
      enamel and has a greater susceptibility to and a faster progression of root caries and
      dentinal hypersensitivity. Root caries commonly occurs in patients who have undergone
      periodontal therapy and extensive root caries often results in the extraction of the tooth.

      Dental professionals often make a variety of recommendations to remedy dental
      hypersensitivity, including the application of fluoride varnishes, anti-hypersensitivity
      toothpaste, gingival grafting procedures and various restorative procedures, aiming to
      occlude the dentinal tubules or desensitize the pulpal nerve endings.

      Since the introduction of Caries Management By Risk Assessment (CAMBRA) in the Journal of
      the California Dental Association in 2007, the marketplace for anti-caries products has
      surged.  As a result, many approaches to the management of dental caries have been
      introduced and dental practitioners and sales representatives have promoted several
      anti-caries products.  In addition, the reduction or the abatement of the progression of
      dental caries (coronal, root and interproximal) as a result of a caries management program
      has been reported. Many caries management products have ingredients that include fluoride
      and calcium phosphate (Amorphous Calcium Phosphate-Casein Phosphopeptide (Recaldent ™),
      Tri-Calcium Phosphate ™ or Novamin ™).  Moreover, encouraging clinical findings have been
      reported, including, but not limited to the reduction of white spot enamel lesions and
      dentinal hypersensitivity.

      The topical application of &quot;antihypersensitivity&quot; materials is a common recommendation
      (least invasive of the &quot;standard of care&quot; recommendations) to diminish dentinal
      hypersensitivity and will serve to provide data for the research study.  The study will
      evaluate which of these products result in the greatest reduction of dentinal
      hypersensitivity. The application of the experimental products for the reduction of dentinal
      hypersensitivity is for research purposes.

      The methods used to test sensitivity in this study have been used in published studies. The
      VAS scale used in this study has also been used for tooth sensitivity studies. A 30%
      decrease in VAS score has been shown to be clinically meaningful.

      This pilot study would investigate the ability of anti-caries products to reduce dentinal
      hypersensitivity when compared to a sensitivity-reducing dentifrice.  It would be a novel
      contribution to the dental community if a material that is proven to reduce tooth decay is
      also proven to reduce dentinal hypersensitivity.  The results may potentially have a
      tremendous impact on the dental community because it may provide dental professionals a
      scientifically-supported approach to improve the comfort and quality of life of periodontal
      patients (patients who are treated for gum disease/ bone loss around teeth) and increase the
      lifespan of teeth that undergo periodontal treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Dentinal Hypersensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks after baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary analysis will be to compare the percent change in dentinal hypersensitivity between the 3 groups.  We assume that the control group may exhibit a modest improvement in dentinal hypersensitivity (~5%) whereas the two test groups should demonstrate a more significant improvement (~30%).  Assuming a common standard deviation of 25%, we will have 58% power to detect a difference between the 3 groups using one way analysis of variance, with 10 subjects per group, and setting alpha to 0.05 (nQuery Advisor, Version 7.0). Up to 13 subjects per group will be recruited, to allow for a more than 20% dropout rate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypersensitivity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sensodyne</arm_group_label>
    <description>There are no specific characteristics for inclusion in this group. Enrollment will be determined randomly.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Crest Cavity Protection &amp; MI Paste Plus</arm_group_label>
    <description>There are no specific characteristics for inclusion in this group. Enrollment will be determined randomly.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clinpro 5000</arm_group_label>
    <description>There are no specific characteristics for inclusion in this group. Enrollment will be determined randomly.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        TUSDM clinics and the greater-Boston community.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  At least 18 years of age

          -  Tooth with exposed root surface and/or exposed dentin

          -  Tooth with a VAS score greater than or equal to 3

          -  No adjacent tooth/teeth with sensitivity (as defined as 2 or higher on the VAS)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participation in another dental study that may alter the results of this study.

          -  A medical condition that could interfere with reliable pain reporting (e.g., pain
             disorders)

          -  Any chronic medical condition that requires the regular use of pain or
             anti-inflammatory medications

          -  Used a desensitizing dentifrice within the preceding four weeks

          -  Have received an antihypersensitivity treatment (varnish or precipitating solution)
             of the identified tooth within the preceding four weeks

          -  Undergoing active orthodontic treatment.

          -  Teeth with carious lesions, buccal vertical cracks in enamel, evidence of
             irreversible pulpitis (pain lasting more than five seconds after air stimulation)

          -  Pregnant/ lactating patients (Clinpro5000 has 5000ppm fluoride and there is a risk of
             ingesting the product)

          -  Patients with Milk Allergy (CPP-ACP is a dairy based product)

          -  Patients on Kidney Dialysis (due to the free calcium in CPP-ACP, dialysis patients
             should be on a diet with limited calcium)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pamela Maragliano-Muniz, DMD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tufts University School of Dental Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pamela Maragliano-Muniz, DMD</last_name>
    <phone>(617) 636-3576</phone>
    <email>Pamela.Maragliano@tufts.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tufts University School of Dental Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pamela Maragliano-Muniz, DMD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 7, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
