<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="92426">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01920854</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RMTI-SFP-9</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01920854</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Single Ascending Dose Study of Soluble Ferric Pyrophosphate Administered Intravenously in Healthy Volunteers.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-blind, Randomized, Placebo-controlled, Single Ascending Dose Study of Intravenously Administered SFP in Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rockwell Medical Technologies, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rockwell Medical Technologies, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the pharmacokinetics of fixed ascending doses of
      intravenously administered Soluble Ferric Pyrophosphate
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  A total of 48 healthy volunteers will be studied.

        -  Depending on the safety profile at completion of the highest dose cohort, an additional
           2 cohorts of subjects may be studied.

        -  Doses of SFP may be modified, depending on the PK and safety findings at each dose
           level.

        -  Cohorts may be dropped for safety or tolerability after discussion with the sponsor.

        -  There will be 6 active and 2 placebo subjects in each study cohort.

        -  Subjects in Cohorts 1-3 will receive ascending doses of SFP by intravenous infusion
           over 4 hours.

        -  Subjects in Cohorts 4-6 will receive ascending doses of SFP by intravenous infusion
           over 12 hours.

      All subjects will be confined in the CRC for 1 day prior to study drug administration and
      for 2 additional days for safety assessments and completion of test procedures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of iron from Soluble Ferric Pyrophosphate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Serum iron, transferrin bound iron and TIBC for Cohorts 1-3 will be collected at 0, 0.5,1, 2, 3, 4, 4.5, 5, 6, 7, 7.5, 8, 9,10, 12,12.5 14, 16, 20, 24,36, and 48 hours.
Serum iron, transferrin bound iron and TIBC for Cohorts 4-6 will be collected at 0, 0.5,1, 2, 4, 6, 9, 12,12.5, 14,16,18,20, 24, 30, 36, and 48 hours.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Tolerability of Soluble Ferric Pyrophosphate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety of Soluble Ferric Pyrophosphate will be determined by assessment of adverse events and laboratory measurements.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Failure, Chronic Therapy; Hemodialysis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Soluble Ferric Pyrophosphate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group/Cohort Designation: Ascending doses of SFP/placebo. Each subject will receive a defined dose of SFP or placebo IV administered under double-blind conditions.  Pharmacokinetics of iron will be measured using a validated assay for iron and transferrin bound iron.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group/Cohort Designation: Ascending doses of SFP/placebo. Each subject will receive a defined dose of SFP or placebo IV administered under double-blind conditions.  Pharmacokinetics of iron will be measured using a validated assay for iron and transferrin bound iron.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Soluble Ferric Pyrophosphate</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Soluble Ferric Pyrophosphate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SFP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18-55 inclusive at the time of consent.  This inclusion criterion will only be
             assessed at the first screening visit.

          2. Male or non-pregnant, non-lactating female who is at least 90 days post-partum.

          3. Subject is willing to comply with any applicable contraceptive requirements of the
             protocol.

          4. Satisfactory medical assessment with no clinically significant or relevant
             abnormalities in medical history, physical examination (PE), vital signs,
             electrocardiogram (ECG) and laboratory evaluation (hematology, biochemistry,
             urinalysis) as assessed by the Investigator.

          5. An understanding, ability and willingness to fully comply with study procedures and
             restrictions.

          6. Ability to provide written, personally signed and dated informed consent to
             participate in the study, in accordance with the International Conference on
             Harmonization (ICH) Good Clinical Practice (GCP) Guideline E6 and applicable
             regulations, before completing any study-related procedures.

          7. Body Mass Index (BMI) between 20.0 and 32.0 kg/m² inclusive.  This inclusion
             criterion will only be assessed at the first screening visit.

          8. Subjects must agree to discontinue all iron preparations for 14 days prior to study
             drug administration.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Current or recurrent disease (e.g. cardiovascular, renal, liver, gastro-intestinal,
             malignancy or other conditions) that could affect the action, absorption or
             disposition of the investigational product utilized in this study, or could affect
             clinical or laboratory assessments.

          2. Hemoglobin &lt; 11 g/dL or Hematocrit &lt; 30%.

          3. Serum iron concentration ≤ 70 µg/dL (male or female).

          4. Current or relevant previous history of physical or psychiatric illness, any medical
             disorder that may require treatment or make the subject unlikely to fully complete
             the study, or any condition that presents undue risk from the investigational product
             or study procedures.

          5. Significant illness, as judged by the investigator, within 2 weeks of the first dose
             of investigational product.

          6. Current use of any medication (including prescription, over the counter [OTC], herbal
             or homeopathic preparations) within 14 days of first dose of investigational product.
             Exceptions are hormonal replacement therapy, hormonal contraceptives, acetaminophen
             and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs.

          7. Known or suspected intolerance or hypersensitivity to iron containing product(s).

          8. History of alcohol or other substance abuse within the last year.

          9. A positive screen for cotinine, alcohol or drugs of abuse.

         10. Male subjects who consume more than 21 units of alcohol per week or three units per
             day.  Female subjects who consume more than 14 units of alcohol per week or two units
             per day.  1 alcohol unit =1 beer = 1 wine (5oz) = 1 liquor (1.5 oz.).

         11. A history of a positive human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibody screen, Hepatitis
             B surface antigen (HBsAg) or Hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody screen.

         12. Use of tobacco in any form (e.g., smoking or chewing) or other nicotine-containing
             products in any form (e.g. gum, patch).  Ex-users must report that they have stopped
             using tobacco for at least 30 days prior to receiving the first dose of
             investigational product.

         13. Routine consumption of more than five units of caffeine per day or subjects who
             experience caffeine withdrawal headaches.  One caffeine unit is contained in the
             following items:  one 6-oz. cup of coffee, two 12-oz. cans of cola, one 12-oz. cup of
             tea, three 1-oz. chocolate bars.

         14. Donation of blood or blood products (e.g., plasma or platelets) within 60 days prior
             to receiving the first dose of investigational product.

         15. Use of another investigational product within 30 days prior to receiving the first
             dose of investigational product or active enrolment in another drug or vaccine
             clinical study.

         16. Pregnancy or intention to become pregnant before completing all study drug treatment.

         17. Current medical status that, in the investigators opinion, would preclude
             participation in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raymond D Pratt, MD FACP</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Rockwell Medical Inc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kalamazoo</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>49007</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 8, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Soluble Ferric Pyrophosphate, Pharmacokinetics, Iron, Hemodialysis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Iron</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
