<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="131311">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02144077</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ALA-BCC-CT008</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-003241-42</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02144077</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy Study for the Treatment of Non-Aggressive Basal Cell Carcinoma With Photodynamic Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Observer Blind, Multinational Phase III Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of BF-200 ALA (Ameluz®) in Comparison to Metvix® in the Treatment of Non-aggressive Basal Cell Carcinoma (BCC) With Photodynamic Therapy (PDT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Biofrontera Bioscience GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Accovion GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Biofrontera Bioscience GmbH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to test the effectiveness and safety of the medicine Ameluz®, used
      with photodynamic therapy (PDT), to treat thin, non-aggressive rodent ulcer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The treatment comprises of up to 2 PDT cycles, each with two PDT sessions one week apart.

      If 12 weeks after the the second PDT all lesions are completely cleared the patient will
      enter the follow-up phase. In case of remaining lesions the patient will receive a second
      PDT cycles starting on the same day.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient complete response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks after the last PDT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Complete responder rate at week 12 after last PDT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lesion complete response</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks after the last PDT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Lesion complete response (completely cleared individual lesions) assessed 12 weeks after the last PDT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction of lesion area</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks after the last PDT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Reduction of total lesion area (summation of sizes of all treated lesions) per patient, assessed 12 weeks after the last PDT.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient complete response</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks after the last PDT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient complete response (complete clearance of all treated lesions) assessed 12 weeks after PDT-2 (first PDT cycle).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall cosmetic outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks after the last PDT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall cosmetic outcome 12 weeks after last PDT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks after the last PDT for the observer-blind study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Frequency and extent of treatment-emergent AEs (TEAEs), including serious AEs (SAEs).
TEAEs are defined as all AEs with onset or worsening after first treatment with randomized investigational medicinal product (IMP).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local skin reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>during and up to 7 days after each PDT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Local skin reactions in the treatment area as assessed by the investigators during illumination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local discomfort</measure>
    <time_frame>during and up to 7 days after PDT</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Local discomfort or pain reported by patients during illumination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">360</enrollment>
  <condition>Basal Cell Carcinoma (BCC)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BF-200 ALA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Topical application of BF-200 ALA gel containing 78 mg/g 5-aminolevulinic acid. Application of a 1 mm thick layer covering each lesion  and 0.5 to 1 cm of surrounding margin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>methyl-aminolevulinate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Topical application of Metvix creme containing 160 mg/g methyl-aminolevulinate. Application of a 1 mm thick layer covering each lesion  and 0.5 to 1 cm of surrounding margin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BF-200 ALA</intervention_name>
    <description>topical treatment for photodynamic therapy combining drug application and subsequent illumination with a narrow spectrum light source (after 3 h of drug incubation)</description>
    <arm_group_label>BF-200 ALA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ameluz</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>methyl-aminolevulinate</intervention_name>
    <description>topical treatment for photodynamic therapy combining drug application and subsequent illumination with a narrow spectrum light source (after 3 h of drug incubation)</description>
    <arm_group_label>methyl-aminolevulinate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Metvix</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Willing and able to sign the informed consent form; must be obtained in writing for
             all patients before starting any study procedures.

          -  Presence of 1to 3 thin (≤2 mm thickness), non-aggressive, primary BCC lesions
             (comprising primary superficial, nodular, or mixed superficial/nodular) in the
             face/forehead, bald scalp, extremities and/or neck/trunk. Confirmation of
             non-aggressiveness and thickness of BCC through biopsies of all lesions taken at
             screening.

          -  The diameter of each lesion should range between ≥ 0.5 cm and ≤2 cm; the total
             maximal treated area is approximately 10 cm² (including a 0.5 - 1.0 cm margin
             surrounding each lesion). The maximal thickness of a lesion should not exceed 2 mm
             (by means of histopathological confirmation).

          -  Target BCC lesions must be discrete and quantifiable and have to be located within
             1-2 treatment areas.

          -  Free of significant physical abnormalities (eg tattoos, dermatoses) in the potential
             treatment area that may cause difficulty with examination or final evaluation.

          -  Accept to abstain from extensive sunbathing and the use of a solarium during the
             observer blind part of the study. Patients with sunburn within the treatment areas
             cannot be included until fully recovered.

          -  Healthy patients and patients with clinically stable medical conditions, including,
             but not limited to controlled hypertension, diabetes mellitus type II,
             hypercholesterolemia, and osteoarthritis, will be permitted to be included in the
             study if their medication is not prohibited by this protocol.

          -  Women of childbearing potential are permitted to participate in this study only if
             they have a negative serum pregnancy test at screening and a willingness to use a
             highly effective method of contraception during the observer blind part of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of hypersensitivity to 5-ALA or any ingredient of BF-200 ALA, MAL or any
             ingredient of Metvix® cream, including arachis oil, or to peanut or soya.

          -  Hypersensitivity to porphyrins.

          -  Current treatment with immunosuppression therapy.

          -  Presence of porphyria.

          -  Presence of BCC lesions on embryonic fusion planes (H-zone).

          -  Presence of more than 3 BCCs.

          -  Presence of malignant or benign tumors or precancerous lesions of the skin other than
             nonaggressive BCC within the treatment area (eg malignant melanoma, squamous cell
             carcinoma (SCC)) within the last 12 weeks.

          -  Gorlin Syndrome or Xeroderma pigmentosum.

          -  Presence of photodermatoses.

          -  Treatment of lesions (actinic keratosis (AK), BCC, SCC, Bowens disease, melanoma) ≤12
             weeks prior to first PDT, except physical treatments (eg cryosurgery, excision
             surgery) that will not be allowed ≤4 weeks prior to screening visit (Visit 1).

          -  Presence of inherited or acquired coagulation defect.

          -  Start of intake of medication with hypericin or systemically-acting drugs with
             phototoxic or photoallergic potential within 8 weeks prior to screening.

          -  Clinically relevant cardiovascular, hepatic, renal, neurologic, endocrine, or other
             major systemic disease making implementation of the protocol or interpretation of the
             study results difficult.

          -  Evidence of clinically significant (CS), unstable medical conditions, such as:

               -  Metastatic tumor or tumor with high probability of metastasis.

               -  Cardiovascular disease (New York Heart Association [NYHA] class III, IV).

               -  Immunosuppressive condition.

               -  Hematologic, hepatic, renal, neurologic, or endocrine condition.

               -  Collagen-vascular condition.

               -  Gastrointestinal condition.

          -  Topical treatment with 5-ALA or MAL outside the treatment area during the observer
             blind part of the study.

          -  Any topical treatment including diclofenac and immunomodulatory agents (eg imiquimod,
             ingenol mebutate) 12 weeks prior to the first PDT session and during the observer
             blind part of the study.

          -  Any physical treatment during the observer blind part of the study within the treated
             target areas.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rolf M. Szeimies, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Klinik fuer Dermatologie und Allergologie (Klinikum Vest - Knappschaftskrankenhaus), Recklinghausen, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Colin Morton, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dermatology Department, Stirling Community Hospital, NHS Forth Valley, United Kingdom</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinikum Vest GmbH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Recklinghausen</city>
        <state>Westfalen-Lippe</state>
        <zip>45657</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rolf-Markus Szeimies, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <email>Rolf-Markus.Szeimies@Klinikum-Vest.de</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 20, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Photodynamic Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>PDT</keyword>
  <keyword>non-aggressive BCC</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Basal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Aminolevulinic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methyl 5-aminolevulinate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
