<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="92558">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02087254</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>XTPTC-293-54</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>PTC-293-54</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02087254</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study for the Evaluation Dabrafenib (Tafinlar) and Trametinib (Mekinist) Plus DNE3 in Patients With Metastatic Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>XTPTC-293-54-for the First Time in Human Studies to Establish the Recommended Dose and Schedule of Oral Dabrafenib, Trametinib and DNE3</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cancer Centre of Monoclonal Therapy, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Melanoma Research Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cancer Centre of Monoclonal Therapy, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Ukraine: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Russia: Pharmacological Committee, Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Belarus: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Previous studies have shown that combination of a BRAF inhibitor (dabrafenib) with MEK
      inhibitor (trametinib) and exhibit synergistic effects on tumor cells (melanoma), together
      with Akt inhibitors. But the major drawbacks of many effective cancer chemotherapeutic
      agents are systemic toxicity and drug resistance. In this regard ,  phytotherapeutic agent
      DNE3 (PI3K-Akt inhibitor) with high anticancer activity and less toxicity to normal tissues
      has been suggested as possible candidates for their capability to improve the efficacy of
      anticancer drugs Dabrafenib and Trametinib.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Previous studies have shown that combination of a BRAF inhibitor (dabrafenib) with MEK
      inhibitor (trametinib) and exhibit synergistic effects on tumor cells (melanoma), together
      with Akt inhibitors. But the major drawbacks of many effective cancer chemotherapeutic
      agents are systemic toxicity and drug resistance. In this regard ,  phytotherapeutic agent
      DNE3 (PI3K-Akt inhibitor) with high anticancer activity and less toxicity to normal tissues
      has been suggested as possible candidates for their capability to improve the efficacy of
      anticancer drugs Dabrafenib and Trametinib.

      The role of PI3K-Akt and MAPKs pathways in the regulation of u-PA or MMPs expressions in
      carcinoma cells has been well studied. It has been shown that an inhibition of p-Akt may
      lead to a reduction in the expression of MMP-2 or u-PA as well as in the invasion of tumor
      cells. DNE3 could reduse the phosphorylation of Akt in B16-F10 cells. To make a linkage
      between p-Akt and protease expressions, the effects of DNE3 on several transcription factors
      were examined. It is well known that the activation of AP-1 and NF- kB and the downstream of
      the PI3K-Akt pathway are associated with inflammation, cell invasion, migration, and
      angiogenesis, and that suppression of any of these transcription factors is potentially an
      effective means to block tumor invasion or metastasis, as well as blocking the factors that
      bind to these regulatory elements, and therefore represents an appropriate approach to
      inhibit the synthesis of MMPs or u-PA. In our studies, DNE3 was found to effectively
      suppress the DNA binding activity and the expression of NF- kB while the protein level of I-
      kB, the endogenous inhibitor of NF- kB, was gradually increased along with the concentration
      of DNE3.

      Us repeatedly in laboratory studies proved thatHS68, human foreskin fibroblast cells, was
      used to demonstrate that DNE3 exerted no cytotoxicity on normal foreskin fibroblast cells.
      In conclusion, Dioscorea nipponica potently inhibits melanoma invasive and metastatic
      potential; therefore, they may constitute a valuable tool in the combination therapy of
      metastatic melanoma and in the prevention of melanoma metastases with Dabrafenib and
      Trametinib
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    When used appear DNE3 toxic properties.  The DSMB determined that due to higher than expected
    risk and safety concerns the study should be closed.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the safety of DNE3  in combination with Dabrafenib and Trametinib and select the optimal dose of DNE3 for the phase II portion in patients with metastasis melanoma (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Maximum-tolerated dose (MTD) of Akt inhibitor DNE3 during therapy Dabrafenib and Trametinib, determined according to incidence of dose-limiting toxicity (DLT), graded using the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0 (Phase I)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration to date of death due to any cause, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival (Phase II) Estimated confidence interval. Tolerability of the regimens in terms of the number of patients who required dose modifications and/or dose delays. (Time Frame: Up to 4 weeks after completion of study treatment ) Tolerability of the regimen in each of the treatment arms will be collected and summarized using descriptive statistics. We will also capture the proportion of patients who go off treatment due to adverse reactions or even those who refuse further treatment for lesser toxicities that inhibit their willingness to continue participation on the trial. These tolerability measures will be assessed within each of the treatment arms and we will explore differences in these measures .</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity rate graded by the NCI CTCAE version 4.0 (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicity rate graded by the NCI CTCAE version 4.0 (Phase II) Safety and Tolerability of dabrafenib, trametinib and DNE3 as assessed adverse events (AEs) ( From the first dose of study treatment until 30 days after discontinuation of study treatment (approximately 1 year but can be up to 3 years)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">78</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>melanoma,Dabrafenib,Trametinib,DNE3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive Dabrafenib 150 mg twice daily orally plus Trametinib 2 mg once daily orally plus DNE3 0.2 g/kg of body weight, daily on a continuous basis. Dabrafenib will be administered under fasted conditions, either 1 hour (hr) before or 2 hours (hrs) after a meal with approximately 200 mL of water with an interval of 12 hours. Trametinib will be administered under fasted conditions, either 1 hr before or 2 hrs after a meal with approximately 200 mL of water. DNE3 will be administered under fasted conditions, either 1 hr before or 2 hrs after a meal with approximately 200 mL of water. Subjects will take their dose of Trametinib and DNE3 concurrently with the morning dose of Dabrafenib. A treatment cycle is 28 days in duration. Subjects will continue treatment until an unacceptable toxicity, disease progression, or death occurs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dabrafenib</intervention_name>
    <description>Dabrafenib 150 mg  orally will be administered. Capsules with unit dose strengths of 50 mg or 75 mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>melanoma,Dabrafenib,Trametinib,DNE3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tafinalar</other_name>
    <other_name>GSK2118436</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trametinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Trametinib 2 mg once daily orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>melanoma,Dabrafenib,Trametinib,DNE3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mekinist</other_name>
    <other_name>GSK1120212</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DNE3</intervention_name>
    <description>DNE3 - 0.2 g/kg of body weight - (a nontoxic concentration of the extract was treated directly to highly metastatic murin melanoma cells (B16F10) and human melanoma cells (A2058) , it exerted a dose-dependent inhibitory effect on the invasion , motility , secretion of MMPs , and u-PA of both cell lines)</description>
    <arm_group_label>melanoma,Dabrafenib,Trametinib,DNE3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dioscorea nipponica Makino with ethyl acetate (DNE3)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed written informed consent

          -  Recheck the results of histological studies and paraffin blocks

          -  Histologically confirmed cutaneous melanoma that is either Stage IIIc (unresectable)
             or Stage IV (metastatic), and determined to be BRAF V600E or V600K mutation-positive
             by the local laboratory.

          -  Measurable tumor by physical or radiographic examination

          -  Subjects must not have had more than 1 previous treatment regimen with chemotherapy,
             interferon, or IL-2 for metastatic melanoma

          -  All prior anti-cancer treatment-related toxicities (except alopecia) must be &lt;= Grade
             1 according to the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0
             at the time of enrollment

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1

          -  Adequate baseline organ function as defined by: absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;=
             1.2 × 109/L; Hemoglobin &gt;= 9 g/dL; Platelet count &gt;= 100 x 109/L; prothrombin time
             (PT) / international normalized ratio (INR) and partial thromboplastin time (PTT) &lt;=
             1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN); Albumin &gt;= 2.5 g/dL; Total bilirubin &lt;= 1.5 x ULN;
             aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine transaminase (ALT) &lt;= 2.0 x ULN;
             Creatinine &lt;=1.5 mg/mL; Left Ventricular Ejection fraction (LVEF) &gt;= lower limit of
             normal (LLN) by ECHO

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test within 7
             days prior to randomization and agree to use effective contraception, during the
             study, and for 30 days after the last dose of study treatment

          -  Men with a female partner of childbearing potential must have either had a prior
             vasectomy or agree to use effective contraception for at least 2 weeks prior to the
             first dose of study treatment until 16 weeks after the last dose of study treatment
             to allow for clearance of any altered sperm

          -  Able to swallow and retain orally administered study treatment and does not have any
             clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities that may alter absorption such
             as malabsorption syndrome or major resection of the stomach or bowels

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior treatment with a BRAF inhibitor (including but not limited to dabrafenib,
             vemurafenib, and XL281/BMS-908662) or a MEK inhibitor (including but not limited to
             trametinib, AZD6244, and RDEA119) or ipilimumab or any other agent targeting a T-cell
             immunomodulatory pathway (including, but not limited to CTLA-4, PD-1, 4-1BB, OX40,
             GITR, CD27, and CD28)

          -  Any major surgery, extensive radiotherapy, chemotherapy with delayed toxicity,
             biologic therapy, or immunotherapy within 21 days prior to randomization and/or daily
             or weekly chemotherapy without the potential for delayed toxicity within 14 days
             prior to randomization

          -  Known Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), Hepatitis B Virus (HBV), or Hepatitis C
             Virus (HCV) infection (with the exception of chronic or cleared HBV and HCV
             infection)

          -  A history of glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency

          -  All known lesions were previously treated with surgery or stereotactic surgery
             (whole-brain radiation is not allowed unless given after definitive treatment with
             surgery or stereotactic surgery)

          -  Brain lesion(s), if still present, must be confirmed stable (i.e., no increase in
             lesion size) for &gt;= 6 weeks prior to randomization (stability must be confirmed with
             two consecutive magnetic resonance image (MRI) or computed tomography (CT) scans with
             contrast,

          -  Asymptomatic with no corticosteroid requirements for &gt;= 4 weeks prior to
             randomization,

          -  No enzyme inducing anticonvulsants for &gt;= 4 weeks prior to randomization

          -  A history or evidence of cardiovascular risk including any of the following LVEF &lt;
             LLN for the institution

          -  A corrected QT interval &gt;=480 msec (e.g. Bazett's formula [QTcB])

          -  A history or evidence of current clinically significant uncontrolled arrhythmias
             (exception: subjects with controlled atrial fibrillation for &gt; 30 days prior to
             randomization are eligible)

          -  A history (within 6 months prior to first dose of study treatment) of acute coronary
             syndromes (including myocardial infarction or unstable angina), coronary angioplasty

          -  A history or evidence of current &gt;=Class II congestive heart failure as defined by
             the New York Heart Association (NYHA)

          -  Treatment refractory hypertension defined as systolic blood pressure &gt;140 millimetres
             of mercury (mmHg) and/or diastolic blood pressure &gt;90 mmHg which cannot be controlled
             by antihypertensive therapy

          -  Patients with intra-cardiac defibrillators

          -  Abnormal cardiac valve morphology (&gt;=grade 2) documented by echocardiogram (subjects
             with grade 1 abnormalities [i.e., mild regurgitation/stenosis] can be entered on
             study). Subjects with moderate valvular thickening should not be entered on study

          -  A history or current evidence/risk of retinal vein occlusion (RVO) or Central serous
             retinopathy (CSR) including

          -  Presence of predisposing factors to RVO or CSR (e.g., uncontrolled glaucoma or ocular
             hypertension, uncontrolled hypertension, uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, or a history
             of hyperviscosity or hypercoagulability syndromes), or

          -  Visible retinal pathology as assessed by ophthalmic examination that is considered a
             risk factor for RVO or CSR such as evidence of new optic disc cupping; Evidence of
             new visual field defects on automated perimetry; Intraocular pressure &gt;21 mmHg as
             measured by tonography

          -  History of any of the following diseases: inflammatory bowel disease or any other
             autoimmune bowel disease; systemic lupus erythematosus; rheumatoid arthritis; or any
             autoimmune ocular diseases. Patients with active autoimmune disease or a history of
             autoimmune disease other than those mentioned above must be approved by the GSK
             medical monitor

          -  Active pneumonitis or interstitial lung disease

          -  Lactating female

          -  History of another malignancy (Exception: Subjects who have been disease-free for 3
             years, or subjects with a history of completely resected non-melanoma skin cancer or
             successfully treated in situ carcinoma are eligible)

          -  Any serious and/or unstable pre-existing medical, psychiatric disorder or other
             conditions that could interfere with subject's safety, obtaining informed consent or
             compliance to the study procedures

          -  Any prohibited medication

          -  Administration of an investigational study treatment within 28 days or 5 half-lives,
             whichever is longer, preceding the first dose of study treatment(s) in this study

          -  Known immediate or delayed hypersensitivity reaction or idiosyncrasy to drugs
             chemically related to the study treatments, their excipients, and/or dimethyl
             sulfoxide (DMSO)

          -  Unwillingness or inability to follow the procedures outlined in the protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew Petrov, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cancer centre of Monoclonal Therapy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gomel Region Clinical Oncology Dispensary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gomel</city>
        <country>Belarus</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Marien Hospital Wesel gGmbH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wesel</city>
        <zip>46483</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arkhangelsk District Clinical Oncology Dispensary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Arkhangelsk</city>
        <zip>163045</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Federal State Institution &quot;Moscow Institute of Cancer Research named after P.A. Hertsen&quot; Ministry of Health of Russian Federation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>125284</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>N.N.Petrov Oncology Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>St.Petersburg</city>
        <zip>197758</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Volgograd District Oncology Dispensary №1</name>
      <address>
        <city>Volgograd</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ul.Gazety Pravda 96</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dnepropetrovsk</city>
        <zip>49000</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kharkiv Regional Clinical Oncology Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kharkiv</city>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lviv Regional State Cancer Diagnostics and Treatment Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lviv</city>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Poltava Regional Clinical Oncology Dispensary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Poltava</city>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vinnytsa Regional Clinical Oncology Dispensary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vinnytsa</city>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belarus</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Ukraine</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 10, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Dabrafenib</keyword>
  <keyword>Trametinib</keyword>
  <keyword>DNE3</keyword>
  <keyword>Dioscorea nipponica</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
