<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82300">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01904448</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-0664</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IDE# G120019/S001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01904448</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Auditory Brainstem Implantation in Young Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Early Feasibility Study of the Safety and Efficacy of the Nucleus 24 Auditory Brainstem Implant in Children With Cochlear or Cochlear Nerve Disorders Not Resulting From Neurofibromatosis Type II</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To purpose of this feasibility study is to demonstrate the safety and efficacy of the
      Nucleus 24 Multichannel Auditory Brainstem Implant (ABI, Cochlear Corp, Sydney, AUS) in
      children without the diagnosis of neurofibromatosis type II (NFII) that have either
      experienced failed cochlear implantation (CI) or have been unable to receive a CI secondary
      to cochlear or cochlear nerve disorders. These conditions can include: developmental or
      acquired cochlear nerve deficiency (CND), cochlear aplasia (Michel), post-meningitic
      cochlear ossification or cochlear malformation.

      This study proposes to implant up to 10 young children (&lt;5 yrs. of age) with the Nucleus 24
      Multichannel ABI (Sydney, AUS) in an attempt to demonstrate safety of the surgical
      procedure, tolerance of device stimulation, and the potential for auditory benefit beyond
      that experienced with their CI. This study will provide the preliminary experience for a
      larger scale clinical trial.

      Aim 1: Demonstrate the safety of ABI surgery in children. Aim 2: Demonstrate the development
      of sound awareness and improved speech understanding among children implanted with the ABI
      when compared to their baseline skills. Aim 3: Demonstrate the development of oral language
      skills following the use of the ABI that were not evident prior to its use.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Complications and related outcomes will be tracked and recorded. These include bleeding, infection, neural injury, cerebrospinal fluid leakage, brain bleeding or bruising, stroke, death. Also, complications and sequelae related to the device such as non-auditory stimulation and device failure will be tracked.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Speech Perception</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Detection audiogram, aided and unaided individual ears
IT-MAIS or MAIS
LING 6 sound test
ESP Low Verbal or Standard- MLV @ 50dB HL
PB-k words and phonemes- MLV @ 50dB HL
MLNT- recorded @ 60dB SPL,  If &gt;50% then
LNT- recorded @ 60dB SPL, If &gt;80%, then
CNC- 50 words @ 60dB SPL
HINT-C- 2 lists of 10 @ 60dB SPL</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Speech Production and Language</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MacArthur-Bates Communicative Development Inventories (CDIs) Pre-School Language Scale, Fourth Edition (PLS-5) The Oral and Written Language Scales (OWLS) Goldman-Fristoe Test of Articulation.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Developmental Cochlear Nerve Deficiency</condition>
  <condition>Acquired Cochlear Nerve Deficiency</condition>
  <condition>Cochlear Aplasia</condition>
  <condition>Post-meningitis Cochlear Ossification</condition>
  <condition>Cochlear Malformation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Auditory Brainstem Implant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>single-arm study of auditory brainstem implantation in children</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Auditory Brainstem Implantation in Children</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Auditory Brainstem Implant</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pre-linguistic hearing loss (birth-5 yrs.; age at ABI 18 months-5yrs) with both:

          -  MRI +/- CT evidence of one of the following: Cochlear nerve deficiency, Cochlear
             aplasia or severe hypoplasia, Severe inner ear malformation, Post-meningitis
             ossification

          -  When a cochlea is present or patent, lack of significant benefit from CI despite
             consistent use (&gt;6 mo.)

          -  Post-linguistic hearing loss (&lt;18 yrs. of age) with both:

          -  Loss or lack of benefit from appropriate CI without the possibility for revision or
             contralateral implantation. Examples might include: Post-meningitis ossification,
             Bilateral temporal bone fractures with cochlear nerve avulsion, Failed revision CI
             without benefit

          -  Previously developed open set speech perception and auditory-oral language skills

          -  No medical contraindications

          -  Willing to receive the appropriate meningitis vaccinations

          -  No or limited cognitive/developmental delays which would be expected to interfere
             with the child's ability to cooperate in testing and/or programming of the device, in
             developing speech and oral language, or which would make an implant and subsequent
             emphasis on aural/oral communication not in the child's best interest

          -  Strong family support including language proficiency of the parent(s) in the child's
             primary mode of communication as well as written and spoken English.

          -  Reasonable expectations from parents including a thorough understanding:

               -  of potential benefits and limitations of ABI

               -  of parental role in rehabilitation

               -  that the child may not develop spoken language as a primary communication mode
                  or even sufficient spoken language to make significant academic progress in an
                  aural/oral environment

          -  Involvement in an educational program that emphasizes development of auditory skills
             with or without the use of supplementary visual communication.

          -  Able to comply with study requirements including travel to investigation sites.

          -  Informed consent for the procedure from the child's parents/legal guardian.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pre- or post-linguistic child currently making significant progress with CI

          -  MRI evidence of one of the following:

               -  normal cochlea and cochlear nerves or NFII

               -  brainstem or cortical anomaly that makes implantation unfeasible

          -  Clear surgical reason for poor CI performance that can be remediated with revision CI
             or contralateral surgery rather than ABI.

          -  Intractable seizures or progressive, deteriorating neurological disorder

          -  Unable to participate in behavioral testing and mapping with their CI. If this
             appears to be an age effect, ABI will be delayed until we can be assured that the
             child will be able to participate, as reliable objective measures of mapping are
             currently not available for mapping these devices.

          -  Lack of potential for spoken language development. This will be considered the case
             when evidence of the following exist:

               -  Severe psychomotor retardation, autism, cerebral palsy, or developmental delays
                  beyond speech that would preclude usage of the device and oral educational
                  development. Autism is a special case where there is the potential for delayed
                  presentation. When early signs are considered present, our group routinely
                  requests a comprehensive developmental assessment for further evaluation prior
                  to considering routine evaluation. A specialized group is readily available at
                  our institution for such an evaluation.

          -  Unable to tolerate general anesthesia (cardiac, pulmonary, bleeding diathesis, etc.).

          -  Need for brainstem irradiation

          -  Unrealistic expectations on the part of the subject/family regarding the possible
             benefits, risks and limitations that are inherent to the procedure and prosthetic
             device.

          -  Unwilling to sign the informed consent.

          -  Unwilling to make necessary follow-up appointments.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Craig A Buchman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Craig A Buchman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>919 966-6484</phone>
    <email>buchman@med.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Holly FB Teagle, AuD</last_name>
    <phone>919 419-1449</phone>
    <email>holly_teagle@med.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599-7600</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Craig A Buchman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>919-966-6484</phone>
      <email>buchman@med.unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Holly FB Teagle, AuD</last_name>
      <phone>919 419-1449</phone>
      <email>holly_teagle@med.unc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Craig A Buchman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 3, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Craig A. Buchman, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor and Vice Chair for Clinical Affairs</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pediatric</keyword>
  <keyword>profound hearing loss</keyword>
  <keyword>auditory brainstem implant</keyword>
  <keyword>cochlear implant</keyword>
  <keyword>developmental or acquired cochlear nerve deficiency (CND)</keyword>
  <keyword>cochlear aplasia (Michel)</keyword>
  <keyword>post-meningitis cochlear ossification</keyword>
  <keyword>cochlear malformation</keyword>
  <keyword>CND</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Meningitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurofibromatosis 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vestibulocochlear Nerve Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
