<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="93957">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01734655</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PBRC12013 The MEQ Study</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01DK094418</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01734655</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Validity of Using the MEQ to Measure Mindful Eating in Pregnant Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Qualitative Evaluation of the Mindful Eating Questionnaire (MEQ) in Pregnant Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Specific Aim of this supplemental project is to qualitatively evaluate the Mindful
      Eating Questionnaire (MEQ) to determine if it is a valid instrument for pregnant women.
      During this project, the MEQ will be qualitatively evaluated in a sample of pregnant women
      who are similar in age, ethnicity, education, and marital status to the women targeted for
      recruitment in the parent study. The qualitative evaluation will include a focus group with
      10 participants followed by 30 individual cognitive interviews. Comments from the interviews
      will be summarized and analyzed systematically for each of the 28 questions of the MEQ and
      the interviewer will use findings from initial interviews to inform subsequent interviews.
      Content validity will be evaluated based on responses from the focus group and cognitive
      interviews, and MEQ items will be evaluated for comprehension, retrieval, judgment, and
      response. Strengths, weaknesses, relevance, comprehensiveness, and interpretations will be
      reported for each of the MEQ questions. We will also have some of the more traditional
      validation parameters (the inclusion of other questionnaires) in the study to collect data
      on convergent and discriminant validity.  The resulting publication will provide readers
      with a thorough report on the utility and appropriateness of using the MEQ to quantify
      mindful eating in pregnant women.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pre-pregnancy maternal overweight/obesity and excess weight gain during pregnancy are
      associated with metabolic abnormalities in mothers and their offspring. Despite guidelines
      developed by the Institute of Medicine (IOM) for appropriate levels of gestational weight
      gain, more than 50% of overweight and obese pregnant women exceed the recommended amount of
      weight gain during pregnancy (CDC 2009). Updated guidelines from the Institute of Medicine
      (IOM) in 2009 suggest that individualized dietary counseling and regular physical activity
      are necessary for pregnant women to achieve appropriate levels of gestational weight gain
      (IOM and NRC 2009), yet few studies have examined weight management in overweight pregnant
      women and none were successful at increasing adherence to the IOM guidelines (Polley, Wing
      et al. 2002; Olson, Strawderman et al. 2004; Asbee, Jenkins et al. 2009; Shirazian, Monteith
      et al. 2010; Phelan, Phipps et al. 2011).

      This project is a supplement to a parent study called Expecting Success: Personalized
      management of body weight during pregnancy (U01 DK094418-01 PIs: Leanne M. Redman, Ph.D. &amp;
      Corby K. Martin, Ph.D.). The parent study will test the efficacy of two interventions at
      promoting appropriate levels of weight gain during pregnancy compared to each other and to a
      usual care control group. Appropriate levels of weight gain during pregnancy will be defined
      by the 2009 IOM gestational weight gain guidelines (CDC 2009). The two interventions include
      training on mindfulness surrounding eating, hunger, and satiety; hence, it is logical to
      test if changes in mindfulness differ between the two intervention groups and the usual care
      group. Moreover, it is possible that change in mindfulness will be associated with the
      study's outcome or different levels of gestational weight gain between the usual care group
      and the two intervention groups. Finally, changes in mindfulness could mediate the effect of
      the two interventions on gestational weight gain.

      Despite the possible importance of mindfulness to the eating behavior and weight management
      of pregnant women, no measure has been validated to measure mindfulness in pregnant women.
      The Mindful Eating Questionnaire (MEQ) is a 28-item self-report instrument that measures
      five domains of mindful eating: disinhibition, awareness, external cues, emotional response,
      and distraction. Mindful eating refers to an unbiased awareness of sensations surrounding
      eating and although a preliminary study found the MEQ to be a valid measure of mindful
      eating in healthy adults, it has not been validated in pregnant women. A valid measure of
      mindful eating is required when an intervention is used to increase mindful eating in
      pregnant women and evaluate if the increase results in healthier eating habits and effective
      weight management. Indeed, effectively measuring mindful eating is central to evaluating: 1)
      if an intervention had the anticipated effect on mindful eating, 2) if increasing mindful
      eating resulted in changes to eating habits and body mass, and 3) if changes in mindful
      eating mediated treatment effects.

      Relationship of the supplement to the parent grant: Mindfulness training is effective at
      helping people manage their eating habits, making mindfulness training a viable strategy to
      use with special populations who struggle with eating and weight management, including
      pregnant women. During the parent study, two personal weight-management interventions
      designed to meet the unique needs of pregnant women will be deployed and mindful eating
      techniques are part of these interventions. Although a preliminary study found the Mindful
      Eating Questionnaire (MEQ) to be valid in a convenience sample of generally healthy adults,
      it is not known if the MEQ is an appropriate and valid instrument for use with pregnant
      women, and the proposed project will answer this question. If the MEQ is valid for use with
      pregnant women, it can be used in the parent study, as well as other studies, to determine
      if the interventions are effectively at training participant to mindfully eat and if changes
      in mindful eating mediate intervention effects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Cross-Sectional</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>validity of the MEQ for use in pregnant women</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed in focus group or cognitive interview</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Content validity will be evaluated based on responses from the focus group and cognitive interviews, and MEQ items will be evaluated for comprehension, retrieval, judgment, and response. A report on the appropriateness of using the MEQ to quantify mindful eating in pregnant women will be generated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Focus Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>The first 10 participants who are enrolled in this study will participate in a 1.5 hour focus group.  Focus groups allow researchers to obtain participant responses and data in a social context where peoples' responses are considered in the context of other peoples' responses. Participants will be asked to complete the MEQ, the Eating Inventory Questionnaire, The Mindful Attention Awareness Scale (MAAS), and the Neighborhood Environment Walkability Scale (NEWS). Participants will then be asked to sequentially respond to each of the 28 items and the response choices from the MEQ and briefly discuss their reaction to the items and response choices. Finally, the focus group will be asked: &quot;Do you believe that the MEQ's items adequately represent what mindful eating means to you?&quot; All responses will be tape-recorded and transcribed verbatim.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Interview</arm_group_label>
    <description>The next thirty participants who are enrolled will complete individual cognitive interviews. Cognitive interviews have been used for many years to evaluate the appropriateness of self-report instruments for special populations and to determine if the wording of questions and response choices could contribute to response error. Cognitive interviews will be used in this study to evaluate the appropriateness of the MEQ and its items for pregnant women.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Forty pregnant women (10 will participate in the focus group and 30 will complete
        individual cognitive interviews) will be recruited who are similar in age, ethnicity,
        education, and marital status to the women who will be recruited for the parent study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18-40 years of age, inclusive

          -  Overweight or obese at time of conception based on self-report (BMI ≥25 and &lt;40
             kg/m2)

          -  Willingness to participate in either the focus group or the individual interview

          -  Establish prenatal care by 12 weeks of gestation

          -  Fluent in the English language; AND

          -  Singleton pregnancy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current multiple gestation

          -  Type I diabetes

          -  Self-reported gestational diabetes mellitus

          -  History or current psychotic disorder

          -  Current major depressive episode, bipolar disorder, or eating disorder

          -  HIV

          -  Current smoking, alcohol or drug use

          -  History of ≥ 3 miscarriages

          -  Current enrollment in Expecting Success (IRB#11024)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Corby K. Martin, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>225-763-2585</phone>
    <email>corby.martin@pbrc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baton Rouge</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70808</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Corby K Martin, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>225-763-2585</phone>
      <email>corby.martin@pbrc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Corby K Martin, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stewart T Gordon, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John W Apolzan, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leanne M Redman, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tiffany M Stewart, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.pbrc.edu/clinical-trials/?studyid=156</url>
    <description>PBRC Web Screener for MEQ</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 16, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 20, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Corby K. Martin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor, Director Ingestive Behavior Laboratory</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
