<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="65606">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02099838</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Tongji201202</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02099838</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness and Safety of Adding Compound Preparation of Pioglitazone and Metformin for Type 2 Diabetic Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Randomized Multiple Center Trial for The Effectiveness and Safety of Adding Compound Preparation of Pioglitazone and Metformin for Type 2 Diabetic Patients Who Have Bad Glycemic Control With the Initial Treatment of Sulfonylureas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Huazhong University of Science and Technology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Wuhan Iron and Steel Workers' Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Wuhan Pu-Ai Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hubei Xinhua Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Huazhong University of Science and Technology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Secondary failure of sulfonylureas (SUs) can occur in about 30%-40% of type 2 diabetic
      patients after treatment with SUs for 5 years, although SUs are widely used in type 2
      diabetic patients. This study was designed to evaluate the effectiveness and safety of
      adding compound preparation of pioglitazone and metformin for type 2 diabetic patients who
      have bad glycemic control with the initial treatment of SUs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design of this clinical trial was multicenter, randomized, double-blind and placebo parallel
      controlled. Type 2 diabetic patients having bad glycemic control with the initial treatment
      of SUs were included. They were randomly divided into experiment group and control group,
      respectively taking compound preparation of pioglitazone and metformin (2mg/500mg) and
      placebo with identical shape immediately before a meal twice a day. Course of the treatment
      was 12 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HbA1c</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measuring venous level of HbA1c at the start of the trail and at week 12 in all subjects, then analyzing the change in HbA1c from baseline at week 12 of experimental group and comparing that between experiment group and control group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FPG</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measuring venous level of FPG(fasting plasma glucose) at the start of the trail and at week 12 in all subjects, then analyzing the change in FPG from baseline at week 12 of experimental group and comparing that between experiment group and control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2hPPG</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measuring venous level of 2hPPG(2-hour postprandial glucose) at the start of the trail and at week 12 in all subjects, then analyzing the change in 2hPPG from baseline at week 12 of experimental group and comparing that between experiment group and control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting Insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measuring venous level of fasting insulin at the start of the trail and at week 12 in all subjects, then analyzing the change in fasting insulin from baseline at week 12 of experimental group and comparing that between experiment group and control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2-hour Postprandial Insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measuring venous level of 2-hour postprandial insulin at the start of the trail and at week 12 in all subjects, then analyzing the change in 2-hour postprandial insulin from baseline at week 12 of experimental group and comparing that between experiment group and control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total Cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measuring venous level of TC(Total Cholesterol) at the start of the trail and at week 12 in all subjects, then analyzing the change in TC from baseline at week 12 of experimental group and comparing that between experiment group and control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total Triglyceride</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measuring venous level of TG(Total Triglyceride) at the start of the trail and at week 12 in all subjects, then analyzing the change in TG from baseline at week 12 of experimental group and comparing that between experiment group and control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HDL</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measuring venous level of HDL(High-Density Lipoprotein) at the start of the trail and at week 12 in all subjects, then analyzing the change in HDL from baseline at week 12 of experimental group and comparing that between experiment group and control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>LDL</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measuring venous level of LDL(Low-Density Lipoprotein) at the start of the trail and at week 12 in all subjects, then analyzing the change in LDL from baseline at week 12 of experimental group and comparing that between experiment group and control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Event Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Calculating the number of subjects having adverse event such as hypoglycemia and the rates of adverse rate in experiment group and control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">98</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pioglitazone and Metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Type 2 diabetic patients only took SUs previously. During  a week for washout before the trial, they received diet and sport instructions, kept the SUs unchanged and didn't use any drugs affecting blood glucose. They all participants added 1 tablet of pioglitazone and metformin twice a day (before breakfast and before dinner) orally for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Type 2 diabetic patients only took SUs previously. During  a week for washout before the trial, they received diet and sport instructions, kept the SUs unchanged and didn't use any drugs affecting blood glucose. They all participants added 1 tablet of placebo twice a day (before breakfast and before dinner) orally for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pioglitazone and Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>taking 1 tablet twice a day (before breakfast and before dinner) orally for 12 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pioglitazone and Metformin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Compound Preparation of Pioglitazone and Metformin</other_name>
    <other_name>Kashuangping</other_name>
    <other_name>H20100180</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>taking 1 tablet twice a day (before breakfast and before dinner) orally for 12 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 2 diabetic patients (WHO criterion, 1999)

          -  19kg/m2 ≤ BMI ≤ 35kg/m2

          -  Subject with the initial treatment of SUs on the basis of controlling diet and sport;
             treatment lasting for no less than 3 months and stable dose for at least 1 month;
             HbA1c 7-11%

          -  No insulin therapy during 6 months before being selected

          -  Not involved in any drug test during 3 months before being selected

          -  No serious heart, liver or kidney diseases

          -  Must have effective contraception methods for women of child-bearing age

          -  Willing to being informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 1 diabetes or other specific types of diabetes

          -  Pregnancy, preparation for pregnancy, lactation and women of child-bearing age
             incapable of effective contraception methods

          -  Uncooperative subject because of various reasons

          -  Abnormal liver function, ALT and AST ＞ twice the upper limits of normal

          -  Impairment of renal function, serum creatinine: ≥ 133mmol/L for female，≥ 135mmol/L
             for male

          -  Serious chronic gastrointestinal diseases

          -  Edema

          -  Serious heart diseases, such as cardiac insufficiency (level III or more according to
             NYHA), acute coronary syndrome and old myocardial infraction

          -  Blood pressure: SBP ≥ 180mmHg and/or DBP ≥ 110mmHg

          -  WBC ＜ 4.0×109/L or PLT ＜ 90×109/L，or definite anemia (Hb：＜ 120g/L for male, ＜ 110g/L
             for female), or other hematological diseases

          -  Endocrine system diseases, such as hyperthyroidism and hypercortisolism

          -  Experimental drug allergy or frequent hypoglycemia

          -  Psychiatric disorders, drug or other substance abuse

          -  Diabetic ketoacidosis and hyperosmolar nonketotic coma requiring insulin therapy

          -  Stressful situations such as surgery, serious trauma and so on

          -  Chronic hypoxic diseases such as pulmonary emphysema and pulmonary heart disease

          -  Combined use of drugs effecting glucose metabolism such as glucocorticoid

          -  Tumor, especially bladder tumor and/or family history of bladder tumor and/or
             long-term hematuria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xuefeng Yu, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Division of Endocrinology, Tongji Hospital, Huazhong University of Science &amp; Technology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tongji Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wuhan</city>
        <state>Hubei</state>
        <zip>430030</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 26, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 24, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Huazhong University of Science and Technology</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Xuefeng Yu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Department of Endocrinology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pioglitazone</keyword>
  <keyword>Metformin</keyword>
  <keyword>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pioglitazone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
