<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35045">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01763320</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>XW125-S002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01763320</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>China Angioplasty &amp; Stenting for Symptomatic Intracranial Severe Stenosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>CASSISS</acronym>
  <official_title>China Angioplasty &amp; Stenting for Symptomatic Intracranial Severe Stenosis (CASSISS): A Prospective Multi-center, Randomized Controlled Trial (RCT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xuanwu Hospital, Beijing</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xuanwu Hospital, Beijing</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      SAMMPRIS (Stenting vs. Aggressive Medical Management for Preventing Recurrent Stroke in
      Intracranial Stenosis) hasn't received the expected results; however, it does not mean that
      clinical exploration on intracranial treatment come to a full stop. On the contrary, a
      discrepancy on reported data between multi-centre RCT and most single center studies urges
      us for thorough investigation in future.

      CASSISS is an investigator-initiated, government-funded RCT that will determine whether
      intracranial stenting and best medical therapy is superior to aggressive medical therapy
      alone for preventing stroke during a mean follow-up of three years in patients with
      symptomatic stenosis of a major intracranial artery (MCA, carotid, vertebral, basilar). This
      trial was launched by Xuanwu Hospital, Capital University of Medical Science, with 10
      collaborators participating. Enrollment will begin in 2013, and it aims to have a sample
      size of 520 subjects (PTAS, 260; medication, 260) in 3 years. The trial is scheduled to
      complete in 2015.

      SAMMPRIS is flawed with defect in design, heterogeneity in experience and credentials of
      operators and high rate of complication; some questions have been raised, and remained
      resolved. CASSISS has been modified based on SAMMPRIS in order to acquire the data for
      China:

      Technique, experience, and credential of the operators are closely related with
      perioperative complications in PTAS. The investigators select 10 representatives from 40
      large-scale medical centers for participation on the basis of geographical distribution. All
      the participants are ranked as top in China. They have the most experienced surgeons or
      interventionist in China, and are fully qualified for this trial. This will guarantee the
      success and safety of technique, maintain the continuity of operator's experience, and make
      the complication rate as low as possible.

      Pre-CASSISS registry trial:

      A registry pilot trial will be performed prior to CASSISS. It aims to test the credentialing
      of interventionists and participating centers. As for the candidate centers, the following
      aspects will be considered: PTAS experiences, peri-operative complications, and the number
      of accumulated PTAS cases in each center. Centers are required to have a team consisting of
      a neurologist, an interventionist, a neurosurgeon, and a research coordinator. All the
      centers involved are required to to perform a competitive registration study of recruiting a
      consecutive 100 PTAS as a pool together as a registration trial within duration of 6 months.
      Certification was achieved by participating centers, whose clinical results are audited by
      means of a validated selection process documenting that they have performed more than 5
      procedures within this period and that the rates of complications (morbidity and mortality)
      are less than 15%. Those who will not satisfy the certification criterion will be excluded
      from the final trial.

      The 3rd-party company is employed to provide trial design, management, supervision, and
      quality control service.

      The 30-day rate of stroke or death associated with stenting in the SAMMPRIS trial (14.7%) is
      nearly 2.5 times as high as CREST, one third of which is symptomatic intracranial
      hemorrhage. It was thought because of reperfusion hemorrhage since the median time from
      qualifying event to randomization in SAMMPRIS is one week only. The investigators modify one
      of inclusion criteria that all the recruited patients routinely undergo MRI plus DWI
      (diffusion-weighted imaging) scans to exclude any possible new lesions. In case of new
      infarction identified on DWI (diffusion-weighted imaging) or qualifying event confirmed by
      neurologist, the patient will be rescheduled for randomization one month later.

      SAMMPRIS was stopped ahead of schedule due to the safety concern. More than half of the PTAS
      patients were lost for follow-up at 1 year, and the remaining were followed up with a mean
      duration less than 1 year. It leaves the question of long-time follow-up data open. Base on
      SAMMPRIS, the investigators' trial will conduct a systematic follow-up system. Upon
      recruitment, all the patients' neurological and imaging examination will be determined at
      baseline, 1 week, 1 month, 1 year, and 2 year after surgery, respectively.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Over two-thirds of stroke deaths worldwide are in developing countries, and China has the
      largest population among developing countries. Unlike in western countries, cerebrovascular
      disease predominates; the number of patients who die from stroke is more than three times
      that from coronary heart disease; furthermore, distribution of cerebrovascular lesions is
      greatly affected by race, and Chinese have more intracranial steno-occlusive disease than
      white. Therefore, it is extremely necessary to update the understanding on incidence,
      prevalence, cost, outcome, recurrence rate, and treatment strategy for intracranial
      steno-occlusive disease in China. Unfortunately, we have little knowledge about it so far.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the number of participants who suffer from Ischemic stroke, death or cardiovascular events after enrollment or after any revascularization procedure of the qualifying lesion in the territory of the symptomatic intracranial artery</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>the number of participants who suffer from Ischemic stroke, death or cardiovascular events after enrollment or any revascularization procedure of the qualifying lesion in the territory of the symptomatic intracranial artery</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the number of participants who suffer from Ischemic stroke, death or cardiovascular events after enrollment or after any revascularization procedure of the qualifying lesion in the territory of the symptomatic intracranial artery</measure>
    <time_frame>beyond 30 days to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>the number of participants who suffer from Ischemic stroke, death or cardiovascular events after enrollment or after any revascularization procedure of the qualifying lesion in the territory of the symptomatic intracranial artery</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the number of participants who suffer from disabling stroke or death</measure>
    <time_frame>beyond 30 days through 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>the number of participants who suffer from disabling stroke or death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the number of participants who suffer from restenosis (&gt;50%) related to intracranial stenting</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>the number of participants who suffer from restenosis (&gt;50%) related to intracranial stenting</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the number of participants who suffer from any stroke, severe transient ischemic attack (TIA), cardiovascular events related to intracranial stenting or medical therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>the number of participants who suffer from any stroke, severe transient ischemic attack (TIA), cardiovascular events related to intracranial stenting or medical therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the changes from baseline in mRS, national institutes of health stroke scale (NIHSS) and Barthel Index</measure>
    <time_frame>at 7 days, 30 days, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months and 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>the changes from baseline in mRS, national institutes of health stroke scale (NIHSS) and Barthel Index</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the number of participants who survives in both groups</measure>
    <time_frame>beyond 12 months to 36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>the number of participants who survives in both groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">380</enrollment>
  <condition>Ischemic Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intracranial stenting group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>all the participants in this group will be performed with intracranial stenting</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>medical group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>all the participants in this group will be given medical therapy including aspirin 100mg + clopidogrel 75mg per day for 90 consecutive days and clopidogrel 75mg per day thereafter</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intracranial stenting group</intervention_name>
    <description>all the participants in this group will be performed with intracranial stenting</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intracranial stenting group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Intracranial stenting group</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>medical group</intervention_name>
    <description>all the participants in this group will be given medical therapy including aspirin 100mg + clopidogrel 75mg per day for 90 consecutive days and clopidogrel 75mg per day thereafter</description>
    <arm_group_label>medical group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>medical group</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Symptomatic status: as evidenced by TIA or non-severe stroke within the past 12 months
        attributed to 70% to 99% stenosis of a major intracranial artery (carotid artery, MCA stem
        [M1], vertebral artery, or basilar artery) are eligible Degree of stenosis: &gt;70% and &lt;99%;
        stenosis may be diagnosed by TCD, MRA, or CTA to qualify for angiogram performed as part
        of the study protocol, but must be confirmed by catheter angiography for enrollment in the
        trial There should be remote infarctions on MRI scan, which could be accounted by the
        occlusion of the terminal cortical branches or hemodynamic compromise (perforator
        occlusion excluded). *infarction due to perforators occlusion is defined as basal ganglia
        or brainstem infarction related with MCA or BA stenosis Age &gt;=30 years and &lt;=80 years;
        non-atherosclerotic intracranial lesion will no be included; Expected ability to deliver
        the stent to the lesion. All the patients should be performed with PTAS beyond a duration
        of 3 weeks from the latest ischemic symptom onset No fresh infarctions identified on MRI
        (indicated as high signals on DWI series) upon enrollment No massive cerebral infarction
        (&gt;1/2 MCA territory), intracranial hemorrhage, epidural or sub-dural hemorrhage, and
        intracranial brain tumor on CT or MRI scan mRS scale score of &lt;=2 Target vessel reference
        diameter must be measure d to be 2.00 mm to 4.50 mm; target area of stenosis is &lt;=14 mm in
        length No childbearing potential or has a negative pregnancy test within the past 1 week
        prior to study procedure; Female patients had normal menses in the last 18 months Patient
        is willing and able to return for all follow-up visits required by the protocol Patient
        understands the purpose and requirements of the study, can make him/herself understood,
        and has signed informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Untoward reaction to anesthesia not able to be overcome by pre-treatment with medications.

        Any condition that precludes proper angiographic assessment or makes percutaneous arterial
        access unsafe.

        Tandem extracranial or intracranial stenosis (70-99%) or occlusion that is proximal or
        distal to the target intracranial lesion Bilateral intracranial vertebral artery stenosis
        of 70% to 99% and uncertainty about which artery is symptomatic (e.g., if patient has
        pontine, midbrain, or temporal occipital symptoms) Presence of a previously placed
        intravascular stent or graft in the ipsilateral distribution within 30 days Previous
        treatment of target lesion with a stent, angioplasty, or other mechanical device, or plan
        to perform staged angioplasty followed by stenting of target lesion Severe vascular
        tortuosity or anatomy that would preclude the safe introduction of a guiding catheter,
        guiding sheath or stent placement.

        Plan to perform concomitant angioplasty or stenting of an extracranial vessel tandem to an
        intracranial stenosis Presence of intraluminal thrombus proximal to or at the target
        lesion Any aneurysm proximal to or distal to stenotic intracranial artery Intracranial
        tumor (except meningioma) or any intracranial vascular malformation Computed tomographic
        or angiographic evidence of severe calcification at target lesion Thrombolytic therapy
        within 24 hours before enrollment Evolving stroke or progressive neurologic signs within
        24 hours before enrollment Stroke of sufficient size (&gt;5cm on CT or MRI) to place patient
        at risk of hemorrhagic conversion during the procedure.

        Hemorrhagic transformation of an ischemic stroke within the past 15 days. Previous
        spontaneous intracerebral (parenchymal) or other intracranial (subarachnoid, subdural, or
        epidural) hemorrhage within 30 days Untreated chronic subdural hematoma &gt;5 mm in thickness
        Intracranial arterial stenosis related to arterial dissection, moya-moya disease; any
        known vasculitic disease; herpes zoster, varicella zoster or other viral vasculopathy;
        neurosyphilis; any other intracranial infection; any intracranial stenosis associated with
        cerebrospinal fluid pleocytosis; radiation-induced vasculopathy; fibromuscular dysplasia;
        sickle cell disease; neurofibromatosis; benign angiopathy of central nervous system;
        postpartum angiopathy; suspected vasospastic process, and suspected recanalized embolus
        Other cardiac sources of emboli such as left ventricular aneurysm, intracardiac filling
        defect, cardiomyopathy, aortic or mitral prosthetic heart valve, calcific aortic stenosis,
        endocarditis, mitral stenosis, atrial septal defect, atrial septal aneurysm, left atrial
        myxoma MI within previous 30 days Chronic atrial fibrillation; any episode of paroxysmal
        atrial fibrillation within the past 6 months, or history of paroxysmal atrial fibrillation
        requiring chronic anticoagulation Intolerance or allergic reaction to any of the study
        medications, including aspirin, clopidogrel, heparin, nitinol, and local or general
        anaesthesia History of life-threatening allergy to contrast dye. If not life-threatening
        and can be effectively pretreated, patient can be enrolled at physicians discretion Recent
        GI bleed that would interfere with antiplatelet therapy. Active bleeding diathesis or
        coagulopathy; active peptic ulcer disease, major systemic hemorrhage within 30 days,
        active bleeding diathesis, platelets count &lt;125,000, hematocrit &lt;30, Hgb &lt;10 g/dl,
        uncorrected INR &gt;1.5, bleeding time &gt;1 minute beyond upper limit normal, or
        heparin-associated thrombocytopenia that increases the risk of bleeding, current alcohol
        or substance abuse, uncontrolled severe hypertension (systolic BP&gt;180 mm hg or diastolic
        BP&gt;115 mm hg), severe liver impairment (AST or ALT &gt;3 times normal, cirrhosis), creatinine
        &gt;265.2μmol/l (unless on dialysis) Major surgery (including open femoral, aortic, or
        carotid surgery) within previous 30 days or planned in the next 90 days after enrollment
        Indication for warfarin or heparin beyond enrollment (note: exceptions allowed for use of
        systemic heparin during stenting procedure or subcutaneous heparin for deep venous
        thrombosis prophylaxis while hospitalized) Inability to understand and cooperate with
        study procedures or provide informed consent.

        Severe dementia or psychiatric problem that prevents the patient from following an
        outpatient program reliably Pregnancy or of childbearing potential and unwilling to use
        contraception for the duration of this study Actively participating in another drug or
        device trial that has not completed the required protocol follow-up period.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Feng Ling, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Xuanwu Hospital, Capital University of Medical Sciences, Beijing, China</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Liqun Jiao, MD</last_name>
    <phone>86-10-83198899</phone>
    <phone_ext>8836</phone_ext>
    <email>jiaoliqun@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Peng Gao, MD</last_name>
    <phone>86-10-83198942</phone>
    <email>gaopengdoc@yahoo.com.cn</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of neurosurgery, Xuanwu hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <zip>100053</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Liqun Jiao, MD</last_name>
      <phone>86-10-83198899</phone>
      <phone_ext>8836</phone_ext>
      <email>jiaoliqun@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feigin VL. Stroke epidemiology in the developing world. Lancet. 2005 Jun 25-Jul 1;365(9478):2160-1.</citation>
    <PMID>15978910</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chimowitz MI, Lynn MJ, Derdeyn CP, Turan TN, Fiorella D, Lane BF, Janis LS, Lutsep HL, Barnwell SL, Waters MF, Hoh BL, Hourihane JM, Levy EI, Alexandrov AV, Harrigan MR, Chiu D, Klucznik RP, Clark JM, McDougall CG, Johnson MD, Pride GL Jr, Torbey MT, Zaidat OO, Rumboldt Z, Cloft HJ; SAMMPRIS Trial Investigators. Stenting versus aggressive medical therapy for intracranial arterial stenosis. N Engl J Med. 2011 Sep 15;365(11):993-1003. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1105335. Epub 2011 Sep 7. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2012 Jul 5;367(1):93.</citation>
    <PMID>21899409</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chimowitz MI, Lynn MJ, Howlett-Smith H, Stern BJ, Hertzberg VS, Frankel MR, Levine SR, Chaturvedi S, Kasner SE, Benesch CG, Sila CA, Jovin TG, Romano JG; Warfarin-Aspirin Symptomatic Intracranial Disease Trial Investigators. Comparison of warfarin and aspirin for symptomatic intracranial arterial stenosis. N Engl J Med. 2005 Mar 31;352(13):1305-16.</citation>
    <PMID>15800226</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zaidat OO, Klucznik R, Alexander MJ, Chaloupka J, Lutsep H, Barnwell S, Mawad M, Lane B, Lynn MJ, Chimowitz M; NIH Multi-center Wingspan Intracranial Stent Registry Study Group. The NIH registry on use of the Wingspan stent for symptomatic 70-99% intracranial arterial stenosis. Neurology. 2008 Apr 22;70(17):1518-24. Epub 2008 Jan 30.</citation>
    <PMID>18235078</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fiorella D, Levy EI, Turk AS, Albuquerque FC, Niemann DB, Aagaard-Kienitz B, Hanel RA, Woo H, Rasmussen PA, Hopkins LN, Masaryk TJ, McDougall CG. US multicenter experience with the wingspan stent system for the treatment of intracranial atheromatous disease: periprocedural results. Stroke. 2007 Mar;38(3):881-7. Epub 2007 Feb 8.</citation>
    <PMID>17290030</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 4, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ischemic stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>intracranial stenting</keyword>
  <keyword>vascular risk factor management</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
