<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="77081">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01701245</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GC-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01701245</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevention and Acute Treatment of Chronic Cluster Headache Compared to Standard of Care</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Multicenter Study for the Prevention and Acute Treatment of Chronic Cluster Headache Using Gammacore, Versus Standard of Care.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ElectroCore LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ElectroCore LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Subjects enrolled into this 10 week study will for the first two weeks document the number
      of cluster headaches and the means of treating (medication) of these attacks.  Subjects will
      then be randomized to into either two groups.  The first group is continuing with standard
      of care and the second group is treatment with the investigational device (GammaCore) for a
      period of 4 weeks.  After this 4 week period, all subjects will treat with the GammaCore for
      another 4 week period. It is hypothesized  the the treatment group will have a reduction in
      mean cluster headaches per week by 50% compared to the standard of care group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is a prospective randomized controlled multi-center investigation designed for
      comparison of two parallel groups, GammaCore® (active treatment) and Standard of Care, SoC,
      (control). The study period begins with a 2 week run-in period, followed by a 4 week
      comparative period when the subjects are randomized to either active treatment or control
      1:1. The comparative period will be followed by a period where all subject will receive
      GammaCore® for 4 weeks.After the subject signed the Consent Form for participation the
      baseline (visit1) data will be collected. Subject will be informed how to complete the 2
      week diary during the run-in period During the run-in period, all subjects will use stable
      SoC according to their individual prescriptions. The subject will record as CH attack
      regarding duration and frequency and the use of medication and oxygen.

      Once subjects have finalized the run-in period, they are randomized to continue in 4 weeks
      comparative period. During this period, the control group continues with stable SoC and the
      active group is provided with a GammaCore® device for prophylactic and acute treatment in
      addition to the stable SoC Subjects stimulate 3 x 2 times daily as part of the prophylactic
      treatment regimen (cervical vagal nerve). Three 90 second stimulations are self-administered
      by the subject with 5 minutes between each stimulation on the right side of the neck.

      This preventive stimulation regimen is performed:

        -  First Daily Treatment - within 1 hour of waking

        -  Second Daily Treatment - 7-10 hours following the first daily treatment

      Acute CH attack:

        -  3 x 90 second treatments consecutively at the onset of pain or symptoms. If the attack
           is not aborted within 15 minutes the subject should be informed to take SOC abortive
           medication.

        -  If an acute cluster headache attack is treated with the GammaCore® device, the subject
           will try to work within the preventive treatment window to avoid a preventive treatment
           in the 2-hour refractory period following the acute treatment.

      A total of minimally 6 stimulations for the preventive part and as needed for the acute
      attacks. The active group also continues with the stable SoC during the entire 4 weeks
      period. Both groups record all CH attacks in the diary together with medication and oxygen
      use. All adverse events shall also be recorded in the diary.

      The end of the 4 week comparative period marks the completion of the randomized part of the
      study, however all subjects are provided the option to continue to a 4 week GammaCore®
      treatment with the same stimulation parameter as during the 4 week randomization period. All
      subjects randomized to the SoC group will receive training.

      During the entire study period, subjects are allowed to take rescue medication including
      oxygen inhalation for abortion of CH attacks. The amount and doses of the medication and
      oxygen are recorded in the diary.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease frequency of cluster headache attacks per week</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint is the reduction in mean number of CH attacks per week. The number of CH attacks will be calculated as the sum of all attacks over the days in the run-in period and divided by the number of weeks, respectively for the last 14 days of treatment during the randomised phase. The reduction will then be the number of CH attacks during treatment period (last 14 days of the randomized treatment period) - number of CH attacks during run-in.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain relief of headache attacks</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The mean pain during run-in will be compared with both the pain relief the last 14 days of the treatment period and the pain relief during the whole treatment period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The frequency of device effects will be compared between the two treatment groups. Only effects which are new after baseline or have increased severity after baseline will be used in the comparison.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EQ-5D-3L</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The EQ-5D-3L during the run-in period will be compared with the EQ-5D-3L during the treatment period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Cluster Headache</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No intervention, standard of care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GammaCore</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Three stimulation treatments 2x/day 7 to 10 hours apart from one another.  In addition, three stimulation treatments at the time of onset of symptoms of a headache attack.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GammaCore</intervention_name>
    <description>vagal stimulation</description>
    <arm_group_label>GammaCore</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        1. Signed Informed Consent Form 2. Subjects between the age of 18-70, both genders 3.
        Subjects diagnosed with chronic cluster headache for at least 1 year, without remission
        periods or with remission periods lasting &lt;1 month, in accordance with the ICHD-II
        classification criteria (2ndEd):

        a. At least 5 attacks fulfilling the following criteria: i. Severe or very severe
        unilateral orbital, supraorbital and/or temporal pain lasting 15-180 minutes if untreated
        ii. Headache is accompanied by at least 1 of the following:

          1. Ipsilateral conjunctival injection and/or lacrimation

          2. Ipsilateral nasal congestion and/or rhinorrhea

          3. Ipsilateral eyelid oedema

          4. Ipsilateral forehead and facial sweating

          5. Ipsilateral miosis and/or ptosis

          6. A sense of restlessness or agitation iii. Attacks have a frequency from 1 every other
             day to 8 per day and are not attributed to another disorder iv. Attacks recur over &gt;
             1 year without remission periods or with remission periods lasting &lt; 1 month.

        4. Has minimum mean attack frequency of 4 CH attacks per week. 5. Is able to distinguish
        CH from other headaches (i.e. tension-type headaches).

        6. Is capable of completing headache pain self-assessments. 7. Agrees to use the
        GammaCore® device as intended and follow all of the requirements of the study, including
        follow-up visit requirements.

        8. Is willing to keep all concomitant medication stable during the entire study period.

        9. Women of child-bearing potential must use 2 methods of contraceptive i.e. hormones and
        condom.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Is currently taking CH prophylactic medication for indications other than CH which in
             the opinion of the clinician may interfere with the study

          2. Has had a change in type or dosage of prophylactic headache medications &lt; 1 month
             prior to enrollment

          3. Has a history of intracranial or carotid aneurysm, intracranial hemorrhage, brain
             tumors or significant head trauma.

          4. Has a lesion (including lymphadenopathy), dysaesthesia, previous surgery or abnormal
             anatomy at the GammaCore® treatment site.

          5. Has other significant pain problem that might confound the study assessments in the
             opinion of the investigator.

          6. Has known or suspected severe atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease, severe carotid
             artery disease (e.g. bruits or history of TIA or CVA), congestive heart failure
             (CHF), known severe coronary artery disease or recent myocardial infarction (within
             5years).

          7. Has had a previous unilateral or bilateral vagotomy.

          8. Has uncontrolled high blood pressure.

          9. Is currently implanted with an electrical and/or neurostimulator device, including
             but not limited to cardiac pacemaker or defibrillator, vagal neurostimulator, deep
             brain stimulator, spinal stimulator, bone growth stimulator, or cochlear implant.

         10. Has a history of carotid endarterectomy or vascular neck surgery on the right side.

         11. Has been implanted with metal cervical spine hardware or has a metallic implant near
             the GammaCore® stimulation site.

         12. Has a history, the last 12 month, of syncope.

         13. Has a history, the last 12 month of seizures.

         14. Has a known history or suspicion of substance abuse or addiction, or overuse of acute
             headache medication for headaches other than CH.

         15. Has psychiatric or cognitive disorder and/or behavioral problems which in the
             opinion of the investigator may interfere with the study

         16. In the opinion of the investigator the subject is incapable of operating the
             GammaCore® device as intended and performing the data collection procedures.

         17. Is participating in any other therapeutic clinical investigation or has participated
             in a clinical trial in the preceding 30 days.

         18. Woman who are pregnant or lactating.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charly Gaul, Dr med</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Migräne- und Kopfschmerzklinik Königstein</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Annelie Anderson</last_name>
    <phone>+46 (0) 721 803076</phone>
    <email>annelie.andersson@electrocoremedical.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Department of Neurology CHR</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liège</city>
        <zip>B-4000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Delphine Magis, Dr</last_name>
      <phone>+32 4230 7811</phone>
      <email>dmagis@chu.ulg.ac.be</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Pascale Gerard, SC</last_name>
      <phone>+32 4 225 63 91</phone>
      <email>pascale.gerard@chrcitadelle.be</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Delphine Magis, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Westdeutsches Kopfschmerzzentrum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hufelandstr. 26</city>
        <state>Essen</state>
        <zip>D-45147</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kasja Rabe, Dr</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0)201-43 696 24</phone>
      <email>kasja.rabe@uni-due.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Melina Braunstein, SC</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0)201-43696-0</phone>
      <email>melina.braunstein@uni-due.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kasja Rabe, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steffen Nägel, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maja Bak, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Neurologische Klinik und Poliklinik</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10117</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Uwe Reuter, Dr</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0) 30 450560-274</phone>
      <email>uwe.reuter@charite.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Heike Israel-Willner, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+49 030 8445-0</phone>
      <email>Heike.Israel@charite.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Uwe Reuter, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lars Neeb, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Heike Israel-Willner, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Krankenhaus Lindenbrunn, Department of Neurology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Coppenbrügge</city>
        <zip>D-31863</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stefan Evers, Prof</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0) 5156-782290</phone>
      <email>everss@uni-muenster.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stefan Evers, Prof</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Migräne- und Kopfschmerzklinik Königstein</name>
      <address>
        <city>Königstein im Taunus</city>
        <zip>D-61462</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Charly Gaul, Dr med</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0) 6174 29040</phone>
      <email>c.gaul@migraene-klinik.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sabrina Stillger, SC</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0)6174 29040</phone>
      <email>s.stillger@migraene-klinik.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charly Gaul, Dr med</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Neurology, University of Munich</name>
      <address>
        <city>Munich</city>
        <zip>D-813 77</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ruth Ruscheweyh, Dr</last_name>
      <phone>+49 89 7095 3900</phone>
      <email>ruth.ruscheweyh@med.uni-muenchen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ozan Eren, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+49 89 7095 3900</phone>
      <email>Ozan.Eren@med.uni-muenchen.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andreas Straube, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ruth Ruscheweyh, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ozan Eren, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Regional Referral Headache Centre Sant' Andrea Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rome</city>
        <zip>IT-00189</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paolo Martelletti, Prof</last_name>
      <phone>+39 63 3776778</phone>
      <email>paolo.martelletti@uniroma1.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Andrea Negro, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+39 339 156 3982</phone>
      <email>andrea.negro@uniroma1.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paolo Martelletti, Prof</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrea Negro, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Southern Hospital, Neurology Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glasgow</city>
        <state>Scotland</state>
        <zip>G51 4TF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alok Tyagi, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 141 201 1100</phone>
      <email>aloktyagi@nhs.net</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anissa Benchiheub, SC</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0)1412 329515</phone>
      <email>anissa.benchiheub@ggc.scot.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alok Tyagi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hull Royal Infirmary, Neurology Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hull</city>
        <zip>HU3 2JZ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fayyaz Ahmed, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 1482 875875</phone>
      <email>fayyaz.ahmed@hey.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anwar Osman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 1482 875875</phone>
      <email>anwar.osman@hey.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fayyaz Ahmed, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anwar Osman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Walton Centre, Neurology Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <zip>L9 7LJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nicholas Silver, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 1515 253611</phone>
      <email>drnicksilver@googlemail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kate O'Hanlon, SC</last_name>
      <phone>+44(0)1515 295666</phone>
      <email>kate.o'hanlon@thewaltoncentre.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nicholas Silver, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Helene Banks, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 2, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 3, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>vagus nerve stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>vagal nerve stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>nVNS</keyword>
  <keyword>VNS</keyword>
  <keyword>cluster headache</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic</keyword>
  <keyword>non invasive</keyword>
  <keyword>gammacore</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cluster Headache</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Headache</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
