<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40024">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01685723</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>cancer_rct_1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01685723</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Smoking Cessation in Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Helping Cancer Patients Quit Smoking by Improving Their Risk Communication: a Cluster Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Food and Health Bureau, Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Queen Mary Hospital, Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tuen Mun Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Hong Kong: Hospital Authority</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Smoking cessation can largely improve cancer prognosis and quality of life among
      cancer patients. However, few patients are aware of the importance to quit at the stage, or
      they have difficulties to quit by self.

      Aim: Test the effectiveness of a tailored and targeted smoking cessation intervention

      Hypothesis: We hypothesize that improving risk communication could significantly increase
      the quit rate of smoking cancer patients

      Design: Cluster randomized controlled trial

      Setting: Outpatient clinics in Queen Mary Hospital and Tuen Mun Hospital (Clinical Oncology
      Departments)

      Subject: Smoking patients who have diagnosed cancer with stable condition and treatments

      Intervention: At baseline, intervention group receives:

        1. health warnings of smoking from oncologists/nurses based on a special design leaflet;

        2. a patient-centred counseling from nurse counselors with emphasis on risk perceptions of
           smoking to cancer prognosis; and

        3. examination of exhale CO level. They will receive up to 8 more telephone counseling
           within 1 month by nurse counselor to reinforce the importance to quit and assist to
           solve any barriers. Control group receive standard care and a generic self-help smoking
           cessation booklet.

      Outcome: Primary outcome is the self-reported 7-day point prevalence quit rate at 6-month
      follow up. Secondary outcomes include:

        1. change in risk perceptions of smoking;

        2. change in the intention to quit;

        3. validated 6-month quit rate;

        4. patient's smoking reduction by at least 50% compared to baseline;

        5. quit attempt(s);

        6. change in health related quality of life; and

        7. cancer recurrence rate at 6-month.

      Significance: This study develops and validates practical smoking cessation interventions
      targeted to cancer patients to improve their cancer prognosis and in long-term, increase
      their survival time.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Smoking causes many types of cancer in general. Past studies have shown that current smokers
      have increased risk of cancer, and most lung cancers are attributable to smoking. Cancer
      (malignant neoplasm) is the number one killer in Hong Kong, which leads to nearly one-third
      of all deaths each year. Cancer patients who continue smoking would result in extra risks of
      all cause mortality, cancer recurrence and second primary cancer as well as reducing
      survival time (Chen et al., 2010). Smoking could also reduce the efficacy of clinical and
      medical treatment of cancer including radio- and chemo-therapies (Benninger et al., 1994;
      Browman et al., 1993) and increase the risk of treatment related side-effects (Rugg et al.,
      1990).

      Cancer patients may present an excellent &quot;teachable moment&quot; for smoking cessation
      interventions, as their current illness could largely be due to smoking. However, few
      smoking cessation programs target on this vulnerable group and only one-third of oncology
      nurses would assist cancer patients quit smoking. Healthcare professionals have the
      responsibility to assist this vulnerable group to quit smoking. Recent randomized controlled
      trials (RCT) suggested behavioral intervention may help cancer patients quit smoking, but
      they are limited by small sample size. No RCT study has ever been done in Hong Kong.

      This study can make an important contribution to evidence-based practice by testing the
      effectiveness of a tailored smoking cessation intervention targeting cancer patients. The
      results primarily serve the purpose to support the development of clinical practice
      guidelines and interventions to promote smoking cessation in cancer patients to improve
      their cancer prognosis and, in the long-run, increase their survival time and quality of
      life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The self-reported 7-day point prevalence (pp) quit rate at the sixth month</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Whether the participant has quitted smoking in the past seven days at the time point of 6 months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in patients' smoking behavior and risk perceptions at the sixth month</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of participants reduced daily cigarette consumption by at least half compared with baseline
Proportion of patients with quit attempt(s)
Patients' intention to quit smoking
Change in patients' risk perceptions
Change in health-related quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biochemical validation of smoking status at the sixth month</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>- Biochemically validated quit rate (saliva cotinine level and exhale CO test)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in patients' smoking behavior and risk perceptions at the twelfth month</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Self-reported 7-day point prevalence (pp) quit rate
Proportion of participants reduced daily cigarette consumption by at least half compared with baseline
Proportion of patients with quit attempt(s)
Patients' intention to quit smoking
Change in patients' risk perceptions
Change in health-related quality of life
Actuarial overall survival rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biochemical validation of smoking status at twelfth month</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>- Biochemically validated quit rate (saliva cotinine level and exhale CO test)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">560</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Smoking Cessation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Counseling group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this group will receive:
Health warning on smoking (with a special designed leaflet) by oncologist or nurse during consultation;
Face-to-face individual smoking cessation counseling by nurse counselor (15-30 minutes);
Assessment of exhale carbon monoxide level at baseline;
Nicotine replacement therapy (may be provided);
Generic self-help smoking booklet; and
Multiple telephone follow up counseling (up to 8 sessions) within one-month period (10-15 minutes).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>General supporting</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this group will receive:
Usual care by oncologist or nurse;
General care and support by nurse counselor (5 minutes);
Generic self-help smoking cessation booklet; and
Multiple telephone follow-ups (up to 8 sessions) to show support and care for patients' disease condition (5 minutes).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Counseling group</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects in this group will receive treatments in the form of improved risk communication measures. These measures include brief advice by oncologist or oncology nurses, a special design leaflet, face-to-face individualized risk communication counselling by nurse counselor, and follow-up telephone counselling emphasizing on risk communication.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Counseling group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>General supporting</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects in this group will receive:
Usual care by oncologist or nurse;
General care and support by nurse counselor (5 minutes);
Generic self-help smoking cessation booklet; and
Multiple telephone follow-ups (up to 8 sessions) to show support and care for patients' disease condition (5 minutes).</description>
    <arm_group_label>General supporting</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Cancer patients smoked weekly in the past 6 months;

          -  patients in all stages 0,I,II,III, or IV;

          -  aged 18 or above; and

          -  can communicate in Cantonese

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  those with unstable medical conditions as advised by the doctor in charge;

          -  poor cognitive state or with mental illness; and

          -  those participating in other smoking cessation program.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sophia SC Chan, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sophia SC Chan, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>852-28192610</phone>
    <email>nssophia@hku.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Hong Kong</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong SAR</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sophia SC Chan, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benninger MS, Gillen J, Thieme P, Jacobson B, Dragovich J. Factors associated with recurrence and voice quality following radiation therapy for T1 and T2 glottic carcinomas. Laryngoscope. 1994 Mar;104(3 Pt 1):294-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8127185</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Browman GP, Wong G, Hodson I, Sathya J, Russell R, McAlpine L, Skingley P, Levine MN. Influence of cigarette smoking on the efficacy of radiation therapy in head and neck cancer. N Engl J Med. 1993 Jan 21;328(3):159-63.</citation>
    <PMID>8417381</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rugg T, Saunders MI, Dische S. Smoking and mucosal reactions to radiotherapy. Br J Radiol. 1990 Jul;63(751):554-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2390690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen J, Jiang R, Garces YI, Jatoi A, Stoddard SM, Sun Z, Marks RS, Liu Y, Yang P. Prognostic factors for limited-stage small cell lung cancer: a study of 284 patients. Lung Cancer. 2010 Feb;67(2):221-6. Epub 2009 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19497635</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 26, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. Sophia Siu-chee Chan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cancer patients</keyword>
  <keyword>Smoking cessation</keyword>
  <keyword>Risk communication</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Smoking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
