<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="159579">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01665794</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-1088</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-01168</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01665794</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Carfilzomib, Pomalidomide, and Dexamethasone in Treating Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multicenter, Open-label, Single-arm, Phase 1b/2 Study of the Safety and Efficacy of Combination Treatment With Pomalidomide, Dexamethasone, and Carfilzomib (PdC) in Subjects With Relapsed and Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Chicago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Chicago</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I/II trial studies the safety and the best dose of carfilzomib and to see how
      well it works when given together with pomalidomide and dexamethasone in treating patients
      with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma. Carfilzomib may stop the growth of cancer
      cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Pomalidomide may stimulate the
      immune system in different ways and stop cancer cells from growing. Drugs used in
      chemotherapy, such as dexamethasone, work in different ways to stop the growth of cancer
      cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. Giving carfilzomib
      together with pomalidomide and dexamethasone may kill more cancer cells
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the maximally tolerated dose (MTD) of carfilzomib when administered in
      combination with fixed dosing pomalidomide and dexamethasone in patients with relapsed and
      relapsed/refractory multiple myeloma.

      II. To determine the efficacy of the combination regimen at the MTD as measured by partial
      response (PR) response rate defined as per International Myeloma Working Group (IMW)
      criteria.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the best stringent complete response (sCR)/CR/nodular complete response
      (nCR) and &gt;= very good partial response (VGPR) rates.

      II. To estimate the time on study (TOS), duration of response (DOR), time to progression
      (TTP), progression-free survival (PFS), and overall survival (OS) distributions.

      III. To further define the toxicity at the MTD.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To perform an analysis of a subset of patients who are refractory to either pomalidomide
      or carfilzomib or lenalidomide, bortezomib, and dexamethasone (RVD) combination.

      II. To evaluate the status of minimal residual disease (MRD) in patient who achieve sCR, CR
      or nCR.

      III. To evaluate prognostic markers and markers of response to pomalidomide, dexamethasone,
      and carfilzomib (PdC) in patients refractory to lenalidomide by analyzing pre-treatment
      clinical covariates and pre-treatment plasma cell profiles by proteomics and gene expression
      profiling (GEP).

      OUTLINE: This is a phase I dose-escalation study of carfilzomib followed by phase II.

      Patients receive carfilzomib intravenously (IV) over 30 minutes on days 1, 2, 8, 9, 15 and
      16, pomalidomide orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days 1-21, and dexamethasone PO or IV on
      days 1, 8, 15, and 22. Treatment repeats every 28 days for at least 8 courses in the absence
      of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients achieving stable disease may
      continue to receive treatment in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
      toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 28 days and then every 3
      months for up to 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MTD of carfilzomib when administered in combination with fixed dosing pomalidomide and dexamethasone</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Partial response rate after 4 courses according to IMW criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion and exact 95% binomial confidence interval for the response rate will be reported adjusted for the two-stage design of this trial.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as at least a partial response to therapy, will be reported along with its exact 95% binomial confidence</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated using the product-limit method of Kaplan and Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of the clinical examination which confirmed the response, until the date of disease progression, or censoring at the date of last clinical follow-up up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessed conditional upon achieving at least a partial response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of first therapy until the date of documented disease progression or death up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated using the product-limit method of Kaplan and Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated using the product-limit method of Kaplan and Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">92</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carfilzomib, pomalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive carfilzomib, pomalidomide, and dexamethasone at indicated doses and schedule every 28 days. Patients may continue to receive treatment in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pomalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Carfilzomib, pomalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CC-4047</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>carfilzomib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Carfilzomib, pomalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kyprolis</other_name>
    <other_name>PR-171</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO or IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Carfilzomib, pomalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Aeroseb-Dex</other_name>
    <other_name>Decaderm</other_name>
    <other_name>Decadron</other_name>
    <other_name>DM</other_name>
    <other_name>DXM</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Relapsed and relapsed/refractory multiple myeloma requiring systemic therapy

          -  All patients must have failed 1+ prior treatment, one of which must include
             lenalidomide therapy and have been determined to be refractory to it

               -  Refractory to lenalidomide will be defined as a history of progression on or
                  within 60 days of completion of a regimen of a minimum of 2 cycles containing
                  full or maximally tolerated dose of lenalidomide

               -  Progressing on lenalidomide maintenance will be allowed provided that the trial
                  of at least 2 months of lenalidomide at 25 mg or maximum tolerated dose was
                  given to meet the lenalidomide refractory status

               -  In addition to lenalidomide refractory, patients refractory to (1) pomalidomide
                  (2) carfilzomib, or (3) RVD are permitted limited to separate cohorts enrollment

          -  Measurable disease, as indicated by one or more of the following:

               -  Serum M-protein &gt;= 0.5 g/dL

               -  Urine M-protein &gt;= 200 mg/24 hours

               -  If serum protein electrophoresis is felt to be unreliable for routine M-protein
                  measurement, then quantitative immunoglobulin levels are acceptable

          -  Life expectancy of more than 3 months

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-2

          -  Bilirubin &lt; 1.5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &lt; 2.5 times ULN

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1.0 x 10^9/L

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 8 g/dL

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 75 x 10^9/L; subjects may receive red blood cells (RBC)
             transfusions or platelet transfusions, if clinically indicated in accordance with
             institutional guidelines; however, screening platelet count should be independent of
             platelet transfusions for at least 2 weeks

          -  Calculated or measured creatinine clearance of &gt;= 30 mL/minute

          -  Written informed consent in accordance with federal, local, and institutional
             guidelines

          -  Females of childbearing potential (FCBP) must have a negative serum or urine
             pregnancy test with a sensitivity of at least 25mIU/mL within 10-14 days and again
             within 24 hours prior to starting course 1 of pomalidomide and must either commit to
             continued abstinence from heterosexual intercourse or begin TWO acceptable methods of
             birth control, one highly effective method and one additional effective method AT THE
             SAME TIME, at least 28 days before she starts taking pomalidomide; FCBP must also
             agree to ongoing pregnancy testing; men must agree to use a latex condom during
             sexual contact with a FCBP even if they have had a successful vasectomy; all patients
             must be counseled at a minimum of every 28 days about pregnancy precautions and risks
             of fetal exposure

          -  Subjects must agree to adhere to all study requirements, visit schedule, outpatient
             treatment, required concomitant medications, and laboratory monitoring

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-secretory or hyposecretory multiple myeloma, defined as &lt; 0.5 g/dL M-protein in
             serum, &lt; 200 mg/24 hr urine M-protein, or disease only measured by serum free light
             chain

          -  Patients for whom there is the prospect of stem cell transplantation in the next 6
             months in the treatment plan are excluded (including patients for whom the PdC
             regimen is being considered as pre-transplant cytoreduction)

          -  POEMS syndrome (polyneuropathy, organomegaly, endocrinopathy, monoclonal protein, and
             skin changes)

          -  Plasma cell leukemia

          -  Waldenström's macroglobulinemia or immunoglobulin M (IgM) myeloma

          -  Radiotherapy to multiple sites or immunotherapy within 4 weeks before start of
             protocol treatment (localized radiotherapy to a single site at least 1 week before
             start is permissible)

          -  Participation in an investigational therapeutic study within 3 weeks or within 5 drug
             half lives (t1/2) prior to first dose, whichever time is greater

          -  Refractory to bortezomib, except if meeting criteria for RVD-refractory cohort

          -  Pregnant or lactating females

          -  History of allergy to mannitol or prior hypersensitivity to thalidomide, lenalidomide
             or pomalidomide

          -  Major surgery within 3 weeks prior to first dose, prior peripheral stem cell
             transplant within 12 weeks of study enrollment, subject has received any anti-cancer
             therapy including chemotherapy, immunotherapy, radiotherapy, hormonal (with the
             exception of hormones for thyroid conditions or estrogen replacement therapy [ERT],
             or any investigational therapy) within 21 days of enrollment

          -  Myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to enrollment, New York Heart Associate
             (NYHA) class III or IV heart failure, uncontrolled angina, severe uncontrolled
             ventricular arrhythmias, or electrocardiographic evidence of acute ischemia or active
             conduction system abnormalities

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension or diabetes

          -  Acute active infection requiring systemic antibiotics, antivirals, or anti fungals
             within two weeks prior to first dose

          -  Known or suspected human immunodeficiency (HIV) infection, known HIV seropositivity

          -  Active hepatitis A, B, or C infection

          -  Non-hematologic malignancy within the past 3 years except adequately treated basal
             cell, squamous cell skin cancer, thyroid cancer, carcinoma in situ of the cervix or
             breast, prostate cancer &lt; Gleason grade 6 with stable prostate specific antigen
             levels or cancer considered cured by surgical resection alone

          -  Any clinically significant medical disease or condition that, in the investigator's
             opinion, may interfere with protocol adherence or a subject's ability to give
             informed consent

          -  Significant neuropathy (grades 3-4, or grade 2 with pain) at the time of the first
             dose and/or within 14 days before enrollment

          -  Contraindication to any of the required concomitant drugs, including proton-pump
             inhibitor (eg, lansoprazole), enteric-coated aspirin, allopurinol or if a history of
             prior thrombotic disease, warfarin or low molecular weight heparin

          -  Subjects in whom the required program of PO and IV fluid hydration is
             contraindicated, eg, due to pre-existing pulmonary, cardiac, or renal impairment

          -  Subjects with known or suspected amyloidosis of any organ

          -  Subjects with pleural effusions requiring thoracentesis or ascites requiring
             paracentesis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrzej Jakubowiak</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Chicago Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637-1470</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrzej J. Jakubowiak</last_name>
      <phone>773-834-1592</phone>
      <email>ajakubowiak@medicine.bsd.uchicago.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrzej J. Jakubowiak</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hackensack University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David S. Siegel</last_name>
      <phone>201-336-8704</phone>
      <email>dsiegel@humed.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David S. Siegel</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 13, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone 21-phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
