<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="3002">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01687101</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SDS/STPAIN/01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01687101</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>STOPAIN in the Treatment of a Single Migraine Attack</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Tolerability of STOPAIN in the Treatment of a Single Migraine Attack</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Thomas Jefferson University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Thomas Jefferson University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open label pilot study of 25 subjects with a diagnosis of episodic migraine with
      or without aura.  STOPAIN is an over-the-counter product that is used for the temporary
      relief of minor aches and pains of muscles and joints associated with simple backache,
      arthritis, strains, bruises and sprains. We plan to have subjects apply the product during a
      single migraine attack to see if it will alleviate the headache pain and associated
      symptoms.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open label, 2 visit,  pilot study of 25 subjects with a diagnosis of episodic
      migraine with or without aura according to the International Classification of Headache
      Disorders (2nd Edition-2004).

      Subjects will be screened at Visit 1 after being properly consented for participation in the
      study.  Screening procedures will include assessment of the medical history, headache
      history, current medications, vital signs, height and weight measurements and a urine
      pregnancy test for women of childbearing potential.  Investigators will determine the
      eligibility of study subjects.  Subjects will be instructed on how and when to apply the
      topical gel to treat a migraine attack.  In addition, subjects will be instructed how to
      complete the take home diary.  The study medication will be used at home to treat a single
      migraine attack.

      At the time of at-home treatment the subject will apply the study medication.  The gel will
      be applied to the area below and abutting the back base of the skull to base of neck and
      span from behind and between both ears.  The quantity shall be two pumps from the metered
      dosing bottle.   The best way to apply is to pump once onto the fingertips and apply the gel
      to one-half of the application area and pump again onto the fingertips and apply the gel to
      the other half of the application area.   Massage in for 5 to 10 seconds to make sure there
      is reasonably uniform coverage.   (Do not cover with cloth or bandage or lie down on a
      pillow until the gel has completely dried - about 10 minutes or so.)  Do not get any of the
      gel into the eyes or onto mucus membranes.   The gel is not toxic but will cause a burning
      sensation to eyes or mucus membranes.   Wash hands with soap and warm water after
      application.   The gel will give rise to a cooling sensation and to it may feel like a mild
      to moderate stinging or burning sensation.   That is normal.   Anything more than a mild to
      moderate stinging or burning sensation is not expected and should be noted in diary.    If
      there has been no reduction in symptoms after 30 minutes repeat the application.  If there
      is no relief after 2 hours the subject may use other rescue medication.

      Completed subject diaries will provide data on headache severity and the presence or absence
      of nausea, vomiting, photophobia and phonophobia.  Time of resolution of both the headache
      and accompanying symptoms will be collected.  The subjects will record migraine pain
      severity and the presence or absence of associated symptoms at 30, 60, 90 minutes and 2, 4,
      and 24 hours after the administration of study drug.

      Subjects will be asked to treat a single migraine attack within 8 weeks of Visit 1.  After
      treating the attack and completing the diary, they will be asked to return to Jefferson
      Headache Center for a final visit (Visit 2) or to return the diary and other study supplies
      by mail.  Shipping materials will be provided to each participant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of STOPAIN in the Acute Treatment of Migraine</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours post dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy of STOPAIN in the acute treatment of migraine as measured by Pain Freedom (headache pain intensity level equal to &quot;no pain&quot;) at 2 hours post dose using a four point numeric rating scale (no pain, mild pain, moderate pain, severe pain).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>evaluate the tolerability, safety, and sustained pain freedom of STOPAIN</measure>
    <time_frame>2 to 24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the tolerability and safety of STOPAIN  in the acute treatment of  migraine as measured by the frequency and severity of adverse events, frequency of serious adverse events and discontinuations due to adverse events
To evaluate STOPAIN for sustained pain freedom from 2 to 24 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Migraine</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>STOPAIN topical gel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>STOPAIN gel, 2 or 4 pumps of gel, one or two applications, 2 hours</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>STOPAIN topical gel</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>STOPAIN topical gel</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female subjects between the ages of 18 and 65, inclusive

          -  Subjects diagnosed with episodic migraine, with or without aura according to IHS
             criteria  for at least one year prior to screening

          -  Subjects who experience between 1 and 10 migraine attacks (inclusive) per month
             (during the previous 6 months) with no more than 15 days of headache per month.

          -  Subject is using or agrees to use for the duration of participation a medically
             acceptable form of contraception (as determined by investigator), if female of
             child-bearing potential

          -  Subjects who are able to understand and comply with all study procedures.

          -  Subject provides written informed consent prior to any screening procedures being
             conducted

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant and/or lactating women

          -  Subjects who, in the investigator's opinion, have a history or have evidence of a
             medical or psychiatric condition that would expose them to an increased risk of a
             significant adverse event or would interfere with the assessments of efficacy and
             tolerability during this trial

          -  Subjects who have participated in an investigational drug trial in the 30 days prior
             to the screening visit

          -  Subjects who currently have or have had a history of basilar or hemiplegic migraine
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen D Silberstein, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Thomas Jefferson University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stephen D. Silberstein, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>215-955-2243</phone>
    <email>Stephen.Silberstein@jefferson.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephen D. Silberstein, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>215-955-2243</phone>
      <email>Stephen.Silberstein@jefferson.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen D. Silberstein, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 13, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Migraine Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Menthol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
