<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="127905">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02091375</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GWEP1332 Part B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02091375</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>To Assess the Antiepileptic Efficacy of GWP42003-P in Children and Young Adults With Dravet Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double Blind, Placebo Controlled Two-part Study to Investigate the Dose-ranging Safety and Pharmacokinetics, Followed by the Efficacy and Safety of Cannabidiol (GWP42003-P) in Children and Young Adults With Dravet Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GW Pharmaceuticals Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GW Pharmaceuticals Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To investigate the potential antiepileptic effects of cannabidiol (GWP42003-P) in children
      and young adults with Dravet syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      GWEP1332 Part B will recruit an entirely new group of subjects to GWEP1332 Part A. Part B is
      a 1:1 randomized, double blind placebo-controlled 12-week comparison of GWP42003-P versus
      placebo. The aim of Part B is to assess the antiepileptic efficacy of GWP42003-P as an
      adjunctive antiepileptic treatment compared with placebo, with respect to the percentage
      change from baseline in convulsive seizure frequency in children and young adults.

      Following establishment of initial eligibility and baseline measurements, subjects will
      enter Part B and begin a 28-day baseline observation period. Subjects who have experienced
      least four convulsive seizures (tonic-clonic seizures and/or drop attacks) during the
      baseline period and who meet all of the other inclusion and none of the exclusion criteria
      will be eligible to continue in the study.

      Eligible subjects will then be randomized to receive either GWP42003-P or placebo on a 1:1
      basis, and will titrate up to the dose that was identified in Part A as the maximum
      tolerated dose (up to 20 mg/kg/day: to be confirmed following completion of Part A by an
      independent Data Safety Monitoring Committee who will review unblinded safety and
      pharmacokinetic data from Part A).

      Subjects will receive investigational medicinal product for 12 weeks, consisting of a
      seven-day titration period, followed by an 11-week stable dose period.

      Efficacy and safety will be monitored at various clinic visits and via telephone.

      Efficacy measures include:

        -  Assessing changes from baseline in non-convulsive seizure frequency, sleep disruption,
           daytime sleepiness and conducting behavioral assessments in subjects taking GWP42003-P
           as an adjuvant treatment, when compared with placebo.

        -  Assessing the safety of GWP42003-P when compared with placebo. After completion of the
           Part B treatment period, subjects will be offered the option of entering an open label
           extension study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean percentage change from baseline to the end of treatment in convulsive seizure frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>0-12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The percentage change from baseline to the end of treatment in convulsive seizure frequency during the last 28 days of the evaluable period was measured in subjects taking GWP42003-P compared with placebo. A negative value indicates an improvement in condition.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects who experienced a 50% or more reduction in convulsive seizures from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>0-12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of subjects who experienced a 50% or more reduction in convulsive seizures from baseline is presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in non-convulsive seizure frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>0-12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The mean change from baseline in non-convulsive seizure frequency is presented. A negative value indicates an improvement in condition.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in sleep disruption 0-10 Numerical Rating Scale score</measure>
    <time_frame>0-12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The subject's caregiver will be asked: &quot;On a scale of '0 to 10', please indicate the number that best describes the subject's sleep disruption in the last 24 hours.&quot;
The markers range from 0 = slept extremely well, to 10 = unable to sleep at all.
A negative value indicates an improvement in condition.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in Epworth Daytime sleepiness scale score</measure>
    <time_frame>0-12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in the Daily Living: Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scale score</measure>
    <time_frame>0-12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Vineland-II is an individually administered instrument for assessing adaptive behaviors including  Communication, Daily Living Skills, Socialization, and Motor Skills. These were assessed by the caregiver using a rating scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Caregiver Global Impression of Change at the end of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>End of week 14 of treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Caregiver Global Impression of Change comprised the following question to be rated on a seven-point scale:
• Since your child started treatment, please assess the status of your child's overall condition (comparing their condition now to their condition before treatment) using the scale below.
The markers were: Very Much Improved; Much Improved; Slightly Improved; No Change; Slightly Worse; Much Worse Very Much Worse.
The number of caregivers who selected each marker at the end of treatment is presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in the Quality of Life in Childhood Epilepsy (QOLCE) score</measure>
    <time_frame>0-12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The QOLCE is composed of 16 subscales assessing seven domains of Health Related Quality of Life (physical function, social function, emotional well-being, cognition, behavior, general health and general quality of life). These were assessed by the caregiver.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsy</condition>
  <condition>Dravet Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GWP42003-P</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will up-titrate GWP42003-P to the maximum tolerated dose (to be confirmed from Part A of the study) over a period of seven days, then commence a further 11 weeks of twice-daily dosing (total of 12 weeks).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo control matched to the GWP42003-P arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GWP42003-P</intervention_name>
    <description>GWP42003-P is an oral solution presented as an oily solution containing 25 mg/mL cannabidiol (CBD: FT0086) or 100 mg/mL CBD (FT0095) dissolved in the excipients sesame oil and anhydrous ethanol with added sweetener (sucralose) and strawberry flavoring.</description>
    <arm_group_label>GWP42003-P</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cannabidiol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo control</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo oral solution contains the excipients sesame oil and anhydrous ethanol with added sweetener (sucralose) and strawberry flavoring.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject must be male or female aged between 2 and 18 years (inclusive).

          -  Subject must have a documented history of Dravet syndrome which is not completely
             controlled by current antiepileptic drugs.

          -  Subject must be experiencing four or more convulsive seizures (tonic-clonic seizures
             and/or drop attacks) during the 28-day baseline observation period.

          -  Subject must be taking one or more antiepileptic drugs at a dose which has been
             stable for at least four weeks.

          -  All medications or interventions for epilepsy (including ketogenic diet and vagus
             nerve stimulation) must have been stable for four weeks prior to screening and
             subject is willing to maintain a stable regimen throughout the study.

        Key Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has clinically significant unstable medical conditions other than epilepsy.

          -  Subject has had clinically relevant symptoms or a clinically significant illness in
             the four weeks prior to screening or randomization, other than epilepsy.

          -  Subject is currently using or has in the past used recreational or medicinal
             cannabis, or synthetic cannabinoid based medications (including Sativex®) within the
             three months prior to study entry and is unwilling to abstain for the duration for
             the study.

          -  Subject has any known or suspected hypersensitivity to cannabinoids or any of the
             excipients of the investigational medicinal products.

          -  Subjects who have been part of a clinical trial involving another investigational
             product in the previous six months.

          -  There are plans for the subject to travel outside their country of residence during
             the study.

          -  Subjects previously randomized into this study. In particular, subjects who
             participated in Part A of the study cannot enter Part B.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard Potts</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0) 1980 557000</phone>
    <email>r@gwpharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 17, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cannabidiol</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epilepsies, Myoclonic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
