<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="55263">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01802632</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D5160C00001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01802632</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AZD9291 First Time In Patients Ascending Dose Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>AURA</acronym>
  <official_title>Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Anti-tumour Activity of AZD9291 in Patients With Advanced Non Small Cell Lung Cancer Who Progressed on Prior Therapy With an Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor Agent</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AstraZeneca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Australia: Department of Health and Ageing Therapeutic Goods Administration</authority>
    <authority>France: Afssaps - Agence française de sécurité sanitaire des produits de santé (Saint-Denis)</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>Japan: Ministy of Health, Labor and Welfare</authority>
    <authority>South Korea: Korea Food and Drug Administration (KFDA)</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Agencia Espanola de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios</authority>
    <authority>Taiwan: Department of Health</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Italy: National Monitoring Centre for Clinical Trials - Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will treat patients with advanced NSCLC who have already received at least one
      course of  specific anti-cancer treatment but the tumour has started to re-grow following
      that treatment. This is the first time this drug has ever been tested in patients, and so it
       will help to understand what type of side effects may occur  with the drug  treatment, it
      will measure the levels of drug in the body, it will also measure the anti-cancer activity.
      By using these pieces of information together the best dose of this drug to use in further
      clinical trials will be selected.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A Phase I/II, Open-Label, Multicentre Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability,
      Pharmacokinetics and Anti-tumour Activity of Ascending Doses of AZD9291 in Patients with
      Advanced Non Small Cell Lung Cancer who have Progressed Following Prior Therapy with an
      Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor Agent (AURA)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety, tolerability and efficacy (ORR) of AZD9291, assessed by number and severity of adverse events as recorded on the case report form, vital signs, laboratory variables, physical examination, electrocardiogram, ophthalmic examinations and RECIST1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Adverse events will be collected from baseline until 28 days after the last dose, expected average 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Physical exam (screening, first dosing day, first day of multiple dosing, Day 1 of every 3-week cycle and treatment discontinuation). ECG and vital signs (screening, Day 1 and 2 of first dosing, Day 1, 8 and 15 of multiple dosing and Day 1 of every 3-week cycle, treatment discontinuation, and if occurrence of any cardiac adverse event). Lab variables (screening, first dosing day, Day 1, 8 and 15 of multiple dosing, Day 1 of every 3-week cycle and treatment discontinuation). Eye exam (at screening and upon occurrence of any visual AE). CT/MRI at screening and every 6 weeks until progression</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma concentrations of AZD9291 and 2 active metabolites (AZ5104 and AZ7550) and pharmacokinetic parameters following single dose (Cmax, tmax, AUC, terminal rate constant, clearance, half life, volume of distribution and mean resistance time)</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples will be collected from each subject at pre-specified times after the first dose of the study on Day 1 (pre-dose, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 24, 48, 72, 120 hours post dose)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma concentrations of AZD9291 and 2 active metabolites (AZ5104 and AZ7550) and pharmacokinetic parameters following dosing with AZD9291 (Cmax, tmax, AUC, terminal rate constant, clearance, half life, volume of distribution and mean resistance time)</measure>
    <time_frame>A blood sample will be taken on the day of the optional tumour biopsy (pre-dose and at the time of the tumour biopsy on Cycle 1 Day 15)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma concentrations of AZD9291 and 2 active metabolites (AZ5104 and AZ7550) and pharmacokinetic parameters following multiple doses (steady state Cmax, tmax, Cmin AUC, clearance, accumulation ratio and time dependency)</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples will be collected from each subject at pre-specified times during the multiple dosing cycles (Cycle 1-pre-dose Day 1, 8 and 15. Cycle 2- pre-dose, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 24 hours post dose)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic markers to assess correlations with disease activity, effects of study drug and clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Optional tumour biopsy samples will be collected at screening, Day 15 and treatment discontinuation, expected average 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic markers to assess correlations with disease activity, effects of study drug and clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Plasma samples for extraction and analysis of circulating free tumour DNA (cfDNA) will be taken at screening, day 1 of dosing, 6 weekly (in line with RECIST assessments), discontinuation, 28 days after last dose and disease progression</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of tumour response, duration of response, tumour shrinkage, progression free survival and overall survival as assessed by RECIST 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>CT or MRI at screening and every 6 weeks (from first dose of multiple dosing) until disease progression or withdrawal from study, expected average 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic markers in EGFRm+ T790M+ tumours at selective endpoints</measure>
    <time_frame>Optional tumour biopsy samples collected at screening and Cycle 1 Day 15 (Paired Biopsy)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported outcomes: EORTC QLQ C-30 and QLQ-LC13</measure>
    <time_frame>Expansion and Extension cohorts only: Questionnaires completed at screening, Cycle 1 Day 1, every 6 weeks relative to first dose, discontinuation and progression</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacogenetics</measure>
    <time_frame>Optional blood sample collected during screening, no more than 28 days before first dose of AZD9291</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">498</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Non Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Advanced (Inoperable) Non Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Daily dose of AZD9291</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Daily oral dose of AZD9291</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AZD9291</intervention_name>
    <description>Starting dose 20 mg, administered once daily. If tolerated subsequent cohorts will test increasing doses of AZD9291, until a maximum tolerated dose or maximum feasible dose is defined</description>
    <arm_group_label>Daily dose of AZD9291</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Provision of signed and dated, written informed consent prior to any study specific
             procedures, sampling and analyses

          -  Aged at least 18 years.  Patients from Japan aged at least 20 years.

          -  Histological or cytological confirmation diagnosis of Non Small Cell Lung Cancer
             (NSCLC).

          -  Radiological documentation of disease progression while on a previous continuous
             treatment with an EGFR TKI e.g. gefitinib or erlotinib (with the exception of 1st
             line expansion cohort). In addition other lines of therapy may have been given. All
             patients must have documented radiological progression on the last treatment
             administered prior to enrolling in the study.

          -  Patients (with the exception of 1st line expansion cohort) must fulfil one of the
             following:

               -  Confirmation that the tumour harbours an EGFR mutation known to be associated
                  with EGFR TKI sensitivity (including G719X, exon 19 deletion, L858R, L861Q) OR

               -  Must have experienced clinical benefit from EGFR TKI, according to the Jackman
                  criteria (Jackman et al 2010) followed by systemic objective progression (RECIST
                  or WHO) while on continuous treatment with EGFR TKI.

          -  Previous treatment with a single-agent EGFR TKI (e.g. gefitinib or erlotinib).

          -  Females should be using adequate contraceptive measures, should not be breast feeding
             and must have a negative pregnancy test prior to start of dosing or evidence of
             non-child bearing potential.

          -  Male patients should be willing to use barrier contraception.

          -  For 1st Line expansion cohort ONLY, confirmation that the tumour is EGFRm+ve and have
             had no prior therapy for their advanced disease (for 1st line patients biopsy will be
             at time of diagnosis of advanced disease).

          -  For dose expansion and extension cohorts, patients must also have confirmation of
             tumour T790M mutation status (confirmed positive or negative) from a biopsy sample
             taken after disease progression on the most recent treatment regimen (irrespective of
             whether this is EGFR TKI or chemotherapy).

        Prior to entry a result from the central analysis of the patient's T790M mutation status
        must be obtained.

        - World Health Organisation (WHO) performance status 0-1 with no deterioration over the
        previous 2 weeks and a minimum life expectancy of 12 weeks.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Treatment with an EGFR TKI (erlotinib or gefitinib) within 8 days (approximately 5x
             half-life) of the first dose of study treatment.

          -  Any cytotoxic chemotherapy, investigational agents or other anticancer drugs from the
             treatment of advanced NSCLC from a previous treatment regimen or clinical study
             within 14 days of the first dose of study treatment.

          -  AZD9291 in the present study (ie, dosing with AZD9291 previously initiated in this
             study).

          -  Any evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic diseases, including uncontrolled
             hypertension, active bleeding diatheses, or active infection.

          -  Past medical history of interstitial lung disease, drug-induced interstitial lung
             disease, radiation pneumonitis which required steroid treatment, or any evidence of
             clinically active interstitial lung disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Serban Ghiorghiu, MSD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>AstraZeneca</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>AstraZeneca Clinical Study Information</last_name>
    <phone>800-236-9933</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTrialTransparency@astrazeneca.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>AstraZeneca Cancer Study Locator Service http://www.emergingmed.com/networks/AstraZeneca</last_name>
    <phone>1-877-400-4656</phone>
    <email>astrazeneca@emergingmed.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlotte</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kogarah</city>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nedlands</city>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pierre Benite Cedex</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Herblain</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villejuif</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Essen</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Köln</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Würzburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Genova</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orbassano</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chiba-shi</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuoka</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuoka-shi</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Habikino-shi</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hirakata-shi</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hiroshima-shi</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kanazawa</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kashiwa-shi</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kobe-shi</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Matsuyama-shi</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Okayama-shi</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shinjuku-ku</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sunto-gun</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Takatsuki-shi</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yokohama-shi</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tainan</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newcastle upon Tyne</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Japan</country>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Oncology,</keyword>
  <keyword>Non Small Cell Lung Cancer,</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic,</keyword>
  <keyword>EGFR sensitivity mutation,</keyword>
  <keyword>T790M resistance mutation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
