<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="20084">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02005211</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D5010C00003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02005211</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Two-part Single and Multiple Dose Study to Assess the Safety , Pharmacokinetics and Effects of AZD3293 in Healthy Japanese Young and Elderly Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Single and Multiple Ascending Dose Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Effect on Biomarkers of AZD3293 in Healthy Japanese Male and Non-Fertile Female Volunteers Including Elderly</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AstraZeneca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare</authority>
    <authority>Japan: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study consists of two parts, ie, single dose part with young healthy subjects (Part 1)
      and single and multiple dose part with elderly healthy subjects (Part 2), to assess the
      safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of AZD3293 following single and
      multiple ascending dose administration to healthy subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I, randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, single centre study to
      assess the safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of AZD3293 following
      single and multiple ascending dose administration to healthy subjects.  This study consists
      of two parts, ie, single dose part with young healthy subjects (Part 1) and single and
      multiple dose part with elderly healthy subjects (Part 2).  The study design allows a
      gradual escalation of dosage levels between sequential cohorts with safety monitoring to
      ensure the safety of the healthy subjects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety profile in terms of Adverse Events assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline up to 20 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability in terms  of vital signs (blood pressure, pulse and body temperature) and physical exams</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline up to 20 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability  in terms of lab variables assessment(chemistry, hematology, urinalysis, renal safety)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline up to 20 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability  by assessing changes in  12-lead digital electrocardiogram parameters (rhythm, rate, morphology, QT/QTc interval)</measure>
    <time_frame>Fron Baseline up to 20 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of telemetry, as reported by Investigator Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline up to 20 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) captures the occurrence, severity, and frequency of suicide-related thoughts and behaviors during the assessment period. Some questions are yes/no and some are on a scale of 1 (low severity) to 5 (high severity). Completed suicide and non-fatal suicide events are yes/no questions and results presented are the number of participants with these events. Worsening of suicidal ideation was an increase in severity of suicidal ideation from baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the effect of AZD3293 on plasma biomarkers relevant for Alzheimer Disease (AD) as assessed by AZD3293 plasma levels and plasma abeta 40 and 42 levels.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 17 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>effect of single and multiple dose Pharmacokinetics for AZD3293 and its metabolite following oral administration as assessed by Cmax and AUC.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 17 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics/Pharmacodynamics relationship of the effect of AZD3293 on biomarkers relevant for Alzheimer Disease (AD) in plasma as assessed by correlation of AZD3293 exposure with the effect on plasma abeta 40 and 42 levels.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 17 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Japanese Young and Elderly Male and Non-fertile Female Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AZD3293</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>AZD3293 will be administered as single dose of an oral solution in Part 1 and single and multiple doses of an oral solution in Part 2. The ascending doses are planned to be 15, 50 and 150 mg for young subjects in Part 1 and 15 and 50 mg for elderly subjects in Part 2. Before proceeding to next dose level, safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetic data from the previous cohort(s) will be evaluated by a Safety Review Committee. Part 2 will start after confirming safety and tolerability in Part 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo given (2 subjects in each cohort)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AZD3293</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral solution</description>
    <arm_group_label>AZD3293</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral solution</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy Japanese elderly and young males and females (of non-childbearing potential)

          -  Body mass index (BMI) between 17 and 27 kg/m2 and weigh at least 40 kg and no more
             than 100 kg

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Psychiatric disease/condition, GI, renal, hepatic, cardiovascular, psychiatric, or
             retinal diseases or disorders

          -  Use of antipsychotic drugs , or chronic use of antidepressant or anxiolytic drugs.

          -  Frequent use (more than 2 days per week during the last 12 weeks) of tobacco or other
             nicotine products.

          -  Neurological disease, including seizures, recent memory impairment, or clinically
             significant head injury.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert C Alexander, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>AstraZeneca</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kei Sakamoto, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sugioka Memorial Hospital, Medical Co. LTA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>AstraZeneca Clinical Study Information</last_name>
    <phone>800-236-9933</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTrialTransparency@astrazeneca.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuoka-shi</city>
        <state>Fukuoka</state>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 15, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 4, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>AZD3293</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy volunteers</keyword>
  <keyword>Young volunteers</keyword>
  <keyword>Elderly volunteers</keyword>
  <keyword>Japanese volunteers</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase 1</keyword>
  <keyword>Single and multiple ascending dose study</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
