<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="5053">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02150902</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRIS 2771</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>TBD</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02150902</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Augmented Wide Area Circumferential Catheter Ablation for Reduction of Atrial Fibrillation Recurrence</brief_title>
  <acronym>AWARE</acronym>
  <official_title>AUGMENTED WIDE AREA CIRCUMFERENTIAL CATHETER ABLATION FOR REDUCTION OF ATRIAL FIBRILLATION RECURRENCE - A RANDOMIZED CLINICAL TRIAL (The AWARE Trial)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Ottawa Heart Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Ottawa Heart Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Atrial fibrillation (AF) is an abnormal heart rhythm in which the top chambers of the heart
      beat very fast. AF catheter ablation is a known technique to convert heart rhythm from AF to
      normal rhythm. The technique sends out electrical energy through a catheter (long thin round
      solid tubes) to destroy the heart tissues in a focused area where AF is starting. This
      technique is practiced at many hospitals, including the Heart Institute, and is not
      experimental.

      The AWARE study will compare two techniques of AF catheter ablation:

        1. Ablation of tissues in wide circular bands around the opening of the pulmonary veins
           (bring blood back from lungs) in the left upper chamber of the heart.  A medicine
           called adenosine will be given to unmask any incompletely ablated area. Additional
           ablations will be given if required. This is standard procedure.

        2. Same as above but adenosine will not be used. Instead, additional ablation of a second
           circular band of tissues around the opening of the pulmonary veins will be given. This
           additional ablation is not standard procedure and is considered experimental.

      We want to see if adding more ablation sites will help maintain normal heart rhythm and
      reduce the rate of return to AF. We will compare the occurrence of medical events and
      complications between the two groups.

      Identical supplies and equipment used in both techniques have been approved by Health
      Canada. Adenosine is currently approved by Health Canada for the treatment and diagnosis of
      arrhythmias.

      342 participants from The University of Ottawa Heart Institute will be randomly assigned
      &quot;similar to flipping a coin&quot; to treatment group 1 or group 2.

      After the ablation, participants can expect to remain in hospital for up to about 4 days.
      They will have study follow-up at the Heart Institute every 3 months for 1 to 3 years,
      depending on when they enter the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Clinical relevance:

      The problem of PV reconnection and recurrent AF after catheter ablation for paroxysmal AF is
      one of the important challenges faced by treating physicians.

      Rationale:

      The understanding of the role contact force plays in adequate lesion formation during
      catheter ablation and the fact that this may reduce pulmonary vein (PV) reconnection and AF
      recurrence is an exciting advance in the field of catheter ablation for AF. A few small
      clinical trials have demonstrated the safety and feasibility of contact force guided
      catheter ablation in reducing PV reconnection and AF recurrence. There is a clear need for
      well designed and adequately powered clinical trials to evaluate the effectiveness of this
      new strategy.

      Objective:

      Using contact force (CF) technology, our intention is to evaluate an &quot;augmented- wide area
      circumferential catheter ablation strategy&quot; that could potentially reduce the incidence of
      pulmonary vein reconnection and AF recurrence after catheter ablation in patients with
      paroxysmal AF.

      Hypothesis:

      In patients with symptomatic, antiarrhythmic medication resistant paroxysmal AF an
      augmented-wide area circumferential catheter ablation strategy will result in fewer
      electrocardiographically documented AF recurrences compared to conventional wide-area
      catheter ablation.

      All subjects in the control arm of the trial will undergo wide area circumferential catheter
      ablation (WACA; lesions delivered 1-2 cm away from the pulmonary vein ostium) around all
      four pulmonary veins to the endpoint of electrical isolation (demonstrated by entry and exit
      block using differential pacing). Catheter ablation will be performed using CF and VISITAG
      guidance (average CF &gt;10g, Force time integral (FTI) &gt; 500 g-sec and minimum ablation
      duration &gt;10 sec). Dormant PV conduction will be tested using adenosine, after completion of
      the lesion set, and additional lesions will be delivered to eliminate dormant PV conduction.

      In the experimental arm of the trial all subjects will undergo WACA as described above;
      however without adenosine testing. In addition these subjects will receive &quot;augmented&quot;
      ablation lesions, guided by CF feedback, on the outer aspect of the first WACA lesion set.
      Our hypothesis is that this &quot;belts and suspender&quot; strategy of redundant, CF guided antral
      ablation lesions will result in a wider band of irreversible atrial muscle and cardiac
      autonomic ganglionated-plexi damage. It is our expectation that the augmented WACA strategy
      will result in more durable PV isolation and thereby significantly reduce AF recurrence.

      Trial Design:

      This trial will be a single blinded (patients blinded), prospective, parallel arm randomized
      clinical trial. Subjects who satisfy the inclusion and exclusion criteria will be enrolled
      in the clinical trial. Subjects will be randomized (1:1) to either the control arm (WACA
      only) or the experimental arm (augmented- WACA). Patients randomized to the experimental arm
      will go on to have augmented-WACA. The first three-month period after catheter ablation will
      be considered a &quot;blanking-period&quot; and atrial tachyarrhythmias (AF, Atrial Flutter [AFl] or
      Atrial Tachycardia [AT]) occurring during this period will be documented. However, these
      will not be considered treatment failures. Patient accrual will occur over a 24-month period
      and each subject will have a minimum follow-up period of 12 months. The total duration of
      the trial will be 36-months (24 months for accrual and a minimum of 12 months of follow up
      for each subject). Patients will be followed up every three months after ablation, with
      transtelephonic monitoring as well as a 2-week loop recording prior to each follow up visit,
      for the entire duration of the trial. This f/u concurs with recommendations from 2012 Heart
      Rhythm Society/European Heart Rhythm Association/European Cardiac Arrhythmia Society Expert
      Consensus Statement on Catheter and Surgical Ablation of Atrial Fibrillation:
      Recommendations for Patient Selection, Procedural Techniques, Patient Management and
      Follow-up, Definitions, Endpoints, and Research Trial Design.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrence of any ECG documented AF, AFl or AT</measure>
    <time_frame>between days 91 and 364 after catheter ablation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to first recurrence of any ECG documented AF, AFl or 	AT (symptomatic or asymptomatic) occurring between days 91 and 364 after catheter ablation in the absence of Class I or III antiarrhythmic drug therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>repeat catheter ablation procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>days 91 and 364 after catheter ablation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The need for repeat catheter ablation procedure because of documented recurrence of symptomatic AF, AFl or AT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ECG documented AF</measure>
    <time_frame>during the first 90 days after catheter ablation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Incidence of any ECG documented AF (symptomatic or asymptomatic) during the first 90 days after catheter ablation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>emergency department visits or hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>from randomization to day 364</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The need for emergency department visits or hospitalizations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>procedure related complications</measure>
    <time_frame>from ablation to day 364</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Composite safety endpoints- procedure related complications (Stroke, PV stenosis, Pericarditis, Cardiac perforation, Atrio-esophageal fistula, Major bleeding) and/or death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>from randomization to day 364</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quality of Life (EQ-5 and Canadian Cardiovascular Society-Severity of AF scales)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">342</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Augmented- WACA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Augmented- wide area circumferential catheter ablation for atrial fibrillation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>WACA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Wide area circumferential catheter ablation procedure for atrial fibrillation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Wide area circumferential catheter ablation</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects in the control arm of the trial will undergo wide area circumferential catheter ablation (WACA; lesions delivered 1-2 cm away from the pulmonary vein ostium) around all four pulmonary veins to the endpoint of electrical isolation (demonstrated by entry and exit block using differential pacing). Catheter ablation will be performed using contact force (CF) and electroanatomical mapping system guidance (average CF &gt;10g, FTI &gt; 500 g-sec and minimum ablation duration &gt;10 sec). Dormant pulmonary vein conduction will be tested using adenosine, after completion of the lesion set, and additional lesions will be delivered to eliminate dormant PV conduction.</description>
    <arm_group_label>WACA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>WACA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Augmented- wide area circumferential ablation procedure</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects in this group will have WACA performed as described 	for WACA. Following completion of the WACA procedure a second set 	of circumferential ablation lesions will be delivered around the first 	set of ablation lesions. The ablation catheter tip will be positioned at 	each of the ablation lesions along the first WACA line and then 	moved away 	(from the PV ostia) until healthy, non ablated tissue is 	recorded from the catheter tip. Energy will be delivered using CF 	and FTI data as described previously. Once the first WACA ablation 	line has been completely duplicated the procedure will be deemed 	complete. In case PV isolation is not achieved after the first WACA 	lesion set repeat electrophysiologic testing will be performed to 	determine whether the augmented-WACA procedure was 	successful in achieving PV isolation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Augmented- WACA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Augmented WACA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must meet all of the following criteria:

               1. Age ≥18 years and ≤ 80 years

               2. Subjects with paroxysmal AF and at least three symptomatic episodes (on subject
                  history) during the previous 6 months

               3. Subjects must have symptomatic AF that is refractory to at least one class I or
                  Class III antiarrhythmic medication, be intolerant of antiarrhythmic medications
                  or refuse to trial antiarrhythmic medications

               4. At least one episode of AF documented on 12-lead ECG, Trans-telephonic monitor
                  (TTM) or Holter monitor within 12 months of randomization in the trial

               5. Subjects must be on continuous systemic oral anticoagulation with either
                  warfarin (INR 2-3) or newer-oral anticoagulants (Dabigatran, Rivaroxaban,
                  Apixaban or Edoxaban) for 28 days prior to the day of ablation or must have
                  undergone a recent (&lt; 48 hrs) trans-esophageal echocardiogram (TEE) prior to the
                  day of ablation to exclude left atrial thrombus

               6. Subjects must be able to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects should not have any of the following criteria-

               1. History of previous catheter or surgical ablation for AF

               2. Presence of intracardiac thrombus

               3. Subjects with contraindication to systemic oral anticoagulation therapy

               4. Subjects with reversible causes of AF

               5. Subjects with left atrial dimension &gt; 55 mm on echocardiography

               6. Subjects with significant valve disease (moderate or severe mitral/aortic
                  stenosis or regurgitation)

               7. Subjects that are pregnant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Girish Nair, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Ottawa Heart Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Girish Nair, MD</last_name>
    <phone>613-761-4705</phone>
    <email>gnair@ottawaheart.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Susan McClinton, BScNursing</last_name>
    <phone>613-761-5208</phone>
    <email>smcclinton@ottawaheart.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Ottawa Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1Y 4W7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Girish Nair, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 27, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Catheter ablation for atrial fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment for atrial fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>comparison of catheter ablation techniques for atrial fibrillation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Recurrence</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
