<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="166644">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02106598</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-249</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02106598</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Targeted Silica Nanoparticles for Image-Guided Intraoperative Sentinel Lymph Node Mapping in Head and Neck Melanoma Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Targeted Silica Nanoparticles for Image-Guided Intraoperative Sentinel Lymph Node Mapping in Head and Neck Melanoma Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Current imaging devices usually detect cancer prior to surgery. However, these devices
      cannot be used during the surgical procedure to visualize lymph nodes with cancer (called
      &quot;sentinel lymph nodes&quot;). As a part of the standard of care, the patient will initially
      undergo imaging of their lymph nodes prior to their surgery. They will be injected with a
      radioactive dye around the tumor site, and images will be acquired about 2 hours later using
      a device to image where the dye travels to in the neck. In addition, we will test, for the
      first time in humans, a new, experimental dye-labeled particle (dots), cRGDY-PEG-Cy5.5-C
      dots for lymph node mapping. This particle, the size of a small protein, will be injected
      around sites of melanoma in the operating room to identify diseased nodes using a hand-held
      camera system. The dye-labeled particle can be viewed in tissues that may contain tumor. The
      particles will not treat the cancer and any images or information found during this study
      will not be used for your treatment. The information collected may be used to guide the
      design of future studies to detect and/or treat tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>feasibility of conducting pre-operative SLN mapping</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>using real-time optical detection procedures and intradermal single- or double-dose injection/s of non-radioactive cRGDY-PEG-Cy5.5-C dots about the primary tumor site. Feasibility will be determined on the basis of achieving adequate image contrast for detection, as defined by signal-to-background ratios, and whether optical signal distinguishes diseased SLNs from non-diseased ones</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Head and Neck Melanoma Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>preoperatively administered technetium-99m (99mTc) sulfur colloid with intraoperatively injected fluorescent cRGDY-PEG-Cy5.5-C dots (0.1 - 0.5 ml over a dose range of ~0.25 to ~1.2 nanomoles in 4 quadrants about the primary lesion) for identification of sentinel nodes. Intraoperative NIR fluorescence imaging will be performed using a state-of-the-art hand-held fluorescence camera system (f 2.4) for real-time optical visualization of nodal disease, along with gamma counting for 99mTc sulfur colloid, to determine if concordance can be established as a continuous endpoint. Results will be histologically confirmed in resected tissue specimens.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fluorescent cRGDY-PEG-Cy5.5-C dots</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Head and Neck Melanoma Patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  Histologically confirmed diagnosis of melanoma at MSKCC

          -  Newly-diagnosed or recurrent (local, regional, metastatic) malignant melanoma
             patients in whom SLN mapping is indicated

          -  Residual clinically or radiographically evident tumor, including primary cutaneous
             and mucosal melanomas

          -  Prior radiation therapy, chemotherapy, or surgery in patients requiring flap
             reconstruction in the head and neck region.

          -  Newly diagnosed patients with previous excisional biopsy. Normal baseline cardiac
             function based upon EKG and pre-operative evaluation

          -  ANC&gt;1000/mcl and platelets&gt;100,000/mcl.

          -  Bilirubin level of &lt; 2.0 mg/dl in the absence of a history of Gilbert's disease (or
             pattern consistent with Gilbert's).

          -  If patients have a history of malignancy other than melanoma, they must be
             disease-free for ≥ 5 years at the time of enrollment.

          -  All patients of childbearing and child-creating age must be using an acceptable form
             of birth control

          -  Women who are pre-menopausal must have a negative serum pregnancy test

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known pregnancy or breast-feeding.

          -  Medical illness unrelated to the tumor which in the opinion of the attending
             physician and principal investigator will preclude administration of the agent. This
             includes patients with uncontrolled infection, chronic renal insufficiency,
             myocardial infarction within the past 6 months, unstable angina, cardiac arrhythmias
             other than chronic atrial fibrillation and chronic active or persistent hepatitis, or
             New York Heart Association Classification III or IV heart disease.

          -  History of any malignancy other than melanoma for which the disease-free interval is
             &lt;5 years and/or on active therapy for that malignancy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michelle Bradbury, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michelle Bradbury, MD, Phd</last_name>
    <phone>646-888-3373</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Snehal Patel, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-3412</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michelle Bradbury, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-3373</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Snehal Patel, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-3412</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michelle Bradbury, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 3, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sentinel Lymph Node Mapping</keyword>
  <keyword>Intraoperative Sentinel</keyword>
  <keyword>Head and Neck</keyword>
  <keyword>Targeted Silica Nanoparticles</keyword>
  <keyword>cRGDY-PEG-Cy5.5-C dots</keyword>
  <keyword>13-249</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
