<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="38664">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02124122</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FDA IND# 13710-Protocol 2</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01AT002733</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02124122</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety of Lactobacillus Reuteri in Healthy Children Ages 2 to 5 Years in Peru</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety of Lactobacillus Reuteri in Healthy Children Ages 2 to 5 Years in Peru</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tulane University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Complementary and Alternative Medicine (NCCAM)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Asociacion Benefica PRISMA</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tulane University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1 study to assess the safety and tolerability of Lactobacillus reuteri (Lr)
      strain DSM 17938 in healthy children in Peru.  It is a preliminary study in support of a
      clinical trial to assess safety and efficacy of L. reuteri for treatment of pediatric
      diarrhea in Peru.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase I blinded randomized study of the safety and tolerability of Lactobacillus
      reuteri DSM 17938 given daily for a period of five consecutive days. Upon enrollment
      subjects will be randomized to one of two treatment groups in a ratio of treatment to
      placebo of 2:1.  Subjects will be randomized to receive either:

      A.  Lactobacillus reuteri (Lr):  108 (100 million) organisms of Lactobacillus reuteri per
      dose, given once daily for a five-day treatment period that corresponds to a dose of the
      closely related L. reuteri ATCC 55730 strain that has shown to be therapeutic for infantile
      colic.  The strain used in this study (DSM 17938) has been cured of an antibiotic resistance
      plasmid found in the original BioGaia strain (L. reuteri ATCC 55730).

      B.   Placebo oil preparation, administered as 5 drops of the oil vehicle used in
      manufacturing the Lr suspension, given once daily for a five-day study period (BioGaia AB,
      Stockholm, Sweden).

      In the first 30 subjects randomized, administration of each dose of the study preparation
      drops (A or B above) will be immediately followed by offering 2 ounces of flavored PediaSure
      ® (Abbott Laboratories) nutritional supplement to each child.  The second 30 subjects
      enrolled will not be offered PediaSure ® after product administration.  This format will
      also allow us to assess the impact of concurrent administration of a buffering non-lactose
      containing formula with prebiotic nutritional properties on intestinal colonization with L.
      reuteri  by PCR.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>number of participants with positive blood culture for L reuteri</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants are followed an average of 36 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean daily temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days of study product administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lactobacillus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lactobacillus reuteri (Lr):  108 (100 million) organisms of Lactobacillus reuteri per dose, given once daily for a five-day treatment period that corresponds to a dose of the closely related L. reuteri ATCC 55730 strain that has shown to be therapeutic for infantile colic.  The strain used in this study (DSM 17938) has been cured of an antibiotic resistance plasmid found in the original BioGaia strain (L. reuteri ATCC 55730).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo oil preparation, administered as 5 drops of the oil vehicle used in manufacturing the Lr suspension, given once daily for a five-day study period (BioGaia AB, Stockholm, Sweden).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lactobacillus reuteri</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Lactobacillus</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BioGaia Probiotic Drops</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children ages 2-5 years with no exclusion criteria

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1)  No enrollment of family members in households where any of the following are
             present:

               1. Another study participant in the household

               2. Pregnancy or current breastfeeding by any household member

               3. Presence of an infant under age 6 months living in the household

               4. Presence of immune suppressed individuals or use of immunosuppressive agents
                  (including but not limited to corticosteroids and methotrexate, etc.) by any
                  household member

               5. Presence of a serious congenital anomaly or chronic medical condition that in
                  the opinion of the investigators would contraindicate participation in any
                  household member, including history of gastrointestinal surgery, chronic
                  gastrointestinal illness, abnormal intestinal anatomy, or abnormal bowel
                  functionality

                  2)  Allergy to penicillin or cephalosporins or gentamicin 3) History of
                  antibiotic use in the last 30 days 4) Use of probiotic products within the past
                  90 days, including masato (local product with fermenting bacteria) and yogurt
                  products containing live bacterial cultures.

                  5)   History of diarrheal illness within the past 30 days 6)  Presence of fever
                  or a pre-existing adverse event monitored in the study 7)  Positive results on
                  serum diagnostic tests for antibodies to HIV.

                  Testing for Hepatitis B core antigen, and Hepatitis C is not necessary in
                  children as in adults, since there is universal vaccination for Hepatitis B
                  among children in this community, and both forms of hepatitis are rare and
                  largely asymptomatic in this age group.

                  8) Presence of severe anemia, defined as serum hemoglobin &lt; 8 gm/dL

                  9)   Out of range laboratory values for tests monitored as potential adverse
                  events, as described in Appendix 2, B.   LABORATORY VALUES, and detected based
                  on Day 0 blood test results.  However, subjects will only be excluded based on
                  serum hemoglobin if they meet exclusion criterion 8.

                  10) Pre-enrollment stool sample (collected within 14 days of Day 1 of the study)
                  is positive for L. reuteri  by PCR.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard A Oberhelman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tulane School of Public Health and Tropical Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Margaret N Kosek, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins School of Public Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Margaret N Kosek, MD</last_name>
    <phone>011-51-65-234250</phone>
    <email>mkosek@jhsph.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Pablo Yori, MS</last_name>
    <phone>011-51-65-234250</phone>
    <email>pyori@jhsph.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Community of Santa Clara</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santa Clara</city>
        <state>Loreto</state>
        <country>Peru</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Margaret N Kosek, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Peru</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 24, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tulane University School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Richard A. Oberhelman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Focus</keyword>
  <keyword>safety</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
