<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="41728">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01729624</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Rec No: 12/SW/0252</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01729624</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PRO Development for ANCA Associated Vasculitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Qualitative Study Using Interviews With Patients Who Have Anti-neutrophil Cytoplasm Antibody (ANCA) Associated Vasculitis, to Develop a Patient Reported Outcome (PRO) Measure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A qualitative study using interviews with patients who have antineutrophil cytoplasm
      antibody (ANCA) associated vasculitis, to develop a patient reported outcome (PRO)measure
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibody (ANCA) associated vasculitis (AAV) have
      inflammation in the small blood vessels leading to involvement in different body areas,
      e.g., the kidneys, lungs and skin. Untreated, the risk of death is over 80%; with current
      treatment, patients often suffer from ongoing disease activity, damage or treatment side
      effects which have a negative impact on quality of life. Because patients with AAV can have
      a wide range of disease features, the investigators hypothesise that general patient
      reported outcome (PROs) measurements, may not be specific enough to describe the full impact
      on quality of life.

      The main objective of this project is to start from patients' experiences to develop a
      disease specific PRO for patients with AAV. Patients diagnosed with AAV will be recruited
      through clinics or inpatients at the Oxford University Hospitals (OUH) National Health
      Service (NHS) Trust, or, if the patients have previously consented to be contacted about
      future studies, through the Diagnostic and Classification of Vasculitis (DCVAS) or The
      Characterisation and Determinants of Quality of Life in ANCA Associated Vasculitis (VasQoL)
      study databases. After informed consent is obtained, individual patient interviews will be
      conducted; these will last for approximately one hour and will be recorded and transcribed.
      Themes will be independently extracted and amalgamated by the researchers. Approximately 25
      patients with different types of ANCAassociated vasculitis and varying disease duration will
      be interviewed until saturation, i.e., no new substantive themes emerge. These themes will
      then evolve into individual candidate questionnaire items. Candidate items will be piloted
      on approximately 25 different patients with AAV using questionnaires and interviews, until
      no further comments arise, to produce a final set of candidate questionnaire items. The
      duration of the study 1.5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>This is a qualitative research study based on semi-quantitive exploratory patient interviews and therefore it is not appropriate to define only one outcome measure.</measure>
    <time_frame>No formal outcome measure therefore not applicable</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The principle research objective: The investigators are going to interview patients with anti-neutrophil cytoplasm antibody associated vasculitis, to develop and pilot questionnaire items for a patient reported outcome measure specifically for their disease.
The secondary research objective is to describe the impact of ANCA-associated vasculitis on the quality of life of patients attending the Oxford University Hospitals NHS Trust, based on individual anonymised interviews.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Wegener Granulomatosis</condition>
  <condition>Microscopic Polyangiitis</condition>
  <condition>Churg-Strauss Syndrome</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with ANCA-associated vasculitis seen at the Oxford University Hospitals NHS
        Trust.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant is willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the
             study.

          -  Male or female

          -  Aged 18 years or above (no upper limit).

          -  Diagnosed with granulomatosis with polyangiitis- Wegeners (GPA), Churg Strauss
             Syndrome (CSS) or microscopic polyangiitis (MPA)and fulfil either Chapel Hill
             consensus conference definitions or American College of Rheumatology (ACR)
             classification criteria.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable or unwilling to give independent written informed consent

          -  Significant communication barrier e.g., inability to speak English

          -  Membership of the steering committee
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joanna C Robson, MBBS PhD</last_name>
    <phone>01865227329</phone>
    <email>joanna.robson@ndorms.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Raashid Luqmani, DM FRCP, FRCP(E)</last_name>
    <phone>01865227807</phone>
    <email>raashid.luqmani@ndorms.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Oxford</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <state>Oxfordshire</state>
        <zip>OX37LD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joanna C Robson, MBBS PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 14, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 25, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Wegener Granulomatosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Microscopic Polyangiitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Churg-Strauss Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Antibodies, Antineutrophil Cytoplasmic</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Churg-Strauss Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vasculitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wegener Granulomatosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Systemic Vasculitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Microscopic Polyangiitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anti-Neutrophil Cytoplasmic Antibody-Associated Vasculitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Antineutrophil Cytoplasmic</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
