<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="132856">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01964378</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KF6005/07</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012‐001316‐35</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1143-1808</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01964378</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CORAL - Cebranopadol Versus Morphine Prolonged-release in Patients With Chronic Moderate to Severe Pain Related to Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>CORAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Efficacy, Safety, and Tolerability of Oral Cebranopadol Versus Morphine Sulfate PR in Subjects With Chronic Moderate to Severe Pain Related to Cancer.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Grünenthal GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Forest Laboratories</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Grünenthal GmbH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Slovakia: State Institute for Drug Control</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Agencia Española de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Federal Agency for Medicines and Health Products, FAMHP</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pain is one of the most common symptoms associated with malignant tumor. The purpose of this
      trial is to determine whether cebranopadol is as effective in patients with cancer related
      pain as morphine sulfate prolonged release.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The trial comprises an enrollment period, a treatment period (titration and maintenance),
      and a follow-up period. Participants will receive either cebranopadol or morphine for 44
      days. Initially participants will be titrated after 2 and then every 4 days to a morphine or
      cebranopadol dose that provides adequate analgesia and is tolerated. The titration period is
      planned to last 16 days. Thereafter the dose of morphine prolonged release or cebranopadol
      is to be kept stable for a further 28 days, i.e. no dose adjustments will be allowed during
      the maintenance period. This 28 day period is the maintenance period. The follow-up period
      is planned for up to 18 days after the end of last pain medication treatment intake.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Average amount of daily rescue medication at the end of the maintenance period.</measure>
    <time_frame>The last two weeks of the expected 6 week treatment period.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Morphine sulfate immediate release 10 mg tablets will be supplied as rescue medication to trial participants. No dose adjustments of the morphine prolonged release or cebranopadol will be allowed during the maintenance period. The daily use of morphine sulfate 10 mg immediate release tablets will be documented by each participant in the trial. The primary endpoint is the average amount of daily rescue medication intake over the last 2 weeks of the maintenance period. It will be analyzed by means of a mixed-effects model for repeated measures (MMRM).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants with clinically relevant pain reduction at the end of the maintenance period.</measure>
    <time_frame>The last two weeks of the expected 6 week treatment period.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For this assessment, each participant is to indicate the level of pain on an 11-point Numerical Rating Scale, where a score of 0 indicated &quot;no pain&quot; and a score of 10 indicated &quot;pain as bad as you can imagine&quot;. The participants enter their pain intensity in their diary on a daily basis. The pain intensity score in the 14 days prior to the final evaluation in the maintenance period will be compared with the baseline, the baseline pain intensity will be calculated based on the 3 days prior to treatment allocation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in weekly mean of the daily Average Pain Intensity Score from Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; End of Week 6 (6 Weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will be asked: &quot;Please rate your pain by selecting the one number that best describes your pain on average during the last 24 hours.&quot; every day in the morning. They will score their pain intensity on an 11-point Numerical Rating Scale (NRS) where a score of 0 indicated &quot;no pain&quot; and a score of 10 indicated &quot;pain as bad as you can imagine&quot;. The weekly mean value of the 24 h average pain intensity will be calculated as a mean score of these daily entries of average pain intensity for each trial week.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate to treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; End of Week 6 (6 Weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pain intensity will be recorded daily by each participant in the morning on an 11-point Numerical Rating Scale, ranging from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst imaginable pain). From this the weekly average 24-hour pain intensity will be calculated. The number of participants with a 0, 10, 20, 30, up to a 100% reduction in weekly mean pain intensity will be reported over each week and over the last two weeks of the maintenance period.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Score of the Neuropathic Pain Symptom Inventory (NPSI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; End of Week 6 (6 Weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The participant with neuropathic pain (determined by the completion of the DN4 [Douleur Neuropathique] at enrollment) will rate their symptoms of neuropathic pain on Neuropathic Pain Symptom Inventory (NPSI). Ten out of 12 questions are answered on an 11-point scale 0 (no symptom present) to 10 (worst imaginable).  Two out of 12 questions are answered by selecting one of 5 possible responses. Mean scores of NPSI will be calculated.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>EuroQol-5 Dimension (EQ-5D) Health Questionnaire over time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; End of Week 6 (6 Weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The EuroQol-5 Dimension Health Questionnaire is a generic health related quality of life instrument. The participants will answer 5 questions on 5 dimensions of their health related quality of life: mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression. Each question has 3 possible answers reflecting 3 levels of impact on the quality of life.
Participants will also rate their current health state on the visual analogue scale (VAS; 0 = worst imaginable health state and 100 = best imaginable health state). A positive change indicates an improvement.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Physical and Mental Component Scores from the Short Form 12® Health Survey (SF-12).</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; End of Week 6 (6 Weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Physical and Mental Component Scores are calculated from the responses by participants to 12 questions. These 12 questions cover 8 domains, (physical functioning, role-physical, bodily pain, general health, vitality, social functioning, role participation with emotional health problems, and mental health) that a participant was asked to rate over the last week. Questions are scored on a Likert-scale. An overall value for the physical and mental component summary is calculated. A positive change will indicate an improvement</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Patient global impression of change (PGIC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; End of Week 6 (6 Weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In the Patient Global Impression of Change (PGIC) the participant indicates the perceived change over the treatment period compared to his condition prior to the start of treatment. The participant is requested to choose one of seven categories. Scores range from very much improved to very much worse.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical global impression of change (CGIC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; End of Week 6 (6 Weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In the Clinical Global Impression of Change (CGIC) the clinician indicates the perceived change in patient's condition over the treatment period as compared to patient's condition prior to the start of treatment. The clinician is requested to choose one of seven categories. Scores range from very much improved to very much worse.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Overall score of the Patient Assessment of Constipation Symptoms (PAC-SYM)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; End of Week 6 (6 Weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The Constipation Assessment (PAC-SYM) is a 12-item self-report questionnaire that assesses the severity of symptoms of constipation during past 2 weeks. There are 3 subscales with 4 items on Abdominal symptoms, 3 on rectal symptoms and 5 on stool symptoms. Each item is rated on a 5-point Likert scale, where 0=absent, 1=mild, 2=moderate, 3=severe, 4=very severe. If the changes in the overall or subscale scores are positive then there is a worsening in symptoms associated with constipation.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in weekly mean of the daily Worst Pain Intensity Score from Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; End of Week 6 (6 Weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will be asked: &quot;Please rate your pain by selecting the one number that best describes your pain at its worst during the last 24 hours.&quot; every day in the morning. They will score their pain intensity on an 11-point Numerical Rating Scale (NRS) where a score of 0 indicated &quot;no pain&quot; and a score of 10 indicated &quot;pain as bad as you can imagine&quot;. The weekly mean value of the 24 h worst pain intensity will be calculated as a mean score of these daily entries of worst pain intensity for each trial week. A positive change will indicate an improvement, whilst a negative change will indicate a worsening of pain.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">524</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cebranopadol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Once daily oral administration. 200, 400 or 600 µg film coated tablets. Dosage 200 µg to 1000 µg per day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Morphine Prolonged Release</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Twice daily oral administration. 15, 30 or 45 mg morphine sulfate capsules. Dosage 30 to 150 mg per day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cebranopadol</intervention_name>
    <description>Participant will take one or two tablet(s) of cebranopadol in the morning and one or two placebo double-dummy morphine-like capsule(s) in the morning and the evening.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cebranopadol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GRT6005</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Morphine Prolonged Release</intervention_name>
    <description>Participant will take one or two morphine capsule(s) in the morning and in the evening and one or two placebo double-dummy cebranopadol-like tablet(s) in the morning.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Morphine Prolonged Release</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. signed informed consent.

          2. negative pregnancy test before first dose.

          3. Female and male participants willing to use acceptable and highly effective methods
             of birth control.

          4. The following criteria must be fulfilled by participants:

               1. Require daily analgesia for their pain,

               2. Diagnosed with active cancer,

               3. Receiving daily opioid treatment at doses not higher than 90 mg oral morphine or
                  its equivalent (World Health Organization Step II and Step III analgesics) for
                  an appropriate length of time,

               4. Participants must be dissatisfied with their current pain treatment,

               5. Participants must be suffering from cancer-related but not cancer
                  therapy-related chronic pain for a period of 4 weeks or more prior to
                  enrollment.

          5. Eastern Cooperation Oncology Group (ECOG) score 2 or below.

          6. Average pain intensity over the last 24 hours of 5 or more calculated from the pain
             assessments recorded during the last 3 days prior to randomization.

          7. Compliance with the use of the electronic diary defined as at least 3 out of 4 of the
             24 hour Numerical Rating Scale entries available during the last 4 days prior to and
             including the day of allocation to treatment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Evidence of ongoing alcohol and or drug abuse and/or a history of alcohol and/or drug
             abuse within the last 2 years.

          2. A clinically significant disease other than cancer which in the investigator's
             opinion may affect efficacy or safety assessments e.g., significant unstable cardiac,
             vascular, pulmonary, gastrointestinal, endocrine, neurological, infectious disease,
             psychiatric (resulting in disorientation, memory impairment or inability to report
             accurately) or metabolic disorders.

          3. Any gastrointestinal disorder that could affect the absorption and/or elimination of
             Investigational Medicinal Product.

          4. Any planned major surgery during the trial.

          5. Known to or suspected of not being able to comply with the trial protocol and the use
             of Investigational Medicinal Product.

          6. History of seizure disorder and/or epilepsy or any condition associated with a
             significant risk of seizure or epilepsy. Known history and/or presence of symptomatic
             cerebral tumor or cerebral metastases.

          7. Moderate to severe hepatic impairment corresponding to Child-Pugh classification B
             and C. Impaired hepatic cellular integrity indicated by aspartate transaminase or
             alanine transaminase greater than 3 times the upper limit of normal at the Enrollment
             Visit.

          8. Inadequate baseline bone marrow reserve with a white blood cell count below 2000/µL,
             a platelet count 100 000/µL or less, and a hemoglobin level below 8 g/dL at the
             Enrollment Visit.

          9. Impaired renal function. Creatinine clearance less than 60 mL per minute at the
             Enrollment Visit (calculated from the Cockcroft-Gault formula).

         10. Forbidden concomitant medications

         11. Uncontrolled hypertension

         12. Clinically relevant history of hypersensitivity, allergy or contraindications to
             opioid medication or any of the excipients of morphine sulfate (Prolonged Released or
             Immediate Release), or cebranopadol film-coated tablets.

         13. Chronic hepatitis B or C, or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) known by history, or
             presence of active hepatitis B or C within the 3 months before the Enrollment Visit.

         14. History of torsade de pointes and/or presence of risk factors for torsade de pointes
             (e.g., heart failure, hypokalemia, or bradycardia).

         15. Marked prolongation of QTcF (greater than 450 milliseconds) at the Enrollment Visit.

         16. Employees of the sponsor, investigator, or trial site or family members of the
             employees, sponsor, or investigator.

         17. Concurrent participation in another trial or planning to be enrolled in another
             clinical trial (i.e., administration of experimental treatment in another clinical
             trial) during the course of this trial.

         18. Previous participation in this or other trials with cebranopadol.

         19. Participant has received an experimental drug or used an experimental medical device
             within 30 days before the planned start of treatment.

         20. Not receiving opioid treatment for cancer-related pain at the enrollment visit (i.e.,
             opioid naïve).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Director Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Grünenthal GmbH</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Grünenthal Clinical Trials Central Information Desk</last_name>
    <phone>+ 49 241 569</phone>
    <phone_ext>3223</phone_ext>
    <email>Clinical-Trials@grunenthal.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>René Allard</last_name>
    <phone>+49 241 569</phone>
    <phone_ext>3001</phone_ext>
    <email>rene.allard@grunenthal.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BE005</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels</city>
        <zip>1020</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BE008</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels</city>
        <zip>1000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BE004</name>
      <address>
        <city>Verviers</city>
        <zip>4800</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SK004</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bratislava</city>
        <zip>851 07</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SK002</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bratislava</city>
        <zip>833 10</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SK003</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kosice</city>
        <zip>042 66</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SK001</name>
      <address>
        <city>Prešov</city>
        <zip>080 01</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SK005</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pruské</city>
        <zip>018 52</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ES012</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>8022</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GB004</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <zip>LS14 6UH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GB002</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <zip>LS17 6QD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GB003</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <zip>M20 4BX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GB001</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sheffield</city>
        <zip>S10 2JF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Slovakia</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cancer-related pain</keyword>
  <keyword>neuropathic related cancer pain</keyword>
  <keyword>morphine</keyword>
  <keyword>cebranopadol (GRT6005)</keyword>
  <keyword>Numerical Rating Scale</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Morphine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
