<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="31709">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01815918</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11007</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01815918</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Low Dose Corticosteroids on Perioperative Markers of Thrombosis and Fibrinolysis in Total Knee Replacement</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Low Dose Corticosteroids on Perioperative Markers of Thrombosis and Fibrinolysis in Total Knee Replacement</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital for Special Surgery, New York</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital for Special Surgery, New York</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      One postoperative complication following unilateral or bilateral total knee replacement is
      thrombosis (blood clot formation). In this prospective, double-blinded randomized controlled
      clinical trial, researchers are investigating the effect of steroids on biochemical markers
      of thrombosis. Furthermore, elevated cellular markers of thrombosis (specifically IL-6) have
      been linked to postoperative depression following total knee replacement surgery. Hence the
      investigators are also checking if use of hydrocortisone, a steroid, may help reduce the
      incidence of postoperative depression.

      Other studies have shown that surgery causes some reaction in the body that is consistent
      with inflammation.  When the inflammation is extensive, it may affect different parts of the
      body. It may also lead to clotting disorders and result in blood clots. In a previous study
      by this principal investigator (see reference 22, &quot;Use of low-dose steroids in decreasing
      cytokine release during bilateral total knee replacement&quot;), hydrocortisone was administered
      over 24 hours following surgery to patients who underwent bilateral total knee replacements.
      The investigator found lower levels of cellular markers consistent with inflammation
      (specifically the protein, IL-6). Steroid use also showed additional benefits, such as
      decreased pain and better range of motion at the knee.

      In this study, investigators recruit patients undergoing total knee replacement surgery.
      Patients are randomized to receive three 100 mg doses of hydrocortisone or three doses of a
      saline placebo. In addition to analyzing patients' blood samples for hydrocortisone's effect
      on clotting factors (i.e. IL-6), investigators record patients' pain scores and patients'
      oral analgesic use. To assess patients' well-being, patients are contacted one month and 3
      months following their surgeries and administered the Patient Health Questionnaire (see
      reference 23, &quot;The PHQ-9: validity of a brief depression severity measure.&quot;)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacodynamics Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of hydrocortisone on thrombotic activity</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 hours following surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients randomized to receive hydrocortisone will receive three 100 mg doses:
prior to surgery, 8 hours after the first dose and 16 hours after the first dose. Blood samples will be taken to assess hydrocortisone's effect on cellular markers of inflammation and clotting.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hydrocortisone's effect on depression</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 months following surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Elevated IL-6 has been linked to post-operative depression following total knee replacement surgery. Patients will be administered the patient health questionnaire (PHQ-9) one month and 3 months following surgery to assess their well-being.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain scores and opioid consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 months following surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pain scores (rated on a scale of 0-10) will be taken throughout study participation. We will also record analgesic use to see if patients who received hydrocortisone needed fewer pain killers to control their postoperative pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blinding assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 months following surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Throughout each patient's study participation, the patient and the data collector will be asked to guess their treatment status. This helps ascertain if there is an association between blinding status, treatment effect and the depression measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Total Knee Replacement</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive a saline placebo before surgery, 8 hours after the first dose and 16 hours after the first dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive 3 100 mg of hydrocortisone: prior to surgery, 8 hours after the first dose and 16 hours after the first dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydrocortisone</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients randomized to treatment arm will three doses of 100 mg of hydrocortisone at the following times: prior to surgery, 8 hours after the first dose and 16 hours after the first dose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ala-Cort</other_name>
    <other_name>Ala-Scalp HP</other_name>
    <other_name>Anusol HC</other_name>
    <other_name>Aquanil HC</other_name>
    <other_name>Beta HC</other_name>
    <other_name>Cetacort</other_name>
    <other_name>Colocort</other_name>
    <other_name>Corta-Cap</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients receive placebo prior to surgery, 8 hours after the first dose and 16 hours after the first dose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients undergoing unilateral or bilateral total knee replacement

          -  Age 50-90

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients on steroid therapy regardless of dose or duration of  treatment or those
             requiring stress-dose steroids preoperatively

          -  Patients who are smokers

          -  Patients under 50 years of age

          -  Patients over 90 years of age

          -  Patients with diabetes

          -  Patients with a prior history of corticosteroid intolerance

          -  Patients with previous complications of steroid use
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kethy Jules-Elysée, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital for Special Surgery, New York</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital for Special Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.hss.edu/</url>
    <description>This is a link to the Hospital for Special Surgery home page.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boermeester MA, van Leeuwen PA, Coyle SM, Wolbink GJ, Hack CE, Lowry SF. Interleukin-1 blockade attenuates mediator release and dysregulation of the hemostatic mechanism during human sepsis. Arch Surg. 1995 Jul;130(7):739-48.</citation>
    <PMID>7611862</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Busso N, Belin D, Failly-Crépin C, Vassalli JD. Plasminogen activators and their inhibitors in a human mammary cell line (HBL-100). Modulation by glucocorticoids. J Biol Chem. 1986 Jul 15;261(20):9309-15.</citation>
    <PMID>3087993</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Collen D, Hoylaerts MF. Relationship between inflammation and venous thromboembolism as studied by microparticle assessment in plasma. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2005 May 3;45(9):1472-3.</citation>
    <PMID>15862421</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cremeans-Smith JK, Soehlen S, Greene K, Alexander T, Delahanty DL. In-hospital levels of C-reactive protein and IL-6 predict post-operative depressive symptoms among patients undergoing total knee replacement surgery. Brain Behav Immun. 2009 Nov;23(8):1096-103. doi: 10.1016/j.bbi.2009.06.148. Epub 2009 Jun 24.</citation>
    <PMID>19559081</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fox EA, Kahn SR. The relationship between inflammation and venous thrombosis. A systematic review of clinical studies. Thromb Haemost. 2005 Aug;94(2):362-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16113826</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Høgevold HE, Høiseth A, Reikerås O. Effect of high-dose corticosteroids on the incidence of deep vein thrombosis after total hip replacement. Arch Orthop Trauma Surg. 1991;111(1):29-31.</citation>
    <PMID>1722989</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jansen NJ, van Oeveren W, van den Broek L, Oudemans-van Straaten HM, Stoutenbeek CP, Joen MC, Roozendaal KJ, Eysman L, Wildevuur CR. Inhibition by dexamethasone of the reperfusion phenomena in cardiopulmonary bypass. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 1991 Oct;102(4):515-25.</citation>
    <PMID>1656149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levi M, Cromheecke ME, de Jonge E, Prins MH, de Mol BJ, Briët E, Büller HR. Pharmacological strategies to decrease excessive blood loss in cardiac surgery: a meta-analysis of clinically relevant endpoints. Lancet. 1999 Dec 4;354(9194):1940-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10622296</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levi M, van der Poll T. Two-way interactions between inflammation and coagulation. Trends Cardiovasc Med. 2005 Oct;15(7):254-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16226680</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Medcalf RL, Van den Berg E, Schleuning WD. Glucocorticoid-modulated gene expression of tissue- and urinary-type plasminogen activator and plasminogen activator inhibitor 1 and 2. J Cell Biol. 1988 Mar;106(3):971-8.</citation>
    <PMID>3126194</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Medcalf RL, Kruithof EK, Schleuning WD. Plasminogen activator inhibitor 1 and 2 are tumor necrosis factor/cachectin-responsive genes. J Exp Med. 1988 Aug 1;168(2):751-9.</citation>
    <PMID>3137305</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nilsson T, Carlsson J, Sundqvist G. Inactivation of key factors of the plasma proteinase cascade systems by Bacteroides gingivalis. Infect Immun. 1985 Nov;50(2):467-71.</citation>
    <PMID>3902645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parvizi J, Mui A, Purtill JJ, Sharkey PF, Hozack WJ, Rothman RH. Total joint arthroplasty: When do fatal or near-fatal complications occur? J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2007 Jan;89(1):27-32.</citation>
    <PMID>17200306</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pulido L, Ghanem E, Joshi A, Purtill JJ, Parvizi J. Periprosthetic joint infection: the incidence, timing, and predisposing factors. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2008 Jul;466(7):1710-5. doi: 10.1007/s11999-008-0209-4. Epub 2008 Apr 18.</citation>
    <PMID>18421542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reikeras O, Clementsen T. Thrombosis markers in hip versus knee arthroplasty: a pilot study. J Orthop Surg (Hong Kong). 2009 Dec;17(3):291-5.</citation>
    <PMID>20065366</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharrock NE, Go G, Sculco TP, Salvati EA, Westrich GH, Harpel PC. Dose response of intravenous heparin on markers of thrombosis during primary total hip replacement. Anesthesiology. 1999 Apr;90(4):981-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10201667</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van der Poll T, Levi M, Hack CE, ten Cate H, van Deventer SJ, Eerenberg AJ, de Groot ER, Jansen J, Gallati H, Büller HR, et al. Elimination of interleukin 6 attenuates coagulation activation in experimental endotoxemia in chimpanzees. J Exp Med. 1994 Apr 1;179(4):1253-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8145042</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Deventer SJ, Büller HR, ten Cate JW, Aarden LA, Hack CE, Sturk A. Experimental endotoxemia in humans: analysis of cytokine release and coagulation, fibrinolytic, and complement pathways. Blood. 1990 Dec 15;76(12):2520-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2124934</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Giezen JJ, Chung-A-Hing JE, Vegter CB, Bouma BN, Jansen JW. Fibrinolytic activity in blood is distributed over a cellular and the plasma fraction which can be modulated separately. Thromb Haemost. 1994 Dec;72(6):887-92.</citation>
    <PMID>7740459</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Voshaar RC, Banerjee S, Horan M, Baldwin R, Pendleton N, Proctor R, Tarrier N, Woodward Y, Burns A. Predictors of incident depression after hip fracture surgery. Am J Geriatr Psychiatry. 2007 Sep;15(9):807-14. Epub 2007 Aug 13.</citation>
    <PMID>17698601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wagner DD, Burger PC. Platelets in inflammation and thrombosis. Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol. 2003 Dec;23(12):2131-7. Epub 2003 Sep 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14500287</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jules-Elysee KM, Lipnitsky JY, Patel N, Anastasian G, Wilfred SE, Urban MK, Sculco TP. Use of low-dose steroids in decreasing cytokine release during bilateral total knee replacement. Reg Anesth Pain Med. 2011 Jan-Feb;36(1):36-40. doi: 10.1097/AAP.0b013e31820306c5.</citation>
    <PMID>21455087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kroenke K, Spitzer RL, Williams JB. The PHQ-9: validity of a brief depression severity measure. J Gen Intern Med. 2001 Sep;16(9):606-13.</citation>
    <PMID>11556941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital for Special Surgery, New York</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kethy Jules Elysee MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr. Kethy Jules-Elysee</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Orthopedic Procedures</keyword>
  <keyword>Prostheses and Implants</keyword>
  <keyword>Joint Prosthesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Knee Prosthesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Arthroplasty, Replacement, Knee</keyword>
  <keyword>Thromboembolism</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>B-Cell Differentiation Factor-2</keyword>
  <keyword>Differentiation Factor-2, B-Cell</keyword>
  <keyword>B-Cell Stimulatory Factor-2</keyword>
  <keyword>BSF-2</keyword>
  <keyword>IFN-beta 2</keyword>
  <keyword>MGI-2</keyword>
  <keyword>Interleukin-6 (IL-6)</keyword>
  <keyword>Steroids</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnenediones</keyword>
  <keyword>Hydrocortisone</keyword>
  <keyword>Physiological Effects of Drugs</keyword>
  <keyword>Therapeutic Uses</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cortisol succinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone 17-butyrate 21-propionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone-17-butyrate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Physiological Effects of Drugs</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
