<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40119">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01822223</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Bio-LL-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01822223</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Effectiveness of Laser-Ablated Implant-Abutments to Promote Tissue Healing</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Controlled, Double-Blind, Randomized, Parallel-Arm, Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Effectiveness of Laser-Ablated Implant-Abutments for Enhanced Oral Mucosal Healing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>BioHorizons, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama at Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine which implant-abutment design is more likely to
      promote early soft-tissue healing processes and/or will enhance longitudinal peri-implant
      bone and soft-tissue health.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will assess the integrity of the peri-implant oral soft-tissue attachment to
      implant abutments by comparing tissue responses to a laser-ablated implant-abutment and an
      implant-abutment manufactured with a smooth surface.

      Investigators will assess the initial post-surgical peri-implant attachment-seal and will
      test whether or not the tissue-abutment interface re-forms with equal integrity when the
      abutment is removed and replaced with a new abutment.

      Data will include histological, radiographic, clinical, and subjective aesthetics to compare
      the effectiveness of two abutment designs. Both devices are supplied by the BioHorizons
      Implant Systems Inc. of Birmingham, Alabama; the abutments are analogous in design and
      material except the test device has a laser-ablated surface and the control abutment is
      smooth.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proliferation of Perpendicular Connective Tissue Fibers Attached to the Abutment</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks post-abutment placement</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Tissues surrounding the abutment will be harvested via a 2 mm internal-diameter soft-tissue trephine. The tissue will be placed in an appropriately labeled vial containing a fixative; a batched histological assessment, via scanning microscopy, will be performed after tissues have been collected from 100% of participants. Microscopic analysis will categorize the proliferation and nature of peri-abutment soft tissue cells, the orientation of connective tissue fibers (if present), and will identify functionally oriented perpendicular connective tissue fibers formed as an attachment to the abutment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Grams of Force needed to disrupt tissue attachment to the abutment</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks post-abutment placement</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>A  force transducing periodontal probe instrument will electronically capture the  grams of force needed to disrupt the attachment to the implant abutment; tissues will be probed from the gingival margin to the alveolar bone crest at 4 points around each abutment and an adjacent tooth: measurements will be captured from the mesial, buccal, distal, and lingual.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in millimeters of clinical attachment to the abutment</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks, 12 weeks, 16 weeks, 12 months post-abutment placement</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>A periodontal probe will be used to measure the level of clinical attachment to the abutment in millimeters. Measurements will be captured at 4 points around each abutment; mesial, buccal, distal, and lingual.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in millimeters of gingival recession surrounding the abutment</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks, 12 weeks, 16 weeks, 12 months post-abutment placement</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>A periodontal probe will be used to measure the depth of gingival recession surrounding the abutment in millimeters. Measurements will be captured at 4 points around each abutment; mesial, buccal, distal, and lingual.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Millimeters of Osseous Support to the Implant</measure>
    <time_frame>Implant placement, 16 weeks, 12 months post-implant placement</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Radiographs and image-processing software will be used to measure peri-implant linear bone height and to assess bone support over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Jaw, Edentulous, Partially</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Laser-ablated dental implant-abutments</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Laser-ablated dental implant abutments will be attached to surgically placed dental implants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Smooth implant-abutments</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Smooth dental implant-abutments will be attached to surgically placed dental implants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dental implant-abutments</intervention_name>
    <description>At week-8, abutments will be removed and replaced with new Laser-Lok速 abutments. An inter-arm randomization will assign subjects to one of two sub-groups per treatment arm. Sub-groups 1-a &amp; 2-a: will receive a new Laser-Lok速 abutment and a soft-tissue biopsy at week-8; a force-probe clinical attachment assessment of the same site will be delayed until week-16.
Sub-groups 1-b &amp; 2-b: will receive a new Laser-Lok速 abutment and a force-probe clinical attachment assessment at week-8; a biopsy harvested from the same study site will be delayed until week-16.
The implants will be restored following standard technique and a final visit will occur 6 months following permanent restoration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Laser-ablated dental implant-abutments</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Smooth implant-abutments</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BioHorizons' Laser-Lok速 abutment</other_name>
    <other_name>BioHorizons' smooth-surfaced abutment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. At least 19 years old

          2. Healthy enough to under go treatment

          3. Have one or more edentulous sites that exhibit adequate natural bone and sufficient
             keratinized tissue

          4. Demonstrated willingness to undergo study treatment and to comply with study timeline
             -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Full edentulism

          2. Any chronic health condition or medication that in the opinion of the investigators
             may adversely affect bone healing

          3. Any indication of an inability to make autonomous decisions

             -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael S Reddy, DMD, DMSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama at Birmingham School of Dentistry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294-0007</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 10, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 27, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dental Implants</keyword>
  <keyword>Implant abutments</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Jaw, Edentulous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Jaw, Edentulous, Partially</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mouth, Edentulous</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
