<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="85842">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02135250</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013022</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02135250</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study on Therapeutic Effect of Treating Mental Stress Induced Myocardial Ischemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study on Therapeutic Effect of Treating Mental Stress Induced Myocardial Ischemia With Conventional Therapy for Coronary Heart Disease Combined With Traditional Chinese Medicine :Design and Methods</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Meiyan Liu</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Beijing Anzhen Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to discuss whether the combined treatment of traditional Chinese medicine
      (TCM) and western medicine for Mental Stress Induced Myocardial Ischemia (MSIMI) does
      effect, namely the conventional therapy for Coronary Heart Disease( CHD) combining with TCM
      - Xinkeshu tablets.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A large number of evidence-based medical researches have proven that bad mood and mental
      stress are related to poor prognosis. Having recognized that acute emotional stress can
      induce cardiovascular events, many clinical tests of mental stress have been carried out to
      observe the correlation between emotional stress and cardiac damage, which ultimately lead
      to the formalization of the concept of Mental Stress Induced Myocardial Ischemia(MSIMI). In
      the past 3 decades, it has been evidenced that mental stress is internally related to
      myocardial ischemia. According to current studies, over 70% patients with stable coronary
      heart disease have MSIMI and are exposed to three or four times higher risk of
      cardiovascular events. However, few articles are about the therapeutic effect of MSIMI
      treatment. This study aims to discuss whether the combined treatment of traditional Chinese
      medicine (TCM) and western medicine for MSIMI does effect, namely the conventional therapy
      for CHD combining with TCM - Xinkeshu tablets.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treadmill exercise test</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The Cox proportional hazards model is used to evaluate the effect of treatment on the composite endpoint of death or first cardiac-related hospitalization. Patients who have not experienced an event by the end of the follow-up period will be coded as censored at the time of last contact.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Therapy of Chinese Traditional Herbal Medicine</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>the placebo is not drug</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Xinkeshu tablet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>4 Xinkeshu tablets are given three times per day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Xinkeshu tablets</intervention_name>
    <description>4 Xinkeshu tablets are given three times per day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Xinkeshu tablet</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Xinkeshu tablets</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>the placebo is not drug.</description>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  above 18 years old,

          -  having coronary stenosis (&gt; 70%) measured by coronary arteriography,

          -  with medical  history of myocardial infarction or revascularization     procedures,

          -  or with sufficient proof for having CHD.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Recent myocardial infarction, coronary artery bypass graft surgery, or other
             revascularization procedures (≤ 3 months)

          -  left ventricular ejection fraction(LVEF) &lt; 30% measured by echocardiography,
             radionuclide ventriculography, or cardiac catheterization

          -  Life threatening arrhythmia or arrhythmia interrupting the interpretation of ischemia

          -  Unable to withdraw from anti-anginal medications during ischemic assessment phase

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Current or previous history of bipolar disorder, cyclothymia, schizophrenia,
             schizoaffective or schizophreniform disorder, or other psychotic disorders Active
             suicidal ideation

          -  Current substance abuse or history of substance abuse in the previous 6 months

          -  Significant cardiac, pulmonary, metabolic, renal, hepatic disease, or malignancy,
             interfering with subject's participation in this study Seizure (history and/or
             present) with/without treatment

          -  Currently taking antidepressants that cannot be discontinued
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anzhen Beijing</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Capital Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Liu Meiyan</last_name>
    <phone>13001241364</phone>
    <phone_ext>86</phone_ext>
    <email>zhanglijun0411@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beijing Anzhen Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100029</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Liu Meiyan</last_name>
      <phone>13001241364</phone>
      <phone_ext>86</phone_ext>
      <email>zhanglijun0411@126.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Liu Meiyan</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burg MM, Jain D, Soufer R, Kerns RD, Zaret BL. Role of behavioral and psychological factors in mental stress-induced silent left ventricular dysfunction in coronary artery disease. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1993 Aug;22(2):440-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8335813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rozanski A, Bairey CN, Krantz DS, Friedman J, Resser KJ, Morell M, Hilton-Chalfen S, Hestrin L, Bietendorf J, Berman DS. Mental stress and the induction of silent myocardial ischemia in patients with coronary artery disease. N Engl J Med. 1988 Apr 21;318(16):1005-12.</citation>
    <PMID>3352695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ironson G, Taylor CB, Boltwood M, Bartzokis T, Dennis C, Chesney M, Spitzer S, Segall GM. Effects of anger on left ventricular ejection fraction in coronary artery disease. Am J Cardiol. 1992 Aug 1;70(3):281-5.</citation>
    <PMID>1632389</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldberg AD, Becker LC, Bonsall R, Cohen JD, Ketterer MW, Kaufman PG, Krantz DS, Light KC, McMahon RP, Noreuil T, Pepine CJ, Raczynski J, Stone PH, Strother D, Taylor H, Sheps DS. Ischemic, hemodynamic, and neurohormonal responses to mental and exercise stress. Experience from the Psychophysiological Investigations of Myocardial Ischemia Study (PIMI). Circulation. 1996 Nov 15;94(10):2402-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8921780</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deanfield JE, Shea M, Kensett M, Horlock P, Wilson RA, de Landsheere CM, Selwyn AP. Silent myocardial ischaemia due to mental stress. Lancet. 1984 Nov 3;2(8410):1001-5.</citation>
    <PMID>6149394</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giubbini R, Galli M, Campini R, Bosimini E, Bencivelli W, Tavazzi L. Effects of mental stress on myocardial perfusion in patients with ischemic heart disease. Circulation. 1991 Apr;83(4 Suppl):II100-7.</citation>
    <PMID>1826235</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rozanski A, Blumenthal JA, Kaplan J. Impact of psychological factors on the pathogenesis of cardiovascular disease and implications for therapy. Circulation. 1999 Apr 27;99(16):2192-217. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10217662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carpeggiani C, Skinner JE. Coronary flow and mental stress. Experimental findings. Circulation. 1991 Apr;83(4 Suppl):II90-3.</citation>
    <PMID>2009633</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Soufer R, Bremner JD, Arrighi JA, Cohen I, Zaret BL, Burg MM, Goldman-Rakic P. Cerebral cortical hyperactivation in response to mental stress in patients with coronary artery disease. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1998 May 26;95(11):6454-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9600987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 6, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Beijing Anzhen Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Meiyan Liu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Traditional Chinese Medicine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress, Psychological</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
