<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="141275">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01955083</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>hyli38</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01955083</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Analysis of Snore Sound Following Minimal Invasive Surgery in Sleep-disordered Breathing Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Analysis of Snore Sound Following Minimal Invasive Surgery in Sleep-disordered Breathing Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Science Council, Taiwan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Taiwan: Department of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      1. Background：The methods of anti-snore (treatment of snoring ) can be divided into
           conservative, invasive and minimal invasive treatment. IN brief, minimal invasive
           surgery involving radiofrequency and pillar implant demonstrates significantly
           improvement of snoring without major complication. Previous studies usually evaluated
           snoring through subjective measures such as visual analog scale visual analog scale.
           Rare reports analyzed snore sound instrumentally and no report demonstrates the
           correlation between subjective perception and objective assessment of snoring before
           and after surgical intervention.

        2. Purposes：

             1. Development of snore sound spectrum.

             2. Exploration of the correlation between subjective perception and objective
                assessment of snoring.

             3. Comparison of changes in snoring before and after minimal invasive surgery and
                between two kinds of MIS to have a understanding of surgical impact in subjective
                and objective measurement.

        3. Method：We plan to enroll 30 subjects diagnosed by polysomnography as simple snoring or
           mild OSA with major complaint of snoring and favorable anatomic structure for minimal
           invasive surgery. All eligible subjects will be instructed the purpose, process and all
           related rights of this study and sign inform consent in outpatient clinic. Subjects
           start to complete Snore Outcome Survey (SOS, a validated questionnaire) and visual
           analog sure of snoring (VAS). Objective overnight snore sound recoding is arranged in
           sleep center. Subjects then receive minimal invasive surgery：radiofrequency or pillar
           implant of the soft palate by randomization. Both radiofrequency and pillar implant are
           common techniques in treating snoring and performed under local anesthesia as an
           outpatient procedure on sitting position. All subjects received repeated snore sound
           recording and completion of SOS and VAS three months after MIS.

        4. Outcomes

             1. Development of snore sound spectrum in sleep-disorder breathing patients.

             2. Correlation of parameters between snore sound recording (loudness, frequency,
                count, regularity, etc ) and clinical parameters.

             3. Correlation between objective (snore sound analysis) and subjective (SOS,VAS)
                assessment of snoring.

             4. Comparison of changes in snoring (particular in objective assessment) after
                radiofrequency or pillar implant.

             5. Comparison of changes in snoring between radiofrequency and pillar implant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recent publications have demonstrated reductions in snoring with several minimal invasive
      surgery (MIS) methods of the soft palate including radiofrequency (RF) surgery and pillar
      implant (PI). Despite modest effects in the treatment of obstructive sleep apnea, patients
      often wish to receive MIS for habitual snoring. However, the efficacy in reducing snoring
      has mainly been determined by self-reported questionnaires in the past. Further, the
      definition of surgical success in snoring treatment has not been universally defined. To
      date, changes in snoring sound characteristics following MIS have not been demonstrated.

      Many cohort studies and a few randomized controlled trials or clinical controlled trials
      have compared MIS with a placebo, different energy generators, different material rigidity,
      or different operative techniques. RF of the soft palate produces volumetric tissue
      reduction and selective scar tissue5 to reduce obstruction and induce stiffness. However,
      the RF energy delivered to the soft palate can be inadequate and may result in residual or
      recurrent snoring. PI can decrease palatal flutter by increasing the rigidity of the soft
      palate through implant identity and tissue fibrosis. In addition, PI can be chronically
      retained in the muscle layer of the soft palate thereby producing a long-term anti-snoring
      effect. Nevertheless, whether PI provides a better efficacy in the treatment of snoring than
      RF surgery is still unknown.

      The primary aim of the current study was to compare the anti-snoring effect between PI and
      RF by subjective assessments in a randomized controlled parallel trial. The secondary aim
      was to explore and compare the acoustic changes in snoring sounds after PI and RF.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Snore sound analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>August 2010~July 2012</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Snore Outcome Survey (SOS) , Visual analog scale (VAS), acoustic characteristics of snoring sound</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Snoring</condition>
  <condition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pillar implant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 1- Pillar implant (Study group):
15 subjects undergo pillar implant surgery of the soft palate for the treatment of snoring.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Radiofrequency</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 2- Radiofrequency (control group):
15 subjects undergo radiofreeuncy of the soft palate for the treatment of snoring.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pillar implant</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects receive pillar implant of the soft palate under local anesthesia as an outpatient procedure on sitting position. Using the delivery tool of the PI system, the mucosa of the soft palate close to the hard palate-soft palate junction (approximate 0.5 cm) was punctured in the midline. The needle was inserted to the uvular muscle and moved parallel to the curve of the soft palate towards the tip of the uvula. After reaching the insertion point, the implant was delivered steadily after which the needle was withdrawn. This process was repeated for the second and third implants in the bilateral para-midline with a 0.2 cm horizontal distance from the first implant.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pillar implant</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Pillar implant (Medtronic Inc., USA)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiofrequency</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects receive radiofrequency under local anesthesia as an outpatient procedure on sitting position. RF energy was delivered via a generator (Somnus® Model S2, Gyrus-ACMI Corporation, Maple Grove, MN, USA) with the power set to 10 watts and the maximal target temperature to 85°C. The needle electrode was inserted through the mucosa into the muscle layer at the entry points (approximately 1 cm below the hard palate-soft palate junction). The electrode was kept in place until 600 J had been delivered at the midline and 300 J at both para-midline sites (approximately 1 cm horizontal distance).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Radiofrequency</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Somnus® Model S2 (Gyrus-ACMI Corporation, USA)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. simple snoring or mild obstructive sleep apnea

          2. major complaint of snoring

          3. favorable anatomic structure for minimal invasive surgery.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. moderate or severe obstructive sleep apnea

          2. pathological obesity

          3. significant craniofacial anomaly

          4. elderly

          5. unfavorable anatomic structure for minimal invasive surgery.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hsueh Yu Li, professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kweishan</city>
        <state>Taoyuan</state>
        <zip>333</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cgmh.org.tw/</url>
    <description>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital at Linkou is a tertiary medical center in Taiwan (R.O.C.).</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2010</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 27, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 29, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Obstructive sleep apnea</keyword>
  <keyword>snoring</keyword>
  <keyword>radiofrequency</keyword>
  <keyword>pillar implant</keyword>
  <keyword>snore sound analysis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Snoring</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
