<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="94233">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02092155</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00086126</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02092155</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The BLAST Trial- Biomarker Levels During Indwelling Pleural cAtheter Sample Testing</brief_title>
  <acronym>BLAST</acronym>
  <official_title>Biomarker Levels During Indwelling Pleural Catheter Sample</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Some patients that have a tunneled pleural catheter will not have the pleural fluid (water
      around the lung) return after some time (pleurodesis). The purpose of this study is to
      understand how the investigators can predict who will achieve pleurodesis and how this
      occurs by studying the pleural effusion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      An alternative and emerging treatment for malignant pleural effusions is the placement of a
      chronic indwelling pleural catheter such as the Rocket® catheter.  The Rocket® catheter is a
      16 French, 66 cm long, silicone catheter with side holes along its distal 24 cm.  The
      proximal shaft has a polyester cuff designed to promote fibrosis in the subcutaneous tissue
      into which it is tunneled.  This prevents dislodgement of the catheter and minimizes the
      risk of infection.  The proximal end contains a self-sealing valve designed to enhance the
      safety of the catheter.  The self-sealing valve prevents entry of air into the pleural space
      and inadvertent leakage of pleural fluid unless the catheter is accessed with the matched
      drainage line.   The matched drainage line is connected to a 600 milliliter vacuum bottle.
      Pleural fluid is removed by inserting the access tip of the drainage line into the
      self-sealing valve of the Rocket® catheter, allowing vacuum drainage of the pleural space.

      As discussed above, tunneled pleural catheters (TPC) are ideal for treatment of MPE
      associated with a trapped or non-expandable lung which will not have sufficient visceral and
      parietal pleura apposition for chemical pleurodesis.  Transforming growth factor-Beta 1
      (TGF-β) is a profibrotic cytokine, and a potent inducer of Plasminogen activator inhibitor-1
      (PAI-1) in human pleural mesothelial cells. PAI-1 inhibits protease-dependent fibrinolytic
      activity and along with TGF-β, its concentration is increased in exudative and tuberculous
      pleural effusion. TGF-β levels in pleural fluid have been shown to correlate with pleural
      thickness in tuberculosis pleurisy and empyema in rabbits.

      TGF-β is a multifunctional cytokine primarily produced by mesothelial cells in the pleural
      space, but can also originate from lung parenchymal macrophages that migrate to the pleural
      space. In humans, TGF-β consists of three isoforms (TGF-β1, TGF-β2, and TGF-β3). They share
      many biological activities and their actions on cells are qualitatively similar in most
      cases.  TGF-β stimulates the extracellular matrix production and studies support that TGF-β
      over-production is a key regulator in pleural fibrosis and chemical pleurodesis. Moreover,
      TGF-β signaling for the production of PAI-1 is clearly noted in human mesothelial cells of
      different origins. Different inflammatory stimuli in the pleural space including malignancy
      and infection may activate TGF-β up-regulation and enhanced production which in turns
      results in PAI-1 expression.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the median time to pleurodesis</measure>
    <time_frame>12 week follow up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Duration of follow-up will be 12 weeks.  After 12 weeks, all patients who do not achieve spontaneous pleurodesis will adhere to the standard drainage protocol.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TGF-B levels over time</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the threshold TGF-B level to determine accuracy of predicting auto-pleurodesis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">95</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Pleural Effusions</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Indwelling tunneled pleural catheter</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TGF-β  markers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rocket Indwelling Pleural Catheter</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Indwelling tunneled pleural catheter</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Pleural effusion (etiology fulfilling one of the following criteria):

               1. Malignant effusion confirmed by cytology or pleural biopsy

               2. exudative effusion in the setting of known malignancy with no other identifiable
                  cause

               3. Malignant effusion due to tumors that are historically rapidly responsive to
                  systemic therapy (small cell lung cancer, hematological malignancies) will only
                  be included if refractory to standard chemotherapy

          -  18 years of age

          -  Symptoms such as shortness of breath, cough, or chest fullness/chest discomfort

          -  Demonstration of symptomatic improvement after therapeutic thoracentesis

          -  Recurrent pleural effusion after therapeutic thoracentesis

          -  Capacity to provide informed consent

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Projected life expectancy less than 30 days.

          -  Radiographic evidence of trapped lung - persistent lung collapse with failure of the
             majority (&gt;50%) of the lung to reexpand following drainage of a pleural effusion

          -  Previous lobectomy or pneumonectomy on the affected side

          -  Patient receiving intrapleural chemotherapy

          -  Chylothorax - pleural effusion with triglyceride levels &gt; 110 mg/dl or chylomicrons
             on lipoprotein analysis, most commonly due to trauma/obstruction of the thoracic duct

          -  Parapneumonic effusion - pleural effusion associated with pneumonia

          -  Empyema - infected pleural space as defined by purulent pleural fluid, positive gram
             stain, or positive culture

          -  Inability to adequately perform pleural drainage at home

          -  Uncorrectable bleeding disorder

          -  Skin infection at the site of intended catheter insertion

          -  Pregnant women - detected by spot urine testing prior to the procedure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lonny Yarmus, DO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karen Oakjones-Burgess</last_name>
    <phone>410-955-5288</phone>
    <email>kfriel2@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ricardo Ortiz</last_name>
    <phone>410-955-5288</phone>
    <email>rortiz7@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen Oakjones-Burgess</last_name>
      <phone>410-955-5288</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 19, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 17, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lonny Yarmus</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pleural Effusion</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pleural Effusion, Malignant</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
