<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="36841">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01935921</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2013-00807</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00807</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UPCI 12-084</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9196</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA047904</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01935921</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ipilimumab, Cetuximab, and Intensity-Modulated Radiation Therapy in Treating Patients With Previously Untreated Stage III-IVB Head and Neck Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase Ib Trial of Concurrent Cetuximab (ERBITUX®) and Intensity Modulated Radiotherapy (IMRT) With Ipilimumab (YERVOY®) in Locally Advanced Head and Neck Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and best dose of ipilimumab when given together
      with cetuximab and intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) in treating patients with
      previously untreated stage III-IVB head and neck cancer. Monoclonal antibodies, such as
      ipilimumab and cetuximab, can block tumor growth in different ways. Some block the ability
      of tumors to grow and spread. Others find tumor cells and help kill them or carry
      tumor-killing substances to them. Specialized radiation therapy, such as IMRT, that delivers
      a high dose of radiation directly to the tumor may kill more tumor cells and cause less
      damage to normal tissue. Giving ipilimumab together with cetuximab and IMRT may kill more
      tumor cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To identify the starting dose of ipilimumab, in combination with standard cetuximab-IMRT
      in patients with high- or intermediate-risk, locally advanced head and neck squamous cell
      carcinoma (HNSCC), for use in a future clinical efficacy trial.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To estimate the clinical response of patients with high- or intermediate-risk, locally
      advanced HNSCC treated with above regimen using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors
      (RECIST) 1.1 criteria.

      II. To estimate the 2-year progression-free survival of patients with high- or
      intermediate-risk, locally advanced HNSCC treated with the above regimen.

      III. To investigate serum, lymphocyte and tissue biomarkers as predictors of
      progression-free survival, toxicity and other outcome parameters in patients with high- or
      intermediate-risk, locally advanced HNSCC treated with above regimen.

      IV. To estimate the association by dose-response modeling between dose of Ipilimumab,
      clinical response and biomarkers.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of ipilimumab.

      Patients receive cetuximab intravenously (IV) over 60-120 minutes on days 1, 8, 15, and 22.
      Treatment with cetuximab repeats every 4 weeks for 2 courses. Beginning in week 2 of course
      1, patients undergo concurrent IMRT 5 days per week for 7 weeks. Beginning in week 4 (day 1
      of course 2) patients also receive ipilimumab IV over 90 minutes once every 21 days for 3
      courses. Treatment continues in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
      Patients achieving disease progression may undergo surgery after completion of therapy.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 12 weeks for 1 year,
      every 6 months for 1 year, and then every 12 months for 3 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of dose limiting toxicities (DLTs) at each dose level assessed using National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical response by RECIST criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be analyzed by generalized linear models with dose-response analysis using logistic regression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be analyzed by generalized linear models.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T cell phenotypes</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T regulatory and myeloid-derived suppressor cell (MDSC) cell counts</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HPV status</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum factors and tumor infiltrates</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Hypopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Verrucous Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Hypopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Verrucous Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Verrucous Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cetuximab, IMRT, and ipilimumab)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive cetuximab IV over 60-120 minutes on days 1, 8, 15, and 22. Treatment with cetuximab repeats every 4 weeks for 2 courses. Beginning in week 2 of course 1, patients undergo concurrent IMRT 5 days per week for 7 weeks. Beginning in week 4 (day 1 of course 2) patients also receive ipilimumab IV over 90 minutes once every 21 days for 3 courses. Treatment continues in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients achieving disease progression may undergo surgery after completion of therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cetuximab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cetuximab, IMRT, and ipilimumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>C225</other_name>
    <other_name>C225 monoclonal antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>IMC-C225</other_name>
    <other_name>MOAB C225</other_name>
    <other_name>monoclonal antibody C225</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>intensity-modulated radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo IMRT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cetuximab, IMRT, and ipilimumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IMRT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ipilimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cetuximab, IMRT, and ipilimumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>anti-cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated antigen-4 monoclonal antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX-010</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX-CTLA-4</other_name>
    <other_name>monoclonal antibody CTLA-4</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cetuximab, IMRT, and ipilimumab)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC) stage III/IVB, excluding T1N1,
             histologically or cytologically confirmed squamous cell carcinoma or undifferentiated
             carcinoma of the head and neck; patients should not have distant metastasis; primary
             sites include: oropharynx, hypopharynx, larynx

          -  Patients must have high or intermediate risk disease, defined as follows:

               -  High risk: non-oropharyngeal subsite including larynx or hypopharynx (p16 status
                  not required) or human papilloma virus (HPV)/p16- oropharynx subsite

               -  Intermediate risk: HPV/p16+ oropharyngeal squamous cell cancer with: &gt;= 10 pk-yr
                  smoking history and &gt;= N2 nodal disease, or the presence of T4 tumor or N3 nodal
                  disease, irrespective of smoking status

          -  Patients must have measurable disease, defined as at least one lesion that can be
             accurately measured in at least one dimension (longest diameter to be recorded for
             non-nodal lesions and short axis for nodal lesions) as &gt;= 20 mm with conventional
             techniques or as &gt;= 10 mm with spiral computed tomography (CT) scan, magnetic
             resonance imaging (MRI), or calipers by clinical exam

          -  Patients should be newly diagnosed HNSCC, with no prior therapy for this disease

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status typically =&lt; 1
             (Karnofsky &gt;= 70%)

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3,000/mcL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,200/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 75,000/mcL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 2 mg/dL (=&lt; 3 mg/dL in case of Gilbert's syndrome)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 2 times institutional upper limit of normal (IULN)

          -  Creatinine clearance &gt;= 40 mL/min/1.73 m^2

          -  Patients must have the ability to understand and to sign written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had prior chemotherapy, radiotherapy, or surgery with curative
             intent for HNSCC

          -  Patients with a history of prior treatment with ipilimumab, anti-programmed cell
             death 1 (PD 1) antibody, cluster of differentiation 137 (CD137) agonist or other
             immune activating therapy such as anti-cluster of differentiation 40 (CD 40) antibody

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Autoimmune disease: patients with a history of inflammatory bowel disease, including
             ulcerative colitis and Crohn's disease, are excluded from this study, as are patients
             with a history of symptomatic non-gastrointestinal autoimmune disease (e.g.,
             rheumatoid arthritis, systemic progressive sclerosis [scleroderma], systemic lupus
             erythematosus, autoimmune vasculitis [e.g., Wegener's Granulomatosis]); central
             nervous system (CNS) or motor neuropathy considered of autoimmune origin (e.g.
             Guillain-Barre syndrome and Myasthenia Gravis, multiple sclerosis)

          -  Patients with known immunodeficiency disorder, or presumed to be unable to respond to
             anti-cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated protein 4 (CTLA 4) monoclonal antibody (mAb)

          -  Patients with distant metastatic disease (stage IVC)

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to cetuximab or ipilimumab

          -  Patient is &lt; 2 years free from a second primary malignancy unless the other
             malignancy is non-melanomatous skin cancer or an in-situ tumor treated with curative
             intent

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements; patients with chronic hepatitis B or hepatitis C infections are
             excluded

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-positive patients on combination antiretroviral
             therapy are ineligible
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Ferris</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert L. Ferris</last_name>
      <phone>412-623-0327</phone>
      <email>ferrisrl@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert L. Ferris</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 3, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Laryngeal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Verrucous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypopharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Laryngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oropharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cytotoxic T-lymphocyte antigen 4</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cetuximab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
