<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="15100">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02094508</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999914073</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-I-N073</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02094508</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of TMP-SMX Prophylaxis on Malaria Infection and Immunity in Children in Uganda</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole Prophylaxis on Malaria Infection and Immunity in Children in Uganda</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Malaria is a disease that affects many children and adults in Uganda and Africa. If it is
      not treated, it can make some people severely ill. TMP-SMX (Trade names Bactrim, Septrin) is
      a drug that is given to children born to HIV-positive mothers to help prevent infection.
      Studies have shown that TMP-SMX also may kill malaria infection in the very early stages of
      infection in the body, which may positively impact the way the body can fight malaria
      infection. Researchers want to know if giving TMP-SMX for 6 months longer than usual helps
      children fight malaria better in this way.

      Objective:

      - To find out if taking TMP-SMX for longer than usual helps fight off malaria in infants.

      Eligibility:

      - Infants 0-6 weeks of age who are HIV negative.

      Design:

        -  Infants will be screened with a medical history and physical exam. A small amount of
           blood will be taken. The mothers    medical records will be reviewed. Mothers will be
           asked about when they breastfeed.

        -  Participants will take TMP-SMX according to their doctor   s orders. In Uganda, mothers
           will get a mosquito net with insecticide on it as per standard of care.

        -  Participants will come to the clinic once a month, every month, until the study ends in
           2   3 years. Each visit will repeat the screening visit.

        -  Participants will also visit the clinic every month for a medical history, physical
           exam, and different blood tests.

        -  Six weeks after breastfeeding is stopped, children taking TMP-SMX will come into the
           clinic and will either be taken off the drug or will continue taking the drug for 6
           more months.

        -  If a child becomes sick, it is important that the mother bring him or her to the RHSP
           clinic in Rakai.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Malaria remains one of the most significant causes of morbidity and mortality throughout the
      world. Recent studies indicate that drugs used in HIV management can have antimalarial
      properties. In animal models, prophylactic doses of trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole (TMPSMX),
      an antibiotic commonly used as prophylaxis against opportunistic infections in HIVexposed
      and HIV-infected patients, have been shown to arrest liver stage development of malaria
      parasites. Indeed, the liver stage of malaria parasites may be important to target since it
      is during this stage that clinical symptoms are absent and fewer parasites are present.
      TMP-SMX, used in HIV-exposed and HIV-infected subjects for opportunistic infection
      prophylaxis, significantly reduces clinical malaria, even in areas of moderate to high
      transmission intensity and high antifolate drug resistance. It is possible that reduction in
      liver stage parasite burden contributes to this unexpected effect. Nonetheless, the
      contribution of this liver-stage parasite killing to the reduction in clinical malaria
      observed in patients receiving TMP-SMX remains undescribed. Our primary objective aims to
      answer whether TMP-SMX reduces liver stage malaria infection.

      For our exploratory objectives, we are interested in TMP-SMX effects on the development of
      anti-infection malaria immunity and effects on transmission. In mice, TMP-SMX prophylaxis
      during repeated malaria exposures has been shown to induce protective, anti-infection
      immunity against malaria (Charlotte Hobbs, unpublished data), which is distinct from
      naturally acquired immunity in which, after multiple infections, patients have less severe
      disease. TMP-SMX impact on the development of malaria-specific immunity, however, requires
      further investigation. Also, TMP-SMX has been shown to have sporonticidal (mosquito-oocyst
      killing) activity at levels achieved in patients on TMP-SMX prophylaxis in susceptible
      strains of P. falciparum, but the effects of TMP-SMX on transmission in the field remain
      undescribed.

      This randomized study plans to enroll 164-220 HIV-uninfected, HIV-exposed (HUE) and 60
      HIV-uninfected, HIV-unexposed (HUU) children in Kalisizo Hospital Health Center, Labor and
      Delivery Unit, Kalisizo, located within Rakai District, Uganda. HUE children will be
      randomized 1:1 into 2 arms. In the first arm (Standard of Care [SOC] arm), 82-110 children
      will receive TMP-SMX until 6 weeks after cessation of breast-feeding (age 12-18 months). In
      the second arm (Extended Prophylaxis [EP] arm), 82-110 children will receive SOC and remain
      on TMP-SMX for an additional 6 months after the cessation of breast-feeding. The 60 HUU
      children will serve as controls to establish baseline infection parameters in the community.
      Blood will be drawn from all subjects monthly via heel/finger stick to analyze malaria
      parasitemia.  Additionally, venous blood will be drawn every 6 months to analyze cellular
      and humoral immunity. The duration of this study participation will be a minimum of 2 and up
      to 3 years.

      Assessment of TMP-SMX impact on liver stage malaria infection and the development of
      protective anti-infection immunity in children will help guide decisions regarding TMP-SMX
      prophylaxis duration for HIV-exposed children in malaria endemic areas.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary outcome is to measure the incidence rate (number of new malaria parasitemia episodes) in HUE children on SOC versus EP TMP-SMX prophylaxs.</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMP-SMX</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Infant must be 0-6 weeks of age.

               2. Parent/legal guardian must be able and willing to provide signed informed
                  consent on behalf of the child subject, agree to bring the child to the study
                  site for visits, and seek medical care for intercurrent illness for the child
                  subject at the study site.

               3. Parent/legal guardian of HUE subjects must agree to be compliant with
                  administering the daily prophylactic doses of TMP- SMX according to the schedule
                  provided by the study team.

               4. Mothers must consent to a review of their medical records and a monthly
                  assessment of breast-feeding status.

               5. Mother/guardian must live within 15 km of the Kaliziso District Hospital.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Child has a diagnosis of HIV-infection or clinical or laboratory evidence of other
             chronic infection or disease (including renal or hepatic insufficiency).

          2. Other condition that in the opinion of the investigator would jeopardize the safety
             or rights of a subject participating in the study or would render the subject unable
             to comply with the protocol.

          3. Other than the study described above in Subject Recruitment and Enrollment (Study
             #13-I-N074), study subjects should not participate in a malaria vaccine study or have
             a history of involvement in such a study.

          4. Contraindication to TMP-SMX (HUE subjects only) that in the judgment of the
             investigator contraindicates participation in this study including:

               1. Documented megaloblastic anemia due to folate deficiency.

               2. Hyperbilirubinemia

               3. Marked hepatic damage

               4. Renal insufficiency
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Weeks</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charlotte V Hobbs, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Charlotte V Hobbs, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-4236</phone>
    <email>hobbsc3@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rakai Health Sciences Program Clinic (RHSP)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rakai</city>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Uganda</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu Y, Ellis RD, Shaffer D, Fontes E, Malkin EM, Mahanty S, Fay MP, Narum D, Rausch K, Miles AP, Aebig J, Orcutt A, Muratova O, Song G, Lambert L, Zhu D, Miura K, Long C, Saul A, Miller LH, Durbin AP. Phase 1 trial of malaria transmission blocking vaccine candidates Pfs25 and Pvs25 formulated with montanide ISA 51. PLoS ONE. 2008 Jul 9;3(7):e2636.</citation>
    <PMID>18612426</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Achan J, Kakuru A, Ikilezi G, Ruel T, Clark TD, Nsanzabana C, Charlebois E, Aweeka F, Dorsey G, Rosenthal PJ, Havlir D, Kamya MR. Antiretroviral agents and prevention of malaria in HIV-infected Ugandan children. N Engl J Med. 2012 Nov 29;367(22):2110-8. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1200501.</citation>
    <PMID>23190222</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hobbs CV, Voza T, Coppi A, Kirmse B, Marsh K, Borkowsky W, Sinnis P. HIV protease inhibitors inhibit the development of preerythrocytic-stage plasmodium parasites. J Infect Dis. 2009 Jan 1;199(1):134-41. doi: 10.1086/594369.</citation>
    <PMID>19032102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 20, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parasitemia</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV-Exposed</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV-Unexposed</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver Stage</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Trimethoprim-Sulfamethoxazole Combination</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
