<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="26835">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01961115</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CITN-04</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-01605</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CITN-04</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CITN-04</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U01CA154967</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01961115</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>INCB024360 and Vaccine Therapy in Treating Patients With Stage III-IV Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Pilot Trial of an Indoleamine 2,3, Dioxygenase-1 (IDO1) Inhibitor (INCB024360) Plus a Multipeptide Melanoma Vaccine (MELITAC 12.1) in Patients With Advanced Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Incyte Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Virginia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot phase II trial studies how well INCB024360 (indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase 1 [IDO1]
      inhibitor INCB024360) and vaccine therapy work in treating patients with stage III-IV
      melanoma. IDO1 inhibitor INCB024360 may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of
      the enzymes needed for cell growth. Vaccines made from peptides and antigens may help the
      body build an effective immune response to kill tumor cells. Giving IDO1 inhibitor
      INCB024360 with vaccine therapy may be an effective treatment for advanced melanoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the extent to which a regimen of INCB024360 that normalizes serum kynurenine
      (Kyn)/ tryptophan (Trp) ratios alters the tumor microenvironment of melanoma, including
      determining the number and character of tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes as determined by
      examination of serial biopsies with immunohistochemistry (IHC) and gene signatures.

      II. To determine the extent to which continued INCB024360 treatment plus the addition of the
      multipeptide melanoma vaccine, MELITAC 12.1 (MELITAC 12.1 peptide vaccine), further alters
      the tumor microenvironment of melanoma, including determining the number and character of
      tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes as determined by serial biopsies evaluating IHC and gene
      signatures.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine whether a regimen of INCB024360 that normalizes serum Kyn/Trp ratios plus
      MELITAC 12.1 vaccine changes the level or character of the vaccine-induced clusters of
      differentiation (CD) 8+ and CD4+ T-cell immune responses as measured in peripheral blood, as
      compared to prior published experience.

      II. To evaluate the extent to which INCB024360 plus MELITAC 12.1 vaccine alters the number
      and character of peripheral blood mononuclear cell (PBMC) populations, including T and
      natural killer (NK) cells, as evaluated by multiparameter flow cytometry.

      III. To evaluate the extent to which INCB024360 plus MELITAC 12.1 vaccine alters the PBMC
      transcriptome.

      IV. To assess the safety and tolerability of INCB024360 plus MELITAC 12.1 vaccine.

      V. To obtain preliminary data on the tumor response rate of INCB024360 plus MELITAC 12.1
      vaccine by objective response rate (ORR), time to tumor progression, and overall survival.

      VI. To associate any observed changes with the expression of IDO1 protein by IHC in tumor or
      tumor-infiltrating cells.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive IDO1 inhibitor INCB024360 orally (PO) twice daily (BID) on days 1-98 and
      receive MELITAC 12.1 peptide vaccine intradermally (ID)/subcutaneously (SC) on days 21, 28,
      35, 56, 77, and 98 in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 1 year.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the concentration and number of CD8+ cells infiltrating tumor by IHC</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the level or character of the vaccine-induced CD8+ and CD4+ specific T-cell immune responses by IFN-gamma ELISPOT</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessment of immunologic response will be based on a fold-increase measure from baseline as well as using a positivity threshold.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the number and character of PBMC populations, including T and NK cells, as evaluated by multiparameter flow cytometry</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PBMC transcriptome</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Analysis of PBMC gene signature. This may be compared to immunologic response, tumor biopsy data and clinical response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events using the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate using the Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) or Immune-Related Response Criteria (irRC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to tumor progression using RECIST or irRC</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time measurement criteria are met for complete response or partial response until the first date that recurrent and progressive disease is objectively documented, assessed up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in expression of IDO1 protein by IHC in tumor or tumor-infiltrating cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Mucosal Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Intraocular Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Intraocular Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Intraocular Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Intraocular Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Intraocular Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (INCB024360, MELITAC 12.1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive IDO1 inhibitor INCB024360 PO BID on days 1-98 and receive MELITAC 12.1 peptide vaccine ID/SC on days 21, 28, 35, 56, 77, and 98 in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IDO1 inhibitor INCB024360</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (INCB024360, MELITAC 12.1)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>INCB024360</other_name>
    <other_name>indoleamine-2,3-dioxygenase inhibitor INCB024360</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MELITAC 12.1 peptide vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given ID/SC</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (INCB024360, MELITAC 12.1)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MELITAC 12.1</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (INCB024360, MELITAC 12.1)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have malignant melanoma validated by histology or cytology; patients
             may have had primary cutaneous, mucosal, or ocular melanoma or metastasis from an
             unknown primary site

               -  NOTE: patients must have measurable disease, defined as at least 1 lesion that
                  can be accurately measured in at least 1 dimension (longest diameter to be
                  recorded for non-nodal lesions and short axis for nodal lesions) as &gt;= 20 mm
                  with conventional chest x-ray or as &gt;= 10 mm with spiral computed tomography
                  (CT) scan, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), or calipers by clinical exam

          -  Unresectable stage III or IV validated by clinical criteria (including recurrent
             melanoma), or patients with multiple skin/soft tissue metastases that may be
             resectable but are judged to have a future recurrence risk exceeding 90% (e.g.,
             multiple in-transit melanoma metastases); tumor deemed amenable to biopsy
             (excisional, incisional, or core, with at least 100 mm^3 tumor volume per biopsy
             date) and fine-needle aspiration (FNA) biopsy

               -  NOTE: patients with unresectable advanced stage III or IV melanoma (including
                  recurrent melanoma) are only eligible if they have failed at least one other
                  first-line systemic therapy (other than adjuvant therapy); exceptions to this
                  requirement are those patients who have refused and/or are ineligible for other
                  systemic therapies

               -  NOTE: v-raf murine sarcoma viral oncogene homolog B (BRAF)i should be considered
                  for all 'unresectable&quot; or metastatic melanoma with BRAFV600E mutation; for low
                  burden in-transit disease patients may enter trial without prior systemic
                  therapy

                    -  Stage IV no evidence of disease (NED) is excluded by this criterion

          -  Patients may have had prior systemic therapy without constraint on the number of
             prior treatment regimens except:

               -  Patients may not have had &gt; 450 mg/m^2 doxorubicin

               -  Patients may not have had &gt; 3000 centigray (cGy) to fields encompassing the
                  entire pelvis

          -  Patients must not be on any other systemic therapy within the following intervals
             before study enrollment:

               -  1 week after stereotactic radiosurgery of the brain or comparable technology

               -  4 weeks after cytotoxic chemotherapy or external beam radiation therapy

               -  6 weeks after chemotherapy regimens including BCNU (carmustine) or mitomycin C

               -  12 weeks after ipilimumab, programmed cell death 1 (PD-1) antibody, or other
                  immunologically active antibody

               -  NOTE: patients receiving prior cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated protein 4
                  (CTLA-4), anti-PD1 antibody or other immunologic therapy must show evidence of
                  normal pituitary function at baseline

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-1 (Karnofsky &gt;= 70%)

          -  Life expectancy of at least 6 months

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3,000/mcL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 75,000/mcL

          -  Hemoglobin &gt; 9 g/dL

          -  Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal (bilirubin &lt; 3 ×
             institutional upper limit of normal for Gilbert's syndrome)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST)(serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT)(serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             must be less than institutional upper limit of normal (liver function tests [LFT's]
             must be within normal limits)

          -  Creatinine &lt; 1.5 x × institutional upper limit of normal OR

          -  Creatinine clearance &gt;= 60 mL/min/1.73 m^2 for patients with creatinine levels above
             institutional normal

          -  Prothrombin time (PT), international normalized ratio (INR) =&lt; 1.5 x institutional
             upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) within normal limits

          -  Thyroxine (T4) within normal limits

          -  Patients must express human leukocyte antigen (HLA) -A1+, -A2+, or -A3+ (80% of
             patients)

          -  Lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) &lt; 3 × upper limits of normal

               -  [NOTE: these criteria will select against patients with bulky disease and will
                  select for patients with less disease and earlier disease]

          -  Participants must not have had prior autoimmune disorders requiring cytotoxic or
             immunosuppressive therapy, or autoimmune disorders with visceral involvement;
             participants must not have an active or inactive autoimmune disorders (e.g.,
             rheumatoid arthritis, moderate or severe psoriasis, multiple sclerosis, inflammatory
             bowel disease, etc.) or who are receiving therapy for an autoimmune or inflammatory
             disease requiring these therapies are also excluded

          -  The following will not be exclusionary:

               -  Resolved ipilimumab associated inflammatory disease

               -  The presence of laboratory evidence of autoimmune disease (e.g., positive
                  antinuclear antibody [ANA] titer) without associated symptoms

               -  Subjects with vitiligo, thyroiditis, or atopic dermatitis, but otherwise not
                  meeting this criterion may be enrolled; individual cases can be discussed with
                  the sponsor

          -  Not believed curable with surgery alone

          -  Not currently receiving therapy

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test within 48 hours
             before initiating protocol therapy

               -  NOTE: women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate
                  contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control or abstinence) before
                  study entry and for the duration of study participation; should a woman become
                  pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is participating in
                  this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately; men treated or
                  enrolled on this protocol must also agree to use adequate contraception before
                  the study, for the duration of study participation, and 4 months after
                  completing INCB024360 and MELITAC 12.1 administration

               -  NOTE: subjects are considered not of child bearing potential if they are
                  surgically sterile, have undergone a hysterectomy, bilateral tubal ligation, or
                  bilateral oophorectomy, or are postmenopausal; menopause is the age associated
                  with complete cessation of menstrual cycles and menses, and implies the loss of
                  reproductive potential; by a practical definition, the term assumes menopause
                  after 1 year without menses with an appropriate clinical profile at the
                  appropriate age

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had cytotoxic chemotherapy, radiotherapy, interferon (IFN),
             immunosuppressive therapy, or steroids within 4 weeks (6 weeks for nitrosoureas or
             mitomycin C) before entering the study or those who have not recovered from adverse
             events (AEs) due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier

          -  Ipilimumab, anti-PD1, anti-programmed cell death 1 ligand 1 (PDL1) or other
             immunologically active therapy within 12 weeks

          -  Active immunosuppressive therapy, including concurrent systemic immunosuppressive
             therapy or steroid therapy with more than 7 consecutive days of steroids within the
             prior 4 weeks

               -  The use of prednisone or equivalent &lt; 0.125 mg/kg/day (absolute maximum of 10
                  mg/day) as replacement therapy is permitted

               -  Inhaled corticosteroids are permitted

          -  Cardiovascular disease that meets one of the following: congestive heart failure (New
             York Heart Association class III or IV), active angina pectoris, or recent myocardial
             infarction or acute coronary syndrome (within the last 6 months)

          -  History of peripheral vascular disease (PVD) or extensive diabetes

          -  Current or history of systemic autoimmune disease requiring systemic therapy,
             including significant autoimmunity associated with prior ipilimumab therapy

          -  Cirrhosis, chronic hepatitis C virus positivity, or chronic hepatitis B infection;
             subjects who may not tolerate immune-mediated hepatitis due to compromised hepatic
             reserve also excluded from participation including: subjects with extensive liver
             metastasis (as judged by the investigator); subjects who drink more than two standard
             alcoholic beverages per day on a regular basis; subjects who consume more than 2
             grams of acetaminophen per day on a regular basis

               -  A positive hepatitis B serology indicative of previous immunization (i.e.,
                  hepatitis B surface antibody [HBsAb]-positive and hepatitis B core antibody
                  [HBcAb]-negative), or a fully resolved acute hepatitis B infection is not an
                  exclusion criterion

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents for melanoma

          -  Patients who have had a grade one or grade two gastrointestinal adverse event during
             or after receiving anti-CTLA-4, anti-PD1 or anti-PD, without a colonoscopy verifying
             complete resolution of the adverse event

          -  Patients who have experienced bowel perforation, neurologic involvement, Guillain
             Barré syndrome, Myasthenia Gravis, Steven Johnson syndrome and other intractable
             events or grade 4 non-laboratory toxicity

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Pregnancy, nursing, or unwilling to take adequate birth control during therapy

               -  NOTE: pregnant women are excluded from this study; breastfeeding should be
                  discontinued if the mother is treated with INCB024360 and MELITAC 12.1

          -  Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or other history of immunodeficiency
             disorder

               -  NOTE: HIV-positive patients taking combination antiretroviral therapy are
                  ineligible

          -  Extensive active brain disease, including symptomatic brain metastases or the
             presence of leptomeningeal disease

               -  Patients with brain metastasis, after definitive therapy with surgery or
                  stereotactic radiation and stable off steroids for &gt; 4 weeks, are eligible

          -  Any malignancy that has not been in complete remission for at least 3 years

               -  NOTE: patients with cured basal or squamous cell skin cancer are not excluded

          -  Monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitor use within the past 3 weeks or prior evidence of
             serotonin syndrome

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to INCB024360, MELITAC 12.1, or other vaccine components

          -  Prior organ allograft or allogeneic transplantation, if the transplanted tissue is
             still in place

          -  Medical or psychiatric illness that would, in the opinion of the investigator,
             preclude participation in the study or the ability of patients to provide informed
             consent for themselves

          -  History of pulmonary disease such as emphysema or chronic obstructive pulmonary
             disease (COPD), (forced expiratory volume in one second [FEV1] &gt; 60% of predicted for
             height and age); pulmonary function tests (PFTs) are required in patients with
             prolonged smoking history or symptoms of respiratory dysfunction

          -  Subjects who are currently receiving therapy with a potent cytochrome P450, family 3,
             subfamily A, polypeptide 4 (CYP3A4) inducer or inhibitor; subjects may enter
             screening when therapy with the potent inhibitor or inducer is completed

          -  Use of any UDP glucuronosyltransferase 1 family, polypeptide A9 (UGT1A9) inhibitor
             including: diclofenac, imipramine, ketoconazole, mefenamic acid, and probenecid from
             screening through follow-up period

          -  Low-dose Coumadin (1 mg) is acceptable; however, doses that increase INR are not
             permitted; if an alternative to Coumadin-based anticoagulants cannot be used, the INR
             should be monitored weekly after initiation of therapy and upon discontinuation of
             INCB024360, until INR normalization
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Craig Slingluff</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cancer Immunotherapy Trials Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University/Winship Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Keith A. Delman</last_name>
      <phone>404-778-3303</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Keith A. Delman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dartmouth Hitchcock Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lebanon</city>
        <state>New Hampshire</state>
        <zip>03756</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marc S. Ernstoff</last_name>
      <phone>603-650-5534</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marc S. Ernstoff</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Douglas S. Tyler</last_name>
      <phone>919-684-6858</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Douglas S. Tyler</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Virginia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22908</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Craig L. Slingluff</last_name>
      <phone>434-924-1730</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Craig L. Slingluff</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uveal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
