<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="48414">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01675128</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>120187</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12-C-0187</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01675128</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ISIS 183750 With Irinotecan for Advanced Solid Tumors or Colorectal Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Study of ISIS 183750 in Combination With Irinotecan in Irinotecan-refractory Colorectal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Irinotecan is a drug that is used to treat colon or rectal cancer. It affects the DNA of
      growing cancer cells. It is most often used with other chemotherapy drugs. Researchers want
      to test it with an experimental drug, ISIS 183750. They want to see if the drugs are a safe
      and effective treatment for advanced solid tumors or colorectal cancer that has not
      responded to other treatments.

      Objectives:

      - To test the safety and effectiveness of ISIS 183750 with irinotecan for advanced solid
      tumors or colorectal cancer.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who have solid tumors or colorectal cancer that has
      not responded to other treatments.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood and urine
           samples will also be collected. Tumor tissue samples may be collected as well before
           and after treatment. Imaging studies will also be performed.

        -  Participants will take ISIS 183750 once a week for 28-day cycles of treatment. On the
           first cycle, they will also have ISIS 183750 on days 3 and 5.

        -  Participants will take irinotecan every second week, beginning on day 15 of the first
           cycle.

        -  Treatment will be monitored with frequent blood tests and imaging studies.

        -  Treatment will continue as long as the cancer does not grow and the side effects are
           not severe.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      The eukaryotic translation initiation factor - eIF4E - is a potent oncogene that is found to
      be dysregulated in approximately 30% of human cancers. Upregulation of eIF4E is an early
      event in colorectal cancer (CRC) and correlates with CRC progression. ISIS 183750 is a
      second-generation antisense oligonucleotide (ASO) designed to inhibit the production of the
      human eukaryotic translation initiation factor 4E (eIF4E) protein.

      Objectives:

      Primary:

      To establish Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) and establish safety for the combination of ISIS
      183750 and irinotecan in advanced solid tumors.

      Secondary:

        -  To evaluate Response Rate, PFS, OS for the combination of ISIS 183750 and irinotecan in
           advanced irinotecan-refractory colorectal cancer.

        -  To perform correlative studies to evaluate the effect of eIF4E inhibition on relevant
           regulated proteins and immune cells.

        -  To characterize the plasma pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters for ISIS 183750 in the
           absence and presence of irinotecan

        -  To characterize the plasma PK parameters for irinotecan in the presence of ISIS 183750

      Eligibility:

      -Adult patients with irinotecan-resistant colorectal cancer.

      Design:

        -  This is a single-arm phase I/II study whereby all patients will receive the combination
           of ISIS 183750 and irinotecan. All cycles are 28 days.

        -  Cycle 1 only: ISIS 183750 will be administered intravenously on Cycle 1 Days 1, 3, 5,
           8, 15 and 22.

        -  Cycle 2 and beyond: ISIS 183750 will be administered as an intravenous infusion every
           week without break, i.e. Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle. Patients will be
           re-staged every 8 weeks.

        -  Irinotecan will be administered at a dose of 160mg/m2 as an intravenous infusion every
           second week commencing on Day 15 of Cycle 1. The primary endpoint of the study will be
           to establish MTD for the combination of ISIS 183750 and irinotecan in advanced solid
           tumors. The phase II portion of the study will be confined to irinotecan-refractory
           colorectoal cancer. Irinotecan-refractory will be defined as patients who have
           radiological evidence of disease progression whilst receiving irinotecan or within 3
           months after completing it.

        -  Correlative studies will comprise: Mandatory pre- and post- dose biopsies for eIF4e
           mRNA and protein (IHC) analysis will be performed in the phase II portion of the study;
           Immune subsets; PET responses (only in expansion cohort); Pharmacokinetic data
           regarding the interaction of irinotecan and ISIS183750 in 10-12 patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of eIF4e and protein (HC) in pre- and post- tumor biopies</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the effect of eIF4E on relevant regulated proteins and immune cells</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate Response Rate, PFS, and OS</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ISIS 183750 will be administered intravenously on Cycle 1 Days 1, 3, 5, 8, 15 and 22.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ISIS 183750 will be administered as an intravenousinfusion every week without break, i.e. Days 1, 8, 15and 22 of a 28-day cycle. Patients will be re-stagedevery 8 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ISIS 183750</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Irinotecan</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Phase I: Patients must have histopathological confirmation of carcinoma by the
             Laboratory of Pathology of the NCI prior to entering this study.

          -  Phase II: Patients must have histopathological confirmation of Colorectal Carcinoma
             (CRC) by the Laboratory of Pathology of the NCI prior to entering this study. For
             this portion of the study patients must also have irinotecan-refractory colorectal
             cancer and have also received prior treatment for advanced/metastatic disease with an
             oxaliplatin-, bevacizumab-, or EGFR inhibitor-containing (only for subjects with wild
             type Kras) regimen. Irinotecan-refractory will be defined as patients who have
             radiological evidence of disease progression whilst receiving irinotecan or within 3
             months after completing it.

          -  Patients must have disease that is not amenable to potentially curative resection or
             ablative techniques and have received at least one prior standard chemotherapeutic
             regimen for metastatic disease.

          -  All patients enrolled will be required to have measurable disease. For the phase II
             portion of the study patients must have disease that is amenable to biopsy and be
             willing to undergo this.

          -  Age greater than18 years

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 3 months

          -  ECOG performance status 0-2

          -  Patients must have acceptable organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  leukocytes &gt; 3,000/mcL

               -  absolute neutrophil count &gt;  1,500/mcL

               -  platelets &gt; 100,000/mcL

               -  total bilirubin Within normal institutional limits

               -  Serum albumin greater than or equal to 2.5 g/dL

               -  Patients are eligible with ALT or AST measuring 3 x ULN if no liver metastasis
                  or up to5 x ULN with liver metastasis.

               -  creatinine &lt; 1.5X institution upper limit of normal

               -  OR

               -  creatinine clearance &gt; 45 mL/min/1.73 m2, as calculated below, for patients with
                  creatinine levels above institutional normal

               -  Estimated creatinine clearance (mL/min)

                    -  Females     see calculations

                    -  Males     see calculations - May use a 24 hr. urine collection to determine
                       creatinine clearance.

               -  Measured creatinine clearance (mL/min)

          -  Patients must have recovered from any acute toxicity related to prior therapy,
             including surgery. Toxicity should be &lt;  grade 1 or returned to baseline.

          -  Patients must not have other invasive malignancies within the past 3 years (with the
             exception of non-melanoma skin cancers, carcinoma in situ of the cervix and
             noninvasive bladder cancer that has had successful curative treatment).

          -  The effects of ISIS 183750 on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this reason
             women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry, for
             the duration of study participation, and for 3 months after dosing with study
             medication ceases. However, adequate contraception for male patients should be used
             for 16 weeks post- last dose due to sperm life cycle. Should a woman become pregnant
             or suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is participating in this study,
             she should inform her treating physician immediately. Women of child-bearing
             potential must have a negative pregnancy test prior to entry.

          -  Patient must be able to understand and willing to sign a written informed consent
             document.

          -  Men and women of all races and ethnic groups are eligible for this trial.

          -  Ejection fraction &gt;  55% on echocardiogram.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy (or so-called    targeted    systemic therapy),
             large field radiotherapy, or major surgery must wait 4 weeks after completing
             treatment prior to entering the study.

          -  Patients may not be receiving any antineoplastics or other drugs intended to treat
             cancer within 4 weeks prior to starting ISIS 183750.

          -  Patients with known brain metastases will be excluded from this clinical trial
             because of their poor prognosis and because they often develop progressive neurologic
             dysfunction that would confound the evaluation of neurologic and other adverse
             events. Patients with clinically significant ascites, pleural effusion, and/or
             peripheral edema, unless the ascites or pleural effusion occurred as a result of
             malignancy.

          -  Patients with known hypersensitivity to irinotecan.

          -  Patients with known homozygous mutations in the UTG1A1 allele, or with unknown UTG1A1
             status but who could not tolerate irinotecan even after dose reduction.

          -  Patients with bleeding diathesis and subjects who are receiving anticoagulation
             treatment with INR &gt;  2.5 are excluded.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, hypertension
             (systolic BP &gt;  160, diastolic BP &gt;  100), ongoing or active systemic infection,
             symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia or
             psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
             requirements.

          -  HIV-positive patients receiving anti-retroviral therapy are excluded from this study
             due to the possibility of pharmacokinetic interactions between antiretroviral
             medications and the investigational agent.

          -  Known hepatitis B or hepatitis C infection.

          -  Pregnancy and breast feeding are exclusion factors. Enrolled patients must agree to
             use adequate contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence)
             prior to study entry, the duration of study participation and 3 months after the end
             of the treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tim F Greten, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Suzanne Fioravanti, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 594-6544</phone>
    <email>fioravas@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tim F Greten, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-4723</phone>
    <email>gretentf@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>888-624-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2012-C-0187.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>André T, Louvet C, Maindrault-Goebel F, Couteau C, Mabro M, Lotz JP, Gilles-Amar V, Krulik M, Carola E, Izrael V, de Gramont A. CPT-11 (irinotecan) addition to bimonthly, high-dose leucovorin and bolus and continuous-infusion 5-fluorouracil (FOLFIRI) for pretreated metastatic colorectal cancer. GERCOR. Eur J Cancer. 1999 Sep;35(9):1343-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10658525</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bendell JC, Nemunaitis J, Vukelja SJ, Hagenstad C, Campos LT, Hermann RC, Sportelli P, Gardner L, Richards DA. Randomized placebo-controlled phase II trial of perifosine plus capecitabine as second- or third-line therapy in patients with metastatic colorectal cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2011 Nov 20;29(33):4394-400. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2011.36.1980. Epub 2011 Oct 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21969495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennouna J, Lang I, Valladares-Ayerbes M, Boer K, Adenis A, Escudero P, Kim TY, Pover GM, Morris CD, Douillard JY. A Phase II, open-label, randomised study to assess the efficacy and safety of the MEK1/2 inhibitor AZD6244 (ARRY-142886) versus capecitabine monotherapy in patients with colorectal cancer who have failed one or two prior chemotherapeutic regimens. Invest New Drugs. 2011 Oct;29(5):1021-8. doi: 10.1007/s10637-010-9392-8. Epub 2010 Feb 2.</citation>
    <PMID>20127139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 16, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 25, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Human Eukaryotic Translation Initiation Factor 4E (eIF4E) protein</keyword>
  <keyword>Refractory</keyword>
  <keyword>Oncogene</keyword>
  <keyword>Maximum Tolerated Dose</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Irinotecan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
