<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="19990">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01884311</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SCIG03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01884311</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacokinetics (PK) and Safety of Subgam®VF in Primary Immunodeficiency Diseases</brief_title>
  <acronym>SCIG03</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase III, Multicenter, Open-Label Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics and Safety of Subgam®VF in Primary Immunodeficiency Diseases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bio Products Laboratory</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bio Products Laboratory</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main objective of the study is to determine the pharmacokinetics profile of Subgam-VF.
      The secondary objectives are to assess the safety of Subgam-VF and refine the dose
      adjustment coefficient for Subgam-VF needed for subjects switching from prior intravenous
      immunoglobulin (IGIV) therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study suspended pending advice from the FDA
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the PK profile of Subgam-VF and compare the Area under the curve  to a given treatment period (AUC [0-t)]) with historical data all standardized to 1 week at steady state from Gammaplex 5% IGIV Primary Immune studies (GMX01 and GMX04)</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the safety of Subgam-VF including the incidence of adverse events (AEs) and site infusion reactions in subjects with primary immunodeficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse events:	Number and percent of infusions associated with 1 or more AEs during the study and specifically AEs that begin during the infusion or within 72 hours after completion of the infusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Refine the dose adjustment coefficient for Subgam-VF</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 26</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Immune Deficiency Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Common Variable Immunodeficiency</condition>
  <condition>X-linked Agammaglobulinaemia</condition>
  <condition>Hyper-Immunoglobulin M (IgM0Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Subgam-VF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Subgam</intervention_name>
    <description>Subgam-VF dose will be given as 1.45 of the established IGIV dose (expressed in mg/kg/week) for 26 weeks (26 infusions) beginning one week after the last IGIV infusion. Dose of Subgam-VF will then be adjusted based on the ratio of the Immunoglobulin G (IgG) average concentration achieved with Subgam-VF compared to IGIV.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Subgam-VF</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Subgam-VF</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          1. Aged between 2 and 75 years.

          2. Diagnosed with primary immunodeficiency disease e.g. common variable
             immunodeficiency, X-linked and autosomal forms of agammaglobulinaemia, hyper-IgM
             syndrome.

          3. Currently receiving a licensed IGIV at a dose that has not changed by ± 50% of the
             mean dose for at least three months before study entry (Visit 1) and

               1. Dose is between 300 and 800 mg/kg/infusion.

               2. The infusion interval is between 21 and 28 days inclusive for IGIV.

               3. Has maintained a trough level of ≥ 5 g/L (500 mg/dL) for the last three months
                  before Visit 1.

          4. Female subjects who are (or become) sexually active must practice contraception by
             using a method of proven reliability for the duration of the study.

          5. Females of child-bearing potential must have a negative result on an human chorionic
             gonadotropin (HCG)-based pregnancy test.

          6. Willing to comply with all aspects of the protocol for the duration of the study.

          7. Signed an informed consent form. In the case of subjects under the legal age the
             parent/guardian will sign an informed consent form and where appropriate the subject
             will sign an assent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Is currently using subcutaneous IgG (SCIG).

          2. Has a history of any severe anaphylactic reaction to blood or any blood-derived
             product.

          3. Has selective IgA deficiency, history of reaction to products containing IgA, or has
             a history of antibodies to immunoglobulin A (IgA).

          4. Has impaired cellular or innate immunity (i.e. only subjects with impaired humoral
             immunity to be included)

          5. Has evidence of an active infection at the time of enrolment.

          6. Has previously completed or withdrawn from this study.

          7. Is currently receiving, or has received, any investigational agent within the prior
             three months.

          8. Is pregnant (confirmed by a positive result on an HCG-based pregnancy test) or is
             nursing.

          9. Is positive for any of the following at screening:

               -  Serological test for Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) 1&amp;2, hepatitis C virus
                  (HCV), or Hepatitis B Surface Antigen (HBsAg)

               -  Nucleic acid Amplification Test [Polymerase Chain Reaction - PCR] (NAT) for HCV

               -  NAT for HIV

         10. Has levels at screening greater than 2.5 times the upper limit of normal as defined
             at the central laboratory of any of the following:

               -  Alanine transaminase (ALT)

               -  Aspartate transaminase (AST)

         11. Has severe renal impairment (defined as serum creatinine greater than two times the
             upper limit of normal or blood urea nitrogen (BUN) greater than 2.5 times the upper
             limit of normal for the range of the laboratory doing the analysis); the subject is
             on dialysis; or has a history of acute renal failure.

         12. Is known to abuse alcohol, opiates, psychotropic agents, or other chemicals or drugs,
             or has done so within the past 12 months.

         13. Has a history of deep vein thrombosis (DVT), or thrombotic complications of IGIV
             therapy.

         14. Suffers from any acute or chronic medical condition, (e.g. renal disease or
             predisposing conditions for renal disease, coronary artery disease, or protein losing
             state, proteinuria) that the investigator feels may interfere with the conduct of the
             study.

         15. Has an acquired medical condition, such as chronic lymphocytic leukemia, lymphoma,
             multiple myeloma, chronic or recurrent neutropenia (ANC &lt; 1000 x 109/L).

         16. Is receiving the following medication:

               -  Steroids (long-term daily, &gt; 0.15 mg of prednisone equivalent/kg/day).
                  Requirement for short or intermittent courses would not exclude a subject.

               -  Immunosuppressive drugs

               -  Immunomodulatory drugs

         17. Has non-controlled arterial hypertension (systolic blood pressure &gt; 160 mmHg and/or
             diastolic blood pressure &gt; 100 mmHg).

         18. Has anemia (hemoglobin &lt; 10 g/dL) at screening.

         19. Has severe dermatitis that would preclude sites for safe product administration.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tim J. Aldwinckle, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Bio Products Laboratory Limited</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Primary Immune Deficiency Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Common Variable Immunodeficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>X-linked agammaglobulinaemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Hyper-IgM Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Subcutaneous</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunoglobulins</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Agammaglobulinemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Common Variable Immunodeficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Genetic Diseases, X-Linked</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
