<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="134608">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02066779</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>851-2013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02066779</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>iPad Based Platform to Improve Outcomes From DBS Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mobile Computing Platform to Improve Outcomes From Deep Brain Stimulation (DBS) Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test the use of a deep brain stimulation (DBS) clinical
      decision support tool for bedside, postoperative care.  The idea of this study is that the
      use of a DBS clinical support system for individual patient management will enable
      considerable time savings compared to standard care.

      More specifically, the investigators will implement an iPad based decision support system
      and measure it's effectiveness in an established clinic.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      If the subject decides to participate, they will follow the typical clinic visit schedule
      for patients that have had DBS surgery. They will be expected to have several DBS
      programming sessions to determine the best setting. These sessions will include completing
      questionnaires and testing movement and coordination.

      The investigators are comparing the 2 types of programming.  Subjects will be &quot;randomized&quot;
      into one of the two study groups.  One group will have the DBS system programmed using
      standard clinical care and one group will have the DBS system programmed using a iPAD
      computerized system. Randomization means that one is put into a group by chance. It is like
      flipping a coin.  Subjects will have an equal chance of being placed in either group.
      Neither the subject nor the investigator can choose what group a subject will be in.

      A subject's standard clinical care will not change unless they are in the group that is
      randomized to use the iPAD computerized system to select the settings. Both groups will
      follow the same schedule of office visits that all subjects with DBS follow.  For the group
      which has their DBS programmed using the iPAD computerized system, the clinical decision
      support tools will be used bedside during postoperative care.  These tools will not provide
      the final DBS settings and investigators do not anticipate that this approach will obviate
      the need for motor exams.  The clinical decision support system is meant to help programmers
      choose good initial settings and then explore around those initial settings to optimize
      patient care.

      As part of usual patient care, some tests and questionnaires will be administered.
      Investigators will use the results of those tests and questionnaires for this research
      study.

      The only difference between this study and routine clinical care at the UF Center for
      Movement Disorders &amp; Neurorestoration outpatient clinic is that a subject may be programmed
      with the use of a computerized, iPad-based tool, and the time spent will be recorded in each
      programming visit.  The only additional questionnaire patients will be asked to complete
      beyond what is normally performed in our clinic is the multi-dimensional caregiver strain
      index (MCSI).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in deep brain stimulation (DBS) programming time compared to standard care for patients using an iPad based decision support system</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Total time spent programming standard care versus total time spent programming for the DBS decision tool group will be compared.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in caregiver strain for DBS patients using the iPad-based clinical decision support tool</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Multi-Dimensional Caregiver Strain Index (MCSI) is an 18-question self-report scale with 6 subscales of caregiver strain: physical strain, social constraints, financial strain, time constraints, interpersonal strain, and elder demanding/manipulative behavior.  A higher score is considered indicative of a greater caregiver strain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in score on Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS) for patients with standard care versus the DBS decision tool group</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The UPDRS is a rating scale used to follow the longitudinal course of Parkinson's disease. The UPDRS is made up of 5 sections: (1) Evaluation of Mentation, behavior, and mood; (2) Self-evaluation of the activities of daily life (ADLs) including speech, swallowing, handwriting, dressing, hygiene, falling, salivating, turning in bed, walking, cutting food; (3) Clinician-scored monitored motor evaluation; (4) Hoehn and Yahr staging of severity of Parkinson disease; (5) Schwab and England ADL scale.  The higher the UPDRS score, the greater the disability from PD.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Parkinsons Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>iPad-based Clinical Support Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this treatment arm will receive deep brain stimulation (DBS) programming at regular intervals as part of routine clinical care.  DBS stimulation programming will be done with the use of a iPad-based computerized tool.  These sessions will include completing questionnaires and testing movement and coordination. One additional questionnaire will be asked to complete which is the multi-dimensional caregiver strain index (MCSI).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Clinical Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this treatment arm will receive DBS programming at regular intervals as part of routine clinical care.  These sessions will include completing questionnaires and testing movement and coordination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>iPad-based Clinical Support Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects in this treatment arm will receive deep brain stimulation (DBS) programming at regular intervals as part of routine clinical care. DBS stimulation programming will be done with the use of a iPad-based computerized tool. These sessions will include completing questionnaires and testing movement and coordination. One additional questionnaire will be asked to complete which is the multi-dimensional caregiver strain index (MCSI).</description>
    <arm_group_label>iPad-based Clinical Support Care</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>iPad-based Tool</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Clinical Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects in this treatment arm will receive DBS programming at regular intervals as part of routine clinical care.  These sessions will include completing questionnaires and testing movement and coordination.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Clinical Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of idiopathic Parkinson's Disease

          -  Planning to receive a DBS device at Shands/University of Florida (UF), or

          -  Had a DBS device implanted, at Shands/UF, that hasn't been programmed yet

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Had a DBS device implanted at a site other than Shands/UF

          -  Any previous DBS programming
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael S Okun, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stacy Merritt, MA</last_name>
    <phone>352-273-5614</phone>
    <email>stacy.merritt@neurology.ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida Center for Movement Disorders &amp;Neurorestoration</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32607</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael S Okun, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pam Zeilman, ARNP</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Irene Malaty, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ramon Rodriguez, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stacy Merritt, MA</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://movementdisorders.ufhealth.org/</url>
    <description>UF Center for Movement Disorders &amp; Neurorestoration</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 17, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>deep brain stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>DBS</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinsons</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinsons Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinson's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>STN</keyword>
  <keyword>STN DBS</keyword>
  <keyword>GPi</keyword>
  <keyword>GPi DBS</keyword>
  <keyword>globus pallidus</keyword>
  <keyword>subthalamic nucleus</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
