<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="55460">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02075632</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P2200440</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02075632</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate Product Duration of Use Experience With Alclometasone Dipropionate Cream</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Mult-Center, Open-Label Study to Evaluate Product Duration of Use Experience With Aclometasone Diproprionate Cream</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, open-label study to evaluate whether participants follow the
      duration of use instructions for short-term use of alclometasone dipropionate in a
      population of participants with itchy skin conditions who would use OTC treatments for
      relief. The study population will be composed of two different cohorts: chronic condition
      sufferers (eczema or psoriasis) and participants who suffer from occasional itchy skin
      experiences (such as poison ivy, oak, sumac, insect bites, or skin irritations due to
      jewelry, cosmetics, detergents, or soaps) where an anti-itch medication would be used.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Approximately 313 participants who are currently suffering from an itchy skin condition
      caused by eczema or psoriasis or any occasional itchy skin experiences will be enrolled into
      the study to get 250 participants who complete the study (at least 100 to each of the
      cohorts). After evaluation of the study criteria, the site staff will dispense product and a
      diary card to the subject to use over the next 14 days. At the end of the 14 days, each
      participant will come to the research site to return the remaining product and undergo the
      study termination interview with the Concentrics nurse via telephone. The study will be
      conducted in approximately 15 research sites located throughout the United States (US).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2006</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with incorrect duration of use of the medication</measure>
    <time_frame>Day1-Day 14</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>A participant was evaluable for analysis of the rate of incorrect use if he or she used the study medication at least once and provided use information at least 8 days after the enrollment visit.Participants who used study medication for more than 7 consecutive days were asked why they did so.
* Participants were allowed to select multiple reasons also if applicable</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of times per day participants used the product</measure>
    <time_frame>Day1-Day14</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of days on which study medication was used, was be summarized for all subjects and by cohort in evaluable subjects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">310</enrollment>
  <condition>Eczema</condition>
  <condition>Allergy Symptoms</condition>
  <condition>Psoriasis</condition>
  <condition>Itch</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alclometasone dipropionate cream</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Alclometasone dipropionate cream 0.05% will be applied by the participants topically on the affected areas per label instructions for 14 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alclometasone dipropionate cream</intervention_name>
    <description>Alclometasone dipropionate cream 0.05% (15 g)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Alclometasone dipropionate cream</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age: At least 12 years of age.

          -  Condition: Currently experiencing itch associated with one of the following skin
             conditions:

               -  psoriasis or eczema,

               -  minor skin conditions such as those caused by poison ivy, oak, or sumac, insect
                  bites, or use of cosmetics, soaps, detergents, or jewelry.

          -  Compliance: Subject or subject's parent or legal guardian understands and is willing,
             able and likely to comply with all study procedures and restrictions.

          -  Consent: Subject or subject's parent or legal guardian demonstrates ability to read
             and understand English and is willing to participate as evidenced by voluntary
             written informed consent and has received a signed and dated copy of the informed
             consent form (and assent as appropriate).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy: Women who are known to be pregnant (as self-reported) or who are intending
             to become pregnant over the duration of the study. Women of childbearing potential
             will be allowed to participate in the study so long as they are practicing a reliable
             method of contraception (e.g. hormonal birth control such as pill, patch, implant or
             injection; intrauterine device, double barrier methods, tubal ligation, vasectomized
             spouse or abstinence).

          -  Corticosteroid Use: Subject has used a corticosteroid treatment within two weeks of
             the screening visit at the start of the study.

          -  Breast-feeding: Women who are breastfeeding.

          -  Allergy/Intolerance: Known or suspected intolerance or hypersensitivity to
             alclometasone cream (or closely related compounds), or any of their stated
             ingredients.

          -  Participation in another clinical study or receipt of an investigational drug within
             30 days of the screening visit at the start of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 28, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alclometasone dipropionate</keyword>
  <keyword>Eczema</keyword>
  <keyword>Psoriasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Itch</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Eczema</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Alclometasone dipropionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
