<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="33406">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01831219</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-PROTO-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01831219</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ROBODOC® CLINICAL TRIALS: LONG-TERM FOLLOW-UP</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Follow-Up Study of Subjects Enrolled in the Pin-Based (IDE G920035) and Pinless (IDE G000071) ROBODOC® Surgical System Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Curexo Technology Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Curexo Technology Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a follow-up study looking at the and long-term results of two methods of preparing
      the thigh bone to receive an implant during hip replacement surgery.  For one group of
      patients in the original study, the surgeon used a cutting tool called a broach and a
      special hammer on patients who had standard hip replacement operations.  For the other
      patients, the surgeon used a surgical robot which was equipped with a cutting tool, like a
      drill, to prepare the thigh bone.  The purpose of this study is to collect additional
      information confirming that the surgical robot is safe and effective when used as
      recommended.  Only patients who were enrolled in the original clinical trials are eligible
      for this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A. Description This study is a follow-up study looking at mid- and long-term outcomes for
      participants in the IDE G920035 and IDE G000071 Clinical Trials. The IDE G920035 was a
      randomized, controlled trial with a 1:1 ROBODOC:control randomization. The IDE G000071 was a
      randomized, controlled trial with a 3:1 ROBODOC:control randomization.

      B. Selection Criteria Only subjects who were originally enrolled in the IDE G920035 and IDE
      G000071 Clinical Trials are eligible to participate in this study.  Subjects selected for
      this study will have completed a minimum of the 3 month follow-up requirements of the IDE
      G920035 and IDE G000071 Clinical Trials. Enrolled subjects must be willing to give a
      relevant medical history, undergo a focused physical examination of their operative hip(s),
      have an AP and lateral x-ray taken of their operative hip(s) and complete the Harris Hip
      Score, SF-12, UCLA Activity Score, VAS pain self-assessment, and Western Ontario and
      McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC) questionnaires.

      The study subject may be reimbursed for reasonable travel expenses associated with their
      participation in the study. All requests for reimbursement must be pre-approved by Curexo
      Technology Corporation.

      C. Data Collection Subjects participating in this study will be asked to visit the study
      site to undergo a physical examination of their operative hip(s). During this visit, they
      will be asked to give a relevant medical history, have AP and lateral radiographs taken of
      their operative hip(s), and complete the Harris Hip Score, SF-12, UCLA Activity Score, VAS
      pain self-assessment, and WOMAC questionnaires.

      If the subject has obtained AP and lateral radiographs within the last year, these can be
      used instead of requiring them to obtain new radiographs specifically for this study.

      If the subject is unable or unwilling to come in for the examination, they will be asked to
      fill out the Harris Hip Score, SF-12, UCLA Activity Score, VAS pain self-assessment, and
      WOMAC questionnaires via mail or over the phone with the Study Nurse/Coordinator.
      Additionally, they will be asked to obtain current AP and lateral radiographs taken of their
      operative hip(s) with their current orthopaedic surgeon to be transferred to the study site.

      D. Blinding An independent radiologist or orthopaedic surgeon, experienced in reading hip
      x-rays, who is blinded to the original randomly assigned study group, will read the
      follow-up x-rays taken on subjects enrolled in this study.

      E. Randomization There will be no further randomization of subjects in this study. Prior
      subject records will determine the original study group (ROBODOC or manual control) to which
      the subject was randomly assigned in IDE G920035 or IDE G000071.

      F. Baseline Measurements No baseline measurements will be collected for this follow-up
      study. G. Power and Sample Size The sample size will be determined by the number of
      qualifying subjects from the IDE G920035 and IDE G000071 Clinical Trials who can be located
      and who agree to participate in this follow-up study. We anticipate approximately 20
      patients from IDE G920035 and 30 patients from IDE G000071 to agree to study participation.
      This sample size will provide 82% power (α = 0.05, 2-tailed) to detect a 20% (5 versus 2.5,
      pooled SD = 3.0) difference between the ROBODOC and control groups on the VAS at the last
      available follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Migration of the implant</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient x-rays will be evaluated for Migration of the implant as described by Gruen et al and Johnson et al.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Bone remodeling</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient x-rays will be evaluated for bone remodeling as described by Gruen et al and Johnson et al.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of osteolysis</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient x-rays will be evaluated for presence of osteolysis as described by Gruen et al and Johnson et al.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Heterotopic bone formation</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient x-rays will be evaluated for heterotopic bone formation as described by Gruen et al and Johnson et al.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress shielding</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient x-rays will be evaluated for stress shielding as described by Engh et al.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Linear polyethylene wear</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient x-rays will be evaluated for linear polyethylene wear as described by Gruen et al and Johnson et al.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Harris Hip Score</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Harris Hip Score will be measured to determine clinical outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>12-Item Short Form Health Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The 12-Item Short Form Health Survey (SF-12) will be used to measure clinical outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC) will be used to measure clinical outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>UCLA Activity Score</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The UCLA Activity Score will be used to measure clinical outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analog Pain Score</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Visual Analog Scale pain questionnaire will be used to measure clinical outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Implant Survivorship</measure>
    <time_frame>At follow-up visit (7-20 years post-operatively)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Implant survivorship will be determined from the medical history CRF by comparing the percentage of ROBODOC and manual control subjects who have required revision or re-operation THA procedures on the hip in question since their original study procedure which took place 7-20 years previously.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ROBODOC</arm_group_label>
    <description>The ROBODOC group received total hip arthroplasty using the ROBODOC Surgical system for preparation of the femoral canal for a femoral stem implant.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional</arm_group_label>
    <description>The conventional group received total hip arthroplasty using the conventional manual tools including a broach to prepare the femoral cavity for femoral stem replacement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects included in this study will have been enrolled in either the IDE G920035 or the
        IDE G000071 Clinical Trial and will have completed the follow-up requirements to those
        trials.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects included in this study will have completed the follow-up requirements of the
             IDE G920035 or the IDE G000071 Clinical Trial;

          -  Subjects must be willing to give a relevant medical history, undergo a focused
             physical examination of their operative hip(s) and have an AP and lateral x-ray taken
             of their operative hip(s);

          -  Subjects must be willing to complete the Harris Hip Score, SF-12, WOMAC, UCLA
             Activity Score, and VAS pain self-assessment questionnaires; and

          -  Subjects must be willing to sign an informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  There are no exclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William L Bargar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Orthopaedics, University of California at Davis</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sutter Institute for Medical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sacramento</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95816</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bargar WL, Bauer A, Börner M. Primary and revision total hip replacement using the Robodoc system. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 1998 Sep;(354):82-91.</citation>
    <PMID>9755767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>arthroplasty</keyword>
  <keyword>hip arthroplasty</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
