<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="99076">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01818258</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IMPAACT P1092</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01AI068632</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01818258</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Steady State PK in Malnourished HIV Infected Children</brief_title>
  <acronym>P1092</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase IV Evaluation Of The Steady State Pharmacokinetics Of Zidovudine, Lamivudine, and Lopinavir/Ritonavir in Severely Malnourished HIV-1-Infected, Antiretroviral-Naïve Children Who Are Initiating HAART</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>International Maternal Pediatric Adolescent AIDS Clinical Trials Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>International Maternal Pediatric Adolescent AIDS Clinical Trials Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Uganda: National Council for Science and Technology</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      HIV-infected children from sub-Saharan Africa often present with severe malnutrition as
      their AIDS defining illness.  Severe malnutrition that is not responding to nutritional
      rehabilitation is an indication to initiate highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART). In
      severe malnutrition metabolic and or gut structural derangement may lead to inadequate
      antiretroviral (ARV) absorption and or erratic drug levels. The greater surface area to
      weight ratio in severely malnourished children could also place them at higher risk of under
      dosing compared to children with mild to moderate malnutrition.  The paucity of ARV
      pharmacokinetic (PK) data in these vulnerable severely malnourished children speaks to the
      need to determine the PKs of ARVs and the most appropriate time to initiate HAART in this
      group of children.  This study will utilize the recommended weight band dosing which
      simplifies dosing in resource limited settings and is the approach used in the WHO pediatric
      ARV dosing guidelines. It will also use pediatric formulations which have not been studied
      before in severely malnourished children. The findings of this study will determine the PK
      of HAART in this population with the overall goal of determining whether the current
      recommended doses are optimum doses for severely malnourished children and the most
      appropriate time to initiate HAART in the severely malnourished child.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety/ tolerability of ZDV, 3TC and Lopinavir/ritonavir (LPV/r) in severely and normal/mild malnourished children</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 12 and 24 weeks after initiation of HAART</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>numbers (percent) of subjects with at least Grade 3 adverse events related to study drugs and at least Grade 3 adverse events  regardless of the relationship to study drugs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK exposure comparison between severely malnourished children with children with normal/mild malnutrition</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks after initiation of HAART</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Steady-state Area under the curve (AUC) and plasma clearance (CL/F) for ZDV, 3TC, and LPV/r</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimum concentration comparison between severely malnourished children with children with normal/mild malnutrition</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 4, 8, 12, 16, 24, 36 and 48 weeks after initiation of HAART</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To compare the minimum trough concentration of LPV/r between severely malnourished children and children with normal nutrition - mild malnutrition at 1, 4, 8, 12, 16, 24, 36 and 48 weeks following initiation of HAART</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>LPV protein binding comparison between severely malnourished children with children with normal/mild malnutrition</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 12 and 24 weeks after initiation of HAART</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To investigate the impact of malnutrition on LPV protein binding by comparing the free fraction of LPV in severely malnourished children and children with normal nutrition - mild malnutrition at 1, 12 and 24 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Positive</condition>
  <condition>Malnourished</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Severe Malnutrition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Both arms got the ZDV+3TC+LPV/r combination drugs. Zidovudine (ZDV, Retrovir®) will be in a glycerin/sucrose base at a concentration of 10 mg/ml, administered two times daily orally at the WHO weight band dose for 48 weeks.
Lamivudine oral solution (Epivir®, 3TC) is for oral administration. One milliliter (1 mL) of lamivudine oral solution contains 10 mg of lamivudine (10 mg/mL), administered two times daily orally at the WHO weight band dose for 48 weeks.
Lopinavir 80 mg/ritonavir 20 mg per milliliter oral solution (Kaletra®, LPV/r) contains 42.4% alcohol by volume,  administered two times daily orally at the WHO weight band dose for 48 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Nutrition/Mild Malnutrition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Both arms got the ZDV+3TC+LPV/r combination drugs. Zidovudine (ZDV, Retrovir®) will be in a glycerin/sucrose base at a concentration of 10 mg/ml, administered two times daily orally at the WHO weight band dose for 48 weeks.
Lamivudine oral solution (Epivir®, 3TC) is for oral administration. One milliliter (1 mL) of lamivudine oral solution contains 10 mg of lamivudine (10 mg/mL), administered two times daily orally at the WHO weight band dose for 48 weeks.
Lopinavir 80 mg/ritonavir 20 mg per milliliter oral solution (Kaletra®, LPV/r) contains 42.4% alcohol by volume,  administered two times daily orally at the WHO weight band dose for 48 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ZDV+3TC+LPV/r</intervention_name>
    <description>Zidovudine (ZDV, Retrovir®) will be in a glycerin/sucrose base at a concentration of 10 mg/ml, two times daily orally at the WHO weight band dose for 48 weeks Lamivudine oral solution (Epivir®, 3TC) is for oral administration. One milliliter (1 mL) of lamivudine oral solution contains 10 mg of lamivudine (10 mg/mL), two times daily orally at the WHO weight band dose for 48 weeks Lopinavir 80 mg/ritonavir 20 mg per milliliter oral solution (Kaletra®, LPV/r) contains 42.4% alcohol by volume,  two times daily orally at the WHO weight band dose for 48 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Severe Malnutrition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Nutrition/Mild Malnutrition</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &gt;6 to &lt;36 months at entry

          2. Documentation of HIV-1 infection defined as positive results from two samples
             collected at different time points. The same method may be used at both time points.
             All samples tested must be whole blood, serum or plasma.

             Acceptable tests when subjects are ≤18 months of age the first test may be any of the
             following:

               -  One HIV DNA Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR)

               -  One HIV RNA  (quantitative &gt;5,000 copies/mL or qualitative)

               -  One HIV culture (prior to August 2009)

               -  One total HIV nucleic acid If the first test(s) is positive, a second sample
                  collected and tested using any of the tests listed above (except for qualitative
                  RNA assays) in a laboratory participating in an appropriate external quality
                  assurance program and NIH approved.

             Acceptable tests when subjects are &gt; 18 months of age

             The first test may be any of the following:

               -  Two rapid antibody tests from different manufacturers or based on different
                  principles and epitopes

               -  One rapid antibody test AND one [enzyme immunoassay (EIA) OR Western blot (WB)
                  OR immunofluorescence OR chemiluminescence]

               -  One EIA AND one [WB OR immunofluorescence OR chemiluminescence]

               -  One HIV DNA PCR

               -  One HIV RNA (quantitative &gt;5,000 copies/mL or qualitative)

               -  One HIV culture (prior to August 2009)

               -  One total HIV nucleic acid

             If the first test(s) is positive, a second sample collected and tested using any of
             the tests listed above (except for qualitative RNA assays) a laboratory participating
             in an appropriate external quality assurance program and either College of American
             Pathologists (CAP)/Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA) approved (for US
             laboratories) or NIH-approved (for international laboratories).

          3. WHO classification for severe malnutrition (non-edematous) and normal nutrition
             status and mild malnutrition  as described below:

               -  Severe malnutrition defined as weight for height z (WHZ) score  ≤-3 Standard
                  Deviations.

               -  Normal nutrition status defined as weight for height z (WHZ)  score &gt;-1 Standard
                  Deviations.

               -  Mild malnutrition defined as weight for height z (WHZ) score &gt;-2 Standard
                  Deviations ≤-1 Standard Deviations.

          4. Antiretroviral naïve except for ARVs used for prevention of  mother-to-child
             transmission of HIV.

          5. Children with acute serious infection must have been stabilized by at least five days
             on antimicrobials.

          6. Eligible for HAART as defined by WHO pediatric guidelines  described below for
             infants and children:

               -  Initiate ART for all HIV-infected children below 24 months of age irrespective
                  of cluster of differentiation 4 (CD4)count or WHO clinical stage.

               -  Initiate ART for all HIV-infected children between 24 and 59 months of age with
                  CD4 count ≤750 cells/mm3 or % CD4 ≤ 25%, whichever is lower, irrespective of WHO
                  clinical stage.

               -  Initiate ART for all HIV-infected children with WHO HIV clinical stages 3 and 4,
                  irrespective of CD4 count.

          7. Parent or legal guardian able and willing to provide signed informed consent, remain
             within the study area during the study period and agree to have subject followed at
             the clinical site

          8. For severely malnourished children: Clinical improvement after 10 -18 days on
             nutrition rehabilitation defined as: Appetite returned and eating better - child
             shows interest in food even if does not complete amount given:

               -  Weight gain of about 3-5gm/kg body weight/day for 1-2 days

               -  Normalized electrolytes (sodium and potassium)

               -  No evidence of cardiac failure

               -  Loss of apathy and starting to play

               -  Temperature stable - no hypothermia or pyrexia

             For children with normal - mild malnutrition, clinical stability will be indicated
             by:

               -  Good appetite

               -  Normalized electrolytes (sodium and potassium)

               -  Temperature stable - no hypothermia (&lt;35°C) or pyrexia (&gt;37.8° C)

          9. An inpatient in the nutrition rehabilitation unit

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Children with edematous malnutrition at the time of study entry

          2. The following laboratory values within 30 days prior to entry:

               -  Any  ≥ Grade 2 toxicity (except hemoglobin)

               -  Hemoglobin &lt;7.5g/dL

          3. ≥ Grade 3 respiratory distress or presence of cardio respiratory compromise

          4. Chemotherapy for active malignancy

          5. Children with an acute Opportunistic Infection (OI) and on appropriate treatment for
             &lt;5 days

          6. Active tuberculosis disease

          7. Evidence of hepatitis demonstrated by either positive hepatitis B surface antigen or
             clinical hepatitis as evidenced by jaundice and hepatomegaly

          8. Taking any disallowed medications

          9. Any condition, situation, or clinical finding that in the opinion of the investigator
             would place the child at an unacceptable level of risk for injury, or render the
             child/caregiver(s) unable to meet the requirements of the study, interfere with study
             participation, or in the interpretation of study results.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>36 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maxensia O Owor, M.B.Ch.B., MMED</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>International Maternal Pediatric Adolescent AIDS Clinical Trials Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Philippa Musoke, MBChB, PhD</last_name>
    <email>pmusoke@mujhu.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kilimanjaro Christian Medical CRS (12901)</name>
      <address>
        <city>IDC Research Offices</city>
        <state>Moshi</state>
        <country>Tanzania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cynthia Asiyo</last_name>
      <phone>255-68-6113653</phone>
      <email>casiyo@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ann Buchanan, M.D., M.P.H., DTM&amp;H</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Makerere University - JHU Research Collaboration (30293)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kampala</city>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Irene Lubega, MBChB, DTM&amp;H, MMed</last_name>
      <phone>256 712 222290</phone>
      <email>ilubega@mujhu.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mary G. Fowler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UZ-Parirenyatwa CRS (30313)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Harare</city>
        <country>Zimbabwe</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jimijika Batani, BA</last_name>
      <phone>263-7-72272818</phone>
      <email>jbatani@uz-ucsf.co.zw</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Hakim, MBChB., MMed. MMedSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Tanzania</country>
    <country>Uganda</country>
    <country>Zimbabwe</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 12, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Children</keyword>
  <keyword>Positive</keyword>
  <keyword>Malnourished</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Seropositivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malnutrition</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Zidovudine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lamivudine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ritonavir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lopinavir</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
