<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="63803">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01957137</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1670</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01957137</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>InterStim® Sacral Nerve Modulation Cycling Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>InterStim® Sacral Nerve Modulation Cycling Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MedtronicNeuro</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MedtronicNeuro</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study will assess the effects of different InterStim cycling settings on urinary urge
      incontinence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This feasibility study will assess the following outcomes:

        -  Voiding diaries

        -  Patient reported assessments of response or satisfaction

        -  Adverse events
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of urinary urge incontinent episodes per day</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of pads used per day</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported assessment of response</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Degree of urgency for each incontinent episode</measure>
    <time_frame>4 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Urinary Urge Incontinence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Continuous</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The device parameter will be continuous.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cycling Parameter #1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The device parameter will be cyclic program #1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cycling Parameter #2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The device parameter will be cyclic program #2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cycling Parameter #3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The device parameter will be cyclic program #3.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>InterStim® (Device Programming)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Continuous</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cycling Parameter #1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cycling Parameter #2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cycling Parameter #3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Implanted with either Neurostimulator Model 3023 (InterStim) or Neurostimulator Model
             3058 (InterStim II) for at least 3 months

          -  Implanted with tined lead models 3889 or 3093

          -  Tined lead is located at S3 as determined by sensory and motor responses and/or x-ray
             or fluoroscopy and/or compound muscle action potential (CMAP) recordings

          -  Currently showing some efficacy with an InterStim device but has the potential to be
             optimized per the opinion of the Investigator

          -  Primary diagnosis before InterStim implant is urinary urge incontinence over the
             voiding diary reporting period.  The diary reporting period must be at least 2 days

          -  Must be willing to maintain her current regimen (dosage and frequency) of any
             overactive bladder (OAB) medication (anticholinergic or antimuscarinic) or tricyclic
             antidepression medication over the study duration, if applicable.  The term
             &quot;medication&quot; throughout the protocol refers to OAB and/or tricyclic antidepression
             medications.

          -  Female subject 18 years of age or older

          -  Willing and able to accurately complete voiding diaries and questionnaires, attend
             visits (within the visit windows +7 days), and comply with the study protocol that
             includes maintenance of InterStim programming settings over the course of the study

          -  Have not been reprogrammed in the past 28 days

          -  Able to consent to participate by signing the Informed Consent Form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of Multiple sclerosis

          -  History of Reiter's syndrome

          -  History of spinal cord injury or a cerebral vascular accident (CVA)

          -  History of diabetes

          -  Active symptomatic urinary tract infection (UTI)

          -  Stress incontinence as the primary diagnosis

          -  Urgency frequency as a primary diagnosis

          -  Pelvic pain of uncertain etiology that is not associated with a voiding dysfunction
             or where pelvic pain is the primary complaint/diagnosis

          -  Interstitial cystitis as the primary diagnosis

          -  Urinary retention  as the primary diagnosis

          -  Treatment of urinary symptoms with botulinum toxin in the past 12 months or any plan
             to have botulinum toxin treatment during the study

          -  Bilateral lead placement

          -  Have other implantable neurostimulator, pacemaker, or defibrillator

          -  Have knowledge of planned diathermy, microwave exposure, high output ultrasonic
             exposure, RF energy exposure, or MRI scans not included within the scanning
             conditions provided within the MRI Guidelines for InterStim Therapy neurostimulation
             systems.

          -  Have an anticipated system modification within the next 5 months

          -  Women who are pregnant or planning to become pregnant (women of child-bearing
             potential must undergo a pregnancy test, with a clear negative result, no more than 7
             days prior to randomization visit)

          -  Subjects who frequently use the patient programmer to change device program settings
             (&quot;frequently&quot; is defined as at least once a day and does not include shutting off the
             device for safety purposes)

          -  Characteristics indicating a poor understanding of the study or characteristics that
             indicate the subject may have poor compliance with the study protocol.

          -  Study site personnel will contact the Medtronic Study Manager (or designee) to
             determine if a potential subject who plans to enroll in an investigational device or
             drug trial, or is currently enrolled in an investigational device or drug trial is
             eligible for this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven W Siegel, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Metro Urology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>InterStim Cycling Clinical Research Study Team</last_name>
    <email>medtronicneurotrials@medtronic.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Metro Urology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Woodbury</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55125</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amundsen CL, Romero AA, Jamison MG, Webster GD. Sacral neuromodulation for intractable urge incontinence: are there factors associated with cure? Urology. 2005 Oct;66(4):746-50.</citation>
    <PMID>16230129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janknegt RA, Weil EH, Eerdmans PH. Improving neuromodulation technique for refractory voiding dysfunctions: two-stage implant. Urology. 1997 Mar;49(3):358-62.</citation>
    <PMID>9123698</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peters KM, Killinger KA, Ibrahim IA, Villalba PS. The relationship between subjective and objective assessments of sacral neuromodulation effectiveness in patients with urgency-frequency. Neurourol Urodyn. 2008;27(8):775-8. doi: 10.1002/nau.20592.</citation>
    <PMID>18551573</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scheepens WA, Jongen MM, Nieman FH, de Bie RA, Weil EH, van Kerrebroeck PE. Predictive factors for sacral neuromodulation in chronic lower urinary tract dysfunction. Urology. 2002 Oct;60(4):598-602.</citation>
    <PMID>12385915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidt RA, Jonas U, Oleson KA, Janknegt RA, Hassouna MM, Siegel SW, van Kerrebroeck PE. Sacral nerve stimulation for treatment of refractory urinary urge incontinence. Sacral Nerve Stimulation Study Group. J Urol. 1999 Aug;162(2):352-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10411037</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siegel SW, Catanzaro F, Dijkema HE, Elhilali MM, Fowler CJ, Gajewski JB, Hassouna MM, Janknegt RA, Jonas U, van Kerrebroeck PE, Lycklama a Nijeholt AA, Oleson KA, Schmidt RA. Long-term results of a multicenter study on sacral nerve stimulation for treatment of urinary urge incontinence, urgency-frequency, and retention. Urology. 2000 Dec 4;56(6 Suppl 1):87-91.</citation>
    <PMID>11114569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Kerrebroeck PE, van Voskuilen AC, Heesakkers JP, Lycklama á Nijholt AA, Siegel S, Jonas U, Fowler CJ, Fall M, Gajewski JB, Hassouna MM, Cappellano F, Elhilali MM, Milam DF, Das AK, Dijkema HE, van den Hombergh U. Results of sacral neuromodulation therapy for urinary voiding dysfunction: outcomes of a prospective, worldwide clinical study. J Urol. 2007 Nov;178(5):2029-34. Epub 2007 Sep 17.</citation>
    <PMID>17869298</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burks FN, Diokno AC, Lajiness MJ, Ibrahim IA, Peters KM. Sacral neuromodulation reprogramming: is it an office burden? Int Urogynecol J Pelvic Floor Dysfunct. 2008 Aug;19(8):1137-40. doi: 10.1007/s00192-008-0601-3. Epub 2008 Apr 5.</citation>
    <PMID>18392551</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maxwell KM, Clemens JQ, Mazzenga L, Kielb SJ. Reprogramming requirements after sacral nerve stimulator implantation: correlation with preoperative indication. J Urol. 2008 Feb;179(2):549-51.</citation>
    <PMID>18076913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tai C, Shen B, Wang J, Chancellor MB, Roppolo JR, de Groat WC. Inhibitory and excitatory perigenital-to-bladder spinal reflexes in the cat. Am J Physiol Renal Physiol. 2008 Mar;294(3):F591-602. Epub 2007 Dec 26.</citation>
    <PMID>18160624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Woock JP, Yoo PB, Grill WM. Activation and inhibition of the micturition reflex by penile afferents in the cat. Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol. 2008 Jun;294(6):R1880-9. doi: 10.1152/ajpregu.00029.2008. Epub 2008 Apr 23.</citation>
    <PMID>18434446</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Su X, Nickles A, Nelson DE. Neuromodulation in a rat model of the bladder micturition reflex. Am J Physiol Renal Physiol. 2012 Feb 15;302(4):F477-86. doi: 10.1152/ajprenal.00515.2011. Epub 2011 Nov 2.</citation>
    <PMID>22049401</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jiang CH, Lindström S. Prolonged increase in micturition threshold volume by anogenital afferent stimulation in the rat. Br J Urol. 1998 Sep;82(3):398-403.</citation>
    <PMID>9772878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tai C, Shen B, Chen M, Wang J, Roppolo JR, de Groat WC. Prolonged poststimulation inhibition of bladder activity induced by tibial nerve stimulation in cats. Am J Physiol Renal Physiol. 2011 Feb;300(2):F385-92. doi: 10.1152/ajprenal.00526.2010. Epub 2010 Nov 24.</citation>
    <PMID>21106856</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 18, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Urinary</keyword>
  <keyword>Urge</keyword>
  <keyword>Incontinence</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Incontinence, Urge</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
