<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="147930">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01788787</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-1112</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01788787</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ask Advise Connect (AAC) Harris Heath CPRIT</brief_title>
  <official_title>Implementation of an Automated EMR System to Connect Smokers in a Safety Net Healthcare System With Smoking Cessation Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cancer Therapy and Research Center, Texas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objectives:

      The focus of this project is on enhancing utilization of an existing evidence-based smoking
      cessation resource, the Texas Quitline, among low socioeconomic status (SES) and
      racial/ethnic minority smokers with limited access to resources for quitting.

      Specific Aim 1: Evaluate the reach of Ask Advise Connect (AAC) dissemination approach among
      racially/ethnically diverse, underserved smokers recruited through the 13 Harris Health
      System community health clinics. Reach is defined as the proportion of smokers that enroll
      in treatment with the Quitline.

      Specific Aim 2: Evaluate the efficacy of AAC dissemination approach. Efficacy is defined as
      the proportion of smokers who agree to be connected to the Quitline that enroll in treatment
      who successfully achieve abstinence assessed 6 months following treatment enrollment.

      Our primary outcome of interest is 7-day point prevalence abstinence. However, we will also
      examine other definitions of abstinence including 24-hour point prevalence, 30 day point
      prevalence, and continuous abstinence.

      Specific Aim 3:  Evaluate the real-world impact of an AAC dissemination approach. Impact =
      Reach x Efficacy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants:

      Study Test:

      If you agree to take part in this study, you will collect a saliva sample to test for
      cotinine to confirm your smoking status.  Cotinine is a chemical released in your body when
      it breaks down nicotine.  You will receive a kit in the mail with supplies for the testing.
      The study staff will call you to make sure that you received the kit and to discuss the
      instructions with you.  To collect the saliva, you will put a small piece of cotton in your
      mouth for a few minutes.  You will mail the saliva sample back to the study staff, using a
      postage-paid envelope.

      Length of Study:

      Your participation in this study will be complete after you collect the saliva sample and
      mail it back to the study staff. Study data will be destroyed 5 years after the study has
      been completed and the data has been analyzed. Data collected in this study will not be used
      for future research.

      This is an investigational study.

      Up to 1,459 participants will be enrolled in this study.  All will be enrolled at Harris
      Health System clinics.

      Harris Health System Staff:

      If you agree to take part in the interview, you will be asked about your thoughts about
      factors that may help or interfere with carrying out the Ask Advise Connect program (such as
      time demands, resistance from patients and/or co-workers, or concerns about the
      effectiveness of Quitline counseling).  This interview should take about 45 minutes.

      Interviews will be audio-recorded, and the recordings will be sent to an outside company to
      be transcribed (spoken words will be copied down in written form).  Before your recording is
      sent to the outside company, your name and any personal identifying information will be
      coded to protect your privacy.  The transcripts and audio recordings will be encrypted and
      password-protected.  The audio recordings will be erased once the data have been published.

      Interview Data:

      Your responses will not be shared with your colleagues or anyone except the research staff
      at MD Anderson.

      Length of Study:

      Your participation in this study will be over after you complete the interview. Study data
      will be destroyed 5 years after the study has been completed and the data has been analyzed.
      Data collected in this study will not be used for future research.

      This is an investigational study.

      Up to 50 participants will be enrolled in this part of the study.  All will take part at
      Harris Health System clinics.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2049</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the Reach of Ask Advise Connect (AAC) Smoking Cessation Program</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Reach defined as the proportion of smokers that enroll in treatment with the Quitline. To evaluate the reach of AAC, we will calculate the proportion of smokers seen at the 13 Harris Health System community health clinics  during the two-year treatment dissemination period that enroll in treatment with the Quitline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of Ask Advise Connect (AAC) Smoking Cessation Program</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Efficacy is defined as the proportion of smokers who agree to be connected to the Quitline that enroll in treatment who successfully achieve abstinence assessed 6 months following treatment enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5212</enrollment>
  <condition>Tobacco Use Cessation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Texas Quitline</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients interested in smoking cessation treatment by calling the Texas Quitline.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Training Providers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Medical staff (i.e., medical assistants, licensed vocational nurses, registered nurse and physicians).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quitline-Delivered Proactive Telephone Counseling</intervention_name>
    <description>Smokers who enroll in treatment receive standard counseling protocol offered by the Quitline. This includes up to five proactive telephone counseling calls, each designed to provide practical expert support to help smokers develop problem-solving and coping skills, secure social support, and design a plan for successful cessation and long-term abstinence.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Texas Quitline</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Follow-Up Phone Call</intervention_name>
    <description>Six months after enrolling in treatment with the Texas Quitline, an MD Anderson research team member will contact patients to assess their smoking status via telephone.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Texas Quitline</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Smoking Cessation Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Medical staff (i.e., medical assistants, licensed vocational nurses, registered nurse and physicians) receive initial face-to-face group training on how to ask patients about their smoking status, advise them to quit, and connect them with the Quitline. The specific content of the session will include information on quitting smoking, how to implement AAC, the effectiveness of telephone counseling for smoking cessation delivered via quitlines, and pharmacotherapies including nicotine replacement.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Training Providers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Qualitative Interviews Concerning the Implementation of AAC</intervention_name>
    <description>MD Anderson staff conduct individual in-depth interviews with administrative leadership as well as those medical staff who are authorized to enter patient information into the EMR and are trained in the Ask-Advise-Connect approach.  All in-depth interviews will be recorded and transcribed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Training Providers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Saliva sample to test for cotinine.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients from the Harris Health System Community Health Clinics
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 18 years of age or older

          2. Self-reported current smoker

          3. Present for care at one of the 13 Harris Health System (HHS) community clinics

          4. Has a working telephone number

        Exclusion Criteria:

        1) None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer I. Vidrine, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer I. Vidrine, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>713-745-2383</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harris Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cancer Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Tobacco Use Cessation</keyword>
  <keyword>Ask Advise Connect</keyword>
  <keyword>AAC</keyword>
  <keyword>Smoking Cessation Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Texas Quitline</keyword>
  <keyword>Saliva sample</keyword>
  <keyword>Telephone Counseling</keyword>
  <keyword>Nicotine replacement</keyword>
  <keyword>Interviews</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tobacco Use Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
