<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="11618">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01931306</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1200.193</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01931306</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Expanded Access Study of Afatinib in Treatment-naive or Chemotherapy Pre-treated Patients With Non-small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC)</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Label Expanded Access Program of Afatinib (BIBW 2992) in Treatment-naive or Chemotherapy Pre-treated Patients With Locally Advanced or Metastatic Non-small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) Harboring EGFR Mutation(s)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boehringer Ingelheim</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boehringer Ingelheim</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>South Korea: Ministry of Food and Drug Safety (MFDS)</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To provide expanded access and to evaluate the safety, tolerability and efficacy of afatinib
      in patients with locally advanced or metastatic non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) harboring
      Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor (EGFR) mutation(s) and have never been treated with an EGFR
      tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Available</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Expanded Access</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <condition>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Afatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>BIBW2992 low to medium dose once daily</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          1. locally advanced or metastatic Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer

          2. Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor mutation positive result per the institution's
             testing methodology. Any type of EGFR mutation allowed

          3. Treatment naïve or patients who have received one line of chemotherapy, chemotherapy
             include neo adjuvant and adjuvant chemotherapy within 1 year from enrolment

          4. male or female patients age more than 18 years

          5. Adequate organ function, defined as all of the following:

               1. Absolute Neutrophil Count over 1500 per mm3. ANC over 1000 per mm3 may be
                  considered in special circumstances such as benign cyclical neutropenia as
                  judged by the investigator and in discussion with the sponsor.

               2. Platelet count more than 75,000 per mm3

               3. Serum creatinine below 1.5 times of the upper limit of normal

               4. Total Bilirubin below 1.5 times upper limit of institutional normal. Patients
                  with Gilbert's syndrome total bilirubin must be below 4 times institutional
                  upper limit of normal.

               5. Aspartate Amino Transferase or Alanine Amino Transferase below three times the
                  upper limit of normal, if related to liver metastases below five times ULN.

          6. ECOG score between 0 - 2

          7. written informed consent by patient or guardian prior to admission into the trial
             that is consistent with International Conference on Harmonisation - Good Clinical
             Practice guidelines and local law.

        Exclusion criteria:

          1. prior treatment with an EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitor

          2. hormonal anti-cancer treatment within 2 weeks prior to start of trial treatment
             ,continued use of anti androgens and or gonadorelin analogues for treatment of
             prostate cancer permitted

          3. radiotherapy within 14 days prior to drug administration, except as follows:

               1. Palliative radiation to organs other than chest may be allowed up to 2 weeks
                  prior to drug administration, and

               2. Single dose palliative treatment for symptomatic metastasis outside above
                  allowance to be discussed with sponsor prior to enrolling.

          4. major surgery within 4 weeks before starting trial treatment or scheduled for surgery
             during the projected course of the trial

          5. known hypersensitivity to afatinib or any of its excipients

          6. history or presence of clinically relevant cardiovascular abnormalities such as
             uncontrolled hypertension, congestive heart failure New York Heart Association
             classification of over 3, unstable angina or poorly controlled arrhythmia as
             determined by the investigator. Myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to
             starting trial treatment.

          7. Women of Child-Bearing Potential and men who are able to father a child, unwilling to
             use adequate contraception prior to trial entry, for the duration of trial
             participation and for at least 2 weeks after treatment has ended.

          8. childbearing potential who:

               1. are nursing or

               2. are pregnant or

               3. are not using an acceptable method of birth control, or do not plan to continue
                  using this method throughout the trial and,or do not agree to submit to
                  pregnancy testing required by this protocol

          9. any history of or concomitant condition that, in the opinion of the investigator,
             would compromise the patient's ability to comply with the trial or interfere with the
             evaluation of safety for the trial drug

         10. previous or concomitant malignancies at other sites, except effectively treated
             non-melanoma skin cancers, carcinoma in situ of the cervix, ductal carcinoma in situ
             or effectively treated malignancy that has been in remission for more than 3 years
             and is considered to be cured.

         11. requiring treatment with any of the prohibited concomitant medications that can not
             be stopped for the duration of trial participation

         12. known pre-existing interstitial lung disease

         13. presence of poorly controlled gastrointestinal disorders that could affect the
             absorption of the trial drug

         14. active hepatitis B infection, active Hepatitis C infection

         15. meningeal carcinomatosis

         16. symptomatic brain metastases, patients with asymptomatic brain metastases, who were
             previously treated, are eligible provided they have had Stable Disease for at least 4
             weeks on stable doses of medication
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Boehringer Ingelheim</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Boehringer Ingelheim</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Boehringer Ingelheim Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-800-243-0127</phone>
    <email>clintriage.rdg@boehringer-ingelheim.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>1200.193.82003 Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bucheon</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>1200.193.82009 Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Busan</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>1200.193.82001 Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Incheon</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>1200.193.82010 Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jeonnam</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>1200.193.82002 Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jinju</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>1200.193.82004 Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seongnam</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>1200.193.82007 Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>1200.193.82008 Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>1200.193.82005 Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>1200.193.82006 Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
