<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="164988">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02136797</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-070</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02136797</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Third Party Donor Derived CMVpp65 Specific T-cells for The Treatment of CMV Infection or Persistent CMV Viremia After Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial of Third Party Donor Derived CMVpp65 Specific T-cells for The Treatment of CMV Infection or Persistent CMV Viremia After Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to see how well transfusions of T-cells work in treating CMV.
      Tcells are a type of white blood cell that helps protect the body from infection. A
      transfusion is the process by which blood from one person is transferred to the blood of
      another. In this case, the T-cells are made from the blood of donors who are immune to CMV.
      The T-cells are then grown and taught to attack the CMV virus in a lab.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>complete response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>defined as the clearance of the CMV infection 3-7 weeks following completion of the last cycle of CMV CTLs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>safety</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be capturing and tracking Grade 3-5 toxicities which occur within 30 days following an infusion of CMVpp65-specific.  For the evaluation of toxicities, the NCI Standard Toxicity Scale 4.0 will be employed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">41</enrollment>
  <condition>CMV Infection</condition>
  <condition>Persistent CMV Viremia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CMVpp65-CTL  T-cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The T-cells to be infused will be selected based on criteria mentioned in section 4.0 from our bank of GMP grade CMVpp65-CTL. T-cells will be administered by bolus intravenous infusion. In this phase II trial, patients will be treated at doses of 1 x 106 CMVpp65-CTL/kg/dose/week for 3 weeks. Patients will be observed for the following 3 weeks. Additional 3 week courses of CMVpp65-CTL may be administered if levels of CMV DNA in blood are still detectable despite disease stabilization or improvement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CMVpp65 Specific T-cells</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>CMVpp65-CTL  T-cells</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Each patient must satisfy at least one of the following criteria:

               1. The patient must have a clinically documented condition associated with CMV
                  (e.g. interstitial pneumonia, hepatitis, retinitis, colitis) Or

               2. The patient must have microbiological evidence of CMV viremia or tissue invasion
                  as attested by viral culture, or detection of levels of CMV DNA in the blood or
                  body fluids consistent with CMV infection.

        Patient must also satisfy at least one of the following criteria:

          1. The patient's CMV infection is clinically progressing or CMV viremia is persistent or
             increasing (as evidenced by quantitation of CMV DNA in the blood) despite two weeks
             induction therapy with antiviral drugs.

             Or

          2. The patient has developed CMV viremia as attested by viral culture, or detection of
             levels of CMV DNA in blood or body fluids while receiving prophylactic doses of
             antiviral drugs to prevent CMV infection post transplant.

        Or c. The patient is unable to sustain treatment with antiviral drugs due to drug
        associated toxicities (e.g. myelosuppression [ANC&lt; 1000μl/ml without GCSF support] or
        nephrotoxicity [corrected creatinine clearance ≤ 60 ml/min/1.73 m2 or serum creatinine &gt; 2
        mg/dl]) CMV infections are life threatening, and may involve multiple organ systems such
        as the lungs, liver, gastrointestinal tract, hematopoietic and central nervous systems.
        Antiviral drugs used for treatment may also compromise renal and hematopoietic function.
        Therefore, dysfunctions of these organs will not affect eligibility for this protocol.

        4. Patients must meet the following clinical criteria to receive CMVpp65-CTL infusions

          1. Stable blood pressure and circulation, not requiring pressor support

          2. Evidence of adequate cardiac function as demonstrated by EKG and/or echocardiography.

          3. A life expectancy of at least 3 weeks, even if requiring artificial ventilation.

          4. There are no age restrictions The patient's HCT donor has not been previously
             infected by or sensitized to CMV (e.g. a cord blood transplant or a marrow or PBSC
             transplant from a seronegative donor).

        The patient's HCT donor, if seropositive, is either not available or not willing to
        provide leukocytes for generation of CMV-specific T-cells.

        b. There are CMVpp65-specific T-cells available in appropriate doses in the MSKCC Adoptive
        Immune T-cell Therapy Bank that are matched with the patient for 2 HLA alleles and that
        exhibit CMVpp65-specific cytotoxic activity that is restricted by an HLA allele shared by
        the patient

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients requiring high doses of glucocorticosteroids (≥ 0.3 mg/kg prednisone or its
             equivalent)

          -  Patients who are moribund

          -  Patients with other conditions not related to CMV infection (e.g. uncontrolled
             bacterial sepsis or invasive fungal infection) which are also life-threatening and
             which would preclude evaluation of the effects of a T-cell infusion.

          -  Patients who are pregnant Donors in Group 1 (Historical Donors) Donors in Group 1
             would have already been determined to be eligible and will have donated blood or
             leukocytes to establish CMV-specific T-cells under IRB # 05-065, 07-055, 95-024, or
             11-130. There are no additional eligibility requirements for these donors.

        Donor Inclusion Criteria (Prospective Donors):

        Transplant donors and healthy HLA typed volunteers who  give written consent to provide
        Tcells for Third-party donation (section 5.1, Groups 2 and 3),  will need to meet the
        following eligibility requirements prior to donation:

          1. Donors must satisfy the criteria specified in FDA 21 CFR 1271.

          2. Donors must be typed for HLA-A, B, C and DR at high resolution

          3. Donors must have a hemoglobin value &gt; 10g/dl

          4. Donors must be capable of undergoing, at least, a single standard 2 blood volume
             leukapheresis or a donation of one unit of whole blood

        Donor Exclusion Criteria:

          -  HTLV/HIV(+) or Hepatitis B or C antigen(+) donors

          -  Donors who are known CMV seronegative
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard O'Reilly, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard O'Reilly, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-5957</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Aisha Hasan, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-3267</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard O'Reilly, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-5957</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Aisha Hasan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-3267</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard O'Reilly, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 9, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CMVpp65 Specific T-cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>14-070</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cytomegalovirus Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Viremia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
