<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="55315">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01887132</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130164</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-M-0164</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01887132</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Trial of the Drug Donepezil for Sleep Enhancement and Behavioral Change in Children With Autism</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial of Donepezil for REM Enhancement and Behavioral Change in Autism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Some children with autism spectrum disorders (ASD) do not have normal sleep cycles. Some
      of these children spend very little time in the    rapid eye movement (REM)    stage of
      sleep. Some studies suggest that less time in REM sleep can be associated with learning and
      behavior problems. Donepezil is a medication used to treat Alzheimer   s disease.  Donepezil
      can increase REM sleep in some adults with different disorders. A small study showed that
      Donepezil can also increase REM sleep in children with ASD. Researchers now want to see if
      Donepezil can improve communication skills and social interaction in children with ASD. They
      also want to see if any change in symptoms seems to come from changes in REM sleep.

      Objectives:

      - To see if a medication, Donepezil, can improve the way communication skills and social
      interaction develop in young children with autism spectrum disorders.

      Eligibility:

      - Children 22 to 44 months of age with ASD.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a blood test, heart tests, and a sleep study. During
           the sleep study, children will sleep in a darkened room for 2 nights with electrodes on
           their body and a tube under their nose. Parents can sleep in the room with their child.
           A technician will monitor the room all night.

        -  Participants will take the study medication once a day.

        -  Treatment will be monitored at visits every 3 months. At each visit the participant
           will take blood tests, heart tests, or behavior tests. Participants will have 2 more
           sleep studies.

        -  Participation will end after 18 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      i. Objective

      The objective of this study is to investigate the efficacy of donepezil to improve the
      developmental trajectory for core behavioral domains specific to autism, namely reciprocal
      social interaction and communication.

      ii. Study population

      90 children with an autism spectrum disorder between the ages of 24 to 50 months will be
      screened via polysomnogram to find 45 with a relative REM deficiency. This group will then
      be divided into two arms of drug versus placebo. Allowing for a 22 % drop out rate we expect
      17 in each group to complete the study. Additionally, we will enroll 16 children with an ASD
      who do not meet criteria for relative REM deficiency in an open label arm to ascertain
      whether or not donepezil is beneficial to behavior in this group.

      iii. Design

      The proposal is for a 6 month treatment trial of 2.5 mg donepezil/placebo/day followed by 12
      months of longitudinal follow-up. The primary study endpoint will be an examination of
      autism core symptoms and sleep architecture after 12 months.

      iv. Outcome measures

      The primary outcome measure will be:

      An improvement in the Expressive Language and the Receptive Language subscales of the Mullen
      Scales of Early Learning (MSEL) at 12 months.

        1. Secondary outcome measures will be:

           An improvement in the Expressive Language and the Receptive Language subscales of the
           Mullen Scales at 18 months.

        2. An improvement on the severity scale of the Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule
           (ADOS) at 6, 12 and 18 months.

        3. An improvement on the Vineland at 3, 6, 12 and 18 months

        4. We will also measure the change in REM sleep parameters after 6, 12 and 18 months in
           relation to improvements in behavioral indices.

        5. An exploratory analysis will investigate whether normalization of REM parameters also
           improves other measurements of sleep quality in children with autism.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double-Blind, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>12Either an improvement in the Expressive Language and the Receptive Language subscales of the  Mullen Scales of Early Learning (MSEL)OR an improvement on the severity scale of the Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule (ADOS).</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>An exploratory analysis will investigate whether normalization of REM parameters also improves other measurements of sleep quality in children with autism.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in REM sleep parameters after 12 months in relation to improvements in behavioral indices.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Open-Label Donepezil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Donepezil - Blinded</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Donepezil</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Open-Label Donepezil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Donepezil - Blinded</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Diagnosis of an Autism Spectrum Disorder (DSM-IV diagnoses of autistic disorder
                  or Pervasive Developmental Disorder, Not Otherwise Specified).

               2. Male or Female subjects between the ages of 24 and 50 months.

               3. Language scores (from the Mullen Scales of Early Learning) that are at least 1.5
                  SD lower than the mean.

             5. Each legal guardian must have a level of understanding sufficient to agree to all
             required tests and examinations. Each legal guardian must understand the nature of
             the study.

             6. Each subject must be stable for at least 6 weeks on any medication or therapy
             regimen prior to entry into study and must have no newly (within 6 weeks) recognized
             or intolerable adverse effects from that medicine or therapy. No subjects will be
             asked to discontinue any medication in order to qualify for enrollment but subjects
             taking contraindicated drugs will not qualify for enrollment.

             7. Demonstrated REM% two standard deviations or more below the normative values for
             age for the randomized controlled trial part.

             8. English language is primarily spoken at home.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Serious, unstable illnesses including gastroenterologic, respiratory, cardiovascular
             endocrinologic, immunologic, or hematologic disease.

          2. Renal or hepatic dysfunction that would interfere with excretion or metabolism of
             donepezil as evidenced by increase above upper limits of normal for BUN/creatinine,
             or two-fold elevation of serum transaminases (ALT/SGPT, AST/SGOT) or gamma glutamate
             (GGT).

          3. Documented history of hypersensitivity or intolerance to donepezil or other
             piperidine derivative.

          4. Subjects must not be taking any medication known to affect REM sleep (or sleep

             architecture in general) or that is contraindicated for co-administration with
             donepezil.

          5. Presence or history of other unstable neurological disorders such as seizure
             disorders,

        metabolic disorders, narcolepsy or movement disorders.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>24 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ashura W Buckley, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Margaret J Pekar</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-1084</phone>
    <email>pekarm@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ashura W Buckley, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-5190</phone>
    <email>shu.buckley@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-M-0164.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson DK, Lord C, Risi S, DiLavore PS, Shulman C, Thurm A, Welch K, Pickles A. Patterns of growth in verbal abilities among children with autism spectrum disorder. J Consult Clin Psychol. 2007 Aug;75(4):594-604.</citation>
    <PMID>17663613</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson DK, Oti RS, Lord C, Welch K. Patterns of growth in adaptive social abilities among children with autism spectrum disorders. J Abnorm Child Psychol. 2009 Oct;37(7):1019-34. doi: 10.1007/s10802-009-9326-0.</citation>
    <PMID>19521762</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bliwise DL, Carroll JS, Lee KA, Nekich JC, Dement WC. Sleep and &quot;sundowning&quot; in nursing home patients with dementia. Psychiatry Res. 1993 Sep;48(3):277-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8272449</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sleep Architecture</keyword>
  <keyword>Autism</keyword>
  <keyword>Language Development</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Child Development Disorders, Pervasive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Donepezil</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
