<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35174">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01944020</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SLRH13-0119</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>DK26687-13-0119</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01944020</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of CPAP on Energy Expenditure and Energy Intake in Obstructive Sleep Apnea</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of CPAP on Energy Expenditure and Energy Intake in Obstructive Sleep Apnea</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is characterized by recurrent episodes of partial or complete
      loss of airflow during sleep, due to narrowing or closure of the upper airway. The resulting
      hypoxia has many cardiometabolic consequences, and leads to a disruption of sleep quality
      including reductions in the expression of rapid eye movement (REM) sleep and slow wave sleep
      (SWS). Patients also frequently experience excessive daytime sleepiness (EDS), which, when
      present with OSA, defines the clinical entity OSA syndrome (OSAS). Obesity is the leading
      risk factor for the development of OSA. Interestingly, it has been suggested that the
      disorder itself may contribute to further weight gain, presenting a vicious cycle wherein
      OSA and obesity perpetuate each other. OSAS may promote weight gain by placing patients in a
      state of positive energy balance characterized by low levels of physical activity and
      disrupted patterns of appetite-regulating hormones. Continuous positive airway pressure
      (CPAP), the gold-standard treatment of OSAS, may improve energy balance in these patients,
      although this has not yet been adequately studied. The current proposal is for a randomized,
      placebo-controlled, crossover trial investigating the effects of 2 months of active and sham
      CPAP on energy balance in obese patients with moderate-to-severe OSA and EDS. Patients will
      be instructed to use active or sham CPAP at home each night throughout the 2-month treatment
      phases. At the conclusion of each 2-month treatment phase, the investigators will measure
      levels of free-living physical activity, sleepiness, sleep quality, body composition, energy
      metabolism, appetite-regulating hormones, hunger, and ad libitum food intake. It is
      hypothesized that active compared to sham CPAP treatment will result in improvements in
      energy balance, including increased physical activity, reductions in abnormally high levels
      of sleeping metabolic rate and circulating leptin levels, and reductions in hunger and food
      intake. These improvements are hypothesized to be associated with increases in the
      expression of REM sleep and SWS, and reduced EDS as a result of CPAP.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will be a randomized, placebo-controlled, crossover trial investigating the
      effects of 2 mo of active and sham continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) on energy
      expenditure (EE) and energy intake (EI) in obese patients with moderate-to-severe
      obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) and excessive daytime sleepiness (EDS). Following
      pre-experimental baseline measures, patients (blinded to condition) will be instructed to
      use active or sham CPAP at home each night throughout the 2 mo treatment phases. After each
      2 mo treatment phase, patients will undergo a 2-d in-lab testing period at the Clinical
      Research Resource (CRR) at St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital. Upon completion of the laboratory
      phase 1, patients will return home for a 1 mo washout period, followed by the second 2 mo
      treatment phase, including laboratory visit 2.

      At the conclusion of the 2 mo treatment phase, patients will enter the laboratory at the CRR
      at St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital for a 2-d period. Patients will arrive at ~0800 h and will
      remain in the laboratory for the following 48 h. During the first 24 h, patients will remain
      in the whole-room indirect calorimetry chamber (metabolic chamber). During this time in the
      metabolic chamber, EE will be continuously monitored (total 24-h EE), including throughout
      the sleep episode (SMR), upon awakening in the fasted state (RMR), and after standard meals
      (postprandial EE). Blood will be sampled in the fasting state in the morning, and will be
      assayed for select appetite-regulating hormones (leptin, ghrelin, adiponectin, glucagon-like
      peptide-1).

      During the laboratory day 1, standardized meals for a weight maintenance diet will be served
      at fixed time-points, including breakfast (0900 h), lunch (1300 h), snack (1600 h), and
      dinner (1900 h). Ad libitum EI will be measured during laboratory day 2 for each treatment
      phase. Breakfast, lunch, snack, and dinner will still be served at the standard times, but
      each meal item will be served in excess such that patients will be able to eat as much or as
      little of each food as they choose. Additional snack choices will also be freely available
      during the wake episode on laboratory day 2.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Energy expenditure</measure>
    <time_frame>After 2 months of treatment in both experimental phases</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will remain in the whole-room indirect calorimetry chamber (metabolic chamber) for 23 hours during which time their total energy expenditure, as well as sleeping metabolic rate, and resting metabolic rate, will be measured.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ad libitum food intake</measure>
    <time_frame>After 2 months of treatment in both experimental phases</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will be served meals (breakfast, lunch, dinner, snack) at specified times, but food will be served in excess such that participants will be able to eat as much as they want.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Appetite-regulating hormones</measure>
    <time_frame>After 2 months of treatment in both experimental phases</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood will be sampled once in the morning in the fasted state to assay levels of circulating hormones that regulate appetite and hunger, including leptin, ghrelin, adiponectin, and glucagon-like peptide-1</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active CPAP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active CPAP will be a therapeutic dose of positive airway pressure each night for 2 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham CPAP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham CPAP will be a sub-therapeutic dose of positive airway pressure each night for 2 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Active CPAP</intervention_name>
    <description>Active CPAP will be a therapeutic dose CPAP each night for 2 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active CPAP</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham CPAP</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Sham CPAP</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sham CPAP will be a sub-therapeutic dose of CPAP each night for 2 months</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  clinical diagnosis of obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) and excessive daytime sleepiness
             (EDS)

          -  body mass index of at least 30 kg/m^2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  prior treatment with CPAP

          -  cannot be shift workers

          -  type 2 diabetes

          -  poorly controlled severe hypertension

          -  anemia

          -  currently taking anti-psychotic, anti-depressive, or hypnotic medications

          -  females currently taking hormone replacement therapy

          -  females who are pregnant or have given birth within 1 year
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ari Shechter, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New York Obesity Nutrition Research Center, St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ari Shechter, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>212-523-1616</phone>
    <email>ashechter@chpnet.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10025</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ari Shechter, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>212-523-1616</phone>
      <email>ashechter@chpnet.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ari Shechter, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</keyword>
  <keyword>Energy Balance</keyword>
  <keyword>Food Intake</keyword>
  <keyword>Energy Expenditure</keyword>
  <keyword>Sleep</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
