<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="26905">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02115815</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CD-VA-MEDI7510-1134</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02115815</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Safety of the Respiratory Syncytial Virus Vaccine MEDI7510 in Older Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1a Study to Evaluate the Safety of the Respiratory Syncytial Virus Vaccine MEDI7510 in Older Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MedImmune LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MedImmune LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if the administration of single ascending
      intramuscular doses of the RSV sF antigen or MEDI7510 will be safe and well tolerated in
      adults 60 years or older who are healthy or who have stable, chronic underlying medical
      conditions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A phase 1a, first time in human, double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, cohort
      escalation study evaluating the safety and tolerability of a single ascending intramuscular
      dose of RSV sF or MEDI7510 or placebo.

      Approximately 144 subjects will be enrolled at 3 US study centers and randomized in a 5:1
      ratio by cohort to receive a single dose of either  RSV sF or placebo or MEDI7510 on Day 1.

      Cohort 1: RSV sF formulation 1 (n=20) or placebo (n=4) Cohort 1a:  MEDI7510 formulation 1
      (n=20) or placebo (n=4) Cohort 2:  RSV sF (n=20) formulation 2 or placebo (n=4) Cohort 2a:
      MEDI7510 (n=20) formulation 2 or placebo (n=4) Cohort 3:  RSV sF (n=20) formulation 3 or
      placebo (n=4) Cohort 3a:  MEDI7510 (n=20) formulation 3 or placebo (n=4)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The occurence Solicited Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (dosing) through Day 7</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The following Solicited Symptoms will be recorded: Pain at the injection site; redness at the injection site; tenderness/soreness at the injection site; swelling at the injection site. Also assessed will be: Fever greater than/equal to 100.4F; headache; generalized muscle aches; fatigue or tiredness.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The occurence of Adverse Events and Serious Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (dosing) through Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of subjects experiencing adverse events/serious adverse events from administration of IP through Day 28 post dosing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The occurence of Serious Adverse Events, New Onset Chronic Disease (NOCDs) and Adverse Events of Special Interest (AESI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (dosing) through Day 360</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of subjects experiencing SAEs, NOCDs, and AESIs from administration of IP through Day 360 post dosing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Humoral Immunity Assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 29, 61, 91, 181, 271, and 361</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Post-dose geometric mean titers (GMTs) and post dose geometric mean fold rises (GMFRs) from baseline in RSV A neutralizing antibody.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cellular immunity Assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 8 and 29</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Post dose geometric mean counts (GMCs) and GMFRs from baseline of RSV F peptide pool interferon (IFN) gamma ELISPOT responses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Humoral Immunity Assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 29, 61, 91, 181, 271, and 361</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Post dose seroresponse to RSV as measured by neutralizing antibody to RSV A.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Humoral Immunity Assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 29, 61, 91, 181, 271, and 361</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Post dose GMTs and GMFRs from baseline of anti-F immunoglobulin G antibodies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Humoral Immunity Assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 29, 61, 91, 181, 271, and 361</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Post-dose seroresponse to RSV measured by anti-F IgG assay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cellular immunity Assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 8 and 29</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Post dose cell-mediated immune response to RSV F measured by RSV F peptide pool IFN gamma ELISPOT assay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory Syncytial Virus (RSV)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MEDI7510</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>RSV sF antigen plus adjuvant</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RSV sF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>antigen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>sterile saline</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MEDI7510</intervention_name>
    <description>RSV sF antigen plus adjuvant</description>
    <arm_group_label>MEDI7510</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RSV sF</intervention_name>
    <description>antigen</description>
    <arm_group_label>RSV sF</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>sterile saline</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        :-Age greater than or equal to 60 years

          -  Written informed consent and any locally required authorization obtained prior to any
             protocol related procedures

          -  Ambulatory or ambulatory with assistance (not institutionalized, bedridden, or
             homebound

          -  Weight at or above 110 lbs

          -  Hemoglobin within normal range for age and gender -Subject available by telephone

          -  Subject able to understand and comply with the requirements of the protocol, as
             judged by the investigator

          -  Subject able to complete follow-up period of 360 days after dosing

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of allergy to any component of the vaccine

          -  Pregnancy or potential to become pregnant during the study. Females who have had a
             menstrual period within the 12 months prior to study enrollment or are undergoing any
             fertility treatment or who plan to undergo fertility treatments during the study
             period are excluded

          -  Any unstable chronic medical condition, including one that has resulted in change in
             therapy (medication or other) in the 30 days prior to randomization or
             hospitalization in the previous year or might be predicted to result in
             hospitalization in the year after enrollment. Subjects with severe, untreated or
             uncontrolled underlying medical disease that might either compromise subject safety
             or affect the ability to assess safety of the investigational product are excluded

          -  Clinically significant abnormalities in screening laboratory assessments or screening
             ECG

          -  History of hepatitis B or hepatitis C infection

          -  Cognitive disorder such that informed consent cannot be obtained directly from the
             subject

          -  Previous vaccination against RSV

          -  History of allergy to eggs in adulthood

          -  History of or current autoimmune disorder

          -  Immunosuppression caused by disease, including HIV, or medications. Any oral
             prednisone dosing within 30 days of enrollment or planned dosing within the 360-day
             follow-up period would disqualify.

          -  History of splenectomy or of condition affecting splenic function

          -  History of cancer within preceding 5 years other than treated non-melanoma skin
             cancer

          -  Body Mass Index 40 or higher

          -  Significant infection or other acute illness, including fever over 100 F on the day
             prior to or day of randomization

          -  Receipt of any nonstudy vaccine within 30 days prior to study dosing or expected
             receipt of nonstudy vaccine within 30 days after study dosing

          -  Receipt of any investigational product in the 90 days prior to randomization or
             expected receipt of investigational product during the period of study follow-up

          -  Receipt of immunoglobulins or blood products within 4 months of study dosing (120
             days) or expected receipt of investigational product during the period of study
             follow-up History of thrombocytopenia or bleeding disorder or use of anticoagulants.
             Subjects receiving drugs with anti-platelet activity such as nonsteroidal
             antiinflammatory drugs, clopidogrel or aspirin are not excluded

          -  Expected receipt of antipyretic or analgesic medication on a daily or every other day
             basis from randomization through 72 hours after receipt of IP (a daily dose of 163 mg
             or higher is not considered a contraindication to enrollment)

          -  Subjects who have significant scarring, tattoos, abrasions, cuts, or infections over
             the deltoid region of both arms that, in the PI's opinion, could interfere with
             evaluation of injection site local reactions

          -  Any condition that, in the PI's opinion, would interfere with evaluation of the IP or
             interpretation of subject safety or study results

          -  Concurrent enrollment in another clinical study that involves any invasive clinical
             procedure, including phlebotomy

          -  History of alcohol or drug abuse or psychiatric disorder that in the PI's opinion
             would affect the subject's safety or compliance with study

          -  Employees of individuals directly involved with the conduct of the study, individuals
             who themselves are involved with the conduct of the study, or immediate family
             members of such individuals.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eric Sheldon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Miami Research Associates</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Craig Curtis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Compass Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven Bart, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Accelovance Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Judith Falloon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>MedImmune LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amanda Fleming</last_name>
    <phone>301-398-5992</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTrialEnquiries@Medimmune.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kristin Kopasz</last_name>
    <phone>301-398-5079</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Miami Research Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Compass Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32806</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Accelovance, Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rockville</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20850</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 1, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 3, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
