<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="126017">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01848574</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NI10067</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01848574</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Satisfaction Understanding of Patients and Relatives in Emergency Room</brief_title>
  <acronym>SUPER4</acronym>
  <official_title>Satisfaction Understanding of Patients and Relatives in Emergency Room</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evaluation of global understanding and with items of patients admitted to the emergency.

      Prospective observational study randomized in cluster during 6 weeks in 14 centers
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients' comprehension in the emergency department (ED) is relatively low. This is more
      evident for in-patients with more complex diseases. The preliminary study conducted suggests
      that patients' comprehension was improved by the use of standardized information and by
      opening a dialogue. This study however had its limits. It does not deliver proper
      information guideline to physicians working in the ED.

      This study is reproduced on a larger scale for in-patients in the ED concerning their
      comprehension about the medical information given and thus improving the scientific
      evidence. This study has been conducted on a national level in 2 phases with 14
      investigating centers spread in Paris and other provinces:

      First, an observational period was conducted during 2 weeks in each center in order to
      document their homogeneity. At the same time, this period permitted to have a reference
      level of comprehension. During this period, investigators continued to give medical
      information to their patients as usual.  The aim is to adjust the results of the
      comprehensions levels in 2 groups after the experimental study on the &quot;baseline&quot; data.

      Second, an experimental period of 4 weeks: 7 centers are identified as &quot;formal procedure
      group&quot; and their investigators are provided with formal procedures on the patient's
      comprehension in the ED based on updated literature data. At the same time, recommendations
      are given on the information given to patients. 7 other centers &quot;control group&quot; only formal
      presentation on the patient's comprehension in the ED on updated literature data.

      According to the center where the patient is included, he will be either in the &quot;formal
      procedure group&quot; or the &quot;control group&quot;.

      Among all in-patients in the ED, it is planned to include:

        -  700 patients in the observational period (50 in each center)

        -  1400 patients in the experimental period (700 in the formal procedure group and 700 in
           the control group)

      Improvement in the information given to patients is expected due to the participation of the
      centers in this study. This improvement is expected in both arms only due to the fact of
      their participation. Better information level is expected in the &quot;formal procedure group&quot;.

      If this study proves a better information in the procedure group, then our aim will be to
      propose recommendations to ED physicians to improve the information given to in-patients in
      the ED.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Global Comprehension</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Completing the questionnaire independently by the doctor and the patient after patient and physician interview final  and comparison of responses</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comprehension of each items</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Completing the questionnaire independently by the doctor and the patient after patient and physician interview final  and comparison of responses</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2100</enrollment>
  <condition>All Inpatient in Short Stays Emergencies</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual procedure</arm_group_label>
    <description>Investigators will give medical information to their patients as usual.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental procedure</arm_group_label>
    <description>You must use the standardized patient information. The final Information of the patient before the final output should be clear and concise in the presence of trustworthy people if the patient wishes.
Deliver the following information in the orde of the items below:
Decline your identity and function Provide a final diagnosis, indicating the affected organ and Inform prognosis (any severity), and the potential duration of affection
Briefly additional tests:
Radio show
Explain the main abnormalities Explain treatment modalities and setpoint monitoring Finish with an open question: &quot;Do you have questions? &quot;If you think the state anxiety or depression alters the patient's understanding, still deliver all the information listed above.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Emergency in hospital Patients will be enrolled in the study, before their release, before
        the output of emergency or before going in a other inpatient
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient aged 18 years and over

          -  Inpatient Unit in Short Term Hospitalization (UHCD)

          -  Patient who agreed to participate in the study

          -  Patient affiliated to a social security scheme (beneficiary or righ)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient has already been included in the study, which was re-hospitalized for the
             same reason UHCD

          -  Patient in judicial restraint (certificate of non-admission in custody, incarcerated)

          -  Patient for which a decision forced hospitalization was taken

          -  Patient non-Francophone

          -  Patients with underlying cognitive and unable to give their consent

          -  Patient opposed to participate in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yann-Erick Claessens, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cochin Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yann-Erick Claessens, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+33 1 58 41 27 07</phone>
    <email>ye.claessens@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Laurence Lecomte, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+331 58 41 35 45</phone>
    <email>laurence.lecomte@cch.aphp.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cochin Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75014</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marieve Billemont, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+33 1 58 41 27 07</phone>
      <email>marieve.billemont@cch.aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yann-Erick Claessens, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 2, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Understanding</keyword>
  <keyword>Patients</keyword>
  <keyword>Emergency</keyword>
  <keyword>Information</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Emergencies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
