<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="79068">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02081846</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H2O</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02081846</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hospital to Home Outcomes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Hospital to Home Outcomes (H2O): A Study to Improve the Fluidity of Transitions Between Hospital and Home</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Patient Centered Outcome Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To identify barriers to successful transitions that are most meaningful to patients and
      families, and use these identified barriers to iteratively adapt an existing nurse home
      visit program to address these barriers. This study will also test the efficacy of a nurse
      home visit intervention in improving post-discharge outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Investigator), Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reutilization</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients who receive the nurse home visit intervention will have a significantly lower occurrence of any all cause rehospitalization, ED/urgent care revisit, and/or unscheduled follow-up within 30-days post-discharge when compared to the patients enrolled in the control group after 30 days post-discharge. The dependent variable will be a dichotomized indicator of any occurrence of rehospitalization, ED revisit, and/or unscheduled follow-up within 30-days post-discharge. Differences in this outcome between intervention and control groups will be evaluated using logistic regression with the stratification variable (presence or absence of underlying chronic condition and hospitalist medicine general vs. surgical service) included in the model to account for the sampling design.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parental Activation</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients who receive the nurse home visit intervention will have significantly higher parent activation scores 30-days post-discharge when compared to the patients enrolled in the control group after 30 days post-discharge. For this secondary outcome, the dependent variable will be a continuous measure of parent activation.  Difference in this outcome between intervention and control groups will be evaluated using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) using a linear model containing a treatment effect indicator.  Parental activation scores will be checked for normality and data transformations will be entertained, if needed.  Baseline differences will be examined between groups, again using a linear model.  If, by random chance, there is a difference between the groups, the first analysis will be repeated but adding the baseline as a covariate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Parent Identified Measures</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Analysis of secondary outcomes identified through Aim 1 will be tailored to the outcome measure. For example, if parents or caregivers identify days of work missed as an important outcome, our analysis of days of work missed will be restricted to only those parents/caregivers reporting work outside the home. We will take a two-part approach to analysis. First, we will treat it as a binary outcome, comparing the percentage of caregivers that missed at least one day of work during the 30-day follow-up period between the two study arms using logistic regression. Second, we will treat the number of days of work missed as a count outcome and use poisson regression to compare the two study arms. No interim analysis is planned.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1600</enrollment>
  <condition>Focus: Hospitalized Patients</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Home Nurse Visit</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Families in this arm will receive a nurse home visit within 48 hours of discharge.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will receive standard of care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nurse Home Visit</intervention_name>
    <description>We will complete a single center, parallel, randomized, standard-of-care-controlled prospective study to determine the efficacy of a nurse home visit program, an intervention adapted from those studied in other populations (i.e., adults, high-risk infants) and re-engineered through Aim 2, in improving pediatric patient transitions from hospital to home</description>
    <arm_group_label>Home Nurse Visit</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Control patients will be randomized to receive standard-of-care at discharge. This care at our institution includes pediatric hospitalist to PCP verbal and written communication prior to discharge, written documentation for the family regarding prescribed medication regimen, recommended follow-up with outpatient PCP and relevant consultant(s), and delivery of prescribed medications from the hospital pharmacy to the patient's bedside.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient is under 18 years of age

          -  Patient is admitted to Hospital Medicine Service at Base, Surgical Hospital Medicine
             Service at Base, Adolescent Medicine, or Community Pediatrics

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient is discharged to a residential facility

          -  Patient's home residence is outside the home nursing service area

          -  Patient is eligible for &quot;traditional&quot; home nursing services

          -  Caregiver is non-English speaking
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Samir S Shah, MD, MSCE</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hadley S Sauers, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>513-636-7994</phone>
    <email>hadley.sauers@cchmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Samir S Shah, MD, MSCE</last_name>
    <phone>513-636-0409</phone>
    <email>samir.shah@cchmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 5, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>transitions of care</keyword>
  <keyword>reutilization</keyword>
  <keyword>home nurse visit</keyword>
  <keyword>focus groups</keyword>
  <keyword>quality improvement</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
