<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="33331">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01737619</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-0623</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5 P50 CA098258-08 COEUS 4892</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01737619</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>High Risk Endometrial Cancer and Lymph Nodes Metastasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Evaluation of Lymph Node Metastasis at the Time of Surgical Staging for High Risk Endometrial Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to compare positron emission tomography/computed
      tomography (PET/CT) scans and sentinel lymph node mapping in finding lymph nodes that have
      endometrial cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The blood drawn at screening and any leftover lymph node tissue from screening will be
      stored in the gynecologic research bank at MD Anderson for future research related to cancer
      and biomarker testing.

      Before your samples can be used for research, the researchers must get approval from the
      Institutional Review Board (IRB) of MD Anderson.  The IRB is a committee of doctors,
      researchers, and community members.  The IRB is responsible for protecting study
      participants and making sure all research is safe and ethical.

      Your samples will be given a code number.  No identifying information will be directly
      linked to your samples.  Only the researcher in charge of the bank will have access to the
      code numbers and be able to link the samples to you.  This is to allow medical data related
      to the samples to be updated as needed.

      If you are found eligible to take part in this study, you will have a PET/CT scan before
      your surgery and sentinel lymph node mapping procedure during the surgery.

      For the sentinel lymph node mapping procedure, a blue dye, a radioactive colloid, and/or an
      indocyanine green (IC-Green) dye will be injected into your cervix during your surgery.  The
      study staff will then use a device that detects radioactivity and that looks for lymph nodes
      stained with the dye(s). When the study staff locates the sentinel lymph nodes, they will
      remove them.  The sentinel lymph nodes will then be sent to a lab where a pathologist will
      check them to see if they contain cancer cells. Other lymph nodes may be removed as part of
      your standard of care surgery if your surgeon thinks it is in your best interest.

      Length of Study:

      Your participation in this study will be over after your surgery.

      This is an investigational study.  The 2 procedures being compared in this study are
      standard of care.

      Up to 100 participants will be enrolled in this study.  Up to 10 will be enrolled at the
      Harris Health System and up to 90 will be enrolled at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of PET/CT Versus Sentinel Lymph Node Mapping in Detecting Endometrial Cancer Lymph Nodes</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimation of false negative rate for each procedure (PET/CT, sentinel lymph node mapping) and for the combination of the 2 procedures with 90% credible intervals. Posterior probability that the false negative rate is &gt; 10% for each procedure and for the combination of the 2 procedures reported. Biopsy and frozen section analysis tabulated with final histologic grade and surgical stage, and chi-square test used to assess associations between biopsy and frozen section with grade and stage.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Gynecologic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sentinel Lymph Node Mapping</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>PET/CT prior to surgery. Surgical approach as determined by the primary surgeon.
At time of surgery, an endometrial biopsy will be performed once the patient is under anesthesia.  Intra-operative lymphatic mapping with blue dye, radioactive colloid, and/or indocyanine green will be performed.  Sentinel lymph nodes will be removed and labeled as blue, green, and/or hot.  These nodes will be processed separately.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PET/CT Scan</intervention_name>
    <description>PET/CT scan before surgery and sentinel lymph node mapping procedure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sentinel Lymph Node Mapping</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Positron Emission Tomography Scan</other_name>
    <other_name>Computed Tomography Scan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sentinel Lymph Node Mapping</intervention_name>
    <description>Blue dye, a radioactive colloid, and/or an indocyanine green (IC-Green) dye injected into cervix during surgery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sentinel Lymph Node Mapping</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically confirmed high grade endometrial cancer including grade 3
             endometrioid, serous, clear cell, MMMT or any mixed tumor containing one of these
             cell types

          2. Patients with a grade 1/2 tumors and evidence of deep myometrial invasion or cervical
             involvement on preoperative imaging or physical exam

          3. Candidate for surgery.

          4. No evidence of peritoneal disease on preoperative imaging

          5. Negative pregnancy test if of child-bearing age

          6. No preoperative treatment for endometrial cancer including radiation or chemotherapy

          7. Previous hormonal therapy is allowed

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Medical co-morbidities making surgery unsafe, as determined by the primary treating
             physician

          2. Any contraindications to PET/CT or lymph node mapping (inability to control serum
             glucose to a value of &lt;/= 200 mg/dl for FDG-PET/CT)

          3. Does not meet histologic criteria

          4. Evidence of peritoneal or distant metastasis on preoperative imaging

          5. Baseline creatinine (necessary for imaging studies)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pamela Soliman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pamela Soliman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-745-2352</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lyndon B. Johnson General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 27, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gynecologic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Endometrial Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymph Nodes Metastasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgical Staging</keyword>
  <keyword>False negative rate</keyword>
  <keyword>Detection of positive lymph nodes</keyword>
  <keyword>Histologically confirmed high grade endometrial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Sentinel lymph node mapping</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
