<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="68970">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02109640</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-005327-16</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02109640</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Comparison of Targinact vs. Oxycodone on Gut Function After Colorectal Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>TACS</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Blinded Pilot Study to Compare Targinact vs. Oxycodone in Early Return of Gastrointestinal Function After Colorectal Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Edinburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Edinburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: National Health Service</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Two key requirements for discharge from hospital after major abdominal surgery are adequate
      oral analgesia and resumption of oral nutrition. Up to 40% of patients suffer delayed
      discharge after abdominal surgery due to delayed return of gut function, manifesting as
      nausea, vomiting, constipation and abdominal distension. Opiates and their derivatives are
      the mainstay of postoperative analgesic regimens after abdominal surgery and are highly
      effective in achieving adequate pain control. However, opioids cause impaired gut function
      by reducing normal forward propulsion and increasing gut spasm. Opioid receptor blockers
      such as Alvimopan counteract these effects and can accelerate postoperative gut recovery but
      are expensive and cause cardiac complications; alternative painkillers such as non-steroidal
      anti-inflammatories are less effective than opioids and have been linked with increased risk
      of anastomotic leaks.

      Targinact is a combination of prolonged release opioid analgesic (oxycodone hydrochloride)
      and naloxone hydrochloride (an opioid receptor blocker). The formulation of the product
      confines the naloxone action to the gut to reduce the unwanted side-effects on gut function.
      Targinact has been shown in patients with chronic severe pain to provide comparable
      analgesia to other opioid analgesics whilst reducing the unwanted side-effect of
      constipation.

      The Investigators wish to test the hypothesis that Targinact will provide adequate analgesia
      after colonic resection with reduced postoperative gastrointestinal dysfunction. The
      surgical procedure chosen to test this hypothesis is laparoscopic segmental colectomy, a
      consistently reproducible intervention with a postoperative gut dysfunction rate of up to
      40% (prospective data from the Edinburgh Colorectal Unit). The main outcome of the study
      will be return of normal gut function at the time of planned discharge (Day 3).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study hypothesis: Targinact is effective as oral analgesia after major colorectal surgery
      and is associated with less gut dysfunction than Oxycodone.

      Up to 40% of patients suffer delayed return of gut function after elective colorectal
      surgery, leading to prolonged hospital stay and higher inpatient costs. For the patient,
      this is characterised by a variety of symptoms including nausea and vomiting, delayed
      ability to regain normal oral intake, abdominal discomfort/distension and constipation.
      Although post-operative gut dysfunction tends to resolve spontaneously in 3-7 days, both
      symptoms and supportive treatment (nasogastric tube insertion, repeated venous cannulation
      for intravenous fluid administration etc) are unpleasant.

      Elective colorectal surgery is a common hospital intervention hence a reduction in the
      prevalence of post-operative gut dysfunction would be expected to benefit a large number of
      patients with attendant reduction in health service costs. The objective aligns well with
      the current national dissemination of Enhanced Recovery after Surgery programmes by the UK
      Department of Health and Scottish Government.

      Post-operative gut dysfunction is multifactorial. Opioid analgesics are contributory and all
      Enhanced Recovery after Surgery (ERAS) programmes emphasise strategies to minimise systemic
      opioid use (eg using regional or local anaesthetic techniques).

      Targinact has not been evaluated in the setting of short-term post operative analgesia in
      colorectal surgery but offers the potential to achieve effective analgesia with a lower
      incidence of gut dysfunction and therefore an important role within the ERAS program after
      colorectal surgery. Oxycodone is currently the oral opioid analgesic of choice in our unit
      and most patients are prescribed a combination of oxycodone and oxynorm as step-down
      analgesia following cessation of systemic or epidural analgesia, often in combination with
      fentanyl patches.

      Data will be collected from patient hospital records and questionnaires administered by the
      principal investigator and research study nurse.

      Multiple measures will be employed to record both presence of good function and absence of
      dysfunction.

        -  Time to first flatus

        -  Time to first bowel movement

        -  Time from surgery to cessation of iv fluids

        -  Total dose of rescue antiemetic (protocol ondansetron not included)

        -  Reinstitution of iv fluids (Y/N) Quantity of laxative used

        -  Measurement of oral nutritional intake:

      Preoperative intake will be recorded by means of a recall diary. Postoperative oral intake
      will be recorded by the participant using a food diary for 7 days from the date of surgery.
      Energy intake will then be estimated using CompEat Pro® forWindows® (Nutrition Systems,
      Banbury, UK). Time to attain and maintain 80% of normal solid food intake and the percentage
      Recommended Nutritional Intake (RNI) achieved on days 1-3 and days 5-7 after surgery will be
      used in comparisons between study groups.

        -  Validated nausea and vomiting score (Miles and Wengritzky)

        -  Presence of abdominal distension (Y/N)

        -  13C Stable Isotope Gastric Empyting Breath Test to measure gastric motility on the
           second postoperative morning. The technique has been previously used in the Edinburgh
           Department of Surgery and validated to be a reproducible and accurate measurement of
           upper GI motility.

      Additional data to be recorded:

        -  Patient demographics, co morbidity, regular medications

        -  Pre op bowel function questionnaire

        -  Postoperative nausea and vomiting prediction data (Apfel score)

        -  Day 3 achievement of discharge criteria (pain controlled by oral analgesia, tolerating
           adequate oral diet and fluids, independently mobile and willing to go home) Y/N

        -  30-day/Inpatient mortality

        -  Duration of hospital admission

        -  Complications (recorded by organ system and severity as assessed by Clavien/Dindo
           scale)

        -  Unscheduled readmissions to hospital within 30 days of discharge

        -  Patient-reported outcome questionnaire
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of postoperative gut dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 3 post-op</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>25% reduction in the proportion of participants with gut dysfunction, defined as the presence of any of the following sufficient to delay discharge on the 3rd postoperative day: nausea, vomiting, intolerance of oral intake or constipation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain control</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 5 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Total quantity of Morphine used over standard analgesia protocol</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oral analgesia use</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 5 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Total dose of oral Oxycodone or Targinact until discontinued by the participant/discharged from hospital</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 5 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pain scores measured daily using Overall Benefit of Analgesia Score (OBAS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Postoperative Pain</condition>
  <condition>Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Targinact</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral Targinact 10-20mg bd following laparoscopic segmental colectomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oxycodone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral oxycodone 10-20mg bd following laparoscopic segmental colectomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Targinact</intervention_name>
    <description>Post-operative analgesia</description>
    <arm_group_label>Targinact</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oxycodone</intervention_name>
    <description>Postoperative analgesia</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oxycodone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laparoscopic segmental colectomy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Targinact</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Oxycodone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients scheduled for elective laparoscopic segmental colectomy at the Colorectal
             Surgery Unit, Western General Hospital, Edinburgh.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy Age &lt;18 years Patients lacking capacity to give informed consent. Severe
             liver dysfunction (Child's A or greater) Patients participating in another
             therapeutic clinical trial Contraindication to oxycodone, naloxone or Targinact
             Pre-existing dependence on opioid analgesia (current medications will be checked
             prior to discussing consent) Pre-existing use of opioid analgesia for chronic pain
             (current medications will be checked prior to discussing consent) Patients with
             rectal cancer Plan to form any stoma during procedure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hugh M Paterson, MD FRCS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Edinburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hugh M Paterson, MD FRCS</last_name>
    <phone>00447780957402</phone>
    <email>hugh.paterson@luht.scot.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Western General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edinburgh</city>
        <zip>EH4 2XU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hugh M Paterson, MD FRCS</last_name>
      <phone>00447780957402</phone>
      <email>hugh.paterson@luht.scot.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hugh M Paterson, MD FRCS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Felicity Creamer, MBChB</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lassen K, Soop M, Nygren J, Cox PB, Hendry PO, Spies C, von Meyenfeldt MF, Fearon KC, Revhaug A, Norderval S, Ljungqvist O, Lobo DN, Dejong CH; Enhanced Recovery After Surgery (ERAS) Group. Consensus review of optimal perioperative care in colorectal surgery: Enhanced Recovery After Surgery (ERAS) Group recommendations. Arch Surg. 2009 Oct;144(10):961-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19841366</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hendry PO, Hausel J, Nygren J, Lassen K, Dejong CH, Ljungqvist O, Fearon KC; Enhanced Recovery After Surgery Study Group. Determinants of outcome after colorectal resection within an enhanced recovery programme. Br J Surg. 2009 Feb;96(2):197-205. doi: 10.1002/bjs.6445.</citation>
    <PMID>19160347</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simpson K, Leyendecker P, Hopp M, Müller-Lissner S, Löwenstein O, De Andrés J, Troy Ferrarons J, Bosse B, Krain B, Nichols T, Kremers W, Reimer K. Fixed-ratio combination oxycodone/naloxone compared with oxycodone alone for the relief of opioid-induced constipation in moderate-to-severe noncancer pain. Curr Med Res Opin. 2008 Dec;24(12):3503-12.</citation>
    <PMID>19032132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 3, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Colorectal</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Laparoscopic</keyword>
  <keyword>Analgesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Enhanced Recovery</keyword>
  <keyword>Targinact</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vomiting</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Oxycodone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
