<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="21644">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01821612</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A021101</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA031946</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01821612</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chemotherapy and Radiation Therapy Before Surgery Followed by Gemcitabine in Treating Patients With Pancreatic Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Neoadjuvant FOLFIRINOX and Chemoradiation Followed by Definitive Surgery and Postoperative Gemcitabine for Patients With Borderline Resectable Pancreatic Adenocarcinoma: An Intergroup Single-Arm Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alliance for Clinical Trials in Oncology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alliance for Clinical Trials in Oncology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot clinical trial studies combination chemotherapy and radiation therapy before
      surgery followed by gemcitabine hydrochloride in treating patients with pancreatic cancer
      when the tumor is borderline for removal. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as oxaliplatin,
      irinotecan hydrochloride, leucovorin calcium, fluorouracil, and gemcitabine hydrochloride,
      work in different ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells or by
      stopping them from dividing. Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays to kill tumor cells.
      Giving combination chemotherapy together with radiation therapy before surgery may make the
      tumor smaller and reduce the amount of normal tissue that needs to be removed. Giving
      chemotherapy after surgery may kill any tumor cells that remain after surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients receive mFOLFIRINOX chemotherapy comprising oxaliplatin intravenously 85 mg/m2 (IV)
      over 2 hours on day 1, irinotecan 180 mg/m2 IV over 90 minutes on day 1, leucovorin calcium
      400 mg/m2 IV over 2 hours on day 1, and 5-fluorouracil 2,400 mg/m2 IV over 46-48 hours on
      days 1-2. Treatment repeats every 14 days for 4 courses in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      Beginning 2-6 weeks after completion of therapy, patients receive capecitabine 825 mg/m2
      orally (PO) twice daily (BID) 5 days a week and undergo radiation therapy 5 days a week for
      4 weeks. Patients undergo surgery within 4-10 weeks of completing radiation.Beginning 6-8
      weeks after surgery, patients receive gemcitabine IV IV 1000 mg/m2 on days 1, 8, and 15 over
      30 minutes on days 1, 8, and 15. Treatment repeats every 28 days for 2 courses in the
      absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. After completion of study
      treatment, patients are followed up every 4 months for 3 years and then periodically
      thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Accrual rate, calculated by total number of patients accrued divided by number of months from the date the study is opened at the fifth site to the evaluation date</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of treatment-related toxicity during preoperative therapy assessed using Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of treatment delay (greater than 4 weeks) during preoperative therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Completion rate of all preoperative and operative therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Macroscopic (R0/R1) resection rate defined as number of patients achieved R0 or R1 resection during surgery divided by number of evaluable patients</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiographic response rate defined as number of patients who achieved complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 during pre-operative therapy divided by the number of evaluable patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Histopathologic response rate defined as number of patients who achieved CR or PR determined according to histopathologic examination during pre-operative therapy divided by the number of evaluable patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to locoregional recurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of registration to the date of the first documented locoregional recurrence, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to distant recurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of registration to the date of the first documented distant recurrence, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of registration to the date of the death due to all causes, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Acinar Cell Adenocarcinoma of the Pancreas</condition>
  <condition>Duct Cell Adenocarcinoma of the Pancreas</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage II Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFIRINOX, chemoradiation, surgery and gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive mFOLFIRINOX chemotherapy comprised of oxaliplatin, irinotecan hydrochloride, leucovorin calcium and 5-fluorouracil. After completion of chemotherapy, patients receive chemoradiation comprised of capecitabine and radiation then undergo surgery.  After completion of surgery, patients receive gemcitabine hydrochloride.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>oxaliplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients receive 85 mg/m2 intravenously (IV) over 2 hours on day 1. Treatment repeats every 14 days for 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFIRINOX, chemoradiation, surgery and gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>irinotecan hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients receive irinotecan hydrochloride intravenously (IV) 180 mg/m2 over 90 minutes on day 1. Treatment repeats every 14 days for 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFIRINOX, chemoradiation, surgery and gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>leucovorin calcium</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients receive leucovorin calcium 400 mg/m2 intravenously (IV) over 2 hours on day 1. Treatment repeats every 14 days for 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFIRINOX, chemoradiation, surgery and gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>folinic acid</other_name>
    <other_name>calcium folinate</other_name>
    <other_name>citrovorum factor</other_name>
    <other_name>N 5-formyltetrahydrofolate</other_name>
    <other_name>5-formyl-FH4</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>5-fluorouracil</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients receive 5-fluorouracil 2,400 mg/m2 intravenously (IV) over 46-48 hours on days 1-2. Treatment repeats every 14 days for 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFIRINOX, chemoradiation, surgery and gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>capecitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients receive capecitabine 825mg/m2 orally (PO) twice daily (BID) 5 days a week for 4 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFIRINOX, chemoradiation, surgery and gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Xeloda</other_name>
    <other_name>5'-deoxy-5fluoro-N-[(pentyloxy)carbonyl]-cytidine)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>radiation</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive radiation therapy 5 days a week for 4 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFIRINOX, chemoradiation, surgery and gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients undergo pancreaticoduodenectomy within 4-10 weeks of completing chemoradiation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFIRINOX, chemoradiation, surgery and gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>gemcitabine  hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients receive gemicitabine hydrochloride intravenously (IV) 1000 mg/m2 over 30 minutes on days 1, 8, and 15. Treatment repeats every 28 days for 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mFOLFIRINOX, chemoradiation, surgery and gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>2'deoxy-2'</other_name>
    <other_name>2'-difluorocytidine</other_name>
    <other_name>dFDC</other_name>
    <other_name>difluorodeoxycytidine</other_name>
    <other_name>gemcitabine</other_name>
    <other_name>Gemzar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Pre-Registration Eligibility Criteria

          -  Documentation of Disease and Radiographic Staging

               -  Cytologic or histologic proof of adenocarcinoma of the pancreatic head or
                  uncinate process

               -  Objective radiographic staging with a) contrast-enhanced, helical thin-cut
                  computed tomography (CT)/magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan of the abdomen
                  and b) CT scan/MRI of the chest

               -  Note: echoendoscopic staging will be permitted as an adjunctive modality, but
                  all stage definitions below will be determined using CT/MRI as outlined below.
                  In the event echoendoscopic stage and CT/MRI stage are discordant, the CT/MRI
                  stage will be used. Significant discordance should be discussed with the study
                  principal investigator (PI) prior to enrollment 

               -  Borderline resectable primary tumor, defined by the presence of any one or more
                  of the following on CT/MRI, and confirmed by central radiographic review:

                    -  An interface between the primary tumor and the superior mesenteric vein or
                       portal vein (SMV-PV) measuring ≥ 180 degrees of the circumference of the
                       vessel wall 

                    -  Short-segment occlusion of the SMV-PV with normal vein above and below the
                       level of obstruction that is amenable to resection and venous
                       reconstruction

                    -  Short segment interface (of any degree) between tumor and hepatic artery
                       with normal artery proximal and distal to the interface that is amenable to
                       resection and reconstruction 

                    -  An interface between the tumor and superior mesenteric artery (SMA)
                       measuring &lt; 180 degrees of the circumference of the vessel wall

               -  No potentially resectable disease defined as primary tumors with all of the
                  following:  

                    -  An interface between the primary tumor and the superior mesenteric vein or
                       portal vein (SMV-PV) measuring &lt; 180 degrees of the circumference of the
                       vessel wall 

                    -  No radiographic interface between the tumor and the (superior mesenteric
                       artery) SMA, hepatic artery or celiac axis 

                    -  No radiographic evidence of metastatic disease

               -  No metastatic disease defined as any one or more of the following:

                    -  Suspicious lymphadenopathy outside the standard surgical field (i.e.,
                       aortocaval nodes, distant abdominal nodes) 

                    -  Radiographic evidence for metastatic disease in distant organs, such as
                       masses in distant organs or ascites

               -  No locally advanced and/or unresectable disease clearly defined by any one or
                  more of the following by CT/MRI: 

                    -  An interface between the tumor and the SMA measuring ≥ 180 degrees of the
                       circumference of the vessel wall 

                    -  No interface between the tumor and the aorta 

                    -  Occlusion of the SMV or portal vein without a sufficient cuff of normal
                       vein above and below the level of obstruction with which to perform venous
                       reconstruction 

                    -  Long-segment interface (of any degree) between the tumor and the common
                       hepatic artery or its major tributaries with insufficient artery proximal
                       and distal to the interface to perform reconstruction

          -  No prior chemotherapy or chemoradiation for pancreatic cancer

          -  No patients with a &quot;currently active&quot; second malignancy other than non-melanoma skin
             cancers. Patients are not considered to have a &quot;currently active&quot; malignancy if they
             have completed therapy and are free of disease for ≥ 3 years

          -  Baseline peripheral sensory neuropathy must be grade &lt; 2

          -  No patients with known Gilbert's Syndrome or homozygosity for UGT1A1*28 polymorphism

          -  No history of pulmonary embolism in the past 6 months

          -  Age ≥ 18 years of age

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG)/Zubrod performance status 0-1

          -  Pregnancy/Nursing Status: Non-pregnant and non-breast-feeding. Female participants of
             child-bearing potential must have a negative urine or serum pregnancy test prior to
             registration. Perimenopausal participants must be amenorrheic &gt; 12 months to be
             considered not of childbearing potential.

          -  Required Pre-Registration Laboratory Values:

               -  Granulocytes ≥ 2,000/ul

               -  Hemoglobin &gt; 9 g/dL

               -  Platelets ≥ 100,000/ul

               -  Albumin &gt; 3.0 g/dL

               -  Creatinine ≤1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase [SGOT]
                  &amp; alanine aminotransferase (ALT) serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT]) ≤
                  2.5 x ULN

        Registration Eligibility Criteria

          -  Confirmation of pre-registration eligibility criteria as described under
             &quot;Documentation of Disease and Radiographic Staging&quot; by the Alliance Central
             Radiographic Review

          -  Required Registration Laboratory Values:

               -  Bilirubin ≤ 2 mg/dl

               -  Cancer antigen (CA)19-9 &lt; 1000 U/ml (from time point when bilirubin is ≤ 2
                  mg/dl)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthew Katz, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ochsner Clinic Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Orleans</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>W. Charles Conway</last_name>
      <phone>504-842-4482</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>W. Charles Conway</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University/Ingram Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dana Cardin</last_name>
      <phone>615-322-4967</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dana Cardin</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matthew Katz</last_name>
      <phone>713-745-1462</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthew Katz</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Acinar Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Calcium, Dietary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Capecitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oxaliplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Irinotecan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Camptothecin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Formyltetrahydrofolates</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leucovorin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levoleucovorin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
