<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82358">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01969448</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201302004</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01969448</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Assess Perfusion and Patient Satisfaction in Nipple-Areola Mastectomy With Immediate Reconstruction</brief_title>
  <acronym>NASSM</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective Randomized Trial to Assess Perfusion and Patient Satisfaction in Nipple-Areola Mastectomy With Immediate Reconstruction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>LifeCell</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary hypothesis of this study is to determine which of two incision sites
      (inframammary fold incision or the lateral radial incision) provides a more robust blood
      supply to the skin envelope during nipple-sparing mastectomy with immediate reconstruction.

      Following education about the trial and informed consent, patients will be randomized to one
      of the two incisions.  If their surgeon recommends a particular incision, there is also a
      non-randomized cohort. Patients will complete the Breast Q, a questionnaire prior to surgery
      and three months after surgery to capture quality of life data.  During the surgery,
      laser-assisted fluorescent angiography will be performed three times to look at blood
      perfusion with the Spy Elite imaging device.

      Patients will be required to return for postoperative follow up visits: one week, three
      weeks, six weeks, and three months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Robust blood supply to skin envelope during mastectomy and reconstruction</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Laser-assisted fluorescent angiography via the Spy Elite imaging device will be utilized to capture this data during mastectomy and immediate breast reconstruction.  Standard postoperative patient follow up will assess for perfusion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breast Q and Q-score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Which approach to nipple-areola skin-sparing mastectomy renders the most favorable patient reported outcomes during the Breast Q and Q-score?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">84</enrollment>
  <condition>Ductal Carcinoma in Situ (DCIS)</condition>
  <condition>Clinical Stage I Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Prophylactic Mastectomy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inframammary Fold Incision Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this cohort will be randomized to the inframammary fold incision which is in the crease under the breast.
Goal:  28 Patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lateral Radial Incision Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to the lateral radial incision. Goal:  28 Patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Randomized Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in which the surgeon feels that for oncologic reasons must have a specific incision (either inframammary fold or lateral radial incision) and cannot be randomized due to concerns of compromising clinical care but otherwise meet the inclusion and exclusion criteria will be offered participation as part of a non-randomized cohort.
Goal:  28 Patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Inframammary Fold Incision or Lateral Radial Incision</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Randomized Cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lateral Radial Incision</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Lateral Radial Incision Cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Inframammary Fold Incision</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Inframammary Fold Incision Cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laser-assisted fluorescence angiography</intervention_name>
    <description>All study arms will utilize this device to evaluate breast perfusion just prior to mastectomy, at the conclusion of the mastectomy procedure, and following conclusion of reconstruction and immediate implant.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Inframammary Fold Incision Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Lateral Radial Incision Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Randomized Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Spy Elite, LifeCell.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient must be scheduled to undergo either a single or bilateral elective
             nipple-areola skin sparing mastectomy (NASSM)procedure with planned immediate
             reconstruction for prophylaxis, ductal carcinoma in site (DCIS), or clinical Stage I
             breast cancer.

          -  Karnofsky Performance Scale of at least 80%.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  BMI &lt; 20 or &gt; 30

          -  Breast tissue of &gt; 600 grams or &lt; 100 grams in weight

          -  History of lumpectomy (needle biopsies are eligible)

          -  History of radiation to the chest wall or breasts

          -  History of allergy to iodides or iodinated contrast agents

          -  History of previous breast surgery other than primary cosmetic augmentation

          -  Cognitive impairment

          -  Surgeon's opinion at the time of surgery that the subject's well-being would be
             compromised (e.g. significant comorbidities, intraoperative findings of a higher
             stage cancer or other independent acute health problems).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marissa J Tenenbaum, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Colleen Kilbourne, MA</last_name>
    <phone>314-996-3873</phone>
    <email>kilbournec@wudosis.wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West County Plastic Surgeons of Washington University</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63141</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marissa J Tenenbaum, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Terence M Myckatyn, MD, FACS, FRCSC</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julie A Margenthaler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://westcountyplasticsurgeons.wustl.edu/</url>
    <description>Primary clinic location for Drs. Tenenbaum and Myckatyn.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim HJ, Park EH, Lim WS, Seo JY, Koh BS, Lee TJ, Eom JS, Lee SW, Son BH, Lee JW, Ahn SH. Nipple areola skin-sparing mastectomy with immediate transverse rectus abdominis musculocutaneous flap reconstruction is an oncologically safe procedure: a single center study. Ann Surg. 2010 Mar;251(3):493-8. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e3181c5dc4e.</citation>
    <PMID>20134317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cense HA, Rutgers EJ, Lopes Cardozo M, Van Lanschot JJ. Nipple-sparing mastectomy in breast cancer: a viable option? Eur J Surg Oncol. 2001 Sep;27(6):521-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11520082</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paepke S, Schmid R, Fleckner S, Paepke D, Niemeyer M, Schmalfeldt B, Jacobs VR, Kiechle M. Subcutaneous mastectomy with conservation of the nipple-areola skin: broadening the indications. Ann Surg. 2009 Aug;250(2):288-92.</citation>
    <PMID>19638905</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Alcantara Filho P, Capko D, Barry JM, Morrow M, Pusic A, Sacchini VS. Nipple-sparing mastectomy for breast cancer and risk-reducing surgery: the Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center experience. Ann Surg Oncol. 2011 Oct;18(11):3117-22. doi: 10.1245/s10434-011-1974-y. Epub 2011 Aug 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21847697</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Salzberg CA, Ashikari AY, Koch RM, Chabner-Thompson E. An 8-year experience of direct-to-implant immediate breast reconstruction using human acellular dermal matrix (AlloDerm). Plast Reconstr Surg. 2011 Feb;127(2):514-24. doi: 10.1097/PRS.0b013e318200a961.</citation>
    <PMID>21285756</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sacchini V, Pinotti JA, Barros AC, Luini A, Pluchinotta A, Pinotti M, Boratto MG, Ricci MD, Ruiz CA, Nisida AC, Veronesi P, Petit J, Arnone P, Bassi F, Disa JJ, Garcia-Etienne CA, Borgen PI. Nipple-sparing mastectomy for breast cancer and risk reduction: oncologic or technical problem? J Am Coll Surg. 2006 Nov;203(5):704-14. Epub 2006 Sep 11.</citation>
    <PMID>17084333</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palmieri B, Baitchev G, Grappolini S, Costa A, Benuzzi G. Delayed nipple-sparing modified subcutaneous mastectomy: rationale and technique. Breast J. 2005 May-Jun;11(3):173-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15871701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gerber B, Krause A, Dieterich M, Kundt G, Reimer T. The oncological safety of skin sparing mastectomy with conservation of the nipple-areola complex and autologous reconstruction: an extended follow-up study. Ann Surg. 2009 Mar;249(3):461-8. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e31819a044f.</citation>
    <PMID>19247035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tepper OM, Karp NS, Small K, Unger J, Rudolph L, Pritchard A, Choi M. Three-dimensional imaging provides valuable clinical data to aid in unilateral tissue expander-implant breast reconstruction. Breast J. 2008 Nov-Dec;14(6):543-50. doi: 10.1111/j.1524-4741.2008.00645.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19054001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lista F, Ahmad J. Vertical scar reduction mammaplasty: a 15-year experience including a review of 250 consecutive cases. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2006 Jun;117(7):2152-65; discussion 2166-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16772910</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garwood ER, Moore D, Ewing C, Hwang ES, Alvarado M, Foster RD, Esserman LJ. Total skin-sparing mastectomy: complications and local recurrence rates in 2 cohorts of patients. Ann Surg. 2009 Jan;249(1):26-32.</citation>
    <PMID>19106672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashikari RH, Ashikari AY, Kelemen PR, Salzberg CA. Subcutaneous mastectomy and immediate reconstruction for prevention of breast cancer for high-risk patients. Breast Cancer. 2008;15(3):185-91. doi: 10.1007/s12282-008-0059-7.</citation>
    <PMID>18575951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gerber B, Krause A, Reimer T, Müller H, Küchenmeister I, Makovitzky J, Kundt G, Friese K. Skin-sparing mastectomy with conservation of the nipple-areola complex and autologous reconstruction is an oncologically safe procedure. Ann Surg. 2003 Jul;238(1):120-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12832974</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Komorowska-Timek E, Gurtner GC. Intraoperative perfusion mapping with laser-assisted indocyanine green imaging can predict and prevent complications in immediate breast reconstruction. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2010 Apr;125(4):1065-73. doi: 10.1097/PRS.0b013e3181d17f80.</citation>
    <PMID>20335859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Faul F, Erdfelder E, Buchner A, Lang AG. Statistical power analyses using G*Power 3.1: tests for correlation and regression analyses. Behav Res Methods. 2009 Nov;41(4):1149-60. doi: 10.3758/BRM.41.4.1149.</citation>
    <PMID>19897823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Losken A, Zenn MR, Hammel JA, Walsh MW, Carlson GW. Assessment of zonal perfusion using intraoperative angiography during abdominal flap breast reconstruction. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2012 Apr;129(4):618e-24e. doi: 10.1097/PRS.0b013e3182450b16.</citation>
    <PMID>22456376</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashitate Y, Lee BT, Ngo LH, Laurence RG, Hutteman M, Oketokoun R, Lunsford E, Soo Choi H, Frangioni JV. Quantitative assessment of nipple perfusion with near-infrared fluorescence imaging. Ann Plast Surg. 2013 Feb;70(2):149-53. doi: 10.1097/SAP.0b013e31822f9af7.</citation>
    <PMID>21862913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 21, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Nipple-areola skin sparing mastectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Immediate reconstruction</keyword>
  <keyword>Prophylactic Mastectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast-Q</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical Stage I Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Ductal Carcinoma in Situ</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma in Situ</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Intraductal, Noninfiltrating</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Ductal, Breast</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Ductal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
