<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="159888">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02070094</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RSW - 233 - 14</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>A311233-2014</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02070094</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ado-Trastuzumab Emtansine(T-DM1) + ABT-737 in Treating Patients With HER2(+) Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Study of Ado-Trastuzumab Emtansine(T-DM1) + ABT-737 in Treating Patients With HER2(+) Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ukrainian Antitumor Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ukrainian Antitumor Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Ukraine: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study was whether the combination of two different drugs - is safe
      Ado-Trastuzumab Emtansine (T-DM1) and ABT- 737 , and if it can be effective in treating
      breast cancer
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study was whether the combination of two different drugs - is safe
      Ado-Trastuzumab Emtansine (T-DM1) , and ABT- 737 , and if it can be effective in treating
      breast cancer. T-DM1 represents colony monoclonal antibody ( trastuzumab ) , associated with
      chemotherapy . Antibodies to T-DM1 target marker on breast cancer cells called HER2, which
      allows the drug to go directly to the cancer cells . Using T-DM1 in this study considers a
      standard type of cancer treatment in this study. ABT- 737 is an oral medication ( taken by
      mouth ), which researchers believe may help T-DM1 work better and demonstrate the value of
      this combination compared with the agents used alone.

      In the case of breast cancer , it has been particularly difficult because of the very
      heterogeneous nature of the genetic changes that underlie this condition. Known molecular
      concentrate for treatment of breast cancer is the PI3K-AKT signaling pathway . Last treat of
      218 cases, the majority of tumors showed that forty-two % of the main tumor and one hundred
      % of metastases inhabiting genomic aberrations in this pathway .

      Hence, there is substantial energy to rationally combine PI3K-AKT inhibitors into mixture
      treatment protocols.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Lack of funding
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the dose limits toxicity (DLT) of dose escalation ABT-737 in combination with T-DM1</measure>
    <time_frame>The 1st 21 day</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Determine the dose limits toxicity (DLT) of dose escalation ABT-737 in combination with T-DM1 [Time frame: the 1st 21 days] [Designated as a question of security: Yes] DLT from ABT-737 in combination with T-DM1 will be evaluated during the first 21 days (1 cycle = 21 days).
To determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of ABT-737 in combination with T-DM1 [Time frame: the 1st 21 days] [Designated as a question of security: Yes] Security ABT-737 in combination with T-DM1 will be evaluated during the first 21 days (1 cycle = 21 days), which would help to provide the MTD.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 3 months up to 1 year after discontinuation of the study drugs ] [ Designated as safety issue: No ]</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>lood will be collected to determine how the body responds to study drugs [ Time Frame: Day 1, 8, and 15 of Cycles 1, 2, and 3, then every 3 Cycles while the patient remains on study (e.g., Cycles 6, 9, 12, until completion of study) ] [ Designated as safety issue: No ] Bloodwork will be analyzed to evaluate pharmacokinetics
Progression-Free Survival (PFS) [ Time Frame: Every 3 months up to 1 year after discontinuation of the study drugs ] [ Designated as safety issue: No ] PFS will be assessed every 3 months up to 1 year after discontinuation of the study drugs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ado-trastuzumabT-DM1, ABT-737</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug: trastuzumab emtansine 3.6 mg/kg intravenously every 3 weeks over 30-90 minutes repeats every 21 days for 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients achieving response may continue treatment.
Patients receive Bcl-2  inhibitor ABT-737  PO daily on days 1-21 Patients achieving response may continue treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ado -trastuzumab emtansine T-DM1</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>ado-trastuzumabT-DM1, ABT-737</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kadcyla</other_name>
    <other_name>T-DM1</other_name>
    <other_name>trastuzumab-DM1</other_name>
    <other_name>trastuzumab-MCC-DM1 antibody-drug conjugate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bcl-2  inhibitor ABT-737</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients receive Bcl-2  inhibitor ABT-737  PO daily on days 1-21</description>
    <arm_group_label>ado-trastuzumabT-DM1, ABT-737</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ABT-737</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Signed study-specific informed consent form Histologically or cytologically documented
        breast cancer The presence of metastases is not an obstacle for participation in the study
        HER2-positive disease documented as in situ hybridization (ISH)-positive and/or 3+by
        immunohistochemistry (IHC) on previously collected tumor tissue Absolute neutrophil count
        (ANC) &gt; 1500 cells/mm^3 Platelet count &gt; 100,000/mm^3 Hemoglobin &gt; 9.0 g/dL (patients are
        allowed to receive transfused red blood cells [RBC] to achieve this level) Total bilirubin
        =&lt; 1.5 × upper limit of normal (ULN), except in patients with previously documented
        Gilbert's syndrome, in which case the direct bilirubin should be less than or equal to the
        ULN Serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT) (aspartate aminotransferase [AST]) and
        serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase (SGPT) (alanine aminotransferase [ALT]) =&lt; 2.5 × ULN
        Alkaline phosphatase =&lt; 2.5 × ULN (patients with hepatic and/or bone metastases: alkaline
        phosphatase =&lt; 5 × ULN) Serum creatinine &lt; 1.5 × ULN International normalized ratio (INR)
        &lt; 1.5 × ULN Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0, 1, or 2
        Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &gt;= 50% by either echocardiogram (ECHO) or
        multigated acquisition scan (MUGA) Negative results of serum pregnancy test for
        premenopausal women of reproductive capacity and for women &lt; 12 months after entering
        menopause For women of childbearing potential agreement by the patient and/or partner to
        use a highly effective, non-hormonal form of contraception or two effective forms of
        non-hormonal contraception Willingness and ability to comply with scheduled visits,
        treatment plans, laboratory tests, and other study procedures, including bone marrow
        biopsy and thrombokinetic studies

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Known platelet disorder, such as von Willebrand's disease or baseline platelet count of &lt;
        100,000/mm^3 Chemotherapy =&lt; 21 days before first study treatment Trastuzumab =&lt; 21 days
        before first study treatment Lapatinib =&lt; 14 days before first study treatment
        Investigational therapy or any other therapy =&lt; 28 days before first study treatment Any
        prior trastuzumab emtansine

        The patient has not recovered from any resulting acute toxicity (to grade =&lt; 1) Brain
        metastases that are untreated or symptomatic, or require any radiation, surgery, or
        steroid therapy to control symptoms from brain metastases within 30 days of first on-study
        thrombokinetic study; for patients with newly diagnosed brain metastases or unequivocal
        progression of brain metastases on screening scans, localized treatment (i.e., surgery,
        radiosurgery, and/or whole brain radiotherapy) is required before study enrollment;
        subjects with known brain metastases must have clinically controlled neurologic symptoms,
        defined as surgical excision and/or radiation therapy followed by 14 days of stable
        neurologic function prior to the first thrombo kinetic procedure; patients with small
        brain metastases not symptomatic and deemed requiring treatment by managing clinicians or
        study investigators may be permitted to enroll on study History of intolerance (including
        grade 3 or 4 infusion reaction) or hypersensitivity to trastuzumab or murine proteins
        Current peripheral neuropathy of grade &gt;= 3 per the National Cancer Institute Common
        Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) v. 4.0 Current unstable ventricular
        arrhythmia requiring treatment History of symptomatic congestive heart failure (CHF) (New
        York Heart Association [NYHA] classes II−IV) History of myocardial infarction or unstable
        angina within 6 months of enrollment History of a decrease in LVEF to &lt; 40% or symptomatic
        CHF with previous trastuzumab treatment Severe dyspnea at rest due to complications of
        advanced malignancy or requiring current continuous oxygen therapy Current severe,
        uncontrolled systemic disease (e.g., clinically significant cardiovascular, pulmonary, or
        metabolic disease) resulting in a life expectancy of &lt; 6 months Major surgical procedure
        or significant traumatic injury within 28 days before enrollment or anticipation of the
        need for major surgery during the course of study treatment Current pregnancy or lactation
        Current known active infection with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B,
        and/or hepatitis C virus; for patients who are known carriers of hepatitis B virus (HBV),
        active hepatitis B infection must be ruled out based on negative serologic testing and/or
        determination of HBV deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) viral load per local guidelines Assessed
        by the investigator to be unable or unwilling to comply with the requirements of the
        protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Igog Prihoda, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Antitumor Center Ukraine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dnepropetrovsk</city>
        <zip>49489</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kiev</city>
        <zip>03022</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Ukraine</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 19, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>T-DM1</keyword>
  <keyword>ABT-737 is a BH3 mimetic inhibitor of  Bcl-2</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Trastuzumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Maytansine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
