<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="33418">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01790919</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R34 MH094535-01A1</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R34MH094535-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01790919</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving Depression Outcome by Enhancing Memory for Cognitive Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improving Depression Outcome by Enhancing Memory for Cognitive Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Berkeley</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Vanderbilt University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Berkeley</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Existing drug and talking therapies for major depressive disorder (MDD) fail to produce
      complete recovery.  This study will determine if substantial improvements to one of the most
      promising therapies, cognitive therapy (CT), can be achieved by administering a carefully
      designed procedure to improve memory for the content of CT sessions.  This is important
      because (a) memory deficits are common in MDD patients and (b) each CT therapy session
      typically covers a complex array of topics and various skills are taught.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background. Major depressive disorder (MDD) is one of the most prevalent psychiatric
      disorders and a leading cause of disability worldwide. Existing therapies fail to produce
      complete recovery. Progress toward improving outcome must include innovations that are safe,
      powerful, inexpensive and simple (for fast and effective dissemination). The proposed
      research seeks to test one such innovation. We seek to improve outcome by improving memory
      for the content of cognitive therapy (CT) sessions. CT is one of the most promising
      approaches to the treatment of MDD, yet there is room for improvement.

      We believe that adding memory enhancing strategies to CT may improve MDD outcome because:
      (a) MDD is often characterized by memory impairment, (b) there is evidence that the memory
      impairment is modifiable, (c) CT typically entails the activation of emotion, (d) emotion
      can impair or bias memory and (e) there is evidence that memory for the content of therapy
      sessions is poor.

      Aim. To evaluate if two strategies designed to enhance memory for the content of CT sessions
      improve treatment outcome for MDD. Cognitive support involves a series of specific
      procedures that support the encoding and retrieval stages of an episodic memory. Sleep
      enhancement is based on robust evidence that insufficient sleep before learning impairs
      initial memory encoding, and that sleep after learning plays a critical role in the
      subsequent consolidation of memories. It is hypothesized that CT+Cognitive Support and
      CT+Sleep Enhancement, relative to CT-as-usual, will be associated with improved depression
      outcome at the end of treatment and 6 months after the completion of treatment.

      Research Plan. A small pilot feasibility RCT will be conducted on adults with MDD (n = 72)
      who will be randomized to one of three groups: (a) CT+Cognitive Support (n = 24), (b)
      CT+Sleep Enhancement (n = 24) or (c) CT-as-usual (n = 24). Outcome measures will be taken at
      baseline, end of treatment, and 6 months after treatment. Long-term objective. To provide
      the pilot data needed to prepare a larger scale intervention study focused on improving
      outcomes by improving memory for the content of therapy sessions. The outcomes, if positive,
      will have major public health implications because simple, inexpensive memory enhancing
      strategies can be readily included as a standard feature in all psychosocial treatments for
      a broad range of mental illness. Project
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology (IDS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in IDS scores from pre-treatment to post-treatment (defined as within 2 weeks of completing the course of treatment, which is 14 sessions)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Longitudinal Interval Followup Evaluation (LIFE)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Time to relapse</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV (SCID)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment; Within 2 weeks of completing the course of treatment (14 sessions); 6 month followup</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Longitudinal Interval Follow-up Evaluation (LIFE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment; within 2 weeks of completing the course of treatment (14 sessions); 6-month followup</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder (MDD)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Therapy plus Cognitive Support</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cognitive therapy for depression with cognitive support added</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cognitive therapy for depression</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive therapy for depression</intervention_name>
    <description>Cognitive therapy (CT) for depression. There is evidence that CT for major depressive disorder (MDD) can be as effective as antidepressant medication for the initial treatment of moderate to severe MDD. Moreover, following the withdrawal of treatment, patients treated with CT are significantly less likely to relapse than patients treated with antidepressant medication and CT is at least as effective as antidepressant medication in preventing subsequent relapse. Over 14 sessions CT aims to alter the symptomatic expression of depression and reduce risk for subsequent episodes by correcting the negative beliefs and maladaptive information processing presumed to underlie the disorder and alter the systematic tendency to misperceive reality in a pessimistic fashion.
Cognitive support. An intervention to improve memory for the contents of therapy. Cognitive support involves a series of specific procedures that support the encoding and retrieval stages of an episodic memory.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Therapy plus Cognitive Support</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  diagnosis of major depressive disorder (MDD), first episode, recurrent or chronic,
             according to DSM-IV-TR criteria

          -  score of 24 or above on the Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology (IDS)-Clinican and
             26 or above on the IDS-Self-report

          -  older than 18 years of age

          -  if taking medications for mood, medications must be stable for the past 4 weeks

          -  able and willing to give informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  history of bipolar disorder

          -  history of psychosis (including schizophrenia, schizophreniform disorder,
             schizoaffective disorder, delusional disorder, or psychotic organic brain syndrome)

          -  current non-psychotic Axis I disorder if it constitutes the principal diagnosis and
             if it requires treatment other than that offered in the project (including anxiety
             disorders including active PTSD, somatoform disorders, dissociative disorders, or
             eating disorders, etc.)

          -  history of substance dependence in the past six months

          -  IQ below 80

          -  evidence of any medical disorder or condition that could cause depression or preclude
             participation in CT

          -  current suicide risk sufficient to preclude treatment on an outpatient basis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Berkeley</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berkeley</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94720</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 6, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Berkeley</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Allison Harvey</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Clinical Psychology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Depression, Adults</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
