<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="168152">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01859299</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130072</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-EI-0072</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01859299</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intestinal Bacteria and Ocular Inflammatory Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Microbiome and Ocular Inflammatory Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Uveitis and age-related macular degeneration (AMD) are two types of eye diseases related
      to inflammation in the eyes. However, the causes of these diseases are not fully understood.
      Researchers want to look at bacteria in the body that might be related to the inflammation.
      They will study the natural bacteria present in the gut and intestines of people with
      uveitis and AMD to learn what might trigger these diseases.

      Objectives:

      - To study the gut and intestinal bacteria in people with AMD and uveitis.

      Eligibility:

        -  Individuals at least 18 years of age who have quiet (non-inflamed) uveitis.

        -  Individuals at least 18 years of age who have active (inflamed) uveitis that requires
           additional treatment.

        -  Individuals at least 18 years of age who have uveitis or AMD and are having immune
           system therapy at the National Eye Institute.

      Design:

        -  Participants with quiet uveitis will have one study visit. Participants with active
           uveitis will have two study visits. The second visit will be 4 to 6 months after the
           first visit. Participants with uveitis or AMD who are having immune system therapy will
           have two visits. The first will be before the start of the therapy, and the second
           visit will be 4 to 6 months after starting the therapy.

        -  About 12 hours before each study visit, participants will give themselves an enema at
           home. This will clear out the lower intestine for specimen collection.

        -  At each visit, participants will have a full eye examination, including vision and eye
           pressure tests. They will provide blood samples for testing. They will also have an
           anoscopy to collect rectal fluid and study the colon lining.

        -  Treatment will not be provided as part of this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: What precipitates ocular inflammatory episodes remains unknown but a possible
      potentiating factor is the microbiome. The microbiome has become increasingly studied with
      the advent of new techniques, but these have not been applied to uveitis. We wish to
      evaluate microbiome composition in patients with the ocular inflammatory diseases uveitis
      and agerelated macular degeneration (AMD), who may be on standard therapy or receiving
      orally administered tolerizing antigen therapy.

      Study Population: A total of 45 participants will be enrolled in this study. Of those
      participants, the goal is to enroll 15 participants with treated, quiet uveitis, 15
      participants with active uveitis requiring additional systemic therapy and 15 participants
      with uveitis or AMD that are participating in an oral tolerance study at the NEI.
      Participants must be at least 18 years old. Microbiome samples from an existing control
      population of healthy volunteers established by Dr. Jonathan Braun of UCLA will be used as a
      comparison for the microbiome samples obtained from the participants in this study.
      Peripheral blood samples from an existing control population of healthy volunteers
      established at the NEI LI will be used as a comparison for the peripheral blood samples
      obtained from the participants in this study. No healthy volunteers will be recruited in
      this study.

      Design: This is an observational, cross-sectional, single-center study. Participants will
      receive a complete ocular examination with clinical testing as determined clinically and
      will undergo an anoscopy for collection of rectal fluid specimens. Participants with quiet
      uveitis will only have one study visit; participants with active uveitis requiring
      additional systemic therapy or participants who are participating in an oral tolerance study
      at the NEI will have two study visits.

      Outcome Measures: The outcomes will be related to the comparison of the various microbiome
      samples to controls and between groups. In addition, comparisons will be made to these
      findings and the immunome.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome is principal component analysis using the unweighted UniFrac distance metric of microbial composition; the significance between groups will be tested by the Adonis method</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline; 4-6 months post baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Uveitis</condition>
  <condition>Age-Related Macular Degeneration</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Participant must be 18 years of age or older.

               2. Participant must have a diagnosis of one of the following:

                    -  Treated, quiet uveitis; OR

                    -  Active uveitis requiring additional systemic therapy; OR

                    -  Uveitis or AMD and participating in an NEI oral tolerance study.

               3. Participant must be able to undergo slit lamp biomicroscopy.

               4. Participant must understand and sign the protocol   s informed consent document.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        1.Participant has or had a significant active infection (an infection requiring treatment
        as determined by the investigator) that required systemic antibiotic treatment within the
        past two months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert B Nussenblatt, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Eye Institute (NEI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patti Sherry, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-4529</phone>
    <email>patti.sherry@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Robert B Nussenblatt, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-3123</phone>
    <email>drbob@nei.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-EI-0072.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nussenblatt RB, Gery I, Weiner HL, Ferris FL, Shiloach J, Remaley N, Perry C, Caspi RR, Hafler DA, Foster CS, Whitcup SM. Treatment of uveitis by oral administration of retinal antigens: results of a phase I/II randomized masked trial. Am J Ophthalmol. 1997 May;123(5):583-92.</citation>
    <PMID>9152063</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Presley LL, Ye J, Li X, Leblanc J, Zhang Z, Ruegger PM, Allard J, McGovern D, Ippoliti A, Roth B, Cui X, Jeske DR, Elashoff D, Goodglick L, Braun J, Borneman J. Host-microbe relationships in inflammatory bowel disease detected by bacterial and metaproteomic analysis of the mucosal-luminal interface. Inflamm Bowel Dis. 2012 Mar;18(3):409-17. doi: 10.1002/ibd.21793. Epub 2011 Jun 22.</citation>
    <PMID>21698720</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caporaso JG, Lauber CL, Walters WA, Berg-Lyons D, Lozupone CA, Turnbaugh PJ, Fierer N, Knight R. Global patterns of 16S rRNA diversity at a depth of millions of sequences per sample. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2011 Mar 15;108 Suppl 1:4516-22. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1000080107. Epub 2010 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>20534432</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Oral Tolerance</keyword>
  <keyword>Uveitis</keyword>
  <keyword>AMD</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Macular Degeneration</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uveitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chorioretinitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
