<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="30211">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02046317</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HSC-MS-11-0035</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02046317</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ultrasound Guided Femoral Nerve Block on Isolated Femur Fracture Using Echo Friendly Needles</brief_title>
  <acronym>TUFFEN</acronym>
  <official_title>Trial of Ultrasound Guided Femoral Nerve Block on Isolated Femur Fracture Using Echo Friendly Needles</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      For bone fracture injuries, particularly femur fractures, the femoral nerve block (FNB) can
      provide a fast and effective means to control pain. However, this method is not always
      employed due to the fact that positioning the needle and therefore the block can be time
      consuming and challenging, and if not precisely placed, the nerve block results in poor pain
      control.  Traditional methods for nerve blockade include the blind technique and use of a
      peripheral nerve stimulator (PNS). Unfortunately, neither of these methods provide a
      reliable guide for needle placement and can lead to intraneural placement and/or failed
      attempts.

      Hypothesis: When ultrasound technology is implemented in this procedure it may improve the
      success rate when compared to other techniques by providing real-time visual guidance. This
      may result in a faster and prolonged pain relief reducing the amount of analgesics needed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To date, the published information regarding ultrasound guided femoral blocks using echo
      friendly needle is very limited. More so, there is even less information regarding
      ultrasound guided nerve blocks using echogenic versus standard of care needles.

      This study hopes to add to the general knowledge of pain management in the ED setting and
      provide a unique perspective on ultrasound guided techniques using echogenic needles to
      enhance accuracy and success rate of nerve blocks in ED patients. Results from this study
      will be compared to the results of other similar studies to see if these findings are
      comparative to relevant factors.

      The study design will have two comparative arms; in both arms we use the same local
      anesthetic which is Bupivacaine 0.25% with epinephrine; in all cases a total of 15 ml will
      be injected around the femoral nerve. Once identified with ultrasound 5 ml will be injected
      at lateral, medial and posterior aspect of the nerve.  The experimental arm, will receive a
      FNB using an echogenic needle; and the control group will receive a FNB using standard of
      care needles.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Control</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes after initial femoral block</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This study aims to determine if there is any difference in the success rate of femoral nerve block based on pain control between those performed with an echogenic needle and those performed with a standard needle.
The success of the nerve block is measured by pain control. Pain control is assessed based on a visual analog scale of pain 0-10. We are comparing nerve block success rates based on pain control</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Echogenic needle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The experimental arm will receive femoral nerve block using echogenic needles</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care needle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will receive femoral nerve block using standard of care needles</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Femoral Nerve Block</intervention_name>
    <description>Femoral Nerve Block for isolated femur fractures</description>
    <arm_group_label>Echogenic needle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care needle</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years and older

          -  Patients who present to the ED with isolated femur fracture (no other injuries)

          -  Patients who are cognitively alert and are able to verbalize their pain using a
             visual analog scale (VAS)

          -  Patients who are mentally competent to consent for the study

          -  Patients who can communicate in English or Spanish

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Gestation

          -  Prisoners

          -  Patients who cannot communicate in English or in Spanish

          -  Patients who have other significant injuries besides a femur fracture

          -  Patients who are cognitively impaired and/or unable to verbalize their pain using a
             visual analog scale (VAS)

          -  Patients with allergies to local anesthetics

          -  Patients with severe liver disease

          -  Patients with existing peripheral neuropathies in the affected limb

          -  Patients with history of complications from previous femoral blocks

          -  Patients with contraindications for needle insertion at inguinal area

               -  Local signs of infection

               -  Patient on anticoagulants and/or with history of coagulation disorders
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carlos J Roldan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carlos J Roldan, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>713-500 7933</phone>
    <email>carlos.j.roldan@uth.tmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Hermann Hospital Texas Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lyndon Baines Johnson General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77026</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carlos Roldan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor - Emergency Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Femoral Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
