<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="109284">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01933464</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130199</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01933464</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Analysis of the Effect of Topical Cromolyn Sodium on Rosacea-associated Erythema</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Analysis of the Effect of Topical Cromolyn Sodium on Rosacea-associated Erythema</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Diego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to investigate whether topical application of a cromolyn sodium
      solution is able to decrease the facial redness seen in patients with papulopustular
      rosacea.  Previous work in the lab of Dr. Di Nardo on mice has suggested that cromolyn may
      be able to have this effect.  The study will enroll a total of 10 patients.  5 will randomly
      be assigned to receive the cromolyn sodium solution, and the other 5 will be randomly
      assigned to receive the placebo solution.  All participants will be instructed to apply
      their assigned solution twice daily to their face.  Patients will return to the clinic 3, 6,
      and 8 weeks after the distribution of the solutions to measure the efficacy of their
      assigned solution.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Facial erythema</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Facial erythema will be measured using the Clinician's Erythema Assessment applied to 5 areas of the subject's face (chin, nose glabella, left cheek, right cheek), as well as using measurements from a colorimeter applied to each of the 5 locations previous mentioned</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in facial erythema</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will measure participants' change in facial erythema over the course of the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Matrix Metalloproteinase levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Tape stripping methods will be used to determine matrix metalloproteinase levels</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in matrix metalloproteinase levels</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We will compare subjects' matrix metalloproteinase levels at the beginning of the study (baseline) to those at the end of the study (8 weeks after baseline)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, and then 3, 6 and 8 weeks after beginning study intervention</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse events will be recorded at each visit and their likelihood to the study interventions will be recorded</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Papulopustular Rosacea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cromolyn</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this arm will be asked to apply their assigned medication twice daily to their entire face.  The medication they will be receiving is cromolyn sodium ophthalmic solution, 4%.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vehicle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this group will be assigned a solution consisting of only the inactive ingredients in cromolyn sodium ophthalmic solution to apply to their entire face twice daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cromolyn Sodium</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cromolyn</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Crolom</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Normal Saline</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Vehicle</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>0.9% sodium chloride</other_name>
    <other_name>NaCl</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is male or non-pregnant female, 18 - 80 years of age.

          -  Subjects willing and able to give informed consent.

          -  Subjects willing and able to comply with the requirements of the study.

          -  Subject has the clinical diagnosis of at least mild erythema.

          -  Subject has been on a stable dose for greater than 3 months of medications  for
             treatment of concurrent medical condition (including oral contraceptive pills,
             vasodilators, adrenergic blocking agents) OR the investigator has determined that the
             medications are unlikely to affect the patient's rosacea and/or treatment during the
             study

          -  Subject is in general good health in the opinion of the investigator.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has a diagnosis of Steroid Rosacea or Pyoderma Faciale (rosacea fulminans)

          -  Subject has a history of Carcinoid, Pheochromocytoma, Serotonin Syndrome or other
             systemic flushing causes.

        Subject has used facial topical therapies (OTC drug products or prescription products) for
        any reason within the prior 28 days

          -  Subject has used systemic corticosteroid or systemic antibiotics (especially
             doxycycline, minocycline, tetracycline, metronidazole) within the prior 28 days.

          -  Subject has had laser or light-based treatment for rosacea within the prior 3 months.

          -  Subject has had systemic retinoids and retinoid derivatives over the past 6 months

          -  Subject has any history of renal or hepatic insufficiency.

          -  Subject has a known hypersensitivity or allergy to Cromolyn sodium or components of
             the vehicle.

          -  Subject is pregnant or lactating or planning a pregnancy during the duration of the
             study

          -  Subject has been treated with another investigational device or drug within 28 days
             prior to study enrollment or intends to participate in a clinical trial concurrent
             with this study

          -  Subject has clinically significant findings, medical history or conditions (other
             than rosacea), which in the opinion of the Investigator may compromise the study,
             treatment protocol, or safety of the patient or treatment allocation.

        Subject has a known hypersensitivity or allergy to tape or other adhesive materials
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Aimee Two, MD</last_name>
    <phone>858-657-8390</phone>
    <email>ucsddermstudies@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSD Division of Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aimee Two, MD</last_name>
      <phone>858-657-8390</phone>
      <email>ucsddermstudies@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anna Di Nardo, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 28, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 21, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Diego</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anna Di Nardo, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD (Associate Professor of Medicine)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rosacea</keyword>
  <keyword>Cromolyn sodium</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Rosacea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Erythema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cromolyn Sodium</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
