<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="77275">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01957345</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12 068 08</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>PHRCI 2012</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01957345</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of a New Approach of the Diagnosis of Constitutional Functional Disorders of Platelets</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multicentre Evaluation of a New Laboratory Approach for the Diagnosis of Constitutional Functional Disorders of Platelets</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Toulouse</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Toulouse</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Afssaps - Agence française de sécurité sanitaire des produits de santé (Saint-Denis)</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of the study is to evaluate a standardized method of screening for
      platelet signalling defects in patients with constitutional disorders of platelet function
      of unknown origin. We hypothesize that such defects are under-diagnosed in patients, due to
      heavy workup and requirement of relatively large blood sample by conventional biochemical
      methods. We propose to analyse kinase signalling downstream platelet membrane receptors
      using multiplex flow cytometry quantification and fluorescent platelet barcoding.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Little is known of the molecular basis of disorders of signalling pathways potentially
      responsible of constitutional defects of platelet functions (adhesion, aggregation or
      secretion) (1-5). Indeed, in routine practice, this investigation is limited by the
      complexity of the analyse using biochemical methods (western blotting), and the requirement
      of large amount of platelets.

      We have designed a new approach for the quantification of platelet cytoplasmic
      phosphoproteins by flow cytometry. Fresh platelets in platelet rich plasma are analysed at
      baseline or after stimulation by major agonists (ADP, TRAP, thromboxane analogue, or
      collagen-related peptide), with and without relevant inhibitors of each pathway. Multiplex
      barcoding is used to identify each condition, allowing a high throughput analysis (6, 7).
      Platelet signalling profiling of Akt, Slp76, P38 MAPK and LIMK can be obtained from a blood
      sample of less than 10 ml, and within 6h The main objective of the study is to standardize
      the method between clinical laboratories with a standard expertise in flow cytometry. The
      study will be performed in 4 academic hospitals members of the French reference network of
      rare platelet diseases. Three groups of patients referred for mild or severe bleeding
      disorders will be included: 1) a control group of patients (30 per centre) with a bleeding
      disorder definitely other than of platelet origin (e.g. &quot;low&quot; von Willebrand); 2) a group of
      10 patients per centre with definite constitutional platelet disorder (e.g. Glanzmann
      thrombasthenia) and 3) a group of 10 patients per centre with a defect of platelet function
      of unknown origin, potentially defective in signalling pathway.

      The control group will serve to standardize the method between centres and to establish the
      reference values. A quality control will be set up by using frozen platelet preparations.
      The patients with definite platelet disorder will be useful for detecting potential
      signalling defects still not described in these pathologies. Platelet signalling defects
      which could be evidenced in these groups will be further identified by conventional
      biochemical and molecular methods after confirmation on a new sample.

      If this new approach can be proposed to clinical laboratories working on rare platelet
      diseases, we expect an advance in our knowledge in the field. In addition the method has a
      potential in pharmaceutical innovation, for identifying (8) or monitoring new antiplatelet
      agents (9, 10), or identifying platelet defects induced by new &quot;target therapies&quot; designed
      for other diseases such as cancer or immune pathologies (10).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>standardise the method between clinical laboratories</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>This is a pilot study of a new approach of screening platelet signalling pathways disorders by flow cytometry with methodological primary outcomes (12) as follows: 1)to standardise the method between clinical laboratories, 2)to establish reference values of the method and 3)to design a quality control assessment
The primary endpoint will focus on the overall variability of reference values ​​observed in subjects without thrombopathy for each marker after agonist stimulation and corresponding search of an effect if a center-center effect is observed on the reference values its origin will be sought (deviation from the protocol, reagent lot .....) and corrected. The &quot;center effect&quot; will also be analyzed by the quarterly quality control, which will compare the results obtained from the same wafer tests analyzed simultaneously in three sites.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To describe the signalling pathways in platelet disorders</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe the signalling pathways in platelet disorders with definite diagnosis To screen putative defects in bleeding patients with disorders of platelet function of unknown origin To identify more deeply the defects found in these groups.
Several markers will be analyzed, corresponding to routes or levels of different signaling. For each of these markers, the test will evaluate quantitatively the phosphorylation activity of the protein tested. We can thus determine for each subject and each marker, the response to the test defined by:
The percentage increase in the signal (relative to the rest) after stimulation with a receptor agonist,
The percentage increase in the signal (relative to the rest) in the presence of the agonist to the associated receptor antagonist.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Platelet Dysfunction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>bleeding disorder</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Blood punction at patients with bleeding disorder definitely other than of platelet origin (e.g. &quot;low&quot; von Willebrand)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>constitutional platelet disorder</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Blood punction at patients with constitutional platelet disorder (e.g. Glanzmann thrombasthenia)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>defect of platelet function</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Blood punction at patients with defect of platelet function of unknown origin, potentially defective in signalling pathway.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood punction</intervention_name>
    <description>T1 and T2: one blood punction of 2X 4,5 ml with signalisation test (T1 for each arm, T2 at +6 months only if an anomaly at signalysation test is detected)
signalisation test is made by flow cytometry
Stage 1: for arm &quot;bleeding disorder&quot; : flow cytometry analysis to establish reference values ​​observed in subjects without thrombopathy for each marker after agonist stimulation and corresponding search of an effect if a center-center effect is observed on the reference values its origin will be sought and corrected.
Stage 2: for the two others arms: Several markers will be analyzed, corresponding to routes or levels of different signaling. For each of these markers, the test will evaluate quantitatively the phosphorylation activity of the protein tested.</description>
    <arm_group_label>bleeding disorder</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>constitutional platelet disorder</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>defect of platelet function</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patient consulting for hemorrhagic symptomatology with

          -  with a bleeding disorder definitely other than of platelet origin (e.g. &quot;low&quot; von
             Willebrand);

          -  or constitutional platelet disorder (e.g. Glanzmann thrombasthenia)

          -  or with a defect of platelet function of unknown origin, potentially defective in
             signalling pathway.

          -  Informed consent form

          -  patient with social security insurance or equivalent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  treatment interfering with platelets function within 7 days prior to enrollment

          -  age&lt;18 years

          -  thrombocytopenia &lt;100G/L

          -  pregnant or lactating females

          -  subjects under juridical protection guardianship or tutelage measure

          -  subjects involved in another clinical trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pierre SIE, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHU Toulouse</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pierre SIE, Pr</last_name>
    <phone>33 561322289</phone>
    <email>sie.p@chu-toulouse.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Toulouse</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pierre SIE, Pr</last_name>
      <phone>0561322289</phone>
      <email>sie.p@chu-toulouse.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pierre SIE, Pr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nurden A, Nurden P. Advances in our understanding of the molecular basis of disorders of platelet function. J Thromb Haemost. 2011 Jul;9 Suppl 1:76-91. doi: 10.1111/j.1538-7836.2011.04274.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21781244</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rao AK. Inherited defects in platelet signaling mechanisms. J Thromb Haemost. 2003 Apr;1(4):671-81. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12871400</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Noé L, Di Michele M, Giets E, Thys C, Wittevrongel C, De Vos R, Overbergh L, Waelkens E, Jaeken J, Van Geet C, Freson K. Platelet Gs hypofunction and abnormal morphology resulting from a heterozygous RGS2 mutation. J Thromb Haemost. 2010 Jul;8(7):1594-603. doi: 10.1111/j.1538-7836.2010.03885.x. Epub 2010 Apr 16.</citation>
    <PMID>20403096</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Freson K, Hoylaerts MF, Jaeken J, Eyssen M, Arnout J, Vermylen J, Van Geet C. Genetic variation of the extra-large stimulatory G protein alpha-subunit leads to Gs hyperfunction in platelets and is a risk factor for bleeding. Thromb Haemost. 2001 Sep;86(3):733-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11583302</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vaidyula VR, Rao AK. Role of Galphaq and phospholipase C-beta2 in human platelets activation by thrombin receptors PAR1 and PAR4: studies in human platelets deficient in Galphaq and phospholipase C-beta2. Br J Haematol. 2003 May;121(3):491-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12716374</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Krutzik PO, Clutter MR, Trejo A, Nolan GP. Fluorescent cell barcoding for multiplex flow cytometry. Curr Protoc Cytom. 2011 Jan;Chapter 6:Unit 6.31. doi: 10.1002/0471142956.cy0631s55. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21207359</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Krutzik PO, Trejo A, Schulz KR, Nolan GP. Phospho flow cytometry methods for the analysis of kinase signaling in cell lines and primary human blood samples. Methods Mol Biol. 2011;699:179-202. doi: 10.1007/978-1-61737-950-5_9.</citation>
    <PMID>21116984</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carrié D, Garcia C, Gratacap MP, Voisin S, Payrastre B, Sié P. Assessment of platelet response to clopidogrel through measurement of ADP-induced Akt phosphorylation. J Thromb Haemost. 2009 Aug;7(8):1411-3. doi: 10.1111/j.1538-7836.2009.03485.x. Epub 2009 May 15.</citation>
    <PMID>19453937</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lhermusier T, Van Rothem J, Garcia C, Gratacap MP, Payrastre B. Targeted drug therapy: the platelet side. Platelets. 2011;22(7):479-84. doi: 10.3109/09537104.2011.567423. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21973091</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lhermusier T, van Rottem J, Garcia C, Xuereb JM, Ragab A, Martin V, Gratacap MP, Sié P, Payrastre B. The Syk-kinase inhibitor R406 impairs platelet activation and monocyte tissue factor expression triggered by heparin-PF4 complex directed antibodies. J Thromb Haemost. 2011 Oct;9(10):2067-76. doi: 10.1111/j.1538-7836.2011.04470.x.</citation>
    <PMID>21848694</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gratacap MP, Martin V, Valéra MC, Allart S, Garcia C, Sié P, Recher C, Payrastre B. The new tyrosine-kinase inhibitor and anticancer drug dasatinib reversibly affects platelet activation in vitro and in vivo. Blood. 2009 Aug 27;114(9):1884-92. doi: 10.1182/blood-2009-02-205328. Epub 2009 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19494352</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lancaster GA, Dodd S, Williamson PR. Design and analysis of pilot studies: recommendations for good practice. J Eval Clin Pract. 2004 May;10(2):307-12.</citation>
    <PMID>15189396</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 30, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>constitutional functional disorders of platelets</keyword>
  <keyword>platelet signalling defects</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Blood Platelet Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
