<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="97564">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02055157</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>111-202</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-004137-32</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02055157</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 2 Study of BMN 111 to Evaluate Safety, Tolerability, and Efficacy in Children With Achondroplasia</brief_title>
  <acronym>ACH</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 2, Open-label, Sequential Cohort Dose-escalation Study of BMN 111 in Children With Achondroplasia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>BioMarin Pharmaceutical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>BioMarin Pharmaceutical</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>Australia: Human Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <authority>France: Committee for the Protection of Personnes</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 2, open-label, sequential cohort dose-escalation study of BMN 111 in
      children with achondroplasia.  The primary objective is to assess the safety and
      tolerability of daily BMN 111 administered to children with achondroplasia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Measures</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 6 months. Following completion of study (Month 6), a safety follow up visit will be conducted (Month 7).</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Safety evaluations by indicence of adverse events, serious adverse events, laboratory test results (urinaysis, chemistry, hematology), clinically significant changes in vital signs, physical examination, ECG and ECHO results, imaging, and anti-BMN 111 immunogenicity assessments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy measure</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Efficacy will be assessed by change from baseline in height growth velocity (annualized to cm/yr), absolute growth, subject growth compared with ACH and non-ACH standardized pediatric growth curves, and change in body proportions. These will be assessed by anthropometric measurements and measurement ratios.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Achondroplasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BMN 111 - Subcutaneous Injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>111-202 is an open-label sequential cohort dose-escalation study. BMN 111 will be administered as a morning dose in one of the following daily dosing regimens:
• Cohort 1: 2.5 microgram/kg, Cohort 2: 7.5 microgram/kg, and Cohort 3: 15.0 microgram/kg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BMN 111</intervention_name>
    <description>BMN 111 will be administered daily for 6 months in an open-label sequential dose escalation fashion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BMN 111 - Subcutaneous Injection</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Modified recombinant human C-type natriuretic peptide</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Parent(s) or guardian(s) are willing and able to provide written, signed informed
             consent after the nature of the study has been explained and prior to performance of
             any research-related procedure. Also, subjects under the age of 18 are willing and
             able to provide written assent (if required) after the nature of the study has been
             explained and prior to performance of any research-related procedure.

          -  Are 5 to 14 years old, inclusive

          -  Have ACH, documented by clinical grounds and confirmed by genetic testing

          -  Have at least a 6-month period of pretreatment growth assessment in Study 111-901
             immediately before study entry

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test at the
             Screening Visit and be willing to have additional pregnancy tests during the study

          -  If sexually active, willing to use an acceptable method of contraception while
             participating in the study

          -  Are ambulatory and able to stand without assistance

          -  Are willing and able to perform all study procedures as physically possible

          -  Parents or caregivers are willing to administer daily injections to the subjects

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have hypochondroplasia or short stature condition other than ACH (eg, trisomy 21,
             pseudoachondroplasia)

          -  Have any of the following:

               -  Hypothyroidism

               -  Insulin-requiring diabetes mellitus

               -  Autoimmune inflammatory disease

               -  Inflammatory bowel disease

               -  Autonomic neuropathy

               -  Acute illness associated with volume dehydration (eg, nausea, vomiting,
                  diarrhea)

          -  Have an unstable condition likely to require surgical intervention during the study
             (including progressive cervical medullary compression)

          -  Growth plates have fused

          -  Have a history of any of the following:

               -  Renal insufficiency

               -  Anemia

               -  Baseline systolic BP &lt; 75 mm Hg or recurrent symptomatic hypotension  (defined
                  as episodes of low BP generally accompanied by symptoms i.e., dizziness,
                  fainting) or recurrent symptomatic orthostatic hypotension

          -  Cardiac or vascular disease, including the following:

               -  Cardiac dysfunction (abnormal echocardiogram [ECHO] including left ventricle
                  [LV] mass) at Screening Visit

               -  Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy

               -  Congenital heart disease with ongoing cardiac dysfunction

               -  Cerebrovascular disease, aortic insufficiency

               -  Clinically significant atrial or ventricular arrhythmias

          -  Have an ECG showing any of the following:

               -  Right or left atrial enlargement or ventricular hypertrophy

               -  PR interval &gt; 200 msec

               -  QRS interval &gt; 110 msec

               -  Corrected QTc &gt; 440 msec

               -  Second- or third-degree atrioventricular block

          -  Demonstrate vitamin D deficiency (i.e., concentration of 25-hydroxy-vitamin D in the
             blood serum occurs at 12 ng/mL or less)

          -  Require any investigational agent prior to completion of study period

          -  Have received another investigational product or investigational medical device
             within 30 days before the Screening visit

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding at the Screenng Visit or planning to become pregnant (self
             or partner) at any time during the study

          -  Current treatment with antihypertensive medications, ACE inhibitors, angiotensin II
             receptor blockers, diuretics, beta-blockers, calcium-channel blockers, cardiac
             glycosides, systemic anticholinergic agents, any medication that may impair or
             enhance compensatory tachycardia, drugs known to alter renal function

          -  Have been treated with growth hormone, IGF-1, or anabolic steroids in the previous 6
             months or long-term treatment (&gt; 3 months) at any time

          -  Have had regular long-term treatment (&gt; 1 month) with oral corticosteroids (low-dose
             ongoing inhaled steroid for asthma is acceptable)

          -  Concomitant medication that prolongs the QT/QTc interval within 14 days or 5
             half-lives, whichever is longer, before the Screening visit

          -  Unwilling to temporarily discontinue CPAP use for 2 days prior to Screening visit if
             applicable

          -  Have used any other investigational product or investigational medical device for the
             treatment of ACH or short stature

          -  Have had bone-related surgery or expected to have bone-related surgery during the
             study period. Subjects with previous limb-lengthening surgery may enroll if surgery
             occurred at least 18 months prior to the study and healing is complete without
             sequelae

          -  Have aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) at least 3x
             upper limit of normal (ULN) or total bilirubin at least 2x ULN

          -  Have known hypersensitivity to BMN 111 or its excipients

          -  Has a condition or circumstance that, in the view of the Investigator, places the
             subject at high risk for poor treatment compliance or for not completing the study

          -  Concurrent disease or condition that, in the view of the Investigator, would
             interfere with study participation or safety evaluations, or would predispose the
             subject to hypotension (such as recent gastroenteritis or dehydration for any reason)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>BioMarin Pharmaceutical</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Robin McMahon, MPH</last_name>
    <email>rmcmahon@bmrn.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Oakland</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94609</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232-2578</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Parkville</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3052</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75015</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE1 9RT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Achondroplasia</keyword>
  <keyword>Dwarfism</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone Diseases, Developmental</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone Diseases</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Achondroplasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Natriuretic Peptide, C-Type</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
