<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="4911">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01965002</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VAR0095</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>26667</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01965002</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Feasibility of ExAblate MRI Guided High Intensity Focused Ultrasound Tx of Soft Tissue Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Feasibility Study to Evaluate the Safety and Effectiveness of ExAblate Magnetic Resonance Imaging Guided High Intensity Focused Ultrasound Treatment of Soft Tissue Tumors of the Extremities</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pejman Ghanouni</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this project is to evaluate the safety and preliminary efficacy of ExAblate MR
      guided focused ultrasound surgery in the treatment of soft tissue tumors of the extremities.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives include assessment of the incidence and severity of adverse events associated
      with treatment, and the accuracy of ablation by comparing the measured volume treated based
      on MR thermometry and post-contrast non-perfused tissue calculations to the actual treated
      volume in the resected tumor. In addition, the tissue adjacent to the treated region within
      the tumor but outside the gross limits of the ablation will be examined histologically for
      evidence of thermal damage.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety determined by evaluating for the incidence and severity of any device related complication</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will be examined for changes in clinical exam, pain, and limb function, using the Musculoskeletal Tumor Society Score and the Toronto Extremity Salvage Score to compare before and after high-intensity focused ultrasound (HIFU) treatment. A safety profile will be developed for the ExAblate treatment of soft tissue tumors. All adverse events will be captured and summarized.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent successful ablation or non-perfused volume (NPV)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>In the resected specimen, the volume of the ablated area will be determined by obtaining a digital photograph of each pathology slice. The region of interest corresponding to the ablated area will be traced, and the ablated area will be calculated for each slice, and summed to determine the volume.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Accuracy of ablation volume within the tumor</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The percent difference in overlap of actual treated volume to other volume measures will be calculated and a nonparametric 90% coverage tolerance interval with 95% confidence will be constructed for each tumor ablation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Soft Tissue Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MRgHIFU</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ExAblate Magnetic Resonance Imaging Guided High Intensity Focused Ultrasound (MRgHIFU)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>MRgHIFU</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males and females at least 10 years of age.

          2. Patients who have benign or malignant soft tissue tumors of the extremities, flanks,
             pelvis, or shoulders that require surgical intervention.

          3. Tumor must not have been treated previously with radiation.

          4. Patients (or guardians/parents) who are able and willing to give consent (and assent
             where applicable) and able to attend all study visits.

          5. Able to safely undergo MRI exam and receive mild sedation for the treatment.

          6. Patient is able to tolerate being in the MRI scanner for the duration of the study.

          7. Targeted tumor(s) are accessible to the ExAblate device

          8. Patients in whom the targeted volume within the tumor is located deeper than 1 cm
             from the skin

          9. Targeted tumor is clearly visible by non-contrast MRI

         10. Karnofsky Performance Status &gt; 60

         11. Normal platelet count and coagulation profile

         12. Glomerular filtration rate &gt; 60 ml/min

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous radiation treatment to the tumor.

          2. Patients on dialysis.

          3. Patients with acute medical condition (e.g. pneumonia, sepsis) that is expected to
             hinder them from completing this study

          4. Patients with unstable cardiac status including:

               1. Unstable angina pectoris on medication

               2. Patients with documented myocardial infarction within six months of protocol
                  entry

               3. Congestive heart failure requiring medication (other than diuretic)

               4. Patients on anti-arrhythmic drugs

          5. Severe hypertension (diastolic BP &gt; 100 on medication)

          6. Patients with contraindication for MR imaging such as implanted metallic devices that
             are not MRI-safe, size limitations, etc

          7. Patients with severe hematologic, neurologic, or other uncontrolled disease

          8. Known intolerance or allergy to medications used for sedation (midazolam), analgesia
             (fentanyl), and local and regional anesthesia (lidocaine, bupivacaine, and
             ropivacaine)

          9. Known intolerance or allergy to MR contrast agent (gadolinium chelates) including
             advanced kidney disease

             a. Pregnant and nursing patients will be excluded from the study because of a
             contraindication to administering MRI contrast agents to these patients

         10. Karnofsky Performance Score &lt; 60

         11. Severe cerebrovascular disease (multiple CVAs or CVA within 6 months)

         12. Individuals who are not able or willing to tolerate the required prolonged stationary
             position during treatment (can be up to 5 hrs of total table time)

         13. Target volume in tumor is less then 1cm from neurovascular bundles, major blood
             vessels, bowel or bladder.

         14. Targeted tumors:

               -  NOT visible by non-contrast MRI, OR

               -  NOT accessible to ExAblate device

         15. Patient not candidate for either regional anesthesia or mild sedation

         16. Patient should not be part of another trial testing other Investigational Agents or
             Devices
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raffi Avedian</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pejman Ghanouni</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94306</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Raffi Avedian</last_name>
      <phone>650-721-2479</phone>
      <email>ravedian@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raffi Avedian</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 16, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Pejman Ghanouni</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Radiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Soft Tissue Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
