<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="80762">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02110147</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>401.13.001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02110147</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Open-Label Study of Uridine Triacetate in Pediatric Patients With Hereditary Orotic Aciduria</brief_title>
  <official_title>Open-Label Study of Uridine Triacetate in Pediatric Patients With Hereditary Orotic Aciduria</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wellstat Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wellstat Therapeutics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This protocol has two parts - the Main Study which is 42 days in length and the Treatment
      Extension Study which allows the patients who complete the Main Study to continue receiving
      treatment with uridine triacetate.  The purpose of this study is to replace oral
      administration of uridine with oral administration of uridine triacetate in patients with
      hereditary orotic aciduria who have received (or would reasonably be expected to receive)
      clinical benefit from treatment with exogenous uridine.  It is also to document the
      continued clinical benefit of exogenous uridine when patients are switched from oral
      administration of uridine to oral administration of uridine triacetate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Data to be collected during the Main Study include demographic, baseline disease information
      and medical history including all prior disease-directed therapy. In addition, vital signs,
      laboratory values and adverse events information will be collected and recorded.  Urine
      samples will be obtained and measured for orotic acid and orotidine levels.  Systemic levels
      of uridine will be evaluated from plasma samples collected at set timepoints.

      Upon successful completion of the Main Study and entry into the Treatment Extension of the
      study, physical exams and vital signs will be performed every six (6) months. Additionally,
      plasma samples to measure systemic levels of uridine and urine samples to measure levels of
      orotic acid and orotidine will be collected every (6) six months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of orotidine and orotic acid in urine</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Hereditary orotic aciduria patients will be taking uridine triacetate as replacement therapy for uridine.  Levels of orotidine and orotic acid in the urine will be measured during both the main study as well as the extension study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Hereditary Orotic Aciduria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Uridine Triacetate to Replace Uridine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Replacement therapy for oral uridine with oral administration of uridine triacetate in patients with hereditary orotic aciduria who have received or would reasonably be expected to receive) clinical benefit from treatment with exogenous uridine.  The starting dose of uridine triacetate will be 60 mg/kg/day which may be escalated to 300 mg/kg/day of oral uridine triacetate.  The dose may be given once a day or as equally divided doses twice a day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>uridine triacetate</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Uridine Triacetate to Replace Uridine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PN401 (Company Code Name)</other_name>
    <other_name>2',3',5'-tri-O-acetyluridine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (Main Study):

          -  Age equal to or less than 19 years

          -  Patients with diagnosed hereditary orotic aciduria

          -  Judged by the investigator to have the initiative and means to be compliant  with the
             protocol

          -  Able to take oral medications

          -  Able to provide written informed consent (patient or legally authorized
             representative)

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test at screening

          -  Females of childbearing potential or males with partners of childbearing potential
             are to use one of the following acceptable birth control methods:

          -  Surgically sterile or partner is surgically sterile

          -  Using adequate contraception (hormonal contraceptives, double barrier methods, or
             intra-uterine devices)

          -  Patients who claim to be sexually inactive agree to use an acceptable method of
             contraception should she or he become sexually active from 14 days prior to first
             dosing, throughout the study and for 14 days after the last dose administration

        Exclusion Criteria (Main Study):

          -  Has a known allergy to uridine triacetate or any of its excipients

          -  Known to have ornithine transcarbamoylase deficiency

          -  Unable to have the initiative  and means to be compliant with the protocol

          -  Unable to be compliant with taking oral medications

          -  Unable to provide written informed consent (patient or legally authorized
             representative

          -  Female who is pregnant or lactating

        Inclusion Criteria (Treatment Extension)

          -  Patient successfully completed the Main Study

        Exclusion Criteria (Treatment Extension Study)

          -  Patient did not successfully complete the Main Study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>19 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael K. Bamat, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Wellstat Therapeutics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Robert O. Tremmel, PharmD</last_name>
    <phone>443.831.5626</phone>
    <email>rtremmel@wellstat.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>William E. Gannon, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>202.548.4930</phone>
    <email>wgannon@capcitytek.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gerard Vockley, MD</last_name>
      <phone>412-692-7746</phone>
      <email>gerard.vockley@chp.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gerard Vockley, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 1, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Purine-Pyrimidine Metabolism, Inborn Errors</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
