<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="85766">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02033850</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RF-2010-2321706</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02033850</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Rehabilitation of Attention in Patients With Mild Cognitive Impairment and Brain Subcortical Vascular Changes Using the Attention Process Training-II</brief_title>
  <acronym>RehAtt</acronym>
  <official_title>The Rehabilitation of Attention in Patients With Mild Cognitive Impairment and Brain Subcortical Vascular Changes Using the Attention Process Training-II</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria Careggi</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ministero della Salute, Italy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria Careggi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Italy: Ministry of Health</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Subcortical Vascular Dementia (VaD), consequent to deep brain small vessel
      disease (SVD), is the most frequent form of VaD. The term vascular mild cognitive impairment
      (VMCI) defines a transitional state between normal ageing and VaD. Attentional deficits are
      a common finding in patients affected by VMCI or subcortical VaD. At present, no drug
      treatment is available to prevent vascular dementia in patients with VMCI or to improve
      cognitive performances of this large group of patients. Cognitive rehabilitation is directed
      to achieve functional changes by reinforcing, strengthening, or reestablishing previously
      learned patterns of behavior, or establishing new patterns of cognitive activity or
      compensatory mechanisms.

      A hierarchical model of attention has been used to build the Attention Process Training-II
      (APT-II) programme.

      The APT-II programme effectiveness have been demonstrated in traumatic brain injury and
      post-stroke rehabilitation, but there is an increasing interest in the study of cognitive
      rehabilitation in pathological processes that evolve over time, such as chronic
      cerebrovascular diseases (CVD).

      Aims: The purpose of this study is to investigate whether the APT-II programme could be a
      useful tool in the rehabilitation of attention in individuals affected by VMCI with SVD, and
      if so, whether the improvement in performance is generalized to functionality in daily
      activities and quality of life.

      Main Expected Results and Impact: Considering that the APT-II contains specific exercises to
      facilitate generalization to daily life, the skills that are learned by each patient during
      the rehabilitation programme should be generalized to daily activities.

      Furthermore, the improvement of cognitive skills should also improve patient's overall
      quality of life because these learned skills are applicable to real-life situations. The
      main expected results are: 1) an impact of APT-II on disability, everyday cognition, quality
      of life, and performance on attention tests at short and long term after rehabilitation
      programme ending as compared with standard care; 2) a reduction of the risk of transition to
      dementia at 1 year follow-up as compared with control group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functionality in activities of daily living and quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary outcome of this study is to improve functionality in activities of daily living and quality of life in patients who undergo a rehabilitation program with the Attention Process Training-II (APT-II) program.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive performance</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Improvement in cognitive performance will be evaluated according to the evidence of a clinically significant increase in scores for tests included in the extensive neuropsychological assessment. Within and between groups statistical analyses and effect size measures will be carried out.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Transition to dementia</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Dementia diagnosis will be made according to DSM-IV criteria. Staging of dementia severity will be performed according to clinical dementia rating scale. Reduction of the short-term risk of transition to dementia will be evaluated using within and between groups statistical analyses and effect size measures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive plasticity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Improvement in long-term brain activation, as a result of a training-induced cognitive plasticity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Vascular Mild Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>APT-II group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the APT-II group will receive overall up to 40 hours of individual attention process training. Therapy will be administered in one two-hour session each week over a total of 20 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>standard care group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the standard care group will not receive cognitive training or rehabilitation interventions, will be instructed to have an usual lifestyle, and will be conventionally provided of medication and clinic consultations</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Attention Process Training-II</intervention_name>
    <description>Rehabilitation of attention using the Attention Process Training-II</description>
    <arm_group_label>APT-II group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients will be enrolled according to the following criteria:

          -  MCI defined according to Winblad et al. criteria;

          -  Evidence of impairment across attention neuropsychological tests;

          -  Evidence on MRI of subcortical vascular lesions: moderate to severe age-related white
             matter changes (WMC) according to a modified version of the Fazekas scale.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt; 18 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stroke Unit and Neurology, VAS-COG clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Firenze</city>
        <zip>50134</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Leonardo Pantoni, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+39-055-7945519</phone>
      <email>pantoni@unifi.it</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Emilia Salvadori, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 10, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 24, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria Careggi</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Leonardo Pantoni</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Staff neurologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>small vessel disease</keyword>
  <keyword>cognition</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>attention</keyword>
  <keyword>fMRI</keyword>
  <keyword>vascular dementia</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cognition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
