<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="78945">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01928446</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>590</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01928446</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lithium for Suicidal Behavior in Mood Disorders</brief_title>
  <acronym>Li+</acronym>
  <official_title>CSP #590 - Lithium for Suicidal Behavior in Mood Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Observational evidence and findings from clinical trials conducted for other reasons suggest
      that lithium, a drug used for the treatment of bipolar disorder, and, to a lesser extent,
      depression, may reduce rates of suicides and suicide attempts. However, this hypothesis has
      not yet been adequately examined in a randomized clinical trial conducted specifically to
      test lithium's efficacy in preventing suicides. This clinical trial fills this gap.

      This study is feasible within the Department of Veterans Affairs (VA) because it is a large,
      integrated health system with existing programs for identifying patients at risk for suicide
      and delivering enhanced services. In VA, approximately 12,000 patients with depression or
      bipolar disorder survive a suicide attempt or related behavior each year, and 15% of them
      repeat within one year. Experimental treatment in this study will supplement usual care for
      major depression or bipolar disorder, as well as VA's standard, enhanced management for
      patients at high risk.

      The investigators will recruit 1862 study participants, from approximately 30 VA Hospitals.
      Participants will be patients with bipolar disorder or depression who have survived a recent
      episode of suicidal self-directed violence or were hospitalized specifically to prevent
      suicide. Randomly, half will receive lithium, and half will receive placebo.  Neither the
      patients nor their doctors will know whether a particular person has received lithium or
      placebo. The treatment will be administered and the patients will be followed for one year,
      after which patients will go back to usual care. Recruitment will occur over 3 years.

      The investigators are primarily interested in whether lithium leads to increases in the time
      to the first repeated episode of suicidal behavior, including suicide attempts, interrupted
      attempts, hospitalizations specifically to prevent suicide, and deaths from suicide. In
      addition, this study will allow us to explore whether lithium decreases the total number of
      suicidal behaviors, and whether it has comparable effects on impulsive and non-impulsive
      behaviors. If there is an effect of lithium, the investigators will be interested in whether
      or not it could be attributed to improved control of the underlying mental health condition,
      or, alternatively, whether it represents a direct effect of suicide-related behavior.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: To test the hypothesis that lithium augmentation of enhanced usual care will
      reduce the rate of repeated episodes of suicidal self-directed violence (repeated suicide
      attempts, interrupted attempts, hospitalizations specifically to prevent suicide, and deaths
      from suicide) in participants with bipolar disorder or depression who have survived a recent
      event.

      Background: The hypothesis that lithium can prevent suicide in patients with bipolar
      disorder and depression is based on data from observational studies and randomized clinical
      trials conducted to evaluate other outcomes. The question about the effectiveness of lithium
      for suicide prevention is one of major scientific, clinical, and public health significance.
      There have been no adequately powered clinical trials conducted specifically to evaluate
      suicide behaviors as an outcome. Two recent randomized clinical trials failed to recruit
      adequate numbers of subjects to be conclusive.

      The VHA, as a large national healthcare system with an established program for identifying
      new suicide attempts, evaluating patients for underlying mental health and medical
      conditions, providing needed services, connecting Veterans to state-of-the-art suicide risk
      management, and monitoring outcomes is uniquely able to conduct a large scale clinical trial
      of lithium for suicide prevention.

      The rationale for the study is based on the following:

        -  Data from observational studies and double-blind randomized clinical trials suggest
           that lithium can prevent suicide-related behaviors in patients with bipolar disorder
           and major depression.

        -  The high risk of suicide in veterans receiving health care services from VHA has
           persisted despite extensive improvements in mental health services and in programs for
           suicide prevention.

        -  Each month, there are over 1,100 unique VHA patients with bipolar disorder or
           depression who attempt suicide and survive.

        -  Surviving a suicide attempt is the most powerful known risk factor for death from
           suicide in VA and elsewhere.

        -  Approximately 15% of VA survivors reattempt or die from suicide within one year.

        -  Evaluating rates of reattempts in those who have survived attempts is an established
           and effective method for testing interventions that may prevent suicide.

        -  Experimental treatment in CSP-590 would supplement usual care for major depression or
           bipolar disorder.

        -  Study procedures for the management of suicide risk would meet or exceed VA standards
           and requirements.

        -  Study procedures optimize the safety of lithium, including the potential risk of
           overdoses, and meet or exceed all published practice standards. The trial will utilize
           multiple strategies to minimize risks including frequent monitoring and assessment,
           determination of lithium levels during titration and at steady state, and dispensing
           medications in limited quantities in blister packs.

        -  The investigator's survey of VA psychiatrists indicates that the question is clinically
           important and compelling and that a clinical trial that demonstrated the hypothesized
           effect would transform the clinical management of suicidality.

      Design: Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial of lithium versus
      placebo augmentation of enhanced usual care.

      Patient population: VHA patients with bipolar disorder or depression who have survived a
      recent episode of suicidal self-directed violence.

      Primary outcome: Time to the first repeated episode of suicidal self-directed violence,
      including suicide attempts, interrupted attempts, hospitalizations specifically to prevent
      suicide, and deaths from suicide

      Duration: Total study duration will be 4.5 years. Recruitment will occur over 3 years.
      Participants will be followed for one year.

      Sample size calculations and number of sites required: The design of the study is based on
      testing for a 37% reduction in the rate of repeated suicidal self-directed violence, a
      figure based on an effect size of approximately 43% observed in recent studies and then
      allowing for attenuation due to non-adherence.  Adjusting for potential data loss due to
      attrition, 90% statistical power to detect a significant 37% reduction in reattempt rates at
      5% overall type I error would require 1862 subjects. With recruitment of 20% of eligible
      subjects over a three year period, this would require approximately 9310 potentially
      eligible subjects. Based on current suicide surveillance data, this could be achieved with
      29 sites.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to the first repeated episode of suicidal self-directed violence, including suicide attempts, interrupted attempts and hospitalizations for prevention of attempts.</measure>
    <time_frame>Primary outcome is assessed from randomization up to 12 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary hypothesis tested is that lithium augmentation of enhanced usual care is superior to enhanced usual care plus placebo for the prevention of repeated episodes of suicidal self-directed violence over time. We posit a one-year repeat rate of 15% in the placebo group and a 37% reduction of events in the intervention group.
Suicidal self-directed violence includes non-fatal suicide attempts, interrupted attempts (attempts interrupted by patient or by others), hospitalization to prevent suicide and deaths from suicide.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1862</enrollment>
  <condition>Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Bipolar Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Suicide</condition>
  <condition>Suicide, Attempted</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lithium</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lithium in the form of extended release lithium carbonate. Subjects will be started on 600 mg/day (300mg bid) until steady state at target plasma levels between 0.6 and 0.8 meq/liter is achieved. The lowest dose will be 300 mg/day. Lithium will be prescribed for the duration of follow-up (1 year).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo tablets will be given to the patients for the duration of follow-up (1 year). Dose adjustments will mimic the intervention arm of the study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lithium</intervention_name>
    <description>Lithium in the form of extended release lithium carbonate. Subjects will be started on 600 mg/day (300mg bid) until steady state at target plasma levels between 0.6 and 0.8 meq/liter is achieved. The lowest dose will be 300 mg/day. Lithium will be prescribed for the duration of follow-up (1 year).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lithium</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral placebo tablets will be administered for the duration of follow-up (1 year).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Survived an episode of suicidal self-directed violence (including suicide attempts
             and interrupted attempts) that occurred within three months of admission to the
             study, or they were admitted within the past three months to a mental health
             inpatient unit specifically to prevent suicide

          -  Have a diagnosis of an affective disorder meeting DSM-IV-TR (2000) criteria for
             Bipolar I Disorder, Bipolar II Disorder, or current or recurrent Major Depressive
             Disorder

          -  Are able and willing to identify one or more family members, friends, or other
             contacts and give permission for both clinical providers and the Research Team to
             contact them if the patient cannot be reached

          -  Are able to provide informed consent

          -  There is concurrence from the patient's mental health and primary care providers
             about inclusion/exclusion criteria and confirmation of the providers' willingness to
             work with the research team in managing the patient during the course of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder

          -  Cognitive impairment defined as a Brief Orientation Memory and Concentration Test
             score &gt; 10

          -  Lack of decision-making capacity to evaluate the risks versus the benefits of
             participation as determined by Jeste's brief instrument for assessing decisional
             capacity, or adjudication of incompetence and the appointment of a guardian or
             conservator

          -  Six or more previous lifetime suicide attempts as ascertained through SPAN, reports
             from family, or patient self-report

          -  Current or recent (within six months) use of lithium

          -  History of significant adverse effects of lithium as ascertained through the medical
             record or self-report

          -  Unstable medical conditions or specific medical comorbidity:

               -  Congestive heart failure by Framingham criteria

               -  Chronic renal failure defined by national Kidney Foundation Disease Outcome
                  Quality Initiative (KDOQI) criteria

          -  Any possibility of being pregnant or not on appropriate birth control

          -  Lactation and breastfeeding

          -  Concurrent medications:

               -  Diuretics

               -  Angiotensin Converting Enzyme Inhibitors

               -  Angiotensin II Receptor Antagonists

               -  Haloperidol

               -  Clozapine

          -  Active substance abuse:

               -  Active alcohol or opiate dependence requiring medically supervised withdrawal
                  and stabilization

               -  Active cocaine, methamphetamine, other stimulant, hallucinogen, or cannabis
                  abuse requiring stabilization

          -  Enrollment in another randomized interventional clinical trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ira R. Katz, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Philadelphia VA Medical Center, Philadelphia, PA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Matthew Liang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(857) 364-6116</phone>
    <email>Matthew.Liang@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Natalie C Morgenstern, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>(857) 364-5495</phone>
    <email>Natalie.Morgenstern@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Philadelphia VA Medical Center, Philadelphia, PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ira R Katz, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>202-536-8600</phone>
      <email>ira.katz2@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ira R. Katz, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Study Chair</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lithium</keyword>
  <keyword>Placebos</keyword>
  <keyword>Double-blind methods</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical Trials, Randomized</keyword>
  <keyword>Veterans</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bipolar Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Suicide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Suicide, Attempted</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mood Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lithium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lithium Carbonate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
