<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35011">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01724320</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OTX008_101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01724320</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase I, First-in-man Study of OTX008 Given Subcutaneously as a Single Agent to Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, First-in-man Study of OTX008 Given Subcutaneously as a Single Agent to Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>OncoEthix</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>OncoEthix</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Federal Agency for Medicinal Products and Health Products</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <authority>France: Conseil National de l'Ordre des Médecins</authority>
    <authority>France: Committee for the Protection of Personnes</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the recommended dose (RD) for further phase II
      studies, of the Galectin-1 inhibitor OTX008 given subcutaneously in patients with advanced
      solid tumors
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Overexpression of galectin-1 protein is well documented in different types of cancers, with
      associated bad prognostic and enhanced metastases spreading.

      In-vitro/in-vivo preclinical studies showed that OTX008 inhibits galectin-1 expression. In
      different cancer models in animals, OTX008 reduced tumor growing and metastases spreading
      and it was observed a blood vessels architecture normalization.

      Thus, OTX008 appears to be an innovating approach to treat cancers and this clinical phase I
      study aims to evaluate OTX008 therapy in patients with advanced solid tumors.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Limiting Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 weeks of OTX008 treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Dose Limiting Toxicity (DLT) will be assessed during the first 21 days (3 weeks)of OTX008 treatment in each patient to determine Recommended Dose (RD)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 2 and 22 of OTX008 treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>OTX008 plasma concentration will be assessed at days 1, 2 and 22 of OTX008 treatment to determine PK profile of OTX008. Following parameters will be used: Trough (Cmin) and peak (Cmax) of OTX008 concentrations, Tmax, t1/2, steady state, total clearance, AUC (Area Under Curve)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamics (PD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 22 of OTX008 treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Following parameter will be measured: plasma levels of galectin-1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OTX008</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single-arm study of OTX008 given subcutaneously, daily without interruption to patients with advanced solid tumors. Starting dose: 65 mg/day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OTX008</intervention_name>
    <description>OTX008 given daily without interruption, subcutaneously. Starting dose: 65 mg/day</description>
    <arm_group_label>OTX008</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed informed consent prior to beginning protocol specific screening procedures.
             Patients registered in this trial must be treated and followed at the participating
             centers.  Patients should receive the study treatment within 7 days after
             registration

          -  Histologically proven malignant solid tumor

          -  Patients having failed all standard therapies, or for whom standard therapies are
             deemed ineffective or contra-indicated.

          -  Patients aged &gt; 18 years.

          -  ECOG performance status (PS) of 0 to 1

          -  Off previous systemic therapy (except LH-RH agonist therapy started &gt; 2 months prior
             to study entry that could be continued) , radiation therapy, or surgery for at least
             30 days prior to first study treatment administration (45 days for bicalutamide).

          -  Recovery from the toxic effects of prior treatment to NCIC-CTC grade &lt; 1, except
             alopecia

          -  Adequate bone marrow function including:  Neutrophils &gt;= 1.5 x 10E9 /L; platelets &gt;=
             100 x 10E9 /L, Hb &gt; 8g/dL without transfusion.

          -  Creatinine clearance &gt;= 60 mL/min (Cockroft &amp; Gault formula, or MDRD formula for
             patients aged &gt; 65 years).

          -  Adequate LFTs: Total bilirubin &lt; 1 x the institutional upper normal limits (UNL);
             ALAT/ASAT &gt;= 3 x UNL (or &gt;= 5 x UNL in case of liver metastases).

          -  Serum albumin &gt; 28g/L.

          -  Availability of the last tumor imaging within 6 months prior to baseline tumor
             imaging

          -  Availability of archived pathology specimen (paraffin-embedded block) from the tumor

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of prior malignancy other than those previously treated with a curative
             intent more than 5 years ago and without relapse (any tumor) or basal cell skin
             cancer, in situ cervical cancer, superficial bladder cancer, or high grade intestinal
             polyps treated adequately, regardless of the disease-free interval.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women or women of childbearing potential not using adequate
             contraception. Male patients not using adequate contraception.

          -  Tumor sites that necessitate immediate intervention (supportive care, surgery or
             radiation therapy) such as symptomatic brain or leptomeningeal tumor, spinal cord
             compression, other compressive tumor masses, painful bone metastasis, bone fracture,
             etc…

          -  Other serious illness or medical conditions, which, in the investigator's opinion
             could jeopardize patient's safety or hamper understanding of the study by the
             patient, patient's compliance to study treatment, or interpretation of study results.
             These conditions include (but are not restricted to):

               1. Congestive heart failure or angina pectoris not medically controlled.  Previous
                  history of myocardial infarction within 1 year from study entry, uncontrolled
                  hypertension or arrhythmias.

               2. Existence of significant neurologic or psychiatric disorders impairing the
                  ability to obtain consent.

               3. Active infection.

          -  Concurrent treatment with other experimental therapies or participation in another
             clinical trial within 30 days prior to first study treatment administration.

          -  Concurrent treatment with any other anticancer therapy (except LH-RH agonist therapy
             initiated &gt; 2 months prior to study entry).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patrice HERAIT, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+33 6 85 12</phone>
    <phone_ext>00 18</phone_ext>
    <email>pherait@phconsult-onco.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Jules Bordet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels</city>
        <zip>1000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ahmad AWADA, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+32 2 541</phone>
      <phone_ext>31 89</phone_ext>
      <email>ahmad.awada@bordet.be</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ahmad AWADA, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Beaujon - AP-HP</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clichy</city>
        <zip>92110</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eric RAYMOND, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+33 1 40 87</phone>
      <phone_ext>56 17</phone_ext>
      <email>eric.raymond@bjn.aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eric RAYMOND, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Claudius Regaud</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31052</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jean-Pierre DELORD, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+33 5 67 22</phone>
      <phone_ext>25 67</phone_ext>
      <email>delord.jean-pierre@claudiusregaud.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean-Pierre DELORD, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 6, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 2, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>solid tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>first-in-man</keyword>
  <keyword>phase I</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>galectin</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
