<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="152887">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01691690</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB12-00097</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01691690</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Analgesic Effect of IV Acetaminophen in Tonsillectomies</brief_title>
  <official_title>Analgesic Effect of Single Dose Intravenous Acetaminophen in Pediatric Patients Undergoing Tonsillectomy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nationwide Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nationwide Children's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acetaminophen (paracetamol) is a first-line antipyretic and analgesic for mild and moderate
      pain for pediatric patients. Its common use (particularly in oral form) is underscored by
      its wide therapeutic window, safety profile, over the counter accessibility, lack of adverse
      systemic effects (as compared with NSAIDS and opioids) when given in appropriate doses.

      Although the exact anti-nociceptive mechanisms of acetaminophen continue to be elucidated,
      these mechanisms appear to be multi-factorial and include central inhibition of the
      cyclo-oxygenase (COX) enzyme leading to decreased production of prostaglandins from
      arachidonic acid, interference with serotonergic descending pain pathways, indirect
      activation of cannabinoid CB1 receptors and inhibition of nitric oxide pathways through
      N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) or substance P. Of the above mechanisms, the most commonly known
      is that of central inhibition of COX enzymes by which the decreased production of
      prostaglandins diminish the release of excitatory transmitters of substance P and glutamate
      which are both involved in nociceptive transmission (Anderson, 2008; Smith, 2011).

      To date, several studies have shown acetaminophen's opioid sparing effect in the pediatric
      population when given by the rectal or intravenous routes (Korpela et al, 1999; Dashti et
      al, 2009; Hong et al, 2010).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Once enrolled, subjects will have a standardized anesthetic on the day of surgery:

        1. Pre-medication with oral midazolam (0.5mg/kg to maximum dose of 20mg) given 15-20
           minutes before induction

        2. Inhalation induction with sevoflurane and a mixture of N20/02

        3. Propofol 1-1.5 mg/kg to facilitate endotracheal intubation

        4. Morphine 0.1 mg/kg given prior to intubation

        5. Maintenance anesthesia with isoflurane, titrated to 0.8-1 MAC with a mixture of Air/02

        6. Acetaminophen IV (15 mg/kg) vs. saline placebo infused intraoperatively (randomized by
           pharmacy)

        7. Ondansetron (0.15 mg/kg, maximum dose of 4 mg) and dexamethasone (0.25 mg/kg, maximum
           dose of 20 mg) for postoperative nausea prophylaxis.

      Following surgery and extubation, baseline vitals will be obtained and pain scores will be
      assessed in the post anesthesia care unit (PACU) via FLACC (Faces, Legs, Activity, Cry,
      Consolability Scale).The presence of emergence delirium will be assessed via PAED (Pediatric
      Agitation and Emergence Delirium scale). Those subjects whose pain score is assessed at &lt; 4
      will receive standard postoperative care and no analgesics. Assessed pain scores &gt; 4 will
      receive 0.5mcg/kg fentanyl q10 minutes as needed. Variables such as time to extubation in
      the PACU, time to first analgesic delivery, pain scores, # times/total dose of opioids
      given, presence of sedation, nausea/vomiting, duration of oxygen requirement in PACU,
      whether or not patient was discharged to floor on oxygen and total PACU time will be
      recorded during the duration of the patient's PACU stay. Subjects will be discharged to the
      inpatient floor from the PACU once standard discharge criteria have been met.

      Following discharge from the PACU, standardized analgesics will be given for breakthrough
      pain (oral oxycodone 0.1mg/kg q4hrs PRN pain). Enrolled patients will be followed during the
      duration of their inpatient stay. Duration of oxygen requirement on the floor, pain scores
      and number of administered oxycodone doses on the floor will be monitored and recorded.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Analgesic efficacy of single dose intravenous acetaminophen in pediatric patients undergoing tonsillectomy to measure opioid consumption and pain scores in the first 8-12 postoperative hours.</measure>
    <time_frame>8-12 hours post-operatively</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To observe recovery characteristics in the PACU and floor in patients following  tonsillectomy.</measure>
    <time_frame>8-12 hours post-operatively</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Adenotonsillitis</condition>
  <condition>Tonsillitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IV Acetaminophen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive pre-medication with oral midazolam  Participants of this experimental arm of the study will receive Acetaminophen IV to evaluate opioid-sparing effect and pain score reduction..</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saline placebo infused intraoperatively</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>For this arm Morphine will be administered to manage pain.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acetaminophen (paracetamol)</intervention_name>
    <description>Acetaminophen IV (15 mg/kg) administered to evaluate the opioid-sparing effect and pain score reduction in pediatric patients undergoing tonsillectomy or adenotonsillectomy procedures.  In addition, Morphine will be used in this arm to manage pain as in the placebo arm of the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>IV Acetaminophen</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Morphine (hydromorphone)</intervention_name>
    <description>Saline placebo will be infused intraoperatively, and morphine (0.1 mg/kg) will be added to manage pain prior to intubation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saline placebo infused intraoperatively</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female patients aged 2 years and younger than 9 years old requiring
             postoperative admission for tonsillectomy or adenotonsillectomy.

          2. Functional status as assigned by the American Society of Anesthesiology (ASA)
             classification of I (1), II (2) or III (3).

          3. Have a parent/guardian who are able to provide written informed consent in accordance
             with HIC regulations.

          4. Have parent/guardian who are compliant with routine medical care, capable of
             subjective evaluation and able to read, understand and sign the informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female patients age greater than 9 years.

          2. Have an American Society of Anesthesiologists Physical Status &gt; IV (4)(severe disease
             that is life threatening).

          3. Have a known hypersensitivity or allergy to acetaminophen.

          4. Have a known allergy or intolerance to morphine or fentanyl.

          5. Have received chronic opioid analgesic therapy prior to surgery.

          6. Have renal disease.

          7. Have hepatic disease.

          8. Are morbidly obese (% BMI &gt; 95).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>9 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Arlyne Thung, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nationwide Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nationwide Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>N'Diris Barry, BS, RN, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>614-355-3467</phone>
      <email>N'Diris.Barry@NationwideChildrens.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Julie Rice, RN, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>(614) 355-3142</phone>
      <email>Julie.Rice@NationwideChildrens.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Arlyne Thung, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson BJ. Paracetamol (Acetaminophen): mechanisms of action. Paediatr Anaesth. 2008 Oct;18(10):915-21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18811827</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith HS. Perioperative intravenous acetaminophen and NSAIDs. Pain Med. 2011 Jun;12(6):961-81. doi: 10.1111/j.1526-4637.2011.01141.x. Epub 2011 May 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21627768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Korpela R, Korvenoja P, Meretoja OA. Morphine-sparing effect of acetaminophen in pediatric day-case surgery. Anesthesiology. 1999 Aug;91(2):442-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10443608</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dashti GA, Amini S, Zanguee E. The prophylactic effect of rectal acetaminophen on postoperative pain and opioid requirements after adenotonsillectomy in children. Middle East J Anesthesiol. 2009 Jun;20(2):245-9.</citation>
    <PMID>19583073</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hong JY, Kim WO, Koo BN, Cho JS, Suk EH, Kil HK. Fentanyl-sparing effect of acetaminophen as a mixture of fentanyl in intravenous parent-/nurse-controlled analgesia after pediatric ureteroneocystostomy. Anesthesiology. 2010 Sep;113(3):672-7.</citation>
    <PMID>20693884</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 30, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Nationwide Children's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Arlyne Thung</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tonsillitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Acetaminophen</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Analgesics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydromorphone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Morphine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
