<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="38581">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02009722</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-008490</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02009722</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intrathecal Opioids for Pain Control After Cesarean Delivery: Determining the Optimal Dose</brief_title>
  <official_title>Intrathecal Opioids for Pain Control After Cesarean Delivery: Determining the Optimal Dose</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Both hydromorphone and morphine are administered as part of spinal anesthesia to help
      improve pain control after cesarean delivery. In this study, the investigators are going to
      determine the doses of each of those medicines that provides optimal pain control to women
      undergoing cesarean delivery while limiting side effects related to those medicines. The
      investigators hypothesize that the doses of hydromorphone and morphine that provide optimal
      pain control without significant side effects will be 100 micrograms and 150 micrograms,
      respectively. The investigators further hypothesize that at each respective optimal dose,
      side effects will be less in the hydromorphone group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Spinal anesthesia is the most common anesthetic technique used for Cesarean delivery in the
      United States and across the world. Intrathecal opioids are administered along with a local
      anesthetic during spinal anesthesia for Cesarean delivery to provide postoperative
      analgesia. The effectiveness of intrathecal morphine for post-Cesarean pain control is well
      established, but the effectiveness of intrathecal hydromorphone in this patient population
      is limited to case reports and small retrospective studies. No prospective studies have been
      conducted to establish the effectiveness of intrathecal hydromorphone for post-Cesarean
      pain.

      Hydromorphone has been studied extensively as a substitute for intrathecal morphine in
      patients with chronic noncancer pain. In fact, a recent consensus article placed
      hydromorphone as a first line therapy along with morphine for intrathecal pain management.
      Its ability to treat post-Cesarean pain when administered in the epidural space has been
      known for quite some time, but its effects in the intrathecal space are less established.
      In patients undergoing Cesarean delivery, intrathecal doses of 40 to 100 micrograms have
      been reported to provide good pain scores postoperatively with only minimal side effects.
      Doses of up to 300 micrograms have been used, leading to excellent pain control without out
      respiratory depression, but with significant pruritus and nausea.

      Although reducing pain, intrathecal opioids are associated with side effects including
      pruritus, nausea, and respiratory depression. A meta-analysis reviewing twenty-eight studies
      which investigated intrathecal morphine versus placebo demonstrated moderate increases in
      the incidences of pruritus, nausea and vomiting. In fact the incidence of nausea with IT
      morphine has been reported to be 33%. While hydromorphone is similar chemically to morphine,
      it is metabolized differently. Differences in pharmacokinetics may allow for differences in
      side effect profiles. Hydromorphone is more lipid soluble than morphine. This decreases its
      spread within the intrathecal space and enhances its penetration into the dorsal horn of the
      spinal cord where interactions with opioid receptors occur. Some studies have found that
      hydromorphone causes less nausea and pruritus than morphine, while others have not. Although
      opioid-induced respiratory depression is a rare event, studies evaluating intrathecal
      hydromorphone for post-Cesarean delivery pain have not reported any cases of respiratory
      depression.

      The optimal dose of intrathecal morphine for analgesia following Cesarean delivery is still
      debated and the efficacy of intrathecal hydromorphone has not been studied extensively in
      this patient population. The investigators aim to identify the dose of each medication that
      provides good pain relief without causing significant side effects. The investigators will
      then perform a comparative analysis of each drug at their optimal dose.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual analog pain score following spinal anesthesia administration</measure>
    <time_frame>12 hours after administration of spinal anesthesia</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Each patient will be interviewed by a member of the study team 12 hours after receiving their spinal anesthetic (which will include either hydromorphone or morphine). Patients will be asked to rate their current level of pain on a scale of 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst pain imaginable). A pain score &lt;4 will be considered a success.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total opioid medication consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours following spinal administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Total amount of opioids administered to patients in the first 24 hours after spinal administration will be recorded in terms of morphine equivalents.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual analog pain score following administration of spinal anesthesia</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours and 24 hours after spinal administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A member of the study team will interview patients at 6 and 24 hours after spinal administration. Patients will be asked to rate their current level of pain on a scale from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst pain imaginable).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Side effects: Pruritus</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12, and 24 hours after spinal administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will be evaluated by a member of the study team at 6, 12, and 24 hours after spinal administration. The presence and severity of pruritus will be noted by patient endorsement.
Pruritus (graded in the following way: none, mild, moderate, severe)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Side effects: Nausea</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12, and 24 hours after spinal administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will be evaluated by a member of the study team at 6, 12, and 24 hours after spinal administration. The presence and severity of nausea will be noted by patient endorsement.
Nausea (graded as follows: none, minor, moderate, severe)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Side effects: Sedation</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12, and 24 hours after spinal administration</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will be evaluated by a member of the study team at 6, 12, and 24 hours after spinal administration. The presence and severity of sedation will be graded by the Richmond Agitation Sedation Scale
Sedation (measured as follows: integer scale from -5 (unarousable) to +4 (combative))</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Analgesia, Obstetrical</condition>
  <condition>Cesarean Section</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intrathecal hydromorphone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to receive a one-time dose of intrathecal hydromorphone or intrathecal morphine as part of their spinal anesthesia. The starting dose of intrathecal hydromorphone will be 40 micrograms. This will be adjusted in subsequent patients based on the previous patient's success or failure according to an up-and-down methodology utilizing a biased coin design.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intrathecal morphine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to receive a one-time dose of intrathecal hydromorphone or intrathecal morphine as part of their spinal anesthesia. The starting dose of intrathecal morphine will be 100 micrograms. This will be adjusted in subsequent patients based on the previous patient's success or failure according to an up-and-down methodology utilizing a biased coin design.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Morphine</intervention_name>
    <description>Duramorph is administered as part of spinal anesthesia for post-operative pain relief.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intrathecal morphine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Duramorph</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydromorphone</intervention_name>
    <description>Hydromorphone (Dilaudid) is administered in the intrathecal space for post-operative pain control</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intrathecal hydromorphone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dilaudid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women presenting for elective cesarean delivery with no major co-morbidities,
             including pregnancy induced co-morbidities (e.g. pre-eclampsia)

          -  Singleton gestation at term (37-42 weeks)

          -  Desire to have a spinal anesthesia technique for cesarean delivery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current or historical evidence of clinically significant medical disease or condition

          -  Any contraindication to the administration of a spinal technique for anesthesia

          -  History of hypersensitivity or idiosyncratic reaction to opioid medications

          -  Chronic pain syndrome or current regular opioid use

          -  Evidence of anticipated fetal anomalies

          -  Allergy or intolerance to Tylenol, ketorolac, ibuprofen, or oxycodone

          -  BMI &gt; 40
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hans P Sviggum, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hans P Sviggum, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>507-266-2049</phone>
    <email>sviggum.hans@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rochester Methodist Hospital, Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55902</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hans P Sviggum, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>507-266-2049</phone>
      <email>sviggum.hans@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hans P Sviggum, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beatty NC, Arendt KW, Niesen AD, Wittwer ED, Jacob AK. Analgesia after Cesarean delivery: a retrospective comparison of intrathecal hydromorphone and morphine. J Clin Anesth. 2013 Aug;25(5):379-83. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinane.2013.01.014. Epub 2013 Aug 17.</citation>
    <PMID>23965210</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palmer CM, Emerson S, Volgoropolous D, Alves D. Dose-response relationship of intrathecal morphine for postcesarean analgesia. Anesthesiology. 1999 Feb;90(2):437-44. Erratum in: Anesthesiology 1999 Apr;90(4):1241.</citation>
    <PMID>9952150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rauch E. Intrathecal hydromorphone for postoperative analgesia after cesarean delivery: a retrospective study. AANA J. 2012 Aug;80(4 Suppl):S25-32.</citation>
    <PMID>23248827</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rauch E. Intrathecal hydromorphone for cesarean delivery: in search of improved postoperative pain management: a case report. AANA J. 2011 Oct;79(5):427-32.</citation>
    <PMID>23256273</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Terajima K, Onodera H, Kobayashi M, Yamanaka H, Ohno T, Konuma S, Ogawa R. Efficacy of intrathecal morphine for analgesia following elective cesarean section: comparison with previous delivery. J Nippon Med Sch. 2003 Aug;70(4):327-33.</citation>
    <PMID>12928713</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gehling M, Tryba M. Risks and side-effects of intrathecal morphine combined with spinal anaesthesia: a meta-analysis. Anaesthesia. 2009 Jun;64(6):643-51. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19462494</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dougherty TB, Baysinger CL, Henenberger JC, Gooding DJ. Epidural hydromorphone with and without epinephrine for post-operative analgesia after cesarean delivery. Anesth Analg. 1989 Mar;68(3):318-22.</citation>
    <PMID>2465709</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pace NL, Stylianou MP. Advances in and limitations of up-and-down methodology: a précis of clinical use, study design, and dose estimation in anesthesia research. Anesthesiology. 2007 Jul;107(1):144-52. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17585226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gerancher JC, Floyd H, Eisenach J. Determination of an effective dose of intrathecal morphine for pain relief after cesarean delivery. Anesth Analg. 1999 Feb;88(2):346-51.</citation>
    <PMID>9972754</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hans P. Sviggum, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cesarean Delivery</keyword>
  <keyword>Intrathecal Morphine</keyword>
  <keyword>Intrathecal Hydromorphone</keyword>
  <keyword>Obstetrical Analgesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Spinal Anesthesia</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydromorphone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Morphine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Analgesics, Opioid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
