<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="30008">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01778517</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130047</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-N-0047</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01778517</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Functional Movement Disorders With Psychotherapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment of Functional Movement Disorders With Psychotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Functional movement disorder (FMD) is a form of conversion disorder (CD). CD is a disorder
      in which a person has neurological symptoms that do not have a neurological cause. These
      symptoms can include pain, weakness, dizziness, and fatigue. Some thoughts on CD suggest
      that it may come from feelings of anxiety that are    converted    into physical symptoms.
      Treatment for FMD usually involves stress reduction, family help, and regular doctor   s
      appointments. Therapy interventions, however, have not been well studied. Researchers want
      to see if people with FMD get better with psychotherapy. They will study two different types
      of psychotherapy: group therapy and a self-help manual.

      Objectives:

      - To test two different types of therapy treatments for FMD.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who have been diagnosed with FMD by a neurologist.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. They will also
           have a psychological exam, and answer questions about their mood and symptoms.

        -  Participants will be separated into three groups. One group will have group therapy.
           Another will use a self-help workbook designed for people with FMD, and have individual
           therapy sessions. A third group will just have standard care. During the study,
           participants will continue to see their regular doctor.

        -  Group therapy participants will meet once a week for 6 months at the National
           Institutes of Health clinical center. There will be 8 to 10 people per group. Sessions
           will last 75 minutes. These sessions will work on methods for treating FMD.

        -  Self-help workbook participants will have six individual therapy sessions over 3 to 4
           months. They will use the workbooks to learn about and practice methods for treating
           FMD.

        -  All participants will be evaluated at 3, 6, and 12 months during the study.

        -  At the end of the study, participants will have a final follow-up session with exams
           and questions similar to the screening exam. They will return to the care of their
           regular doctor.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives:

      This is an exploratory study of two options for treating functional movement disorders
      (FMD):

        -  Group psychotherapy

        -  Cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT)-based guided self-help.

      Study population:

      We intend to study adult patients with diagnoses of FMD seen by the Human Motor Control
      Section Clinic (HMCS) and who live in the Washington-Baltimore metropolitan area for group
      psychotherapy as well as patients who live out of the area for CBT-based guided self-help.

      Design:

      Patients will be screened for participation through protocol 07-N-0190 (   Neurobiology of
      Psychogenic Movement Disorder and Non-Epileptic Seizures   ). Those who meet the inclusion
      criteria and who live locally will be invited to participate in a treatment study of group
      psychotherapy. The duration of the study for each patient is one year. Local patients who
      meet the inclusion criteria will be divided into two groups of 10 patients each.  Accrual
      will be gradual. All 10 patients in each group will start simultaneously. All participants
      will undergo an initial assessment, followed by an assessment at 3, 6, and 12 months. The
      primary endpoint will be assessed at 6 months; a group of 20 (out-of-area) patients
      randomized to standard of care will serve as the control. Patients will be evaluated with
      the scales described below.

      Patients who are out-of-town and meet the inclusion/exclusion criteria will be invited to
      join the CBT-based guided self-help arm. They will be randomized in two groups of 20
      patients each. One group will undergo CBT; the other will be randomized to standard of care.
      Standard of care is defined as pharmacological or other treatment modalities excluding CBT
      or group psychotherapy (the studied modalities). Subjects will be included on a rolling
      basis, and therapy will be delivered approximately once every two weeks for a total of six
      sessions. Participants will be instructed in the use of CBT-based self-help workbooks aimed
      at treating functional neurological symptoms (Overcoming unexplained neurological symptoms:
      a five areas approach by Dr. Chris Williams, 2011, Hodder and Arnold). Total duration of the
      intervention will be 3-4 months. Subjects will undergo the same assessments as patients in
      the group psychotherapy arm of the study at the same time points.

      Outcome measures:

      Primary Outcome measure

      -Ability to participate in social roles and activities (Neuro-QOL Item Bank) at 6 months
      after initiation of therapy.

      Secondary Outcome Measures

        -  Clinical global impression of severity (CGI).

        -  Subjective and objective depressive and anxiety symptoms, measured with the Beck
           Depression Inventory (BDI), Hamilton Depression Rating Scale-17, State Trait Anxiety
           Inventory (STAI) and Hamilton Anxiety Scale.

        -  Self-assessment of disease severity (5 point Likert scale).

        -  Somatic symptoms (SCL-90).

        -  Insight (ITAQ)

        -  Similar measures at 12 months after initiation of therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ability to participate in social roles and activities (Neuro-QOL Item Bank)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Movement Disorders</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Group Psychotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive behavior therapy based on self help</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Must have participated in Protocol 07-N-0190 (   Neurobiological studies of
             psychogenic movement disorder and non-epileptic seizure   )

          -  Diagnosis of    clinically definite    FMD utilizing Fahn and Williams criteria.  The
             diagnosis must be made by a neurologist

          -  Patients who have active movement symptoms at baseline and score at least 20 percent
             less than the maximum score on the Neuro-QOL Item Bank

          -  Able to give informed consent

          -  All participants should be English-speaking

          -  Age 18 or older

          -  Willingness to come without reimbursement to treatment visits for up to 6 months

          -  Willingness to remain on the same medications for the entire duration of the study

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Have significant neurological disorders (primary or comorbid) such as
             neurodegenerative disorders, stroke, movement disorders or epilepsy

          -  Patients with psychotic disorders or bipolar disorder or history of alcohol and
             substance use disorders  as defined by the DSM-IV-TR (nicotine and caffeine use is
             not criterion for exclusion)

          -  Current suicidal/homicidal ideation

          -  Disease severity requiring inpatient treatment. Chronic pain requiring treatment with
             narcotic medication
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Hallett, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elaine P Considine, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-8518</phone>
    <email>considinee@ninds.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mark Hallett, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-9526</phone>
    <email>hallettm@ninds.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-N-0047.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Williams DT, Ford B, Fahn S. Phenomenology and psychopathology related to psychogenic movement disorders. Adv Neurol. 1995;65:231-57. Review. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>7872143</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carson AJ, Ringbauer B, Stone J, McKenzie L, Warlow C, Sharpe M. Do medically unexplained symptoms matter? A prospective cohort study of 300 new referrals to neurology outpatient clinics. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2000 Feb;68(2):207-10.</citation>
    <PMID>10644789</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feinstein A, Stergiopoulos V, Fine J, Lang AE. Psychiatric outcome in patients with a psychogenic movement disorder: a prospective study. Neuropsychiatry Neuropsychol Behav Neurol. 2001 Jul-Sep;14(3):169-76.</citation>
    <PMID>11513100</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Psychogenic Movement Disorders</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Movement Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Conversion Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
