<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="92417">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01909154</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CME-LEM1</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2010-023285-46</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01909154</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Study of Local Administration of Autologous Bone Marrow Stromal Cells in Chronic Paraplegia</brief_title>
  <acronym>CME-LEM1</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase I Pilot Study to Evaluate the Security of Local Administration of Autologous Stem Cells Obtained From the Bone Marrow Stroma, in Traumatic Injuries of the Spinal Cord</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Puerta de Hierro University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Puerta de Hierro University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Spain: Spanish Agency of Medicines</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of the study is confirm the security, and detecting effect of the local
      administration in damaged nervous tissue, of autologous bone marrow stromal cells. After one
      year of evolution after starting the treatment, it is possible to have efficacy data of this
      treatment, either in some kind of improvement in their paralysis or some kind of aspects
      such as sphincter control, improvement of spasms, pain or any other symptoms you may have as
      a result of spinal cord injury. However the principal objective of this study is to ensure
      that the treatment is applied is well tolerated and without complications, as experience
      with the techniques of cell therapy in humans is currently very limited and specific
      treatment protocol that will be applied, has not yet been tested in patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      It is a clinical trial phase I, single center, non-randomized, uncontrolled, open
      prospective follow-up of a cohort of patients with chronic spinal cord injury (SCI)
      stablished who were administered autologous stromal cells of the bone marrow. Expanded cells
      will be administrated  locally intrathecal (subarachnoid and intramedullary) by
      microinjection and three months later, by lumbar subarachnoid administration. The minimum
      follow-up time for each patient is 12 months after the first administration, or until death,
      if it occurs it before.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Appearance of adverse effects</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The principal variable will be the appearance of adverse effects during administration and during the follow up period:
On a daily Bases: The first week after first administration of CME. Weekly: Until the second administration of CME After second administration of CME it will be done a weekly clinical assessment and during months 9 and 12 of the follow-up period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>sensitivity recovery during Follow-up period: 3, 6, 9 and 12 months and the baseline visit.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Sensitivity recovery, changes in the level of chronic pain, neurophysiological parameters improvement, and changes in the spinal cord morphology on neuroimaging studies.
Sensitive recovery: Follow-up period: 3, 6, 9 and 12 months and the baseline visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Motor recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>Motor recovery during administration and during the follow up period: Follow-up period: 3,6,9, and 12 months and baseline visit.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Motor recovery, changes in the level of chronic pain, neurophysiological parameters improvement, and changes in the spinal cord morphology on neuroimaging studies.
Motor recovery: Follow-up period: 3,6,9, and 12 months and baseline visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Depending on centromedullary post-traumatically injury (minimum  dose of100x106 CME on a first intermedular and subarachnoid  administration and then subarachnoid  administration of 30x106CME,3 months later)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cells.</intervention_name>
    <description>Depending on centromedullary , post traumatically injury (minimum dose 100x106 CME on first intermedular and subarachnoid administration,and then subarachnoid administration of 30x106 CME, 3 months  later)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cells</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Autologous cells from the bone marrow stroma</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female with ages between 18 years and 60 years with of age or older
             functional sequelae chronically established by traumatic injury of the spinal cord
             (spinal segments between the vertebral bodies C6 and L1) and considered irreversible
             (not respond to any other treatment).  In this study, the lesion is considered
             chronically established, when there are no signs of functional recovery after a
             minimum follow-up period of 6 months after the spinal cord injury. The upper age
             limit is justified by the low potential of in vitro expansion of bone marrow stromal
             cells over 60 years.

          -  Complete paraplegia, with loss of motor and sensory function below the lesion (grade
             A in the scale ASIA).

          -  Spinal injury MRI morphologically visible, and without images that suggest spinal
             cord transection, with separation of the both ends of the spinal cord.

          -  Tracking evolutionary possibility after treatment protocol and to comply
             physiotherapy maintained throughout the follow up period.

          -  Written informed Consent according to good clinical practice (GCP) and local
             regulations, obtained before any study procedure.

          -  Hematological parameters and creatinine, serum glutamate oxalacetate transaminase
             (SGOT) and serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase (SGPT) in normal range according to
             laboratory standards, are accepted, however, small  non significant deviations
             according to the investigator.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Pregnancy and lactation

          -  Systemic disease represents an added risk to treatment

          -  Patients with questions about their possible cooperation in
             rehabilitation-physiotherapy treatments later, or negative report psychological
             assessment prior.

          -  Neuroimaging data showing spinal cord section with separation of ends, of the spinal
             cord

          -  Current neoplastic disease diagnosed or treated in the previous five years

          -  Patients treated with hematopoietic growth factors or requiring anticoagulation
             maintained

          -  Added neurodegenerative disease

          -  History of substance abuse, psychiatric illness or allergy to protein products used
             in the process of cell expansion

          -  HIV positive serology and syphilis

          -  Hepatitis B or Hepatitis C active If according to the opinion of investigator there
             are findings on physical examination, abnormal clinical test results or other
             medical, social or psychosocial factors which might adversely affect.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jesus JV Vaquero Crespo, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Universitario Puerta de Hierro-Majadahonda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jesús JV Vaquero crespo, Neurosurgeon</last_name>
    <phone>+34 911916000</phone>
    <email>jvaqueroc@telefonica.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mercedes MZ Zurita Castillo, Biologist</last_name>
    <phone>+34 911916000</phone>
    <email>mzurita.hpth@salud.madrid.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Puerta de Hierro</name>
      <address>
        <city>Majadahonda</city>
        <state>Madrid</state>
        <zip>28222</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jesús JV Vaquero Crespo, Neurosurgeon</last_name>
      <phone>+34 911916000</phone>
      <email>jvaqueroc@telefonica.net</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mercedes MZ Zurita Castillo, Biologist</last_name>
      <phone>+34 911916000</phone>
      <email>mzurita.hpth@salud.madrid.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Geffner LF, Santacruz P, Izurieta M, Flor L, Maldonado B, Auad AH, Montenegro X, Gonzalez R, Silva F. Administration of autologous bone marrow stem cells into spinal cord injury patients via multiple routes is safe and improves their quality of life: comprehensive case studies. Cell Transplant. 2008;17(12):1277-93.</citation>
    <PMID>19364066</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Puerta de Hierro University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jesús Vaquero Crespo, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Doctor on neurosurgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Functional recovery</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurophysiological parameters improvement</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
