<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="146328">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01945086</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR102538</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01945086</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Ustekinumab (STELARA®) in Adult Japanese Participants With Severe Atopic Dermatitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Multicenter, Parallel-Group Study of Ustekinumab in Adult Japanese Subjects With Severe Atopic Dermatitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen Pharmaceutical K.K.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen Pharmaceutical K.K.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Pharmaceuticals and Medical Devices Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the safety and effectiveness of 2 doses of
      ustekinumab compared with placebo (inactive medication) in adult Japanese participants with
      severe atopic dermatitis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized (the study medication is assigned by chance), double-blind (neither
      physician nor participant knows the identity of the assigned treatment), placebo-controlled
      (one of the study medications is inactive), multicenter, parallel group study (each
      participant group receives different treatments simultaneously). Participants will be
      randomly assigned in a 1:1:1 ratio to receive either ustekinumab 45 mg, ustekinumab 90 mg,
      or placebo. The study will consist of a screening period, a 12-week double-blind treatment
      period, and a 12-week follow-up period.  During the double-blind treatment period,
      participants will receive one subcutaneous injection of study medication at Week 0 and Week
      4. Participants will return to the study center for 7 evaluation visits on Weeks 2, 4, 8,
      12, 16, 20, and 24. Clinical response will be evaluated by Eczema Area and Severity Index
      (EASI), Investigator's Global Assessment (IGA), photography, and Dermatology Life Quality
      Index (DLQI). Participants will record their itch condition twice daily using the
      participant daily diary from 2 weeks prior to randomization until Week 12. Blood samples
      will be drawn at time periods during the screening, double-blind treatment, and follow-up
      periods. Participant safety will be monitored throughout the study. Participants are
      permitted to use concomitant topical medications, as defined in the protocol and without any
      increase in dose, from 4 weeks prior to randomization through to the end of the treatment
      period.  After Week 12, additional treatment can be started or the dose of concomitant
      medications can be increased, if no improvement in clinical response is observed; in these
      cases EASI, IGA, and photography evaluations will be stopped. The study duration for each
      participant is expected to be approximately 30 weeks.   Ustekinumab (also known as STELARA)
      is an antibody medication that inhibits the inflammatory proteins IL-12 and IL-23 and is
      approved as a treatment for moderate to severe plaque-type psoriasis; this study will
      examine whether ustekinumab can provide benefit in atopic dermatitis and assess for any
      risks or side effects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change from Baseline to Week 12 in the Eczema Area and Severity Index (EASI) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The EASI is a measure of the severity and extent of atopic dermatitis (AD). Each of the 4 body regions (head and neck, trunk, upper limbs, and lower limbs) are assessed for severity of disease using a scale ranging from 0 (no disease) to 3 (severe disease). In addition, the area of skin affected by AD in each of the 4 body regions is determined using a scale ranging from 0 (no eruption) to 6 (90 to 100 percent extent of the body region affected). The higher the total EASI score, the greater the severity and extent of AD.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants with an Investigator's Global Assessment (IGA) score of &quot;clear&quot; or &quot;almost clear&quot; at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The IGA utilizes a 6-point scale ranging from 0 (clear) to 5 (very severe disease). &quot;Almost clear&quot; is given a score of 1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline to Week 12 in Atopic Dermatitis Itch Scale (ADIS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The ADIS will be used to assess itching twice daily (morning and evening) and uses a scale ranging from 0 (no itching at all) to 10 (worst possible itching).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline to Week 12 in Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>DLQI is a dermatology-specific quality of life instrument designed to assess the impact of the disease on a subject's quality of life.  The DLQI uses 10 questions which are each scored on a scale of 0 to 3; the higher the score, the more quality of life is impaired.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Dermatitis, Atopic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ustekinumab 45 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ustekinumab 90 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ustekinumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive subcutaneous (SC) injections of either ustekinumab 45 mg or ustekinumab 90 mg at Week 0 and Week 4.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ustekinumab 45 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ustekinumab 90 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive SC injections of placebo at Week 0 and Week 4.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Concomitant topical medications for atopic dermatitis</intervention_name>
    <description>Concomitant topical medications (as defined in the protocol) can be used from 4 weeks prior to randomization and throughout the study. However, the dosage cannot be increased and new medications cannot be added until after Week 12.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ustekinumab 45 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ustekinumab 90 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must be Japanese

          -  Must have a diagnosis of atopic dermatitis, with childhood onset (under age of 13),
             in accordance with the definition and diagnostic criteria of the Japanese
             Dermatological Association and must have pruritus and eczematous changes; the
             condition must  be chronic or chronically relapsing in nature

          -  Inadequate response to, or not willing to use strong treatment with a topical
             corticosteroid and/or a topical calcineurin inhibitor and/or phototherapy

          -  Must meet all the following criteria regarding severity of atopic dermatitis:
             Rajka-Langeland score of 8 to 9; severe or very severe disease as defined in standard
             treatment guidelines; an Eczema Area and Severity Index (EASI) score of &gt;= 12; and an
             Investigator's Global Assessment (IGA) score of severe disease or very severe disease

          -  Must conform to the following tuberculosis (TB) screening criteria: no history of
             latent or active TB prior to screening; no signs or symptoms suggestive of active TB;
             no recent close contact with a person with active TB; and a negative Interferon Gamma
             Release Assay (IGRA) result within 2 months prior to the first administration of
             study drug

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of or current clinically significant medical illness that the investigator
             considers should exclude the participant or that could interfere with the
             interpretation of the study results

          -  Has an indeterminate initial and repeat IGRA result or a newly positive IGRA result
             and is unwilling or unable to undergo TB prophylaxis treatment

          -  Has received any of the following medications or therapies within 4 weeks prior to
             randomization: systemic non-steroid immunosuppressive or immunomodulatory drugs;
             systemic corticosteroids; high daily dose of inhaled corticosteroids; topical
             corticosteroids of strongest potency for atopic dermatitis; topical antihistamines
             (including topical doxepin); topical anesthetics; topical nonsteroidal
             anti-inflammatory drugs; topical counter-irritants (eg, capsaicin, menthol,
             wintergreen oil); antidepressants or antipsychotics; soporifics; phototherapy
             including ultraviolet A , ultraviolet B, and psoralen with ultraviolet A (PUVA);
             hyposensitization (desensitization) therapy

          -  Has changed the dose and dosing regimen within 4 weeks prior to randomization of any
             of the following drugs: topical corticosteroid (excluding the strongest potency) for
             atopic dermatitis; topical calcineurin inhibitor; emollients; anti-leukotriene
             therapies (including therapies for other allergic indications); systemic histamine H1
             blocker (including sleep medications with antihistamine properties); sodium
             cromoglicate; suplatast tosilate; tranilast; thromboxane A2 inhibitors; and topical
             or oral herbal preparations for the treatment of atopic dermatitis

          -  Has received any of the following biologic agents within the following time periods:
             any marketed immunomodulatory biologic within a period of 3 months or 5 half-lives,
             whichever is longer, prior to randomization; a biologic agent targeting IL-12 or
             IL-23, including but not limited to ustekinumab (CNTO 1275), briakinumab (ABT-874),
             guselkumab (CNTO 1959) or MK-3222 at any point in time; or an experimental biologic
             therapy within the previous 6 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen Pharmaceutical K.K., Japan Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen Pharmaceutical K.K.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Use link at the bottom of the page to see if you qualify for an enrolling site (see list). If you still have questions:</last_name>
    <email>JNJ.CT@sylogent.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Asahikawa</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Chitose</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Habikino</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Hamamatsu</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Hiroshima</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kumamoto</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kurume</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kyoto</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Maebashi</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Nagasaki</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Osaka</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Sapporo</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Suita</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Yachiyo</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://pam.sylogent.com/cr/CR102538</url>
    <description>To learn how to participate in this trial please click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 13, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dermatitis, Atopic</keyword>
  <keyword>Eczema</keyword>
  <keyword>Ustekinumab</keyword>
  <keyword>CNTO1275</keyword>
  <keyword>STELARA</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis, Atopic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
