<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="79067">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02076646</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PH-L19IL2DTIC-04-12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02076646</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase I/II Dose Escalation Study of the Tumor-targeting Human L19-IL2 Monoclonal Antibody-cytokine Fusion Protein in Combination With Dacarbazine for Patients With Metastatic Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Dose Escalation Study of the Tumor-targeting Human L19-IL2 Monoclonal Antibody-cytokine Fusion Protein in Combination With Dacarbazine for Patients With Metastatic Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Philogen S.p.A.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Philogen S.p.A.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Italy: National Institute of Health (Instituto Superiore di Sanità)</authority>
    <authority>Italy: Ethics Commissions</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Paul-Ehrlich-Institut</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Phase II clinical study is an open-label, multicenter study of L19IL2 in combination
      with Dacarbazine in patients with metastatic melanoma.

      The study is divided in two parts: a phase IIa part, designed to establish the recommended
      dose (RD) of L19IL2 when administered in combination with a fixed dose of Dacarbazine, as
      well as to determine the preliminary tolerability profile; the second phase IIb part
      evaluates the objective response rate (ORR) including a randomized study with a fixed dose
      of Dacarbazine with or without L19IL2, dosed at the RD determined in phase IIa.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Dose limiting toxicity will be assessed during the dose-escalation part of Phase IIa from
      day 1 through day 21 of the first cycle.

      Response will be measured using RECIST criteria every 6 weeks (after every 2 cycles of
      treatment). Patients with stable or responding disease at each assessment may receive
      additional treatment for a maximum of 6 cycles of induction. Patients with stable or
      responding disease after induction may receive L19IL2 (without dacarbazine) every 2 weeks as
      maintenance therapy.

      Tumor expression of ED-B FN and tumor uptake of L19IL2 and of Dacarbazine will be assessed
      via immunohistochemistry and/or other methods deemed appropriate on tumor tissue biopsies.
      Tumor biopsy will be performed on superficial accessible cutaneous and/or subcutaneous
      lesions only. Tumor biopsy will be considered optional and will not preclude patient entry
      on to study should the patient refuse.

      Pharmacokinetics of L19IL2, Dacarbazine and AIC will be assessed from serial blood samples
      using standard methods.

      Overall response rate, PFS, survival rate at 6 and 12 months, and overall survival time for
      all patients and separately for the patients in the Phase IIb part will be assessed using
      standard methods.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I: Establish the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and recommended dose (RD) of L19IL2</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Establish the MTD and the RD of L19IL2 (in combination with dacarbazine) to be used for phase II study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II: evaluation of the antitumor activity</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>evaluation of the best objective response rate (BORR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I: evaluation of the antitumor activity</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate antitumor activity in terms of confirmed best objective response rate (BORR), duration of overall response, disease control rate, progression free survival (PFS) and overall survival (OS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II: Safety and Tolerability of L19-IL2 in combination with DTIC vs DTIC alone.</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluation of the type and the number of adverse events eventually present</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II: Treatment efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigate the duration of overall response, disease control rate, progression free survival (PFS) and overall survival (OS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Melanoma Stage IV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ARM 1: L19IL2 + Dacarbazine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>L19IL2 starting at 480,000 IU/kg  until MTD is reached (in steps of 160,000 IU/kg, i.e., 0.48; 0.64; 0.80 MioIU/kg)
Dacarbazine  1000 mg/m2 (fixed dose)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ARM 2: Dacarbazine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dacarbazine  1000 mg/m2 (fixed dose)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Arm 1: L19IL2 + Dacarbazine</intervention_name>
    <description>L19IL2:  Intravenous (IV) infusion of  on days 1, 8 and 15 of each 21-day cycle over 3 hours via automated device (perfusor).
Dacarbazine: 1 hour intravenous infusion on day 1 of each 21-cycle,administered 30 minutes after the end of the L19IL2 infusion.
L19IL2 starting dosage:  480,000 IU/kg  increasing until MTD is reached (in steps of 160,000 IU/kg, i.e., 0.48; 0.64; 0.80 MioIU/kg) Dacarbazine  dosage: 1000 mg/m2 (fixed dose)
Treatment will terminate at the earliest of the following: disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, withdrawal of consent. Patients will be followed for one year from the start of the treatment or until withdrawal of consent, whichever occurs first.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ARM 1: L19IL2 + Dacarbazine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Arm 2: Dacarbazine</intervention_name>
    <description>Dacarbazine: 1 hour intravenous infusion on day 1 of each 21-cycle at a dosage of 1000 mg/m2 (fixed dose)
Treatment will terminate at the earliest of the following: disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, withdrawal of consent. Patients will be followed for one year from the start of the treatment or until withdrawal of consent, whichever occurs first. until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, withdrawal of consent, whichever occurs first.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ARM 2: Dacarbazine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DETICENE®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 18-70 years of age, inclusive

          2. Must have histologically or cytologically confirmed cutaneous metastatic melanoma
             (Stage IV). For the Phase II part only patients with Stage IV M1a or M1b will be
             enrolled.

          3. Must have measurable disease according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid
             Tumors (RECIST 1.1) as identified by CT or MRI scan within 28 days before the first
             study drug administration.

          4. Baseline LDH within normal range

          5. Maximal 1 line of previous systemic treatment for metastatic disease (prior adjuvant
             melanoma therapy, e.g., IFN, is permitted.

          6. For women of childbearing potential, a negative pregnancy test within 72 hours prior
             to the first dose of study treatment.

          7. Women with reproductive potential must be willing to practice acceptable methods of
             birth control during the study and for up to 12 weeks after the last dose of study
             medication.

          8. Men with reproductive potential must be willing to practice acceptable methods of
             birth control during the study and for up to 12 weeks after the last dose of study
             medication.

          9. Must have Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status of 0-1

         10. Life expectancy of at least three months

         11. Adequate organ function: serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN, total bilirubin ≤ 30 mM/L (or
             mg/dL, ≤ 2.0 mg/dL), hepatic transaminases ≤ 2.5 x ULN, alkaline phosphatase ≤ 2.5 x
             ULN.

         12. ANC count ≥ 1.5 x 10^9/L, platelet count ≥ 100 x 10^9/L, hemoglobin &gt; 9 g/dL

         13. Normal 12-lead ECG and normal bidimensional echocardiogram or MUGA

         14. All toxic effects of prior therapy must have resolved to grade ≤1 unless otherwise
             specified above

         15. Willing and able to give written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant or breastfeeding female

          2. Primary ocular melanoma

          3. Primary mucosal melanoma

          4. Use of any investigational or other anti-cancer drug within 28 days or 5 half-lives,
             whichever is longer, preceding the first dose of DTIC and L19-IL2

          5. Prior radiation to a target lesion, unless there has been clear progression of the
             lesion since radiotherapy

          6. A history of known Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), Hepatitis B Virus (HBV), or
             Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) infection

          7. History or clinical evidence of brain metastases or leptomeningeal disease

          8. Any other malignancy from which the patient has been disease-free for less than 5
             years, with the exception of adequately treated and cured basal or squamous cell skin
             cancer, superficial bladder cancer, or carcinoma in situ of the cervix

          9. Treatment with DTIC within 6 months before start of study

         10. Treatment with Ipilimumab within 6 months before start of study

         11. Hypersensitivity to DTIC

         12. Concomitant use of drugs known to alter cardiac conduction

         13. Chronic use of corticosteroids used in the management of cancer or non-cancer-related
             illness

         14. Unstable or serious concurrent uncontrolled medical conditions

         15. Inadequately controlled cardiac arrhythmias including atrial fibrillation

         16. History of acute or subacute coronary syndromes including myocardial infarction,
             unstable or severe stable angina pectoris

         17. Heart insufficiency &gt; grade II NYHA criteria

         18. Uncontrolled hypertension

         19. Ischemic peripheral vascular disease

         20. Active infection or incomplete wound healing.

         21. History or evidence of active autoimmune disease.

         22. Known history of allergy to intravenously administered proteins/peptides/antibodies

         23. History of organ allograft.or allogeneic peripheral blood progenitor cell or bone
             marrow transplantation

         24. Major trauma including surgery within 4 weeks prior to entering the study.

         25. Any underlying medical or psychiatric condition which in the opinion of the
             investigator will make administration of study drug hazardous or hinder the
             interpretation of study results (e.g. AE).

         26. Melanoma patients with BRAF 600 E mutation who are amenable to receive approved
             treatments able to extend overall survival.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Claus Garbe, Prof. M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Tuebingen (Germany)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michele Maio, Dr.med.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria Senese, Siena (Italy)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Leonardo Giovannoni, Dr</last_name>
    <phone>(0039) 0577 588 539</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tuebingen</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Claus Garbe, Prof. M.D.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Claus Garbe, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria Senese</name>
      <address>
        <city>Siena</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michele Maio, Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michele Maio, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 26, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 24, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Interleukin</keyword>
  <keyword>IL2</keyword>
  <keyword>monoclonal</keyword>
  <keyword>antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>cytokine</keyword>
  <keyword>Dacarbazine</keyword>
  <keyword>metastatic</keyword>
  <keyword>melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>tumor targeting</keyword>
  <keyword>Dose definition</keyword>
  <keyword>L19</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dacarbazine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interleukin-2</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
