<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="26761">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01907815</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2013-01354</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-01354</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-0001</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9443</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016672</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01CM00039</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01907815</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trametinib and Akt Inhibitor GSK2141795 in Treating Patients With Acute Myeloid Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Study of MEK 1/2 Inhibitor Trametinib in Combination With AKT Inhibitor GSK2141795 in Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) With RAS Mutations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well trametinib and Akt inhibitor GSK2141795 work in
      treating patients with acute myeloid leukemia. Trametinib and Akt inhibitor GSK2141795 may
      stop the growth of cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the proportion of patients achieving complete remission (CR) or CR with
      incomplete recovery of platelets (CRp) as best response within 4 cycles of therapy of
      trametinib in combination with GSK2141795 (Akt inhibitor GSK2141795) in acute myeloid
      leukemia (AML) patients with retrovirus-associated deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) sequence
      (RAS) mutations.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the disease-free survival of patients achieving CR/CRp. II. To determine the
      duration of response of patients achieving CR/CRp. III. To determine the toxicity profile of
      trametinib in combination with GSK2141795 in this patient population.

      IV. To determine the biologic effects of trametinib in combination with GSK2141795 on
      leukemia cells.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive trametinib orally (PO) once daily (QD) and Akt inhibitor GSK2141795 PO QD
      on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 12 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete response rate (CRR, defined as CR+CRp) assessed by the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The chi-square test or the Fisher's exact test will be applied to assess the association between categorical variables. 95% confidence interval will be estimated for the combination regimen.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method. Log-rank test will be performed to test the difference in time-to-event distributions between patient groups. Cox proportional hazards model will be used to include multiple covariates in the time-to-event analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method. Log-rank test will be performed to test the difference in time-to-event distributions between patient groups. Cox proportional hazards model will be used to include multiple covariates in the time-to-event analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method. Log-rank test will be performed to test the difference in time-to-event distributions between patient groups. Cox proportional hazards model will be used to include multiple covariates in the time-to-event analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events (AE) assessed by the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicity data will be summarized using frequency tables by AE severity and by relationship to study drug. Toxicity rate with 95% credible interval will be estimated for the combination regimen.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum percentage change in total and phospho-proteins</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks post therapy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in total and phospho-proteins assessed by densitometric quantitative data by western blot analysis, or mean fluorescent intensities by flow cytometry and will be assessed for each patient for all time points and graphically plotted for each dose level.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage change in cellular proteins</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to day 28 post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The 95% confidence interval will be assessed.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Acute Megakaryoblastic Leukemia (M7)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Minimally Differentiated Myeloid Leukemia (M0)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Monoblastic Leukemia (M5a)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Monocytic Leukemia (M5b)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloblastic Leukemia With Maturation (M2)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloblastic Leukemia Without Maturation (M1)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With 11q23 (MLL) Abnormalities</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With Del(5q)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With Inv(16)(p13;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With t(16;16)(p13;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With t(8;21)(q22;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myelomonocytic Leukemia (M4)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Erythroleukemia (M6a)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Pure Erythroid Leukemia (M6b)</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Untreated Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (trametinib, Akt inhibitor GSK2141795)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive trametinib PO QD and Akt inhibitor GSK2141795 PO QD on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Akt inhibitor GSK2141795</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (trametinib, Akt inhibitor GSK2141795)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GSK2141795</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>trametinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (trametinib, Akt inhibitor GSK2141795)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GSK1120212</other_name>
    <other_name>JTP-74057</other_name>
    <other_name>Mekinist</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (trametinib, Akt inhibitor GSK2141795)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed AML, other than acute
             promyelocytic leukemia, as defined by the 2008 World Health Organization (WHO)
             criteria that have relapsed or refractory to standard chemotherapy; unsuitable for
             standard chemotherapy or unwilling to undergo standard chemotherapy; subjects &gt;= 60
             years of age with newly diagnosed AML who are not candidates for or have refused
             standard chemotherapy are eligible

          -  Patients with prior autologous and allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation
             are eligible if patients are off immunosuppression for &gt; 1 month and have no evidence
             of active graft versus host disease (GVHD) except grade 1 skin GVHD

          -  Positive for RAS mutation (neuroblastoma RAS viral (v-ras) oncogene homolog [NRAS]
             codon 12, 13, 61 mutation or v-Ki-ras2 Kirsten rat sarcoma viral oncogene homolog
             [KRAS] codon 12, 13, 61 mutation) at a Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments
             (CLIA)-certified laboratory prior to study entry; mutational testing will be
             performed on bone marrow sample and/or peripheral blood; patients with previously
             known RAS mutations prior to study entry may be considered positive for RAS mutation
             for eligibility prior to a CLIA-certified laboratory confirmation of such a mutation
             at the discretion of the investigator; (appropriate blood and/or bone marrow samples
             must be taken for RAS determination and submitted to a CLIA-certified laboratory
             prior to study entry); however, if such a mutation is not confirmed by the M D
             Anderson Cancer Center (MDACC)/other center's CLIA-certified laboratory, the patient
             may be permitted to stay on the study if they wish and consent to do so but such
             patients' data will be analyzed separately

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 2 (Karnofsky &gt;= 60%)

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 4 weeks

          -  Able to swallow and retain orally-administered medication and does not have any
             clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities that may alter absorption such
             as malabsorption syndrome or major resection of the stomach or bowels

          -  All prior treatment-related toxicities must be Common Terminology Criteria for
             Adverse Events (CTCAE) version (v)4 grade =&lt; 1 (except alopecia) prior to the first
             dose of the study drug

          -  Serum total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN) (isolated
             total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 institutional ULN is acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated
             and direct bilirubin is &lt; 35%)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x
             institutional ULN

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 1.5 mg/dL OR calculated creatinine clearance (Cockroft-Gault
             formula) &gt;= 60 mL/min

          -  Fasting serum glucose =&lt; 150 mg/dl (fasting is defined as at least 8 hours without
             oral intake)

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &gt;= institutional lower limit of normal
             (LLN) by echocardiogram (ECHO) or multigated acquisition scan (MUGA)

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study, during the
             study participation, and for four months after the last dose of drug; women of
             child-bearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test within 14 days
             prior to randomization and agree to use effective contraception throughout the
             treatment period and for 4 months after the last dose of study treatment; should a
             woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is
             participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of another malignancy; exception: patients who have been disease-free for 3
             years, or patients with a history of completely resected non-melanoma skin cancer
             and/or patients with indolent secondary malignancies, are eligible; consult the
             Cancer Therapy Evaluation Program (CTEP) Medical Monitor if unsure whether second
             malignancies meet the requirements specified above

          -  History of interstitial lung disease or pneumonitis

          -  Any major surgery, extensive radiotherapy, chemotherapy with delayed toxicity,
             biologic therapy, or immunotherapy within 21 days prior to randomization; daily or
             weekly chemotherapy (with the exception of hydroxyurea) without the potential for
             delayed toxicity within 14 days prior to randomization unless there is evidence of
             rapidly progressive disease

          -  Use of other investigational drugs within 28 days (or five half-lives, whichever is
             shorter; with a minimum of 14 days from the last dose) preceding the first dose of
             trametinib/GSK2141795 and during the study

          -  Symptomatic or untreated leptomeningeal disease or brain metastases or spinal cord
             compression

          -  Patients with abnormal fasting glucose values at screening will be excluded; in
             addition, patients with type 1 diabetes will also be excluded; however, patients with
             type 2 diabetes will be allowed if diagnosed &gt;= 6 months prior to enrollment, and if
             presenting with regular hemoglobin A1C (HbA1C) =&lt; 8% at screening

          -  Have a known immediate or delayed hypersensitivity reaction or idiosyncrasy to drugs
             chemically related to trametinib or excipients or to dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) or
             GSK2141795

          -  Current use of a prohibited medication; the following medications or non-drug
             therapies are prohibited:

               -  Other anti-cancer therapy while on study treatment; (Note: megestrol [Megace] if
                  used as an appetite stimulant is allowed)

               -  Concurrent treatment with bisphosphonates is permitted; however, treatment must
                  be initiated prior to the first dose of study therapy; prophylactic use of
                  bisphosphonates in patients without bone disease is not permitted, except for
                  the treatment of osteoporosis

               -  The concurrent use of all herbal supplements is prohibited during the study
                  (including, but not limited to, St. John's wort, kava, ephedra [ma huang],
                  gingko biloba, dehydroepiandrosterone [DHEA], yohimbe, saw palmetto, or ginseng)

                    -  Note: For proliferative disease, hydroxyurea will be allowed during weeks 1
                       and 2 of cycle 1 of study; hydroxyurea may be started or the dose changed
                       during that 2-week period if it is clinically indicated; if a subject not
                       previously on a stable dose of hydroxyurea needs to begin hydroxyurea or a
                       subject on a stable dose needs to have their dose increased during the
                       first 2 weeks, the investigator will notify the clinical team that this has
                       been initiated

          -  In vitro data indicate that GSK2141795 is a cytochrome P450 family 3, subfamily A,
             polypeptide 4 (CYP3A4) substrate; drugs that potently inhibit CYP3A4 could lead to
             increased GSK2141795 exposure in subjects, and should either be prohibited or used
             with caution; drugs which are strong inducers of CYP3A and may result in lower
             exposures of GSK2141795 should also be prohibited; GSK2141795 also appears to be a
             moderate in vitro inhibitor of CYP2C8 (50% inhibitory concentration [IC50] 3 mcM) and
             CYP3A4 (IC50 11 mcM); drugs that are substrates of CYP3A4 or CYP2C8 with a narrow
             therapeutic index may be prohibited; drugs that are sensitive substrates of CYP3A4 or
             CYP2C8 should be used with caution; because the lists of these agents are constantly
             changing, it is important to regularly consult a frequently-updated list; medical
             reference texts such as the Physicians' Desk Reference may also provide this
             information; as part of the enrollment/informed consent procedures, the patient will
             be counseled on the risk of interactions with other agents, and what to do if new
             medications need to be prescribed or if the patient is considering a new
             over-the-counter medicine or herbal product

          -  History or current evidence/risk of retinal vein occlusion (RVO)

          -  History or evidence of cardiovascular risk including any of the following:

               -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; institutional LLN

               -  A QT interval corrected for heart rate using the Bazett's formula QTcB &gt;= 480
                  msec

               -  History or evidence of current clinically significant uncontrolled arrhythmias
                  (exception: patients with controlled atrial fibrillation for &gt; 30 days prior to
                  study dose are eligible)

               -  Patient with symptomatic bradycardia, or a history of clinically significant
                  bradyarrhythmias such as sick sinus syndrome, 2nd degree atrioventricular (AV)
                  block (Mobitz type 2)

               -  History of acute coronary syndromes (including myocardial infarction and
                  unstable angina), coronary angioplasty, or stenting within 6 months prior to
                  study dose

               -  History or evidence of current &gt;= class II congestive heart failure as defined
                  by the New York Heart Association (NYHA) functional classification system

               -  Treatment-refractory hypertension defined as a blood pressure of systolic &gt; 140
                  mmHg and/or diastolic &gt; 90 mmHg which cannot be controlled by anti-hypertensive
                  therapy

               -  Patients with intra-cardiac defibrillators

               -  Known cardiac metastases

          -  Known active hepatitis B virus (HBV), or hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection (with the
             exception of chronic or cleared HBV and HCV infection, are eligible); patients with
             human immunodeficiency  virus (HIV) are not eligible if on anti-retroviral
             medications

          -  Any serious/and or unstable pre-existing medical disorder (aside from malignancy
             exception above), psychiatric disorder, or other conditions that could interfere with
             subject's safety, obtaining informed consent or compliance to the study procedures

          -  Animal reproductive studies have not been conducted with trametinib and GSK2141795;
             therefore, the study drug must not be administered to pregnant women or nursing
             mothers; women of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid pregnancy and use
             effective methods of contraception; men with a female partner of childbearing
             potential must have either had a prior vasectomy or agree to use effective
             contraception; if a female patient or a female partner of a patient becomes pregnant
             while the patient receives trametinib/GSK2141795, the potential hazard to the fetus
             should be explained to the patient and partner (as applicable)

          -  HIV-positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nitin Jain</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Olatoyosi M. Odenike</last_name>
      <phone>773-702-3354</phone>
      <email>todenike@medicine.bsd.uchicago.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Olatoyosi M. Odenike</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland/Greenebaum Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maria R. Baer</last_name>
      <phone>410-328-8708</phone>
      <email>mbaer@umm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maria R. Baer</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nitin Jain</last_name>
      <phone>713-745-6080</phone>
      <email>njain@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nitin Jain</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roland B. Walter</last_name>
      <phone>206-667-3599</phone>
      <email>rwalter@fhrcc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roland B. Walter</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Erythroblastic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Megakaryoblastic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Monocytic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelomonocytic, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelomonocytic, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
