<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="114258">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01828567</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CRE 12-288</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01828567</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Will Veterans Engage in Prevention After HRA-guided Shared Decision Making?</brief_title>
  <acronym>ACTIVATE</acronym>
  <official_title>Will Veterans Engage in Prevention After HRA-guided Shared Decision Making?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Department of Veterans Affairs</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The VA has committed to disseminate a web-based Healthy Living Assessment tool and use it as
      the cornerstone of a personalized prevention plan to engage patients to improve their health
      behaviors that lead to high health risk.  Health risk assessments done in isolation,
      however, do not generally lead to behavior change.  Our study will test the effectiveness of
      a Shared Decision Making intervention designed to activate Veterans to enroll in effective
      prevention programs.  The intervention will be conducted over the telephone, by a prevention
      coach, and will be linked to the patients' primary care team.  The co-primary outcomes will
      be patient activation and patient enrollment in prevention programs; 10-year risk of major
      cardiac events will also be measured.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Over half of all deaths, and many illnesses, can be attributed to four modifiable risk
      factors:  tobacco use, overweight/obesity, physical inactivity, and alcohol use. There are
      clear links between these modifiable factors and heart disease, cancer, chronic lung
      disease, and stroke which continue to be the leading causes of death in the United States.
      Significant improvements have been made in controlling conditions that lead to heart
      disease, cancer and stroke (e.g., hypertension and hyperlipidemia).  However, the underlying
      behavioral factors (e.g., obesity, tobacco use, and physical inactivity) have not been
      addressed as well.  Prevention is particularly important for Veterans because of the high
      prevalence of significant risk factors for poor health.  For example, more than 70% of VHA
      patients are overweight (body mass index [BMI]   25kg/m2) and one-third are obese (BMI
      30kg/m2), which is significantly higher than the US population.  Smoking also remains a
      significant problem among Veterans, with VHA enrollment data from 2010 indicating a
      prevalence of 20%. Younger Veterans are at particularly high risk for developing chronic
      illnesses because they are more likely to be overweight/obese and smoke more heavily than
      non-Veterans.

      The investigators propose a two-site, two-arm randomized trial measuring the effectiveness
      of a Shared Decision Making  (SDM) intervention in activating Veterans to enroll in
      effective prevention services,  and improve cardiovascular risk, compared to VA usual care.
      The study will be performed at the Durham and Saginaw VAMCs.  Each arm will have 225
      patients; patients will be VA users with at least one modifiable risk factor (obese,
      inactive, or tobacco user) who are not currently enrolled in a prevention service.   The SDM
      intervention will be conducted by a prevention coach, telephone based, and will use the
      output from VHA's Healthy Living Assessment to engage Veterans in a conversation where
      individual preferences are matched to behaviors, and choices for specific prevention
      services.  The resulting prevention action plan will be shared with the Veterans primary
      care team, and documented in the medical record.

      Outcomes will be obtained at baseline, 1 month and 6 months after enrollment by blinded
      research personnel.  The primary outcomes will be: 1) proportion enrolled in effective
      prevention services; and 2) change in the Patient Activation Measure (PAM).  The secondary
      outcome is 10-year risk of coronary events, as measured by Framingham Risk Score. Process
      evaluations of the intervention and its implementation will also be conducted to inform
      future dissemination and implementation should it prove effective.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Enrollment in prevention services</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 6 months (cumulative)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of veterans enrolled in effective prevention services including weight loss, healthy eating, physical activity, and smoking cessation programs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Activation Measures</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 6 months (separate assessments)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PAM assesses patients capacity to manage their health.  Improvement in PAM scores indicate responsiveness to interventions and improvements in self-management behaviors.   The protocol specifies co-primary outcomes with enrollment in prevention services specified as the most clinically relevant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Framingham Risk Score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Cardiovascular Risk</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">450</enrollment>
  <condition>Health Risk Appraisal</condition>
  <condition>Heart Disease</condition>
  <condition>Prevention</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Primary care phone-based prevention coaching using shared decision making following a Healthy Living Assessment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Shared decision making with a Prevention Coach</intervention_name>
    <description>A series of two phone sessions with a prevention coach. The first to engage the veteran to choose a preferred prevention program and link them to PACT, and a follow-up call one month later to assess the progress of the prevention plan.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        To be included in the study, patients must meet the following:

          -  enrolled in primary care at the Durham or Saginaw VAMC

          -  have one modifiable risk factor identified by a healthy living assessment (physical
             inactivity, overweight or obese by BMI, tobacco user, or heavy alcohol use)

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Individuals will be excluded if they have any of the following:

          -  have been hospitalized for a stroke, myocardial infarction or coronary artery
             revascularization in the past three months

          -  have an active diagnosis of psychosis

          -  have any other health condition they feel would impede participation in the study

          -  reside in a nursing home

          -  are severely impaired in hearing or speech, so that they cannot respond to telephone
             calls

          -  have significant cognitive or memory impairment

          -  do not have access to a telephone

          -  are participating in another prevention intervention study

          -  are already enrolled in a formal prevention service
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eugene Z. Oddone, MD MHSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Veterans Affairs</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marsha Turner</last_name>
    <email>marsha.turner2@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Dana C Tucker, BA</last_name>
    <phone>(919) 286-0411</phone>
    <phone_ext>5741</phone_ext>
    <email>dana.tucker@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Ann Arbor Healthcare System, Ann Arbor, MI</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laura Damschroder, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>734-769-7100</phone>
      <email>laura.damschroder@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Durham VA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eugene Z Oddone, MD MHSc</last_name>
      <phone>919-286-6936</phone>
      <email>eugene.oddone@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aviel Alkon</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eugene Z. Oddone, MD MHSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jennifer M. Gierisch, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maren K. Olsen, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nina Sperber, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 5, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>veterans</keyword>
  <keyword>healthy risk assessment</keyword>
  <keyword>primary prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>shared decision making</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Living Assessment</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
