<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="75566">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01934244</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S0112003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01934244</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Post Approval NovaSure Essure Labeling Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>PANEL</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Safety of NovaSure in the Presence of Essure Following the Essure Confirmation Test (ECT) Post-Approval Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hologic, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hologic, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This post approval, observational study is being conducted to further evaluate the safety of
      the NovaSure Endometrial Ablation System when it is performed in the presence of Essure
      micro-inserts.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A prospective, single arm, multi-center, post approval study that is designed to provide
      additional information on the safety of performing a NovaSure Impedence Controlled
      Endometrial Ablation System in the presence of Essure Permanent Birth Control System,
      following the Essure Confirmation Test has confirmed both bilateral tubal occlusion and the
      satisfactory location of the Essure micro-inserts. The study will be conducted at up to 15
      clinical sites and enroll 318 patients. Patients who meet the inclusion and none of the
      exclusion criteria will have the study explained to them and be invited to participate.
      Enrolled subjects will have baseline data collected at the time of their NovaSure procedure
      and will be followed for 1 month after the NovaSure procedure to be assessed for adverse
      events.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Essure micro-insert removal with NovaSure device</measure>
    <time_frame>NovaSure procedure visit (Day 1)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>At the end of the NovaSure treatment and upon removal of the NovaSure device, the device will be directly observed to see if any Essure micro-insert(s) is(are) attached.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and percentage of subjects with adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>NovaSure Procedure visit (Day 1) and 1 month post NovaSure procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse events reported during and/or immediately post operative the NovaSure procedure.
Adverse events reported up to 1 month after the NovaSure procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">318</enrollment>
  <condition>Menorrhagia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Per Protocol</arm_group_label>
    <description>All enrolled patients in which all inclusion/exclusion criteria were met and the NovaSure endometrial ablation was completed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Primary</arm_group_label>
    <description>All enrolled patients in whom the Novasure device was inserted.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intent to treat</arm_group_label>
    <description>All enrolled patients in which NovaSure device was attempted.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NovaSure Endometrial Ablation</intervention_name>
    <description>The NovaSure Endometrial Ablation device consists of a disposable single-use, conformable bipolar electrode array mounted on an expandable frame that can create a confluent lesion on the entire interior surface area of the uterine cavity.   The device is inserted transcervically into the uterine cavity, and the sheath is retracted to allow the bipolar electrode array to be deployed and conform to the uterine cavity. The disposable device works in conjunction with a dedicated NovaSure RF (radio frequency) controller to perform customized, global endometrial ablation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Per Protocol</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Premenopausal women 18 years of age or older who have abnormal uterine bleeding and are
        candidates for a NovaSure Endometrial Ablation that have already had an Essure Permanent
        Birth Control system procedure and an Essure Confirmation Test that has confirmed both
        bilateral tubal occlusion and the satisfactory location of the Essure micro-inserts.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is 18 years of age or older and premenopausal.

          -  Subject's gynecological history supports the use of NovaSure endometrial    ablation
             for the treatment of menorrhagia.

          -  Subject has had an Essure Permanent Birth Control System procedure.

          -  The Essure Confirmation Test has confirmed both bilateral tubal occlusion and
             satisfactory placement of the Essure micro-inserts.  A written report or ECT
             radiologic films need to be provided by the physician who performed the ECT.  If
             neither is available, the ECT must be repeated prior to enrollment.

          -  Subject is able to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has known or suspected endometrial carcinoma (uterine cancer) or
             pre-malignant conditions of the endometrium, such as unresolved (atypical)
             adenomatous hyperplasia.

          -  Subject has abnormal/obstructive uterine cavity as confirmed by hysteroscopy or other
             imaging study (e.g. congenital malformation, large fibroid or large polyp)

          -  Subject with any anatomic condition (e.g. history of previous classical cesarean
             section or transmural myomectomy) or pathologic condition (e.g. long term medical
             therapy) that could lead to weakening of the myometrium.

          -  Subject has an active genital or urinary tract infection at the time of the procedure
             (e.g., cervicitis, vaginitis, endometritis, salpingitis, or cystitis).

          -  Subject has an intrauterine device (IUD) currently in place.

          -  Subject has active pelvic inflammatory disease or history of recent pelvic infection.

          -  Subject has undiagnosed vaginal bleeding.

          -  ECT unable to adequately assess bilateral tubal occlusion and proper micro-insert
             placement.

          -  Subject has uterine sound measurement greater than 10 cm.

          -  Subject with a uterine cavity length less than 4 cm.

          -  Subject with a uterine cavity width less than 2.5 cm, as determined by the width dial
             of the disposable NovaSure device following device deployment.

          -  Subject is unable to comply with the protocol and be available for follow up

          -  In the opinion of the investigator, the subject has a medical condition that
             precludes safe participation in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Edward Evantash, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Hologic, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Westside Women's Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Arvada</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80005</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Minnesota Gynecology and Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edina</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55435</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Amy Brenner MD &amp; Associates, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Chester</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45069</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tennessee Women's Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.hologic.com</url>
    <description>Hologic, Inc. website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basinski CM, et al: Safety and Effectiveness of Novasure Endometrial Ablation After Placement of Essure Micro-inserts. Journal of Gynecologic Surgery 28(2), 2012</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 9, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Menorrhagia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
