<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="23517">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02090413</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>109MS406</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-001895-40</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02090413</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 4 Study of Effect of Aspirin on Flushing in Dimethyl Fumarate (DMF)-Treated Participants With Relapsing-Remitting Multiple Sclerosis (RRMS)</brief_title>
  <acronym>ASSURE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 4, Randomized, Double-Blind Study With a Safety Extension Period to Evaluate the Effect of Aspirin on Flushing in Subjects With Relapsing-Remitting Multiple Sclerosis Treated With Tecfidera™ (Dimethyl Fumarate) Delayed-release Capsules</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Biogen Idec</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Biogen Idec</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Ireland: Irish Medicines Board</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the study is to evaluate whether 150 mg enteric-coated aspirin
      (ASA) taken twice a day (BID) with BG00012 (dimethyl fumarate, DMF) administration or 75 mg
      enteric-coated ASA taken once daily in the morning (QAM) with BG00012 administration reduces
      the incidence and/or severity of flushing events in subjects with relapsing-remitting
      multiple sclerosis (RRMS) compared with ASA-placebo administered with BG00012 in the
      clinical practice setting..

      Secondary objectives this study in this study population are: To evaluate the safety and
      tolerability of BG00012 administered with and without enteric-coated ASA in the clinical
      practice setting; To evaluate the impact of BG00012 administration on quality of life as
      measured by the Short Form 36 (SF-36®) and European Quality of Life - 5 Dimensions - 5
      Levels (EQ-5D-5L) questionnaires.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There are two parts to this study:

        -  Double-Blind Period from randomization through Week 12

        -  Safety Extension Period from Week 13 to Week 48
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Participant-Reported Flushing Events During the First 4 Weeks Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants reported flushing events using a hand-held reporting device (eDiary) based on the Modified Global Flushing Severity Scale (MGFSS) and Modified Flushing Severity Scale (MFSS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of Participant-Reported Flushing Events During the First 4 Weeks of Treatment based on the MGFSS and MFSS data</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Participant-Reported Flushing Events During Weeks 5-8 and Weeks 9-12 of the study  using MGFSS and MFSS data</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 5-8 and 9-12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of Participant-Reported Flushing Events During Weeks 5-8 and Weeks 9-12 of the study using MGFSS and MFSS data</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 5-8 and 9-12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Participant-Reported Flushing Events During Weeks 1-4, 5-8 and 9-12 of the study using MGFSS and MFSS data</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1-4, 5-8 and 9-12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Participant-Reported Flushing Events During Weeks 13-48 of Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 13-48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants reported flushing events using paper diaries based on the Modified Global Flushing Severity Scale (MGFSS) and Modified Flushing Severity Scale (MFSS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment Discontinuation and Study Withdrawal Due to Any Adverse Event</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment Discontinuation and Study Withdrawal Due to Flushing Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-emergent Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Counts exclude nonserious flushing events or flushing events that lead to treatment discontinuation or study withdrawal</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline to Week 24 and Week 48 in Quality of Life Measurements as Assessed by the Short Form 36 (SF-36) and European Quality of Life - 5 Dimensions - 5 Levels (EQ-5D-5L) Questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to Week 24 and up to Week 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Relapsing-Remitting Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BG00012 + ASA 150 mg BID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Double-Blind Period: Participants take BG00012 orally at a dose of 120 mg twice a day (BID) for the first 7 days and at a dose of 240 mg BID from weeks 2-12. ASA 150 mg is taken BID from Day 1 through Week 4. Safety Extension Period: Participants take BG00012 orally at a dose of 240 mg twice a day (BID) from Week 13-48.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DMF + ASA 75 mg QAM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Double-Blind Period: Participants take BG00012 orally at a dose of 120 mg twice a day (BID) for the first 7 days and at a dose of 240 mg BID from weeks 2-12. ASA 75 mg is taken once daily in the morning (QAM) and ASA-Placebo is taken in the evening from Day 1 through Week 4. Safety Extension Period: Participants take BG00012 orally at a dose of 240 mg twice a day (BID) from Week 13-48.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DMF + ASA-Placebo BID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Double-Blind Period: Participants take BG00012 orally at a dose of 120 mg twice a day (BID) for the first 7 days and at a dose of 240 mg BID from weeks 2-12. ASA-Placebo is taken BID from Day 1 through Week 4. Safety Extension Period: Participants take BG00012 orally at a dose of 240 mg twice a day (BID) from Week 13-48.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BG00012 (Dimethyl Fumarate)</intervention_name>
    <description>The BG00012 dosing regimen is 120 mg twice a day (BID) for the first 7 days and 240 mg BID thereafter. Modifications of the BG00012 regimen are not allowed for the first 12 weeks (double-blind period).</description>
    <arm_group_label>DMF + ASA-Placebo BID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>DMF + ASA 75 mg QAM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BG00012 + ASA 150 mg BID</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dimethyl Fumarate</other_name>
    <other_name>DMF</other_name>
    <other_name>Tecfidera™</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acetylsalicylic acid</intervention_name>
    <description>Aspirin is used in 75mg enteric-coated tablets taken orally for the first 4 weeks of the study. To maintain the blind, participants in the BG00012 + ASA 150 mg BID treatment arm take two 75 mg ASA tablets with each BG00012 dose (BID). Participants in the BG00012 + ASA 75 mg QAM treatment arm take one 75 mg ASA tablet and one ASA-placebo tablet with the morning BG00012 dose, and two ASA-placebo tablets with the evening BG00012 dose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DMF + ASA 75 mg QAM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BG00012 + ASA 150 mg BID</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ASA</other_name>
    <other_name>aspirin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ASA-Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>ASA-placebo tablets look like the enteric-coated ASA tablets and are taken orally for the first 4 weeks of the study. Participants in the BG00012 + ASA-Placebo BID treatment arm take two ASA-placebo tablets with each BG00012 dose (BID).</description>
    <arm_group_label>DMF + ASA-Placebo BID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>DMF + ASA 75 mg QAM</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Naïve to fumaric acid esters (e.g. BG00012 [DMF], Fumaderm®, compounded fumarates)

          -  Diagnosed with RRMS and satisfies the approved therapeutic indication for BG00012

          -  Participants of childbearing potential must practice effective contraception during
             the study through at least the Week 12 visit.

          -  Able to complete the tolerability scales accurately using the electronic diary
             (eDiary) and able to complete the paper Flushing Diaries

        Key Exclusion Criteria:

          -  One or more major comorbidities that, in the opinion of the investigator, may affect
             the outcome of the study or otherwise makes the subject an unsuitable candidate for
             study participation.  The prevailing product labels for both BG00012 and aspirin
             (ASA) should be used as guides.

          -  Known active malignancies

          -  Chronic use of ASA- or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAID)-containing
             products within the month prior to enrolment in the study

          -  A known intolerance to ASA

          -  Active peptic ulceration or a history of peptic ulceration, hemophilia or other
             clotting disorders, or gout

          -  Impaired hepatic or renal function, in the opinion of the investigator

          -  Female subject is pregnant, lactating, or will be attempting to become pregnant
             during the Double-Blind Period (first 12 weeks) of the study.

          -  Currently participating in another interventional clinical trial.

        NOTE:  Other protocol-defined inclusion/exclusion criteria may apply
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Biogen Idec</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Biogen Idec Investigator</last_name>
    <email>clinicaltrials@biogenidec.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>multiple sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>flushing</keyword>
  <keyword>aspirin</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Flushing</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis, Relapsing-Remitting</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Aspirin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dimethyl fumarate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
