<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="151463">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02020889</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>115921</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02020889</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Investigate Mepolizumab in the Treatment of Eosinophilic Granulomatosis With Polyangiitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-blind, Randomised, Placebo-controlled Study to Investigate the Efficacy and Safety of Mepolizumab in the Treatment of Eosinophilic Granulomatosis With Polyangiitis in Subjects Receiving Standard of Care Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States: National Institute of Health; National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases  (NIAID) division</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Italy: Agenzia Italiana del Farmaco</authority>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Belgian Federal Agency for Medicinal and Health Products</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Bundesinstitut für Arzneimittel und Medizinprodukte</authority>
    <authority>Japan: Pharmaceuticals and Medical Devices Agency</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Spanish Agency for Medicines and Health Products</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this randomized, double-blind study is to investigate the efficacy and safety
      of mepolizumab (300 milligram [mg] administered subcutaneously [SC] every 4 weeks) compared
      with placebo over a 52-week study treatment period in subjects with relapsing or refractory
      Eosinophilic Granulomatosis with Polyangiitis (EGPA) receiving standard of care therapy
      including background corticosteroid therapy with or without immunosuppressive therapy.
      During the treatment period, in accordance with standard of care, corticosteroid dose will
      be tapered. The key outcomes in the study focus on evaluation of clinical remission, defined
      as Birmingham Vasculitis Activity Score (BVAS)=0 with a corticosteroid dose of &lt;=4 mg/day
      prednisolone/prednisone, reduction in disease relapse and reduction in corticosteroid
      requirement.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total accrued duration of remission</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline to Week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The accrued number of weeks where BVAS=0 plus prednisolone/prednisone dose &lt;=4 mg/day over the 52 week study treatment period reported as proportion of subjects achieving remission in the following categories: Zero, &gt;0 to &lt;12 weeks, 12 to &lt;24 weeks, 24 to &lt;36 weeks, &gt;=36 weeks</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of subjects who are in remission at both Weeks 36 and 48 of the study treatment period</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 36 and 48</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Remission is defined as BVAS=0 and prednisolone/prednisone dose &lt;=4 mg/day</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first confirmed EGPA relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>EGPA relapse is defined as worsening or persistence of active disease characterised by active vasculitis (BVAS &gt;0) or active asthma symptoms and/or signs with a corresponding worsening in Asthma Control Questionnaire (ACQ) 6 score or active nasal and/or sinus disease with a corresponding worsening in at least one of the sino-nasal symptom questions warranting an increased dose of OCS therapy or an increased dose or addition of immunosuppressive therapy or hospitalisation related to EGPA worsening</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of subjects with an average daily prednisolone/prednisone dose of 0 mg, &gt;0 to &lt;=4.0 mg, &gt;4.0 to &lt;=7.5 mg and &gt;7.5 mg during the last 4 weeks of the study treatment period (48 through 52)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 48 to Week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of subjects in each treatment group who achieve remission (BVAS=0 and prednisolone/prednisone dose &lt;=4 mg/day) within the first 24 weeks of the study and then remain in remission for the remainder of the study treatment period</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 52</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">130</enrollment>
  <condition>Churg-Strauss Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mepolizumab 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each subject will receive mepolizumab 300 mg subcutaneous (SC) injection every 4 weeks (13 administrations) along with standard care. It will be administered as 3 separate injections (100 mg each- total dose 300 mg); individual injection sites will be separated by at least 5 cm. It will be administered into any of the upper arm, thigh or anterior abdominal wall.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each subject will receive placebo (0.9% sodium chloride) SC injection every 4 weeks (13 administrations) along with standard care. It will be administered as 3 separate injections; individual injection sites will be separated by at least 5 cm. It will be administered into any of the upper arm, thigh or anterior abdominal wall.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mepolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Mepolizumab will be provided as a lyophilized cake in sterile vials for individual use to be reconstituted with sterile water for Injection, just prior to use.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mepolizumab 300 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo will be available as 0.9% sodium chloride</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed Consent:  Able to give written informed consent prior to participation in
             the study, which will include the ability to comply with the requirements and
             restrictions listed in the consent form.  Subjects must be able to read, comprehend,
             and write at a level sufficient to complete study related materials.

          -  Age and gender: Male or female subjects age 18 years or older.

          -  EGPA diagnosis: subjects who have been diagnosed with EGPA for at least 6 months
             based on the history or presence of: asthma plus eosinophilia (&gt;1.0x10^9/Liter and/or
             &gt;10% of leucocytes) plus at least two of the following additional features of EGPA; a
             biopsy showing histopathological evidence of eosinophilic vasculitis, or perivascular
             eosinophilic infiltration, or  eosinophil-rich granulomatous inflammation;
             neuropathy, mono or poly (motor deficit or nerve conduction abnormality); pulmonary
             infiltrates, non-fixed; sino-nasal abnormality; cardiomyopathy (established by
             echocardiography or Magnetic Resonance Imaging); glomerulonephritis (haematuria, red
             cell casts, proteinuria); alveolar haemorrhage (by bronchoalveolar lavage); palpable
             purpura; anti neutrophil cytoplasmic anti-body (ANCA) positive (Myeloperoxidase or
             proteinease 3).

          -  History of relapsing OR refractory disease defined as: Relapsing disease:

        Subject must have a past history of at least one confirmed EGPA relapse (i.e., requiring
        increase in oral corticosteroids (OCS) dose, initiation/increased dose of
        immunosuppressive therapy or hospitalisation) within the past 2 years which occurred at
        least 12 weeks prior to Screening (Visit 1) whilst receiving a dose of prednisolone (or
        equivalent) of &gt;=7.5 milligram per day (mg/day). Refractory disease: Either: Failure to
        attain remission (BVAS=0 and OCS dose &lt;=7.5 mg/day prednisolone or equivalent) within the
        last 6 months following induction treatment with a standard regimen, administered for at
        least 3 months. Note: a) Subjects who have received a cyclophosphamide (CYC) induction
        regimen may be included a minimum of 2 weeks after the last dose of daily oral CYC, or 3
        weeks after the last dose of pulsed intravenous CYC prior to Baseline (Visit 2), if their
        total white blood cells (WBC) is &gt;=4x10^9/Liter (tested at the local laboratory, if
        necessary) prior to randomisation. b) Subjects who have received a methotrexate,
        azathioprine, or mycophenolate mofetil induction regimen may be included if on a stable
        dose for at least 4 weeks prior to Baseline (Visit 2). c) Subjects who have received an
        induction regimen comprising corticosteroids alone may be included only if they have
        failed to attain remission after 3 months of treatment AND the corticosteroid dose is &gt;=15
        mg/day prednisolone or equivalent for the 4 weeks prior to Baseline (Visit 2). Or: Within
        6 months prior to Screening (Visit 1), recurrence of symptoms of EGPA (not necessarily
        meeting the protocol definition of relapse) whilst tapering OCS, occurring at any dose
        level &gt;=7.5 mg/day prednisolone or equivalent.

          -  Corticosteroid therapy: Subject must be on a stable dose of oral prednisolone or
             prednisone of &gt;=7.5 mg/day (but not &gt;50 mg/day) for at least 4 weeks prior to
             Baseline (Visit 2).

          -  Immunosuppressive therapy: If receiving immunosuppressive therapy (excluding
             cyclophosphamide) the dosage must be stable for the 4 weeks prior to Baseline (Visit
             2) and during the study (dose reductions for safety reasons will be permitted).

          -  ECG measurements: QTc(F)&lt;450 msec or QTc(F)&lt;480 msec for patients with bundle branch
             block. The QTc is the QT interval corrected for heart rate according to either
             Bazett's formula (QTcB), Fridericia's formula (QTcF), or another method, machine or
             manual overread. For subject eligibility and withdrawal decisions, QTcFwill be used.
             For purposes of data analysis, QTcF will be used as primary though data using both
             correction formulas will be collected and analysed. The QTc should be based on single
             or averaged QTc values of triplicate electrocardiograms (ECGs) obtained over a brief
             recording period.

          -  Female subjects: To be eligible for entry into the study, females of childbearing
             potential (FCBP) must commit to consistent and correct use of an acceptable method of
             birth control (as discussed in the protocol) beginning with consent, for the duration
             of the trial and for 4 months after the last study drug administration.

          -  French subjects: In France, a subject will be eligible for inclusion in this study
             only if either affiliated to or a beneficiary of a social security category.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  GPA or MPA: Diagnosed with granulomatosis with polyangiitis (GPA; previously known as
             Wegener's granulomatosis) or microscopic polyangiitis (MPA).

          -  Organ-threatening EGPA: Organ-threatening EGPA as per European league against
             rheumatism (EULAR) criteria, i.e., organ failure due to active vasculitis, creatinine
             &gt;5.8 gram per deciliter (g/dL) (&gt;513 micromole per liter [µmol/L]) within 3 months
             prior to Screening (Visit 1).

          -  Life-threatening EGPA: Imminently life-threatening EGPA disease defined as any of the
             following within 3 months prior to Screening (Visit 1); Intensive care required;
             Severe alveolar haemorrhage or haemoptysis requiring transfusion or ventilation or
             haemoglobin &lt; 8 gram per liter (g/dL) (&lt;80 g/L) or drop in haemoglobin &gt; 2 g/dL (&gt;20
             g/L) over a 48 hour period due to alveolar haemorrhage; Rapidly progressive
             glomerulonephritis (RPGN) with creatinine &gt; 2.5 milligram per deciliter (mg/dL) (&gt;221
             µmol/L) or rise in creatinine &gt; 2 mg/dL (&gt;177 µmol/L) over a 48 hour period; Severe
             gastrointestinal (GI) involvement, e.g., gangrene, bleeding requiring surgery; Severe
             central nervous system (CNS) involvement; Severe cardiac involvement, e.g.,
             life-threatening arrhythmia, cardiac failure: ejection fraction &lt; 20%, New York Heart
             Association Class III/IV (as discussed in protocol), acute myocardial infarction.

          -  Malignancy: A current malignancy or previous history of cancer in remission for less
             than 12 months prior screening (Subjects that had localized carcinoma (i.e., basal or
             squamous cell) of the skin which was resected for cure will not be excluded).

          -  Liver disease: Unstable liver disease (as defined by the presence of ascites,
             encephalopathy, coagulopathy, hypoalbuminaemia, esophageal or gastric varices or
             persistent jaundice), cirrhosis, and known biliary abnormalities (with the exception
             of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones).

          -  Cardiovascular: Subjects who have severe or clinically significant cardiovascular
             disease uncontrolled with standard treatment including but not limited to: Known
             ejection fraction of &lt;30%,  OR Severe heart failure that meets New York Heart
             Association Class IV  (as discussed in protocol), OR Hospitalised in the 12 months
             prior to Visit 1 for severe heart failure meeting New York Heart Association Class
             III (as discussed in protocol), OR Angina diagnosed less than 3 months prior to or at
             Visit 1 (Screening).

          -  Other concurrent medical conditions: Subjects who have known, pre-existing,
             clinically significant endocrine, autoimmune, metabolic, neurological, renal,
             gastrointestinal, hepatic, haematological, respiratory or any other system
             abnormalities that are not associated with EGPA and are uncontrolled with standard
             treatment.

          -  Infectious disease: Chronic or ongoing active infectious disease requiring systemic
             treatment.

          -  Parasitic infection: Subjects with a parasitic infestation within 6 months prior to
             Screening (Visit 1).

          -  Hepatitis status: Diagnosis of chronic hepatitis B, as evidenced by positive
             Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) at Screening (Visit 1). Japan only: Subjects
             positive for HBsAg , antibodies to HBsAg, i.e., HBsAb, or Hepatitis B core antigen,
             i.e., HBcAb, at Screening (Visit 1). Note: Subjects with antibodies to HBsAg, i.e.,
             HBsAb positive, only (i.e., negative for HBsAg and HBcAb) with a history of hepatitis
             B vaccination can be included.

          -  HIV: Subjects with a known human immunodeficiency virus infection.

          -  Hypersensitivity: Subjects with a known allergy or intolerance to a monoclonal
             antibody or biologic therapy.

          -  Previous mepolizumab: Subjects who have previously received mepolizumab within a 1
             year period prior to Screening (Visit 1).

          -  Prohibited medications: Subjects receiving any of the following: OCS: Subject
             requires an oral corticosteroid dose of &gt;50 mg/day prednisolone/prednisone in the
             4-week period prior to Baseline (Visit 2); Intravenous or SC corticosteroids in the
             4-week period prior to Baseline (Visit 2); Omalizumab within 130 days prior to
             Screening (Visit 1); Cyclophosphamide:  oral CYC within 2 weeks prior to Baseline
             (Visit 2) and IV CYC within 3 weeks prior to Baseline (Visit 2), if their total WBC
             is &gt;=4x10^9/Liter (measured using the local laboratory if necessary); Rituximab
             within 12 months prior to Screening (Visit 1); in addition, the subject must have
             shown recovery of peripheral B-cell count to within the normal range; IV or SC
             immunoglobulin within 6 months prior to Screening (Visit 1); Interferon-α within 6
             months prior to Screening (Visit 1); Anti-TNF therapy within 12 weeks prior to
             Screening (Visit 1); Anti-CD52 (alemtuzumab) within 6 months prior to Screening
             (Visit 1).

          -  Liver Function Tests: obtained at Screening (Visit 1): ALT&lt;2x ULN (upper limit of
             normal) or if subject is on background methotrexate or azathioprine &lt;3x ULN;  AST&lt;2x
             ULN or if subject is on background methotrexate or azathioprine   &lt;3x ULN; Alkaline
             Phosphatase ≤2.0x ULN;Bilirubin ≤ 1.5x ULN (isolated bilirubin&gt;1.5x ULN is acceptable
             if bilirubin is fractionated and direct bilirubin &lt;35%)

          -  Other laboratory parameter exclusions: Creatinine &gt; 2.5 mg/dL (221 µmol/L); WBC &lt; 4
             x10^9/Liter, Platelet count &lt;120,000/millimetre cube (mm^3), Haemoglobin &lt;8 g/dL (&lt;80
             g/L)

          -  Pregnancy: Subjects who are pregnant or breastfeeding. Subjects should not be
             enrolled if they plan to become pregnant during the time of study participation.

          -  Alcohol/substance abuse: A history (or suspected history) of alcohol misuse or
             substance abuse within 2 years prior to Screening (Visit 1).

          -  Other investigational product: Subjects who have received treatment with an
             investigational drug within the past 30 days or 5 terminal phase half-lives of the
             drug whichever is longer, prior to Screening (Visit 1) (this also includes
             investigational formulations of marketed products).

          -  Other clinical study: Subject is currently participating in any other interventional
             clinical study.

          -  Adherence: Subjects who have known evidence of lack of adherence to controller
             medications and/or ability to follow physician's recommendations.

          -  French subjects: the French subject has participated in any study using an
             investigational drug during the previous 30 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is
             longer).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bruxelles</city>
        <zip>1070</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8N 4A6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5T 3L9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bron Cedex</city>
        <zip>69677</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille cedex 20</city>
        <zip>13915</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier cedex 5</city>
        <zip>34295</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75014</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Suresnes</city>
        <zip>92151</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Freiburg</city>
        <state>Baden-Wuerttemberg</state>
        <zip>79106</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Plochingen</city>
        <state>Baden-Wuerttemberg</state>
        <zip>73207</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fulda</city>
        <state>Hessen</state>
        <zip>36043</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bad Bramstedt</city>
        <state>Schleswig-Holstein</state>
        <zip>24576</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jena</city>
        <state>Thueringen</state>
        <zip>07747</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>22767</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <state>Lombardia</state>
        <zip>20132</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <state>Lombardia</state>
        <zip>20162</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Firenze</city>
        <state>Toscana</state>
        <zip>50134</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pisa</city>
        <state>Toscana</state>
        <zip>56126</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miyagi</city>
        <zip>980-8574</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08036</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cambridge</city>
        <zip>CB2 2QQ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leicester</city>
        <zip>LE3 9QP</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portsmouth</city>
        <zip>PO6 3LY</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Japan</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 22, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>eosinophils</keyword>
  <keyword>SB 240563</keyword>
  <keyword>Churg-Strauss Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>mepolizumab</keyword>
  <keyword>safety</keyword>
  <keyword>biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>efficacy</keyword>
  <keyword>corticosteroids</keyword>
  <keyword>Eosinophilic granulomatosis with polyangiitis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Churg-Strauss Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wegener Granulomatosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Systemic Vasculitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
