<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8220">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01883804</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-1408</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01883804</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Methyldopa on MHC Class II Antigen Presentation in Type 1 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Open Label Pilot Study of the Effect of Methyldopa on MHC-II Antigen Presentation in Type 1 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado Denver School of Medicine Barbara Davis Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Juvenile Diabetes Research Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado Denver School of Medicine Barbara Davis Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Type 1 Diabetes is an autoimmune condition in which segments of the immune system cause the
      destruction of insulin producing cells in the pancreas, leaving individuals with an impaired
      ability to control blood glucose levels. Currently there is no cure for Type 1 Diabetes and
      the treatments involve lifelong insulin administration and careful monitoring of blood
      glucose levels. Long-term complications like cardiovascular disease, nerve damage, and
      retina damage, may result. Previous studies have shown that improvement in the control of
      blood glucose can reduce the risks from these long-term complications. Residual insulin
      production, typically within the first few years following diagnosis, helps to reduce an
      individual's need to supplement insulin by injection or pump. This effect helps in
      maintaining the body's ability to regulate blood glucose levels and reducing the needs of
      external insulin.

      Methyldopa, or Aldomet, has been approved by the Food and Drug Administration and is
      commonly used to treat high blood pressure. This drug has been approved for several decades
      and has been shown to be safe and effective. This drug has been identified by the researcher
      to be able to block the communication between two important types of immune cells; which
      play a critical role in the autoimmune processes of Type 1 Diabetes. The investigators
      hypothesize that Methyldopa, over a 6 week treatment period, will block this communication
      and possibly slow down the destruction of insulin producing cells. The investigators hope to
      assess the appropriate and safe dose to achieve this effect, along with the drug's ability
      to maintain insulin production and blood glucose control.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Inhibition of DQ8 Antigen Presentation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators aim to observe inhibition of DQ8 antigen presentation; along with the dose required to achieve this aim. The researchers have devolved an assay to monitor the effect of Methyldopa on the presentation of the DQ8 antigen through the isolation of specific cells found in the blood. Using this assay, the investigators will analyze the ability to block DQ8 antigen presentation as the dose of Methyldopa changes through the course of the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of C-Peptide Changes</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators aim to observe changes in C-peptide production through the use of Mixed Meal Tolerance Tests. C-peptide is a product of insulin secretion and can help investigators monitor changes in insulin amounts over time. Blood samples will be collected at various time points during the Mixed Meal Tolerance Test, each of which will be analyzed for the amount of c-peptide present.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of Insulin Dose and Hemoglobin A1c</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators aim to observe changes in insulin requirements, along with Hemoglobin A1c values, of each participant. Insulin requirements will be reported by each participant during each visit, by way of insulin units being taken or by downloading of insulin pump data. Hemoglobin A1c values will be analyzed during Mixed Meal Tolerance Tests, with the blood already being collected for C-peptide analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability of Methyldopa</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Investigators aim to assess the tolerability of Methyldopa doses required to achieve the primary outcome. This will be assessed through discussions with participants and careful monitoring of any adverse events. Participants will be asked to wear a continuous blood pressure monitor during  the 3 days following any changes in the dose of Methyldopa, or any other time point deemed necessary by the study doctor.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants selected to continue with Methyldopa administration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methyldopa</intervention_name>
    <description>6 weeks of Methyldopa administration; where the dose will be increased according to safety of efficacy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Aldomet</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus

          -  18-46 years of age

          -  Residual C-peptide production during screening

          -  Positive for at least one islet autoantibody: insulin (if only insulin autoantibody
             positive, determination must be within two weeks of insulin initiation), GAD-65, IA-2
             or ZnT8

          -  Positive for at least one gene encoding HLA-DQ8 (DQB*0302)

          -  No history of difficult to control  hypertension (defined as requiring &gt; 2
             anti-hypertensive medications)

          -  Agree to intensive management of diabetes with an HgbA1c goal of &lt; 8.0%

          -  If female: (a) surgically sterile or (b) postmenopausal or (c) if of reproductive
             potential, willing to use medically acceptable birth control (e.g. female hormonal
             contraception, barrier methods or sterilization.) until study completion

          -  If male and of reproductive potential, willing to use medically acceptable birth
             control until study completion, unless the female partner is postmenopausal or
             surgically sterile

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable or unwilling to comply with the requirements of the study protocol

          -  No HLA-DQ8 gene (DQB*0302)

          -  Difficult to control hypertension (defined as requiring &gt; 2 anti-hypertensive
             medications)

          -  History of postural hypotension or Addison's disease

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) &gt; 30 kg/m2

          -  Unstable blood sugar control defined as one or more episodes of severe hypoglycemia
             (defined as hypoglycemia that required the assistance of another person) within the
             last 30 days

          -  Administration of an experimental agent for T1D at any time or use of an experimental
             device for T1D within 30 days of screening, unless approved by the study PI

          -  History of any organ transplant, including islet cell transplant

          -  Active autoimmune or immune deficiency disorder (e.g. sarcoidosis, rheumatoid
             arthritis)

          -  Anticipated pregnancy during the 12 week study period

          -  Any social or medical condition that would, in the opinion of the investigator,
             prevent complete participation in the study or that would pose a significant hazard
             to the subjects' participation

          -  History of active substance abuse within 12 months of screening

          -  A psychiatric or medical disorder that would prevent giving informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>46 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aaron Michels, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Barbara Davis Center for Diabetes, University of Colorado School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Aimon K Alkanani, BA</last_name>
    <phone>303-724-6821</phone>
    <email>aimon.alkanani@ucdenver.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Barbara Davis Center for Diabetes, University of Colorado School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aimon K Alkanani, BA</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-6821</phone>
      <email>aimon.alkanani@ucdenver.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aaron Michels, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.barbaradaviscenter.org/</url>
    <description>Barbara Davis Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Colorado Denver School of Medicine Barbara Davis Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Aaron Michels, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Effect of Methyldopa on MHC class II Antigen Presentation in Type 1 Diabetes</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes Mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>Type 1 Diabetes</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Methyldopa</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
