<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="144829">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02155985</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACTG A5331</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UM1AI068636</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02155985</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Modulation of Immune Activation by Aspirin</brief_title>
  <official_title>Modulation of Immune Activation by Aspirin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AIDS Clinical Trials Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AIDS Clinical Trials Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Since people started taking HIV medications, illness from AIDS has decreased, but other
      serious diseases like heart disease, cancer, and kidney, and liver disease have increased.
      HIV causes inflammation (irritation) inside the body that cannot be felt but can be measured
      by blood. Inflammation can lead to diseases that have become some of the leading causes of
      death in people with HIV. HIV therapy can partially lower levels of inflammation measured in
      blood, however, levels of inflammation in people who have HIV may remain high compared with
      those found in people not infected with HIV.

      Aspirin is a drug that is commonly used for pain relief but is also approved by the Food and
      Drug Administration (FDA) for preventing heart attacks and stroke in those who are at
      increased risk for heart attack and stroke. Aspirin also is used (but is not approved by the
      FDA) to decrease the risk of some cancers in people who are at increased risk. Aspirin is
      thought to decrease risk of heart attack and stroke because it blocks the activation
      (turning on) of platelets (small cells in your blood that help it to clot) and prevents
      blood clots from clogging narrowed blood vessels, a disease called atherosclerosis. It is
      unknown how aspirin might decrease the chance of developing cancer in some people at higher
      risk, but aspirin has been shown to modulate (or change) the immune system. In HIV-infected
      people who have been taking antiretroviral therapy and have an undetectable HIV viral load.
      It has recently been shown that low-dose aspirin 81 mg (baby aspirin), given for one week,
      lowers platelet activation and reduces blood markers of inflammation which may improve the
      function of the immune system. The purpose of the study that you are being asked to
      participate in is to evaluate whether aspirin improves inflammation and immune activation
      when compared to a placebo (inactive medication like a dummy pill) and to determine if 12
      weeks of aspirin 300 mg and aspirin 100 mg is safe for HIV-infected persons on
      antiretroviral therapy (ART). Additionally, it will study whether a higher dose and longer
      duration of aspirin provides further anti-inflammatory (something that prevents irritation)
      and immune-modulating (something that helps or improves the immune system) benefit. This
      will be done using blood and urine tests that measure inflammation and also with a test that
      uses ultrasound to measure the flow of blood in your arm, called flow-mediated vasodilation
      (FMD) of the brachial artery (BART). This is a painless test that bounces sound waves off of
      a blood vessel in your arm.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in sCD14 from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Summary of the number of subjects with at least one grade 3 or higher sign/symptom or laboratory abnormality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in sCD163 from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CD14 from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CD16 from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CD69 from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CD4+CD38+ cell proportion from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CD4+HLA-DR+ cell proportion from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CD8+CD38+ cell proportion from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CD8+HLA-DR+ cell proportion from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in expression of PD-1 on CD4+ from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in expression of PD-1 on CD8+ from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in expression of CTLA-4 on CD4+ from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in expression of CTLA-4 on CD8+ from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in IL-6 from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in d-dimer from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in kynurenine to tryptophan ratio from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in serum thromboxane B2 from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 11-dehydrothromboxane B2 from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in brachial artery FMD from baseline to week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV-1 Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Aspirin 300 mg and placebo for aspirin 100 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>At week 0, participants will be administered aspirin 300mg (one tablet) and placebo for aspirin 100 mg (one tablet) once daily. At week 12, participants will stop both study product tablets to allow for a 4-week washout period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Aspirin 100 mg and placebo for aspirin 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>At week 0, participants will be administered a placebo for aspirin 300 mg (one tablet) and aspirin 100 mg (one tablet) once daily.  At week 12, participants will stop both study product tablets to allow for a 4-week washout period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3: Placebos for aspirin 300 mg and aspirin 100 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>At week 0, participants will be administered a placebo for aspirin 300 mg (one tablet) and placebo for aspirin 100 mg (one tablet) once daily. At week 12, participants will stop both study products tablets to allow for a 4-week washout period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aspirin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Aspirin 300 mg and placebo for aspirin 100 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Aspirin 100 mg and placebo for aspirin 300 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aspirin placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Aspirin 300 mg and placebo for aspirin 100 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Aspirin 100 mg and placebo for aspirin 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3: Placebos for aspirin 300 mg and aspirin 100 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV-1 infection.

          -  Currently on continuous ART for ≥48 weeks prior to study entry. NOTE: This is defined
             as continuous active therapy with no treatment interruption longer than 7 consecutive
             days and a total duration off-treatment of no more than 14 days during the 48 weeks
             prior to entry.

          -  No change in ART regimen within the 12 weeks prior to study entry (except as noted
             below).

        NOTE: Modifications of ART dosing during within the 12 weeks prior to entry are permitted.
        In addition, the change in formulation (eg, from standard formulation to fixed dose
        combination or single tablet regimen) or dosing (eg, from once a day to twice a day) is
        allowed within 12 weeks prior to entry. Within-class single drug substitution (eg, switch
        from nevirapine to efavirenz or from atazanavir to darunavir), are not allowed within 12
        weeks prior to entry. No other changes in ART in the 12 weeks prior to entry are
        permitted.

          -  Screening HIV-1 RNA must be &lt;50 copies/mL and performed by any FDA-approved assay at
             any US laboratory that has a CLIA certification or its equivalent within 45 days
             prior to study entry.

          -  Maintain ART-mediated viral suppression for at least 48 weeks prior to study entry
             defined as:

        A. At least one HIV-1 RNA test result obtained at any time point greater than 48 weeks
        prior to study entry must be BLQ and must be performed by any FDA-approved assay at a
        CLIA-certified laboratory or its equivalent.

        AND

        B. All HIV-1 RNA tests reported during the 48 weeks prior to study entry must be BLQ and
        must be performed by any FDA-approved assay at a CLIA-certified laboratory or its
        equivalent.

        NOTE: A single RNA &quot;blip&quot; of ≤500 copies/mL is permissible if RNA levels most recent
        before and after (may include the screening HIV-1 RNA test) are below the level of
        quantification (BLQ) for the assay. If the RNA level after the blip is the screening HIV-1
        RNA test, the result must be &lt;50 copies/mL.

          -  The following laboratory values obtained within 45 days prior to study entry by any
             US laboratory that has a CLIA certification or its equivalent.

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥750/mm3

               -  Hemoglobin ≥9.0 g/dL for female subjects and ≥10.0 g/dL for male subjects

               -  Platelet count &gt;100,000/mm3

               -  Prothrombin time (PT) &lt;1.2 x upper limit normal (ULN)

               -  Partial thromboplastin time (PTT) &lt;1.5 x ULN

               -  Calculated creatinine clearance (CrCl) ≥30 mL/min, as estimated by the
                  Cockroft-Gault formula NOTE: Calculation for the Cockcroft-Gault equation is
                  available at https://www.fstrf.org/apps/cfmx/apps/common/Portal/index.cfm

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (SGOT) ≤2 x ULN.

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (SGPT) ≤2 x ULN.

               -  Alkaline phosphatase ≤2 x ULN.

               -  Total bilirubin ≤2.5 x ULN. If the subject if taking an indinavir- or
                  atazanavir-containing regimen at the time of screening, a total bilirubin of ≤5
                  x ULN is acceptable.

          -  Female study volunteers of reproductive potential (pre-menopausal women who have not
             had a sterilization procedure (eg, hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy, tubal
             ligation, or salpingectomy) must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test
             performed within 24 hours prior to study entry. Women are considered menopausal if
             they have not had a menses for at least 12 months and have a FSH (follicle
             stimulating hormone) of greater than 40 IU/L or, if FSH testing is not available,
             they have had amenorrhea for 24 consecutive months.

        If the female volunteer is not of reproductive potential (women who are menopausal,
        defined as not having had a menses for at least 12 months with an FSH of greater than 40
        IU/L, or if FSH testing is not available, have had amenorrhea for 24 consecutive months,
        or women who have undergone surgical sterilization, (eg, hysterectomy, bilateral
        oophorectomy, tubal ligation or salpingectomy)), she is eligible without requiring the use
        of a contraceptive method.  Acceptable documentation of sterilization is subject reported
        history of hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy, tubal ligation, tubal micro-insert,
        menopause, or the partner with vasectomy/azoospermia.

          -  If participating in sexual activity that could lead to pregnancy, the female study
             volunteer must be willing to use contraception while receiving protocol-specified
             medication(s) and for the washout period of 4 weeks.  At least one of the following
             methods MUST be used:

               -  Condoms (male or female), with or without a spermicidal agent

               -  Diaphragm or cervical cap with spermicide

               -  Intrauterine device (IUD)

               -  Hormone-based contraceptive

        As hormone-based contraceptives (oral, transdermal, or subdermal) can affect coagulopathy
        biomarkers, subjects who plan on using such a contraceptive during the study must be
        taking the same product for ≥4 weeks prior to screening and be encouraged to continue
        throughout the duration of the study, if medically feasible.

          -  No documented opportunistic infections within 24 weeks prior to study entry

          -  Karnofsky performance score &gt;/= 70 within 45 days prior to study entry

          -  Ability and willingness of subject or legal guardian/representative to provide
             written informed consent.

          -  Willingness to refrain from the use of aspirin or any aspirin-related product (other
             than the study drug), including NSAIDs, from time of screening visit through the end
             of the 16 week trial.

        NOTE: Acetaminophen-based products may be used before and during the trial when analgesics
        are required.

          -  Completion of the pre-entry FMD assessment NOTE:  The FMD must be performed at the
             site and confirmed as acceptable by the University of Wisconsin Atherosclerosis
             Imaging Research Program (UW AIRP) core lab prior to study entry.

          -  Confirmation of the availability of the stored pre-entry fasting specimens (plasma
             and serum); the site must confirm that these specimens have been entered into the
             Laboratory Data Management System (LDMS).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current malignancy (except non-melanoma cancer of the skin not requiring systemic
             chemotherapy or radiation therapy).

        NOTE:  Carcinoma in situ of the cervix or anus is not considered exclusionary.

          -  Prior history of malignancy if the subject is not disease free for 24 or more weeks
             prior to study entry.

          -  Current use or indication for use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs)
             or aspirin that cannot be interrupted for clinical reasons.  Examples of clinical
             reasons include, but are not limited to, known and documented cardiovascular disease
             (history of MI, coronary artery bypass graft surgery, percutaneous coronary
             intervention, stroke, transient ischemic attack, peripheral arterial disease with ABI
             &lt;0.9 or claudication).

          -  Current diagnosis of diabetes with HbA1c ≥8% within 24 weeks prior to screening.

          -  Changes in lipid-lowering or antihypertensive medication within 90 days prior to
             study entry or expected need to modify these medications during the study.

        NOTE: Lipid-lowering medication includes: statins, fibrates, niacin (dose ≥250 mg daily),
        and fish-oil/omega 3 fatty acids (dose &gt;1000 mg of marine oils daily).

          -  Known cirrhosis

          -  Known chronic active hepatitis B NOTE: Active hepatitis B is defined as hepatitis B
             surface antigen positive and hepatitis B DNA positive within 24 weeks prior to study
             entry; subjects with hepatitis B virus (HBV) DNA BLQ for greater than 24 weeks prior
             to study entry are eligible.

          -  Known chronic active hepatitis C NOTE: Active hepatitis C is defined as a detectable
             plasma HCV RNA level within 24 weeks prior to study entry; subjects with HCV RNA BLQ
             for greater than 24 weeks prior to study entry are eligible.

          -  Known inflammatory conditions, such as, but not limited to, rheumatoid arthritis
             (RA), systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), sarcoidosis, inflammatory bowel disease
             (IBD), chronic pancreatitis, autoimmune hepatitis, Adult Stills disease, Rheumatic
             heart disease, bursitis.

          -  Breastfeeding or pregnant

          -  Previous intolerance or allergy to aspirin or any aspirin products.

          -  Frequent use of aspirin or aspirin products (NSAIDs), defined as an average of 2 or
             more times per week in the last 12 weeks prior to study entry.

          -  Immunosuppressant use, such as, but not limited to, systemic or potentially systemic
             glucocorticoids (including injected, ie, intra-articular, nasal or inhaled steroids),
             azathioprine, tacrolimus, mycophenolate, sirolimus, rapamycin, methotrexate, or
             cyclosporine within 45 days prior to study entry.

          -  Use of any systemic antineoplastic or immunomodulatory treatment, investigational
             vaccines, interleukins, interferons, growth factors, or intravenous immunoglobulin
             (IVIG) within 45 days prior to study entry.

        NOTE:  Routine standard of care, including hepatitis A and/or B, human papilloma virus,
        influenza, pneumococcal, and tetanus vaccines are permitted if administered at least 7
        days before study entry and before biomarker/peripheral blood mononuclear cell (PBMC)
        blood collections.

          -  Concurrent use of prohibited medications as per section 5.4

          -  Heavy alcohol use as defined by the National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and
             Alcoholism (NIAAA)
             http://www.niaaa.nih.gov/alcohol-health/overview-alcohol-consumption/moderate-binge-drinking

          -  Alcohol or drug use or dependence that, in the opinion of the site investigator,
             would interfere with adherence to study requirements.

          -  Current use of anticoagulation therapy or conditions requiring use of anticoagulants,
             use such as, but not limited to warfarin (Coumadin), rivaroxaban (Xarelto),
             clopidogrel (Plavix), dabigatran (Pradaxa), apixaban (Eliquis), heparin, ticlopidine
             (Ticlid), Presugrel (Effient).

          -  History of coagulopathy, deep venous thrombosis, pulmonary embolism.

          -  Known active or recent (not fully resolved within 4 weeks prior to study entry)
             invasive bacterial, fungal, parasitic, or viral infections.

        NOTE: Recurrent herpes simplex virus (HSV) is not exclusionary. Subjects on antiviral
        prophylaxis for HSV or VZV are encouraged to remain on treatment for the duration of the
        study if medically feasible.

          -  Serious illness or trauma requiring systemic treatment and/or hospitalization within
             4 weeks prior to study entry.

          -  History of bleeding conditions such as peptic ulcer disease, hemophilia, von
             Willebrand disease, idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura.

          -  History of thrombotic disorders such as protein C or S deficiency.

          -  History of gastrointestinal (GI) bleeding within the past 6 months prior to study
             entry.

          -  History of intracranial hemorrhage.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Judith A Aberg, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Meagan O'Brien, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 3, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Aspirin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
