<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="23572">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02146313</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GO29213</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02146313</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study Evaluating the Safety and Pharmacokinetics of DMUC4064A in Patients With Platinum-Resistant Ovarian Cancer or Unresectable Pancreatic Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, Open-Label, Dose-Escalation Study of the Safety, Tolerability, and Pharmacokinetics of DMUC4064A Administered Intravenously to Patients With Platinum-Resistant Ovarian Cancer or Unresectable Pancreatic Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Genentech</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Genentech</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I, multicenter, open-label, dose-escalation study of DMUC4064A a dministered
      by intravenous (IV) infusion every three weeks (q3w) to cancer patie nts. The study will
      employ a traditional 3 + 3 dose escalation design to determi ne the maximum tolerated dose
      (MTD) of DMUC4064A against platinum-resistant ovar ian cancer. Once a q3w recommended phase
      II dose (RP2D) is identified, two expan sion cohorts (one in platinum-resistant ovarian
      cancer and another in unresectab le pancreatic cancer) may be evaluated to further
      characterize the safety and ac tivity in these patient populations. Time on treatment is
      expected to last appro ximately 1 year.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 to 21</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response according to response evaluation criteria in solid tumors (RECIST)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of objective response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of anti-DMUC4064A antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the concentration curve (AUC) of DMUC4064A</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer, Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose-escalation cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose-expansion cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DMCU4064A</intervention_name>
    <description>Escalating doses given by intravenous infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose-escalation cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DMUC4064A</intervention_name>
    <description>Recommended Phase II dose given by intravenous infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose-expansion cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt;/= 18 years

          -  Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks

          -  ECOG Performance Status of 0 or 1

          -  Measurable disease is defined as at least one bi-dimensionally measurable non-lymph
             node lesion &gt;/= 1 cm on long access diameter on CT or MRI scan OR at least one
             bi-dimensionally measureable lymph node measuring &gt;/= 1.5 cm on short access diameter
             on CT or MRI scan

          -  Adequate hematologic, liver, and renal function

          -  Highly effective contraception as defined by the protocol

        Patients with Ovarian Cancer

          -  Histological documentation of epithelial ovarian cancer, primary peritoneal cancer,
             or fallopian tube cancer.

          -  Documented MUC16 expression (by CA125 or IHC)

          -  Disease that has progressed or relapsed during or within 6 months after the most
             recent treatment with a platinum-containing chemotherapy regimen.

          -  Progression or relapse from prior platinum-based chemotherapy must be documented
             radiographically by RECISTv1.1 criteria

        For ovarian cancer dose expansion cohorts only:

          -  Not more than two prior chemotherapy regimens for the treatment of platinum-resistant
             ovarian cancer

          -  Archival or fresh tumor tissue demonstrating MUC16 expression by central review (by
             IHC)

        Patients with Pancreatic Cancer

          -  Histologic documentation of incurable, locally advanced, or metastatic pancreatic
             ductal adenocarcinoma consisting of unresectable pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma
             (i.e., patients who are not considered eligible for surgical resection with curative
             intent), including recurrence of previously resected disease.

          -  Documented MUC16 expression

          -  Patients for whom no further standard of care therapy exists, must have received
             standard of care chemotherapy in the adjuvant or advanced/metastatic setting

          -  No more than two prior chemotherapy regimens administered for the treatment of
             pancreatic cancer in the adjuvant or advanced/metastatic setting

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Anti-tumor therapy, including chemotherapy, biologic, experimental, or hormonal
             therapy within 4 weeks prior to Day 1

          -  Prior treatment with MUC16 targeted therapy (e.g., oregovomab [OvaRex] or abagovomab)
             including DMUC5754A or with an MMAE-containing ADC

          -  Palliative radiation to bone metastases within 2 weeks prior to Day 1

          -  Prior radiation to lung fields

          -  Major surgical procedure within 4 weeks prior to Day 1

          -  Known active bacterial, viral, fungal, mycobacterial, parasitic, or other infection
             (including HIV and atypical mycobacterial disease but excluding fungal infections of
             the nail beds) at study enrollment or any major episode of infection requiring
             treatment with IV antibiotics or hospitalization (relating to the completion of the
             course of antibiotics) within 4 weeks prior to Cycle 1, Day 1

          -  Evidence of significant uncontrolled concomitant diseases, such as cardiovascular
             disease; nervous system, renal, hepatic, endocrine, or gastrointestinal disorders;
             autoimmune disease, or a serious non-healing wound or fracture

          -  Clinically significant pulmonary symptoms and signs, any active pulmonary or
             respiratory infection at enrollment, pulmonary infiltrates on screening CT scan of
             the chest that are associated with symptoms (including dyspnea), resting or exercise
             SpO2 &lt; 90%, requirement for supplementary oxygen at rest or exercise (either
             continuously or intermittently), moderate (40% - 60% predicted) or severe (&lt; 40%
             predicted) decreased DLCO or mild (&gt; 60% &lt;/= LLN % predicted) decrease with
             clinically significant symptoms)

          -  Clinically significant history of liver disease, including viral or other hepatitis,
             current alcohol abuse, or cirrhosis

          -  Other malignancy within the last 5 years, except for adequately treated carcinoma in
             situ of the cervix, squamous carcinoma of the skin, adequately controlled limited
             basal cell skin cancer, or synchronous primary endometrial cancer or prior primary
             endometrial cancer if protocol criteria are met

          -  Untreated or active central nervous system (CNS) metastases. Patients with a history
             of treated CNS metastases may be eligible

          -  Current Grade &gt; 1 toxicity (except alopecia and anorexia) from prior therapy or Grade
             &gt; 1 neuropathy from any cause

          -  History of severe allergic or anaphylactic reactions to monoclonal antibody therapy
             (or recombinant antibody-related fusion proteins)

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding

          -  Any other diseases, metabolic dysfunction, physical examination finding, or clinical
             laboratory finding giving reasonable suspicion of a disease or condition that
             contraindicates the use of an investigational drug or that may affect the
             interpretation of the results or render the patient at high risk from treatment
             complications
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Hoffmann-La Roche</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Reference Study ID Number: GO29213 www.roche.com/about_roche/roche_worldwide.htm</last_name>
    <phone>888-662-6728 (U.S. Only)</phone>
    <email>global.rochegenentechtrials@roche.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 21, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
