<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="13301">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01925807</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHAMO_SI_Group_001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01925807</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brief Group Intervention for Adolescents With Mild to Moderate Suicidal Ideation and Their Caregivers: Preliminary Investigation for a Novel Treatment Approach</brief_title>
  <official_title>Brief Group Intervention for Adolescents With Mild to Moderate Suicidal Ideation and Their Caregivers: Preliminary Investigation for a Novel Treatment Approach</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Allison Kennedy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mach Gaensslen Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AHSC AFP Innovation Fund</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Suicide is the second leading cause of mortality for Canadian adolescents.  Mental health
      complaints are one of the leading reasons for an emergency department visit at the
      Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario and 60% of adolescents report suicidal ideation.  The
      goal of the present investigation is to test the efficacy of a brief group intervention for
      adolescents with passive suicidal ideation and their caregivers that will focus on coping,
      familial support, and emotional regulation. The investigators hypothesize that a brief group
      intervention, delivered in the weeks following presentation at the emergency department,
      will reduce suicidal ideation and improve coping and familial support more than treatment as
      usual.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Suicidal Ideation</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Suicidal ideation will be measured using the Suicidal Ideation Questionnaire Junior (SIQ-JR; Reynolds, 1988).  The intervention and treatment as usual groups will be compared at initial assessment to determine group equivalence post randomization through the appropriate parametric or non-parametric tests.   Repeated Measures ANOVA or ANCOVA will be used to compare differences in suicidal ideation between the two groups as well as within groups (pre-post changes).  Further comparisons using clinical cut-off will be conducted via McNemar test for matched pairs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Familial Support</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Familial support will be measured using questionnaires for both caregivers and youth.  Youth will respond to the Family Environment Scale (Koren, DeChillo, &amp; Friesen, 1992) and the  Inventory of Parent and Peer Attachment (Armsden &amp; Greenberg, 1987).  Caregivers will respond to the Family Environment Scale and and Relationship Scale Questionnaire (Griffine &amp; Gartholomew, 1994). The intervention and treatment as usual groups will be compared at initial assessment to determine group equivalence post randomization through the appropriate parametric or non-parametric tests. Repeated Measures ANOVA or ANCOVA will be used to compare differences between the two groups as well as within groups (pre-post changes).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Coping Strategies</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Youth coping strategies will be measured using the Youth Stress and Coping Questionnaire (Cloutier et al., 2008).  The intervention and treatment as usual groups will be compared at initial assessment to determine group equivalence post randomization through the appropriate parametric or non-parametric tests. Repeated Measures ANOVA or ANCOVA will be used to compare differences between the two groups as well as within groups (pre-post changes).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Youth depression will be measured using the Children's Depression Inventory-2 Self report (CDI-2; Kovaks, 2010).
The intervention and treatment as usual groups will be compared at initial assessment to determine group equivalence post randomization through the appropriate parametric or non-parametric tests. Repeated Measures ANOVA or ANCOVA will be used to compare differences between the two groups as well as within groups (pre-post changes).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Youth anxiety symptoms will be measured using the Multidimensional Anxiety Scale for Children (MASC-2; March, 1997).
The intervention and treatment as usual groups will be compared at initial assessment to determine group equivalence post randomization through the appropriate parametric or non-parametric tests. Repeated Measures ANOVA or ANCOVA will be used to compare differences between the two groups as well as within groups (pre-post changes).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Suicidal Ideation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention will consist of 6 psycho-educational group sessions for caregivers and 6 psycho-educational group sessions for adolescents.  Adolescent and caregiver sessions will be held separately and will focus on different issues.  For adolescents, the group sessions will focus on coping strategies and emotional regulation.  For caregivers, the group sessions will be focused on attachment, family environment, and validation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment As Usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive normal services offered to adolescents that present to the emergency department with mild to moderate suicidal ideation and moderate psychopathological symptoms.  This includes an  interview with a crisis intervention worker, risk assessment and safety planning, and consultation about community services.  In addition, participants will meet with one of our clinicians to confirm a safety plan is in place, and to fill out questionnaires at the beginning and end of the 6-week study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Group Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention will consist of 6 psycho-educational group sessions for caregivers and 6 psycho-educational group sessions for adolescents. Adolescent and caregiver sessions will be held separately and will focus on different issues. For adolescents, the group sessions will focus on coping strategies and emotional regulation. For caregivers, the group sessions will be focused on attachment, family environment, and validation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment as usual</intervention_name>
    <description>This group will receive normal services offered to adolescents that present to the emergency department with mild to moderate suicidal ideation and moderate psychopathological symptoms. This includes an interview with a crisis intervention worker, risk assessment and safety planning, and consultation about community services. In addition, participants will meet with one of our clinicians to confirm a safety plan is in place, and to fill out questionnaires at the beginning and end of the 6-week study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment As Usual</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  mild to moderate suicidal ideation

          -  presented to the emergency department with a mental health concern

          -  one or two caregiver(s) committed to attending the majority of sessions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  psychosis

          -  schizophrenia

          -  dual diagnosis

          -  developmental disability or delay

          -  major substance abuse

          -  currently receiving mental health services

          -  recent change to psychotropic medication regimen

          -  inability to commit to majority of sessions

          -  children's aid society involvement

          -  inability of at least one caregiver to commit to attending the majority of sessions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Allison Kennedy, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paula Cloutier, MA</last_name>
    <phone>6137377600</phone>
    <phone_ext>3672</phone_ext>
    <email>cloutier@cheo.on.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Allison Kennedy, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>6137377600</phone>
    <phone_ext>2217</phone_ext>
    <email>akennedy@cheo.on.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1H8L1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Allison Kennedy, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diamond GS, Wintersteen MB, Brown GK, Diamond GM, Gallop R, Shelef K, Levy S. Attachment-based family therapy for adolescents with suicidal ideation: a randomized controlled trial. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2010 Feb;49(2):122-31.</citation>
    <PMID>20215934</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rathus JH, Miller AL. Dialectical behavior therapy adapted for suicidal adolescents. Suicide Life Threat Behav. 2002 Summer;32(2):146-57.</citation>
    <PMID>12079031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Armsden, G. C., and Greenberg, M. T. (1987). The Inventory of Parent and Peer Attachment: Relationships to well-being in adolescence. Journal of Youth and Adolescence,16 (5), 427-454.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Allison Kennedy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Psychologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adolescent</keyword>
  <keyword>Suicidal Ideation</keyword>
  <keyword>Emergency Department</keyword>
  <keyword>Crisis</keyword>
  <keyword>Attachment</keyword>
  <keyword>Coping</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Suicidal Ideation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
