<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="33285">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01671319</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CO10104</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01671319</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose Dense TC + Pegfilgrastim Support for Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>ddTC</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Dose-Dense TC (Docetaxel + Cyclophosphamide) With Pegfilgrastim Support for Adjuvant Therapy of pN0, pN1 or Nx Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Madison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Wisconsin, Madison</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the feasibility of giving standard TC chemotherapy
      on a dose dense schedule (ddTC) as well as evaluating the nature and frequency of ddTC side
      effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A standard chemotherapy treatment option for breast cancer after surgery (adjuvant therapy)
      is docetaxel + cyclophosphamide (TC).  This study looks at a different schedule for giving
      the same adjuvant chemotherapy so that treatment can be completed faster (in 8 weeks rather
      than 12 weeks).  This study uses a growth factor drug, pegfilgrastim, to help build blood
      cells that are lowered because of chemotherapy, making it possible to receive TC treatment
      every 2 weeks (referred to as &quot;dose dense TC&quot; or &quot;ddTC&quot;) instead of the standard 3 week
      schedule.  The main study procedures are blood draws, chemotherapy treatment, physical
      exams, and pegfilgrastim injections.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability and Feasibility for dose dense schedule</measure>
    <time_frame>4 cycles each 2 weeks in length for a total of 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate the tolerability and feasibility of delivering 4 cycles (1 cycle = 2 weeks) of docetaxel and cyclophosphamide (TC) on a dose-dense (q2week) schedule with pegfilgrastim support. This regimen will be referred to as dose-dense (dd)TC.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">41</enrollment>
  <condition>Female Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>dose dense TC + pegfilgrastim</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Docetaxel + Cyclophosphamide chemotherapy given every 2 weeks x 4 cycles plus pegfilgrastim given 24-48 hours post day 1 of each cycle</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>docetaxel + cyclophosphamide + pegfilgrastim</intervention_name>
    <description>docetaxel 75 mg/m2 + cyclophosphamide 600 mg/m2 IV every 2 weeks x 4 cycles plus pegfilgrastim 6mg sq 24-48 hours post day 1 of each cycle</description>
    <arm_group_label>dose dense TC + pegfilgrastim</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Taxotere, Cytoxan, Neulasta</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  histologically confirmed invasive carcinoma of the female breast, status post
             definitive surgery (lumpectomy or mastectomy plus nodal evaluation if feasible).
             Patients must initiate therapy with ddTC within 84 days of the last breast or
             axillary surgery performed for curative intent

          -  candidate for chemotherapy by the treating oncologist

          -  Patients with pN2 or pN3 disease are NOT explicitly excluded. However, patients with
             N2 or N3 disease MUST be reviewed with the PI or study chair before being enrolled on
             the study as TC would not normally be considered adequate therapy for such patients.

          -  Patients with bilateral, synchronous invasive breast cancer are eligible as long as
             both primary tumors meet the eligibility criteria.

          -  Patients with estrogen-receptor (ER) and/or progesterone receptor (PR) negative,
             positive, or unknown tumors are eligible.

          -  Patients with HER2 positive, negative or unknown disease are eligible for this trial.
             Patients whose tumors are HER2 positive by either immunohistochemistry (IHC) 3+
             staining or demonstrate gene amplification by FISH should receive trastuzumab,
             following completion of adjuvant cytotoxic therapy with 4 cycles of ddTC.

          -  There must be negative surgical margins for invasive cancer and DCIS. LCIS is
             acceptable at the margin.

          -  Patients with multi-centric breast cancer are eligible as long as all known disease
             is resected from the breast with negative margins.

          -  Age &gt;18 years.

          -  ECOG performance status ≤ 1

          -  Women of childbearing potential should have a negative urine or blood beta-HCG, and
             must agree to contraception if engaging in sexual activity. Should a woman become
             pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while participating in this study, she should
             inform her treating physician immediately. Women must not be pregnant or nursing as
             the chemotherapy drugs used in this study may cause harm to a fetus or newborn.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
             document.

          -  Platelets &gt;/=100,000/μl within 4 weeks of registration.

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;/= 1,500/μl within 4 weeks of registration.

          -  Total bilirubin within normal institutional limits within 4 weeks of registration.

          -  Alkaline phosphatase (alk phos) ≤ 2.5 X institutional Upper Limit of Normal (ULN)
             within 4 weeks of registration.

          -  AST (SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) ≤ 1.5X ULN

          -  Creatinine within normal institutional limits OR Creatinine clearance&gt;/= 60
             mL/min/1.73 m2 for patients with creatinine levels above normal

          -  If patient has received tamoxifen or another selective estrogen receptor modulator
             (SERM) for prevention or for other indications (not for treatment of this cancer),
             they have been discontinued prior to enrollment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient has received previous trastuzumab, chemotherapy, hormonal therapy, or other
             anti-cancer agents (including investigational agents) for this malignancy.

          -  Patient will be receiving GNRH agonists such as goserelin (Zoladex) or leuprolide
             acetate (Lupron) concomitantly with chemotherapy for the purpose of preventing breast
             cancer recurrence.

          -  Patient has inflammatory breast cancer (pT4d) or metastatic breast cancer.

          -  Patient has uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing
             or active infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris,
             cardiac arrhythmia or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit
             compliance with study requirements.

          -  Patient has pre-existing persistent neuropathy.

          -  The patient has received prior chemotherapy or radiotherapy or any malignancy within
             the past 2 years.

          -  Patient has received prior docetaxel or cyclophosphamide within the past 5 years.

          -  Patient has known contraindication or hypersensitivity to docetaxel, cyclophosphamide
             or pegfilgrastim.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amye J Tevaarwerk, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin Carbone Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53792</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 2, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 5, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>female</keyword>
  <keyword>women</keyword>
  <keyword>adjuvant</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
