<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="104028">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01687361</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-A00449-34</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-04</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01687361</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Can Branched Chain Amino Acids Supplementation Reduce Muscle Damage Induced by Neuromuscular Electrical Stimulation? A Combined Functional and Metabolic Non-invasive Investigation in Healthy Humans</brief_title>
  <official_title>Can Branched Chain Amino Acids Supplementation Reduce Muscle Damage Induced by Neuromuscular Electrical Stimulation ? A Combined Functional and Metabolic Non-invasive Investigation in Healthy Humans.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique Hopitaux De Marseille</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique Hopitaux De Marseille</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Afssaps - Agence française de sécurité sanitaire des produits de santé (Saint-Denis)</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Neuromuscular electrical stimulation (NMES) is commonly used in rehabilitation contexts in
      order to increase or restore muscle capacities of hypoactive patients or patients with
      articular trauma. Although this technique seems to be particularly adapted to muscle
      rehabilitation, growing evidence is emerging regarding potential damaging effects of
      electrically- induced isometric contractions in healthy humans. Recent studies have reported
      a 10 to 30-fold increase in creatine kinase (CK) activity coupled to significantly increased
      muscle soreness and impaired force production as a result of NMESs. On that basis, further
      studies should be conducted on these deleterious effects which might limit the clinical
      application of NMES.

      Over the last decade, many studies paid attention to branched-chain amino acids (BCAA)
      supplementation as a potential prophylactic/therapeutic approach. The rationale of this
      approach is that BCAA might increase protein synthesis and reduce protein breakdown through
      physiological mechanisms involving mTOR regulation pathway (mammalian Target of Rapamycin).
      Additionally, BCAA could also be used as energetic substrate during exercise when glycogen
      stores are depleted. Overall, previous results have supported the efficacy of BCAA
      supplementation in attenuating muscle damage. Nevertheless, comprehensive studies
      investigating the effect of amino acid supplementation on markers of muscle damage are still
      scarce.

      Magnetic resonance imaging (IRM) and phosphorus 31 magnetic resonance spectroscopy (31P-MRS)
      are powerful non invasive tools allowing the exploration of skeletal muscle structure and
      energy metabolism.

      This ambitious project is devoted to the anatomical, functional and metabolic
      characterization of BCAA supplementation after NMES using MRI and 31P-MRS. Various markers
      of muscle damage, including maximal voluntary force production, T2 values and apparent
      diffusion coefficient (obtained by MRI) and energy metabolism assessed at rest and during
      exercise (using 31P-MRS), will be obtained before and after NMES. This project is of utmost
      importance for improving our knowledge of anatomic, metabolic and functional events related
      to BCAA supplementation in the context of exercise-induced muscle damage
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>evaluation of the muscular responsiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>24 MONTHS</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>evaluation of the effects of a supplementation in AAB</measure>
    <time_frame>24 MONTTHS</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>on the physiological aspects</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuromuscular Electrical Stimulation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>branched-chain amino acids (BCAA) supplementation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PLACEBO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>branched-chain amino acids (BCAA) supplementation</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>branched-chain amino acids (BCAA) supplementation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PLACEBO</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>PLACEBO</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male

          -  Between 18 and 35 years

          -  Subjects will have to be unhurt:

               -  Any general disease

               -  Psychiatric disorders(confusions)

               -  Any infectious, inflammatory, tumoral, vascular, degenerative or traumatic
                  pathology

          -  They will have to follow no chronic treatment

          -  They will have to be unhurt of any history of alcoholism or drug addiction

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Contraindications for an examination MRI

          -  Suffering from claustrophobia

          -  Having stimulating one cardiac, carriers of a system Holter, carriers of hook(staple)
             (clip) surgical metallic, carriers of a prosthesis or a metallic implant (or quite
             other metallic foreign bodies), carriers of a prosthesis dental (device), carriers of
             a hearing aid, carriers of an insulin pump

          -  Having been hurt by pieces of shrapnel or lead

          -  Having had a dislocation, a fracture or a recent surgical operation (less than 6
             months before the inclusion)

          -  Having followed a treatment with anti-inflammatory drugs during the last 3 months

          -  Having followed a treatment with amino acids during the last 3 months

          -  Having followed a treatment(processing) with anabolic steroids during the last 3
             months

          -  Having participated in a program of body-building of lower limbs during the last 6
             months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>BERNARD BELAIGUES</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique hôpitaux de Marseille</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>jean pierre mattei</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>AP HM</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>JEAN PIERRE MATTEI</last_name>
    <email>jean-pierre.mattei@univ-amu.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assistance Publique Hopitaux de Marseille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <zip>13354</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>jean pierre mattei</last_name>
      <email>jpmattei@ap-hm.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 28, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 20, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
