<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="92291">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01729754</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3222-011</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P07771</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01729754</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety/Tolerability of Subcutaneous SCH 900222/MK-3222 in Participants With Moderate-to-Severe Chronic Plaque Psoriasis (P07771/MK-3222-011)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A 52-Week, Phase 3, Randomized, Active Comparator and Placebo-Controlled, Parallel Design Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety/Tolerability of Subcutaneous SCH 9000222/MK-3222, Followed by an Optional Long-Term Safety Extension Study, in Subjects With Moderate-to-Severe Chronic Plaque Psoriasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being conducted to evaluate the efficacy and safety/tolerability of SCH
      900222/MK-3222 in a population of participants with moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The base study consists of a screening phase of up to 4 weeks followed by a treatment period
      of 52 weeks, and a 20-week follow-up period. The base study is divided into 3 sequential
      parts.

      In Part 1 of the base study (Week 0 to Week 12), participants will be randomized to one of 4
      study arms (Arm A: MK-3222 200 mg + matching placebo to etanercept; Arm B: MK-3222 100 mg +
      matching placebo to etanercept; Arm C: Matching placebo to MK-3222 + matching placebo to
      etanercept; Arm D: Matching placebo to MK-3222 + etanercept 50 mg).

      In Part 2 of the base study (Week 12 to Week 28), participants in Arm A and Arm B will
      receive matching placebo to MK-3222 to maintain blinding at Week 12 and will receive either
      MK-3222 200 mg (Arm A) or MK-3222 100 mg (Arm B) at Week 16. Participants in Arm A and Arm B
      will also receive matching placebo to etanercept once weekly through study Week 28. At study
      Week 12, Arm C participants will be re-randomized to receive their first dose of MK-3222 200
      mg or MK-3222 100 mg, and will receive additional doses of study medication according to
      their re-randomized treatment assignment at Week 16. Participants in Arm C will also receive
      matching placebo to etanercept through treatment Week 28. Participants in Arm D will
      continue with once weekly doses of etanercept through study Week 28 in combination with
      matching placebo to MK-3222.

      In Part 3 of the base study (Week 28 to Week 52), participants in Arm A with &gt;= PASI-75
      response at Week 28 will be re-randomized to either continue MK-3222 200 mg or receive
      MK-3222 100 mg at study Weeks 28, 40, and 52. Participants with &gt;= Psoriasis Area
      Sensitivity Index of 50% (PASI-50) response but &lt; PASI 75% (PASI-75) response will continue
      to receive MK-3222 200 mg every 12 weeks and those participants with &lt; PASI-50 response will
      be discontinued from the study. Participants in Arm B with &gt;= PASI-75 response at Week 28
      will continue to receive MK-3222 100 mg every 12 weeks. Those with &gt;= PASI-50 response but &lt;
      PASI-75 response will be re-randomized to receive continued MK-3222 100 mg or MK-3222 200 mg
      every 12 weeks. Participants in Arm B with &lt; PASI-50 response will be discontinued from the
      study. Participants in Arm C will continue to receive treatment every 12 weeks according to
      their re-randomized treatment assignment. Participants in Arm D that achieve &gt;= PASI-75
      response at Week 28 will be discontinued from the study. Those participants with &lt; PASI-75
      response at Week 28 will be crossed over to MK-3222 200 mg to receive doses at Week 32, Week
      36, and Week 48.

      Eligible participants that choose to enroll in the extension study will have an additional
      treatment period of up to 192 weeks and will be followed for an additional 20 weeks in the
      follow-up period. Each participant will receive MK-3222 200 mg or MK-3222 100 mg every 12
      weeks up to study Week 244 according to their treatment assignment at the conclusion of Part
      3 of the base study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Participants Achieving a Psoriasis Area Sensitivity Index 75% (PASI-75) Response at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Participants With a Physician's Global Assessment (PGA) Score of Clear or Minimal With at Least a 2 Grade Reduction From Baseline at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Experiencing an Adverse Event (AE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 264</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Discontinuing Study Treatment Due to an AE</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 264</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Experiencing an AE Up to Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Discontinuing Study Treatment due to an AE Up to Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Participants Achieving a PASI-75 Response at Week 28</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Participants With a PGA Score of Clear or Minimal With at Least a 2 Grade Reduction From Baseline at Week 28</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Participants Achieving a PASI-90 Response at Week 12 and Week 28</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12, Week 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Participants Achieving a PASI-100 Response at Week 12 and Week 28</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12, Week 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change From Baseline in the Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI) at Week 12 and Week 28</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12. Week 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Participants With a DLQI Score of 0 or 1 at Week 12 and Week 28</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12, Week 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change and Mean Percent Change From Baseline in PASI Score Over Time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change From Baseline in the Nail Psoriasis Severity Index (NAPSI) at Week 12 and Week 28</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12, Week 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1050</enrollment>
  <condition>Plaque Psoriasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 200 mg + Etanercept Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK 200 mg subcutaneously on Weeks 0, 4, 16, and 28 and, optionally, every 12 weeks thereafter until Week 220, plus etanercept placebo twice weekly up to Week 28</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 100 mg + Etanercept Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK 100 mg subcutaneously on Weeks 0, 4, 16, and 28 and, optionally, every 12 weeks thereafter until Week 220, plus etanercept placebo twice weekly up to Week 28</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 Placebo + Etanercept Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching placebo to MK-3222 subcutaneously on Weeks 0 and 4 plus etanercept placebo twice weekly up to Week 28. Participants will be re-randomized 1:1 at Week 12 to receive MK 200 mg or MK 100 mg on Weeks 12, 16, and 28  and, optionally, every 12 weeks thereafter until Week 220.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 Placebo + Etanercept 50 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching placebo to MK-3222 subcutaneously on Weeks 0 and 4 and etandercept 50 mg twice weekly up to Week 12 and then once weekly up to Week 28.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-3222 200 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>MK-3222 200 mg administered SC.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 200 mg + Etanercept Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SCH 900222</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-3222 100 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>MK-3222 100 mg administered SC.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 100 mg + Etanercept Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SCH 900222</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-3222 Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo to MK-3222 administered SC.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 Placebo + Etanercept Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 Placebo + Etanercept 50 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etanercept Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo to etanercept administered SC.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 200 mg + Etanercept Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 100 mg + Etanercept Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 Placebo + Etanercept Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etanercept 50 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Etanercept 50 mg administered SC.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3222 Placebo + Etanercept 50 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Embrel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis for at least 6 months prior
             to enrollment;

          -  Candidate for phototherapy or systemic therapy;

          -  Premenopausal female participants must agree to abstain from heterosexual activity or
             use a medically approved method of contraception or use appropriate effective
             contraception as per local regulations or guidelines

          -  For the extension study: must have completed Part 3 of the base study

          -  For the extension study: must have achieved at least a PASI-50 response by the end of
             Part 3 of the base study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-plaque forms of psoriasis

          -  Presence or history of severe psoriatic arthritis and is well-controlled on current
             treatment regimen

          -  Women of childbearing potential that are pregnant, intend to become pregnant, or are
             lactating

          -  Participant is expected to require topical therapy, phototherapy, or systemic therapy

          -  Presence of any infection or history of recurrent infection requiring treatment with
             systemic antibiotics

          -  Previous use of MK-3222/SCH 900222, or other interleukin-23 (IL-23)/T- helper cell 17
             (Th-17) pathway inhibitors including P40, P19, and IL-17 antagonists, or etanercept

          -  Latex allergy or sensitivity

          -  Active or untreated latent tuberculosis (TB)

          -  For the extension study: women of child-bearing potential that are pregnant, intend
             to become pregnant within 6 months of completing the trial, or that are breast
             feeding

          -  For the extension study: active or uncontrolled significant organ dysfunction or
             clinically significant laboratory abnormalities

          -  For the extension study: expected to require topical treatment, phototherapy, or
             systemic treatment during the extension study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Austria</country>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Czech Republic</country>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Hungary</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 13, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>TNFR-Fc fusion protein</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
