<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="79012">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02014246</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999903329</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>03-AG-N329</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02014246</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genetic Characterization of Movement Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Genetic Characterization of Movement Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - There are two basic types of movement disorders. Some cause excessive movement, some cause
      slowness or lack of movement. Some of these are caused by mutations in genes. Researchers
      want to study the genes of families with a history of movement disorders. They hope to find
      a genetic cause of the disorders. This can help them better understand and treat the
      diseases. This study will not be limited to a particular disorder, but will study all
      movement disorders in general.

      Objectives:

      - To learn more about movement disorders, their causes, and treatments.

      Eligibility:

        -  Adults and children with a movement disorder and their family members.

        -  Healthy volunteers.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with medical history and blood tests. Some will have
           physical exam.

        -  Participants will give a blood sample by a needle in the arm. This can be done at the
           clinic, by their own doctor, or at home.

        -  Participants can volunteer to have their blood sample sent for long-term study. Genetic
           test will be done on the samples. Participants    identity will be kept separate from
           the sample. Participants can request to receive results of the tests.

        -  Participants    samples will be in the study for 5   10 years. Some participants will
           have long-term follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Movement disorders describe a group of neurological disorders that involve motor and
      movement systems. They can be classified into two basic categories: those characterized by
      disordered or excessive movement (&quot;hyperkinesia&quot; or &quot;dyskinesia&quot;), and those characterized
      by slowness, or a lack of movement (&quot;hypokinesia,&quot;    bradykinesia,&quot; or &quot;akinesia&quot;)1.
      Movement disorders are the broad category of Neurologic diseases that include; ALS, ataxia,
      Corticobasal Degeneration, Dystonia, Essential Tremor, Hereditary Spastic Paraplegia,
      Huntington   s Disease, Multiple System Atrophy, Myoclonus, Parkinson   s Disease,
      Progressive Supranuclear Palsy, Restless Legs Syndrome, Rett Syndrome, Tourette Syndrome,
      Wilson   s Disease, Inclusion body Myositis, and as yet undefined movement disorders. We
      propose to undertake a study aimed at further characterizing the genetic basis of movement
      disorders.

      Several disease-causing mutations have been identified that are known to cause movement
      disorders, for example the spinocerebellar ataxia mutations, and mutations in
      alpha-synuclein, parkin, Tau, and torsinA genes. However there are numerous familial forms
      of movement disorders in which the gene defect has not been identified. The first aim of
      this protocol is to collect families with a history of movement disorder in an attempt to
      clone the causative gene. Our experience with the cloning of the Amyloid Precursor Protein
      mutations in Alzheimer   s disease shows that this approach leads to a better understanding
      of the biochemical and physiological processes underlying the disease. By intentionally
      defining the diseases of interest as movement disorders rather than proposing to study a
      particular disease (eg dystonia) we are not limiting the proposed study to what is clearly
      one facet of myriad related disorders. For example dopa-responsive dystonia is known to
      present with a widely varying phenotype, Parkinson   s disease in some, dystonia in others;
      additionally we have shown pure phenotypes of both ataxia or parkinsonism in different
      pedigrees with the same SCA mutations. Limiting ourselves to a specific diagnosis of pure
      Parkinson   s disease for example, would not allow us to make this distinction.

      It is clear there are numerous forms of movement disorders where disease does not appear to
      be inherited in a Mendelian manner. Whilst these may be caused by environmental effects it
      is also reasonable to hypothesize that disease may be caused by complex genetic
      interactions. Furthermore the susceptibility to environmental influence may be affected by
      genetic predisposition. As a second aim in this protocol we will investigate the association
      between genetic polymorphisms and movement disorders. This will be performed by a candidate
      gene approach, assessing the contribution of genes already associated with familial forms of
      disease and likely candidates (for example involved in dopaminergic pathway). Although
      significant association does not imply a causal relationship between the presence of the
      variant and disease, the pathophysiologic significance should be studied further. The
      inevitable problem of false positives within this type of analysis is a real one, which may
      be addressed by independent replications and tightly controlled experiments. Undeniably the
      analytical effort needed to differentiate positives from false positives is considerable,
      and as can be readily seen in other disorders such as Alzheimer   s disease, the literature
      is scattered with positive associations and subsequent refutations. However, it is important
      that research groups continue to identify and replicate these studies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify and characterize genetic contributions to etiology for DNA and lymphoblastoid cell line preparation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>Ataxia</condition>
  <condition>Dystonia</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Previous diagnosis of Movement Disorder by neurologist, other medical care provider, or
        researcher accompainied by sufficient clinical and/or laboratory evidence.

        Clinical confirmation of Movement Disorder by investigator and his associates either by
        exam and/or review of medical records.

        Family member of diagnosed movement disorder patient.

        Healthy controls

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Individuals with any movement disorder secondary to a specific environmental exposure,
        birth injury, metabolic disorder, or brain infection such as encephalitis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew Singleton, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cynthia D Crews</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-3826</phone>
    <email>cc100h@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Andrew Singleton, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-6079</phone>
    <email>singleta@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Aging, Clinical Research Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>NIA Studies Recruitment</last_name>
      <phone>410-350-3941</phone>
      <email>niastudiesrecruitment@mail.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Familial</keyword>
  <keyword>Ataxia</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinsonism</keyword>
  <keyword>Dystonia</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ataxia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dystonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dystonic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Movement Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
