<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="23259">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01747213</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130034</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-AG-0034</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01747213</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bisnorcymserine in Healthy Adult Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Ascending, Single-Dose, Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetic Study of Bisnorcymserine (BNC), a Highly Selective Inhibitor of Butyrylcholinesterase, in Healthy Adult Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Alzheimer   s disease (AD) is a brain disease that impairs memory, cognitive abilities and
      the ability to function independently. It is the most common cause of dementia in older
      people. It is caused by abnormal proteins in the brain that affect how neurons communicate
      with each other. Researchers are looking for drugs that can slow down the disease or treat
      its symptoms. One drug, called bisnorcymserine (BNC), may help improve brain function and
      symptoms in people with AD. BNC is designed to block a chemical that affects how neurons
      communicate with each other. Researchers want to see how BNC works in healthy older
      volunteers.

      Objectives:

      - To look at how the body processes bisnorcymserine taken by mouth and how safe it is for
      healthy older volunteers.

      Eligibility:

      - Healthy volunteers at least 55 years of age.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam, medical history, and blood and
           urine tests.

        -  Within 3 weeks from the screening visit, participants will come to the National
           Institute on Aging clinical unit for a 2-night stay. On the morning of the second day,
           they will take either a BNC capsule or a placebo. They will not know which tablet they
           are taking.

        -  Blood samples will be collected frequently throughout the second and third days of the
           study visit. The last blood sample will be collected about 32 hours after taking the
           study capsule. Participants will have heart function tests and other exams during the
           visit. Once the tests are done, they will leave the clinical center.

        -  Participants will have a final follow-up visit about 1 week after leaving the clinical
           center.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Alzheimer   s disease (AD) is an irreversible, progressive brain disease that slowly impairs
      memory and other cognitive abilities, as well as behavior and the ability to carry out
      tasks. It is the most common cause of dementia among older people. Alzheimer   s disease is
      caused by deposits of abnormal proteins throughout the brain, causing neurons to lose their
      ability to communicate with each other effectively, and eventually die. Communication
      between neurons uses chemicals called neurotransmitters that are secreted from one neuron to
      another across a synapse. Acetylcholine (Ach) is one of the most important
      neurotransmitters. Damage to the Ach (-producing) system in the brain is associated with the
      cognitive and functional deficits in Alzheimer's disease. Restoring this deficit in the
      cholinergic system is one approach to treat the symptoms of Alzheimer's disease. The action
      of Ach in brain is stopped/ blocked mainly by two brain enzymes called cholinesterases
      (ChEs): acetylcholinesterase (AChE) and butyrylcholinesterase (BChE). Inhibitors of these
      enzymes therefore augment the activity of surviving Ach neurons in AD. All ChEs currently
      approved for the treatment of AD mainly inhibit AChE and, secondarily and to a varying
      extent, BChE activities. Nevertheless, BChE remains a viable target in AD and potent,
      reversible and brain-targeted BChE inhibitors have been developed (as a class of drugs
      called cymserine analogs). Scientists at the NIA/NIH have developed a novel BChE inhibitor
      called Bisnorcymserine (BNC). Pre-clinical evidence suggest that BNC may be a safe treatment
      for Alzheimer   s disease. Based on this, we propose this first-in-human study to evaluate
      the safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetics of single doses of BNC tartrate administered
      orally to healthy volunteers aged 55 years and older using a double-blind placebo-controlled
      design. The proposed doses are: 20mg, 40mg, 80mg, 160mg, 270mg and 380mg given as a single
      oral dose. Each dose will be tested in groups of 8 subjects. Six subjects in each cohort
      will receive active drug and two will receive placebo. Subjects will be kept in the unit and
      followed clinically and with laboratory tests for adverse effects for 32 hours; they will
      return for a follow-up visit to assess safety in about 7 days. A Data Safety Monitoring
      Board will evaluate the safety and tolerability associated with each dose level before the
      next higher dose is tested in a new cohort. All research will be performed at the National
      Institute on Aging (NIA) Clinical Research Unit located on the 5th floor of MedStar Harbor
      Hospital.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double-Blind, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer's Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BNC</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Age greater than or equal to 55 years.

        Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must be using an adequate method of contraception
        (such as a barrier method, i.e. condoms with spermicide) to avoid pregnancy throughout the
        study and for up to 30 days after the study drug administration. WOCBP include any female
        who has experienced menarche and who has not undergone successful surgical sterilization
        (hysterectomy, bilateral tubal ligation, or bilateral oophorectomy) or is not
        post-menopausal. Post-menopause is defined as:

          -  Amenorrhea &gt;  12 consecutive months without another cause, or

          -  For women with irregular menstrual periods and taking hormone replacement therapy
             (HRT), a documented serum follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) level &gt;  35 mIU/mL.

        Women who are using oral contraceptives, other hormonal contraceptives (vaginal products,
        skin patches, or implanted or injectable products), or mechanical products such as an
        intrauterine device or barrier methods (diaphragm, condoms, spermicides) to prevent
        pregnancy, or are practicing abstinence or where their partner is sterile (eg, vasectomy)
        are considered to be of childbearing potential.

        WOCBP must have a negative urine pregnancy test (minimum sensitivity 25 IU/L or equivalent
        units of HCG) at screening and prior to study drug administration

        Men must be using an adequate method of contraception (such as a barrier method, i.e.
        condoms with spermicide) to avoid conception throughout the study and for up to 30 days of
        study drug administration.

        Body mass index (BMI) of 18.5 to 34.0, inclusive, and a total body weight of &gt;  50 kg (110
        pounds).

        Participants should be in good general health as determined by medical history, a baseline
        physical examination, vital signs, clinical laboratory tests and electrocardiogram (EKG),
        at the clinical judgment of the Principal Investigator. Participants may have common
        age-related disorders (such as hypertension, type II diabetes, dyslipidemia,
        hypothyroidism) as long as these disorders are being controlled by diet or medication with
        a stable dose and regimen of medication for at least 2 months at the clinical judgment of
        the Principal Investigator.

        Participant is willing and able to sign written informed consent prior to receipt of any
        study medication or beginning study procedures.

        Participant is willing and able to follow instructions, comply with the protocol
        requirements and make all required study visits.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Pregnant or lactating females.

        Subject is positive for HIV, hepatitis B surface antigen or hepatitis C antibody tests at
        screening.

        Subject with a positive urine test for drugs of abuse at screening or at admission to the
        clinic on study Day 1.

        Out-of range laboratory value at screening that has not been reviewed, approved and
        documented as not clinically significant by the Principal Investigator.

        Subject who has resting supine blood pressure outside of a systolic blood pressure range
        of 90-140 mmHg or a diastolic blood pressure outside a range of 50-90 mmHg on two
        consecutive measurements taken up to 10 minutes apart.

        Subject who has resting supine pulse rate greater than 100 bpm or less than 50 bpm on two
        consecutive measurements taken up to 10 minutes apart.

        Subject has taken any alcohol within 48 hours of any study-related activities and cannot
        abstain from drinking alcohol during the entire duration of the subject   s study
        participation.

        Subject has used any tobacco products in the past 12 months.

        A history of significant drug allergy or systemic allergic disease (e.g., urticaria,
        atopic dermatitis).

        A general medical or psychological condition or behavior, including current substance
        dependence or abuse that, in the opinion of the investigator, might not permit the subject
        to complete the study or sign the informed consent.

        Any clinically significant abnormality on screening 12-lead EKG (e.g., heart block,
        conduction disorders, ventricular and/or atrial arrhythmias).

        Routine or PRN consumption of certain medications or herbal supplements that the subject
        is unwilling or advised by her/his physicians to not discontinue prior to and during the
        study. In particular, the following herbal/dietary supplements are not permitted, if used
        within 2 weeks prior to study drug administration at doses higher than the recommended
        daily intake: Omega-3 fatty acids (&gt;  1000 mg/day), Vitamin E (&gt;  400IU/day). Ginkgo
        biloba and ginseng are not permitted, if used at any dose within 2 weeks prior to study
        drug administration.

        Medications that are excluded are:

          -  Insulin

          -  Anti-parkinsonian medications (such as sinemet, amantadine, bromocriptine, pergolide,
             selegiline)

          -  Typical or atypical neuroleptics

          -  Narcotic analgesics at any dose within 4 weeks prior to screening.

          -  Long-acting benzodiazepines or barbiturates within 4 weeks prior to screening

          -  Short-acting anxiolytics or sedative hypnotics more frequently than 2 times per week
             within 4 weeks prior to screening (sedative hypnotics should not be used within 102
             hours of study drug administration)

          -  Medications with known significant cholinergic or anticholinergic side effects (such
             as pyridostigmine, tricyclic antidepressants, meclizine, oxybutynin) within 4 weeks
             prior to screening

          -  Anti-convulsants (such as phenytoin, Phenobarbital, carbamazepine) within 2 months
             prior to screening

          -  Medications for Alzheimer   s disease (such as donepezil or memantine)

          -  Beta-Blockers

          -  Corticosteroids (Systemic)

          -  Neuromuscular-Blocking Agents (non-depolarizing)

          -  Succinylcholine

          -  Any other drug (including prescription, over the counter or herbal medications) that
             would, in the opinion of the Principal Investigator, pose a risk to the subject or
             produce overlapping side effects with the study medication.

        Donation or loss of 400 mL or more of blood within 56 days prior to and subsequent to
        screening.

        Inability to understand or follow study instructions.

        Participation in another research study involving an investigational drug within 30 days
        or 5 halflives, whichever is longer.

        Known allergy or hypersensitivity to the investigational study drug/placebo components.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dimitrios I Kapogiannis, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vickie L Schaffner</last_name>
    <phone>(410) 350-7319</phone>
    <email>schaffnervl@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Dimitrios I Kapogiannis, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(410) 350-3953</phone>
    <email>kapogiannisd@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute on Aging, Clinical Research Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-AG-0034.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arendt T, Bigl V, Walther F, Sonntag M. Decreased ratio of CSF acetylcholinesterase to butyrylcholinesterase activity in Alzheimer's disease. Lancet. 1984 Jan 21;1(8369):173.</citation>
    <PMID>6140490</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cummings JL. Use of cholinesterase inhibitors in clinical practice: evidence-based recommendations. Am J Geriatr Psychiatry. 2003 Mar-Apr;11(2):131-45. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12611743</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Darvesh S, Grantham DL, Hopkins DA. Distribution of butyrylcholinesterase in the human amygdala and hippocampal formation. J Comp Neurol. 1998 Apr 13;393(3):374-90.</citation>
    <PMID>9548556</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 8, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neurodegenerative</keyword>
  <keyword>Cholinergic</keyword>
  <keyword>Single Dose</keyword>
  <keyword>Inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Tolerability</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
