<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="77103">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01733745</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A00978</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01733745</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Systane Family - Meibomian Deficiency</brief_title>
  <official_title>Systane Family Efficacy in Meibomian Gland Functionality for Lipid Deficient Evaporative Dry Eye Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alcon Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alcon Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the efficacy of the Systane family of products
      (Systane Lid Wipes, Systane Balance Lubricant Eye Drops, and Systane Vitamins) on meibomian
      gland functionality in subjects with lipid deficiency related to evaporative dry eye as
      compared to the standard of care warm compresses.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Meibomian Glands Yielding Liquid Secretion (MGLYS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Meibomian gland functionality will be evaluated by the investigator using the Meibomian Gland Evaluator (MGE), a handheld instrument that provides a standardized method for applying consistent, gentle pressure to the outer skin of the lower eyelid. The number of meibomian gland orificies evidencing liquid secretion during expression with the MGE will be documented.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Standard Patient Evaluation of Eye Dryness (SPEED) Questionnaire Responses</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Standard Patient Evaluation of Eye Dryness (SPEED) Questionnaire is a 16-question validated questionnaire that measures the frequency and severity of dry eye symptoms. The SPEED questionnaire will be completed by the patient with no assistance from the office staff, physician, or anyone else.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dry Eye Ocular Surface Disease Index (OSDI) Questionnaire Responses</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Dry Eye OSDI Questionnaire is a 12-question validated questionnaire (resultant overall 0-100 score) that measures ocular symptoms, visual function, and environmental factors that may affect a patient's vision, where 0 = normal and 100 = severe. The OSDI questionnaire will be completed by the patient with no assistance from the office staff, physician, or anyone else.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">26</enrollment>
  <condition>Dry Eye Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Systane Family</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Systane Lid Wipes administered to treated eye(s) twice a day; Systane Balance lubricant eye drops administered to treated eye(s), one drop four times a day; Systane Vitamins, two softgels ingested daily. Duration of treatment is 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Microfiber towels (as warm compresses) warmed to the maximum comfortable temperature and placed over closed eyes for 8 minutes, one time a day. Duration of treatment is 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Systane Lid Wipes</intervention_name>
    <description>Systane Lid Wipes pre-moistened eyelid cleansing wipes for topical ocular external scrubbing of eyelids and eyelashes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Systane Family</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SYSTANE™ LID WIPES</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SYSTANE BALANCE Lubricant Eye Drops</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Systane Family</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SYSTANE® BALANCE</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Systane Vitamins</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Systane Family</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SYSTANE™ Vitamin Omega-3 Supplement</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Microfiber towels</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must have a clinical diagnosis of lipid deficient Evaporative Dry Eye;

          -  Meibomian Gland Functionality - Not more than 6 glands yielding liquid secretion;

          -  Must be willing to discontinue the use of all other Meibomian Gland Dysfunction
             management prior to receiving the study test article at Visit 1, up until the end of
             the study period;

          -  Must have best corrected visual acuity of 6/60 (20/20 Snellen, 1.0 logMAR) or better
             in each eye;

          -  Must be able to follow instructions and be willing and able to attend required study
             visits;

          -  Must read, sign, and date an Ethics Committee reviewed and approved informed consent
             form;

          -  Other protocol-defined inclusion criteria may apply.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History or evidence of ocular or intraocular surgery or serious ocular trauma in
             either eye within the past six months;

          -  Current punctal occlusion of any type (e.g., collagen plugs, silicone plugs).

          -  History of intolerance or hypersensitivity to any component of the study medications.

          -  History or evidence of epithelial herpes simplex keratitis (dendritic keratitis);
             vaccinia; active or recent varicella viral disease of the cornea and/or conjunctiva;
             chronic bacterial disease of the cornea and/or conjunctiva and/or eyelids;
             mycobacterial infection of the eye; and/or fungal disease of the eye.

          -  Pregnant or lactating at the time of enrollment;

          -  Not willing to take adequate precautions not to become pregnant during the study;

          -  Use of any concomitant topical ocular medications during the study period;

          -  Use of systemic medications that may contribute to dry eye unless on a stable dosing
             regimen for a minimum of 30 days prior to Visit 1.

          -  Ocular conditions that may preclude the safe administration of either drop under
             investigation;

          -  Unwilling to discontinue contact lens wear during the study period and for at least
             one week prior to Visit 1;

          -  Participation in an investigational drug or device study within 30 days of entering
             this study;

          -  Other protocol-defined exclusion criteria may apply.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Beth Scott, O.D., MS, FAAO</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Alcon Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Donald R Korb, O.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Korb and Associates</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Contact Alcon Call Center for Trial Locations</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Worth</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>76134</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 26, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 21, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>dry eye</keyword>
  <keyword>lipid deficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>meibomian gland</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dry Eye Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Keratoconjunctivitis Sicca</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tetrahydrozoline</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
