<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="168182">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01924299</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14607</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>I4V-MC-JAGJ</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01924299</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Baricitinib When Administered With Ketoconazole or Fluconazole in Healthy Participants</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Ketoconazole or Fluconazole on the Pharmacokinetics of Baricitinib in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eli Lilly and Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eli Lilly and Company</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main purpose of this study is to look at the effect of ketoconazole and fluconazole on
      how much baricitinib gets into the blood stream.  The study will also look at the
      tolerability of baricitinib and ketoconazole when given together and the tolerability of
      baricitinib and fluconazole when given together.

      Participants will be recruited into one of 2 treatment groups (Group A, Group B).  Each
      treatment group will participate in 2 study periods.  Participants will take baricitinib
      alone in one period and baricitinib with either ketaconazole or fluconazole in the other
      period.  This study will last approximately 7 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK): Maximum concentration (Cmax) of Baricitinib</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose of baricitinib on Day 1 up to 48 hours postdose in Period 1 and Predose of baricitinib on Day 6 or 7 up to 72 hours postdose in Period 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK): Time of Maximum Observed Drug Concentration (tmax) of Baricitinib</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose of baricitinib on Day 1 up to 48 hours postdose in Period 1 and Predose of baricitinib on Day 6 or 7 up to 72 hours postdose in Period 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics, Area Under the Plasma Concentration-Time Curve From Time 0 Hour (h) to Infinity (AUC0-∞) of Baricitinib</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose of baricitinib on Day 1 up to 48 hours postdose in Period 1 and Predose of baricitinib on Day 6 or 7 up to 72 hours postdose in Period 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Baricitinib + Ketoconazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Baricitinib - 10 mg administered orally once a day (QD) on Day 1 of Period 1 and on Day 6 of Period 2.
Ketoconazole - 400 mg administered orally QD for 6 days (Days 3-8) in Period 2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Baricitinib + Fluconazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Baricitinib - 10 mg administered orally once on Day 1 of Period 1 and on Day 7 of Period 2.
Fluconazole - 400 mg administered orally once on Day 3 of Period 2, followed by 200 mg administered orally QD for 6 days (Days 4-9) in Period 2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Baricitinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Baricitinib + Ketoconazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Baricitinib + Fluconazole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LY3009104</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketoconazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Baricitinib + Ketoconazole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluconazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Baricitinib + Fluconazole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Overtly healthy as determined by medical history and physical examination

          -  Female participants not of childbearing potential due to surgical sterilization (at
             least 3 months after surgical hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy with or without
             hysterectomy, or bilateral tubal occlusion/ligation) confirmed by medical history or
             menopause

          -  Have a body mass index of 18 to 29 kilograms per square meter (kg/m^2), inclusive, at
             screening

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who have previously completed or withdrawn from this study or any other
             study investigating baricitinib, and have previously received the study drug

          -  Have known allergies to baricitinib, ketoconazole, fluconazole, related compounds, or
             any components of the baricitinib, ketoconazole, or fluconazole formulations, or
             history of significant atopy

          -  Have a history of or current cardiovascular, respiratory, hepatic, renal,
             gastrointestinal, endocrine, hematological, or neurological disorders capable of
             significantly altering the absorption, metabolism, or elimination of drugs; of
             constituting a risk when taking the study medication; or of interfering with the
             interpretation of data

          -  Have a current or recent history (less than 30 days prior to screening and/or less
             than 45 days prior to day of admission to clinical research unit) of a clinically
             significant bacterial, fungal, parasitic, viral (not including rhinopharyngitis), or
             mycobacterial infection

          -  Have alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline
             phosphatase, total bilirubin, or gamma glutamyl transferase (GGT) values above the
             upper limit of the reference range for the local laboratory at screening or day of
             admission to clinical research unit

          -  Have an absolute neutrophil count (ANC) less than 2 times 10^9 per liter (L) (2000
             cells per microliter [μL]) at screening or day of admission to clinical research
             unit. For abnormal values, a single repeat will be allowed

          -  Intend to use over-the-counter or prescription medication and/or herbal supplements
             within 14 days prior to dosing and during the study (with the exception of occasional
             paracetamol, which will be permitted at the discretion of the investigator), or
             intended use of vitamin supplements from Day 1 until discharge from the Clinical
             Research Unit (CRU)

          -  Have used or intend to use any drugs or substances that are known to be substrates,
             inhibitors, or inducers of cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A4, CYP2C9, or CYP2C19 within 30
             days prior to dosing and throughout the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Call 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559) or 1-317-615-4559 Mon - Fri 9 AM - 5 PM Eastern time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST)</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Eli Lilly and Company</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>For additional information regarding investigative sites for this trial, contact 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559, 1-317-615-4559) Mon - Fri from 9 AM to 5 PM Eastern Time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST), or speak with your personal physician.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <state>West Yorkshire</state>
        <zip>LS2 9LH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 21, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 14, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Fluconazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ketoconazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
