<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="146395">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02024386</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00049150</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02024386</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy Study of Riociguat and Its Effects on Exercise Performance and Pulmonary Artery Pressure at High Altitude</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Riociguat on Gas Exchange, Exercise Performance, and Pulmonary Artery Pressure During Acute Altitude Exposure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Richard Moon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      During ascent to high altitude there is a physiologic response to hypoxia that results in an
      elevated pulmonary arterial pressure associated with decreased exercise performance,
      altitude-induced pulmonary hypertension, and high altitude pulmonary edema (HAPE). Riociguat
      is a novel agent from Bayer Pharmaceuticals that has already demonstrated effectiveness in
      the treatment of pulmonary hypertension, and it may prove to be beneficial in cases of
      altitude-induced pulmonary hypertension or HAPE. This research study, composed of 20 healthy
      volunteers ages 18-40 years, will attempt to mimic the decreased oxygen supply and elevated
      pulmonary artery pressures found in conditions of high altitude, allowing observation of the
      effects of riociguat and exercise on pulmonary arterial pressure, arterial oxygenation, and
      exercise performance. Prior to entering the hypobaric chamber, subjects will have radial
      arterial lines and pulmonary artery catheters placed to obtain arterial and pulmonary artery
      pressure measurements. Subjects will then enter the hypobaric chamber and perform exercise
      tolerance tests at a simulated altitude of 15,000 feet on an electrically braked ergometer
      (exercise bike) before and after administration of riociguat. If, after administration of
      riociguat and exposure to a simulated altitude of 15,000 feet, the exercise performance is
      improved and observed pulmonary artery pressures are lower than those measurements seen
      prior to administration of riociguat, this could lead to development of a prophylactic
      and/or treatment strategy for HAPE and high-altitude pulmonary hypertension. Statistical
      analysis will compare the variables of pulmonary artery pressure, radial arterial pressure,
      ventilation rate, cardiac output, PaO2, and work rate at exhaustion before and after
      administration of the drug riociguat.  The investigator's hypothesis is that riociguat will
      decrease pulmonary artery pressure and improve gas exchange and exercise performance at
      altitude.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background and Significance:

      Impairment of exercise performance during hypoxemia due to altitude exposure or lung disease
      is caused primarily by reduced oxygen delivery to the exercising muscles, due to the
      reduction in arterial oxygen content. This reduction in arterial oxygen content is due to
      reduced alveolar PO2 and ventilation/perfusion (VA/Q) mismatch, and to some extent alveolar
      to end-capillary diffusion impairment. Ultimately, hypoxemia results in secondary diffuse
      pulmonary vasoconstriction (hypoxic pulmonary vasoconstriction, HPV), which in turn causes
      pulmonary hypertension. This secondary pulmonary hypertension is believed to worsen VA/Q
      mismatch, further reducing the PO2, suggesting that pharmacologic blockade of HPV could
      increase PO2 (e.g. during altitude exposure) and thus improve exercise performance.
      Reduction in pulmonary artery pressure (PAP) in individuals susceptible to high altitude
      pulmonary edema (HAPE) could also facilitate both prevention and treatment of HAPE.

      Sildenafil is commonly used to treat pulmonary hypertension, including pulmonary
      hypertension that occurs due to altitude exposure, with variable success in treating cases
      of altitude-induced pulmonary hypertension and HAPE. Sildenafil works via blockade of
      blocksphosphodiesterase-5 (PDE-5) in pulmonary arterioles, causing an increase in cGMP. When
      cGMP is activated by nitric oxide (NO) it induces vasodilatation, and indeed, sildenafil
      administration during altitude exposure does increase arterial oxygenation slightly.
      However, attempting to block HPV with sildenafil by using a pathway that requires NO can
      only be realized if there is sufficient NO available to produce cGMP. During hypoxia
      endogenous levels of NO are depleted due to impaired endothelial NO synthesis. This may
      explain the inconsistent effects of sildenafil when used to improve oxygenation and
      performance at altitude.

      Endogenous concentration of unbound NO is actually quite low, and most of the biological
      effects of NO are mediated through formation of S-nitrosothiols (SNOs) such as
      S-nitrosohemoglobin (SNO-Hb). NO binds to hemoglobin in a PO2-dependent manner, forming
      SNO-Hb so that when PO2 is low, NO-Hb binding is less avid and SNO-Hb is depleted. Depletion
      of SNO-Hb during hypoxia has been proposed as a mechanism that augments HPV, and indeed
      hypoxia has been shown to induce low levels of SNO-Hb. It is quite possible that the
      reduction in available endogenous NO and depletion of SNO-Hb during hypoxia limits the
      effect of the cGMP mechanism by which sildenafil works. Thus, an agent which can activate
      cGMP during periods of hypoxia when NO and SNO-Hb are depleted should be more effective in
      treating altitude-induced pulmonary hypertension.

      Riociguat is a stimulator of soluble guanylate cyclase that bypasses the NO pathway and is
      currently approved by the FDA for treatment of pulmonary hypertension. Riociguat exhibits a
      dual mode of action that i.) stabilizes the reduced form of the nitrosyl-heme complex,
      enhancing the NO-cGMP signaling pathway in the absence of endogenous NO and ii.) acts in
      synergy with endogenous NO by increasing sGC sensitivity to NO. Essentially, riociguat
      stimulates sGC to produce cGMP in the absence of NO, and it is a mechanism by which
      pulmonary vascular resistance could be attenuated during altitude-induced pulmonary
      hypertension. It has recently been shown to augment exercise performance and decrease
      pulmonary artery pressure in both primary pulmonary hypertension and pulmonary arterial
      hypertension (PAH) due to chronic thromboembolic disease. Lowering pulmonary artery pressure
      could improve pulmonary gas exchange and performance at altitude, which has significant
      implications for those living at altitude, conducting military operations, altitude trekkers
      and high-altitude rescue teams. Direct stimulation of sGC also represents a promising
      alternative therapeutic strategy for those susceptible to high altitude pulmonary edema
      (HAPE) when current treatment modalities of nifedipine and sildenafil are ineffective and
      oxygen is unavailable. By itself or in combination with sildenafil, riociguat could produce
      a significant advance in exercise performance during altitude exposure and provide a
      substantial improvement over the current therapeutic options in the prevention and treatment
      of HAPE.

      Design and Procedures:

      This investigation will consist of 20 normal subjects. Medical screening will exclude
      cardiac and pulmonary disease, pregnancy and sickle cell disease/trait in African Americans.

      Subjects will be instrumented with radial arterial lines and pulmonary artery catheters and
      will perform a VO2 max test on a bicycle ergometer in a hypobaric chamber at a simulated
      altitude of 15,000 feet.

      Following the VO2 max test, subjects will return to ground level for a 3-hour rest period.
      At 90 minutes  subjects will be administered riociguat 0.5 mg or 1.0 mg orally. Once study
      subjects are at therapeutic levels of riociguat (30 to 90 minutes after oral
      administration), they will repeat the VO2 max test at 15,000 feet. The dosing of riociguat
      will start at the lowest recommended individual dose (0.5 mg) for the first three subjects.
      If there are no side effects and no clinically important difference in either PAP (5 mmHg
      decrease in mean PAP) or PaO2 (5 mmHg increase) during exercise, then for the remaining
      subjects the dose will be increased to 1.0 mg.

      During the incremental exercise test arterial and mixed blood samples will be analyzed for
      PO2, PCO2, pH, O2 saturation and hemoglobin. Exhaled gas will be collected continuously and
      analyzed for O2 and CO2 concentrations and exhaled volume. Cardiac output will be calculated
      using Fick. Pulmonary and systemic vascular resistances will be calculated from the cardiac
      output and intravascular pressures.

      Outcome measures will be VO2max, maximum mechanical work rate, pulmonary and systemic
      arterial pressures, cardiac output, oxygen delivery and arterial blood gases.

      Beneftits:

      Further understanding of the mechanism of hypoxic pulmonary vasoconstriction will aid in
      prognosis and treatment in conditions of increased pulmonary vascular resistance such as
      congenital heart disease, pulmonary arterial hypertension, and COPD, in addition to
      high-altitude pulmonary hypertension and high-altitude pulmonary edema (HAPE). Furthermore,
      the current treatment modalities for HAPE have demonstrated variable and/or limited
      effectiveness, so riociguat could potentially be used to prevent or treat HAPE in
      susceptible individuals. Additionally, riociguat could substantially improve exercise
      performance in those who must operate in conditions of high-altitude, such as those
      conducting military operations or working in high-altitude rescue teams.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Pulmonary Artery Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured Continuously During Baseline Exercise Testing and Again 3 Hours Later Throughout Exercise Testing After Administration of Riociguat</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Subject pulmonary artery pressures will be continuously monitored via pulmonary artery catheterization.  Measurements obtained during initial exercise test in the hypobaric chamber at a simulated altitude of 15,000 feet will be compared with measurements obtained during exercise testing at the same altitude after administration of Riociguat.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Radial Arterial Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured Continuously During Baseline Exercise Testing and Again 3 Hours Later Throughout Exercise Testing After Administration of Riociguat</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Subject systemic arterial pressures will be continuously monitored via radial artery catheterization. Measurements obtained during initial exercise test in the hypobaric chamber at a simulated altitude of 15,000 feet will be compared with measurements obtained during exercise testing at the same altitude after administration of Riociguat.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Arterial Oxygen Saturation (PaO2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured Periodically During Baseline Exercise Testing and Again 3 Hours Later Throughout Exercise Testing After Administration of Riociguat</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Subject arterial oxygen saturation (PaO2) will be periodically monitored at fixed intervals via arterial blood gas measurements. Measurements obtained during initial exercise test in the hypobaric chamber at a simulated altitude of 15,000 feet will be compared with measurements obtained during exercise testing at the same altitude after administration of Riociguat.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Ventilation Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured Continuously During Baseline Exercise Testing and Again 3 Hours Later Throughout Exercise Testing After Administration of Riociguat</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Subject ventilation rates will be monitored continuously using a multi-channel A/D converter (PowerLab™) connected to a personal computer, using Chart™ software (ADInstruments, Colorado Springs, CO). Measurements obtained during initial exercise test in the hypobaric chamber at a simulated altitude of 15,000 feet will be compared with measurements obtained during exercise testing at the same altitude after administration of Riociguat.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Work Rate at Exhaustion</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured Continuously During Baseline Exercise Testing and Again 3 Hours Later Throughout Exercise Testing After Administration of Riociguat</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subject work rates at exhaustion (in watts) will be continuously monitored using an ergometer (exercise bicycle). Measurements obtained during initial exercise test in the hypobaric chamber at a simulated altitude of 15,000 feet will be compared with measurements obtained during exercise testing at the same altitude after administration of Riociguat.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Cardiac Output</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured Continuously During Baseline Exercise Testing and Again 3 Hours Later Throughout Exercise Testing After Administration of Riociguat</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects cardiac output will be continuously monitored using a multi-channel A/D converter (PowerLab™) connected to a personal computer, using Chart™ software (ADInstruments, Colorado Springs, CO). Measurements obtained during initial exercise test in the hypobaric chamber at a simulated altitude of 15,000 feet will be compared with measurements obtained during exercise testing at the same altitude after administration of Riociguat.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension, Pulmonary</condition>
  <condition>Altitude Sickness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Riociguat</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Riociguat 0.5 mg tablets, one-time oral dose of 0.5 or 1.0 mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Riociguat</intervention_name>
    <description>After completion of first V02 max test at altitude, subjects will have a 3-hour rest period.  Riociguat will be administered at the 90-minute mark of this rest period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Riociguat</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Adempas</other_name>
    <other_name>NDA 204819</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy males and females

          -  Non-smoking

          -  Non-pregnant females

          -  Ages 18 - 40 years old

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Serious pulmonary or cardiovascular comorbidities

          -  Pregnant women

          -  VO2max &lt; 35 mL/kg per minute

          -  Sickle cell trait or disease

          -  Smokers

          -  Lung disease

          -  Hypertension

          -  Cardiac disease and left bundle branch block

          -  Taking nitrates, nitric oxide donors (such as amyl nitrite), and phosphodiesterase
             (PDE) inhibitors (including specific PDE-5 inhibitors, such as sildenafil, tadalafil,
             or vardenafil, or non-specific PDE inhibitors, such as dipyridamole or theophylline).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard E Moon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard E Moon, MD</last_name>
    <phone>919-906-5651</phone>
    <email>richard.moon@dm.duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jon S Andrews, BS, BA</last_name>
    <phone>910-322-0054</phone>
    <email>jon.andrews@dm.duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke Center for Hyperbaric Medicine and Environmental Physiology, Trent Drive, Building CR2, Room 0584, Box 3823,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard E Moon, MD</last_name>
      <phone>919-906-5651</phone>
      <email>richard.moon@dm.duke.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jon S Andrews, BS, BA</last_name>
      <phone>910-322-0054</phone>
      <email>jon.andrews@dm.duke.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard E Moon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jon S Andrews, BS, BA</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Natoli, MS</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John J Freiberger, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Torre-Bueno JR, Wagner PD, Saltzman HA, Gale GE, Moon RE. Diffusion limitation in normal humans during exercise at sea level and simulated altitude. J Appl Physiol (1985). 1985 Mar;58(3):989-95.</citation>
    <PMID>2984169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gale GE, Torre-Bueno JR, Moon RE, Saltzman HA, Wagner PD. Ventilation-perfusion inequality in normal humans during exercise at sea level and simulated altitude. J Appl Physiol (1985). 1985 Mar;58(3):978-88.</citation>
    <PMID>2984168</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wagner PD, Gale GE, Moon RE, Torre-Bueno JR, Stolp BW, Saltzman HA. Pulmonary gas exchange in humans exercising at sea level and simulated altitude. J Appl Physiol (1985). 1986 Jul;61(1):260-70.</citation>
    <PMID>3090012</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ghofrani HA, Reichenberger F, Kohstall MG, Mrosek EH, Seeger T, Olschewski H, Seeger W, Grimminger F. Sildenafil increased exercise capacity during hypoxia at low altitudes and at Mount Everest base camp: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled crossover trial. Ann Intern Med. 2004 Aug 3;141(3):169-77.</citation>
    <PMID>15289213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richalet JP, Gratadour P, Robach P, Pham I, Déchaux M, Joncquiert-Latarjet A, Mollard P, Brugniaux J, Cornolo J. Sildenafil inhibits altitude-induced hypoxemia and pulmonary hypertension. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2005 Feb 1;171(3):275-81. Epub 2004 Oct 29.</citation>
    <PMID>15516532</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McMahon TJ, Moon RE, Luschinger BP, Carraway MS, Stone AE, Stolp BW, Gow AJ, Pawloski JR, Watke P, Singel DJ, Piantadosi CA, Stamler JS. Nitric oxide in the human respiratory cycle. Nat Med. 2002 Jul;8(7):711-7. Epub 2002 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>12042776</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lundberg JO, Weitzberg E, Gladwin MT. The nitrate-nitrite-nitric oxide pathway in physiology and therapeutics. Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2008 Feb;7(2):156-67. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18167491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McMahon TJ, Ahearn GS, Moya MP, Gow AJ, Huang YC, Luchsinger BP, Nudelman R, Yan Y, Krichman AD, Bashore TM, Califf RM, Singel DJ, Piantadosi CA, Tapson VF, Stamler JS. A nitric oxide processing defect of red blood cells created by hypoxia: deficiency of S-nitrosohemoglobin in pulmonary hypertension. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2005 Oct 11;102(41):14801-6. Epub 2005 Oct 3.</citation>
    <PMID>16203976</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allen BW, Stamler JS, Piantadosi CA. Hemoglobin, nitric oxide and molecular mechanisms of hypoxic vasodilation. Trends Mol Med. 2009 Oct;15(10):452-60. doi: 10.1016/j.molmed.2009.08.002. Epub 2009 Sep 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19781996</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubin LJ, Naeije R. Sildenafil for enhanced performance at high altitude? Ann Intern Med. 2004 Aug 3;141(3):233-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15289224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Droma Y, Hanaoka M, Ota M, Katsuyama Y, Koizumi T, Fujimoto K, Kobayashi T, Kubo K. Positive association of the endothelial nitric oxide synthase gene polymorphisms with high-altitude pulmonary edema. Circulation. 2002 Aug 13;106(7):826-30.</citation>
    <PMID>12176955</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahsan A, Charu R, Pasha MA, Norboo T, Charu R, Afrin F, Ahsan A, Baig MA. eNOS allelic variants at the same locus associate with HAPE and adaptation. Thorax. 2004 Nov;59(11):1000-2.</citation>
    <PMID>15516480</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luo Y, Chen Y, Zhang Y, Zhou Q, Gao Y. Association of endothelial nitric oxide synthase (eNOS) G894T polymorphism with high altitude pulmonary edema susceptibility: a meta-analysis. Wilderness Environ Med. 2012 Sep;23(3):270-4. doi: 10.1016/j.wem.2012.03.007. Epub 2012 Jul 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22795910</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Follmann M, Griebenow N, Hahn MG, Hartung I, Mais FJ, Mittendorf J, Schäfer M, Schirok H, Stasch JP, Stoll F, Straub A. The chemistry and biology of soluble guanylate cyclase stimulators and activators. Angew Chem Int Ed Engl. 2013 Sep 2;52(36):9442-62. doi: 10.1002/anie.201302588. Epub 2013 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>23963798</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ghofrani HA, D'Armini AM, Grimminger F, Hoeper MM, Jansa P, Kim NH, Mayer E, Simonneau G, Wilkins MR, Fritsch A, Neuser D, Weimann G, Wang C; CHEST-1 Study Group. Riociguat for the treatment of chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension. N Engl J Med. 2013 Jul 25;369(4):319-29. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1209657.</citation>
    <PMID>23883377</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ghofrani HA, Galiè N, Grimminger F, Grünig E, Humbert M, Jing ZC, Keogh AM, Langleben D, Kilama MO, Fritsch A, Neuser D, Rubin LJ; PATENT-1 Study Group. Riociguat for the treatment of pulmonary arterial hypertension. N Engl J Med. 2013 Jul 25;369(4):330-40. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1209655.</citation>
    <PMID>23883378</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Forster PJ. Effect of different ascent profiles on performance at 4,200 m elevation. Aviat Space Environ Med. 1985 Aug;56(8):758-64.</citation>
    <PMID>3929759</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>West JB. Improving oxygenation at high altitude: acclimatization and O2 enrichment. High Alt Med Biol. 2003 Fall;4(3):389-98.</citation>
    <PMID>14561244</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beidleman BA, Muza SR, Fulco CS, Cymerman A, Ditzler D, Stulz D, Staab JE, Skrinar GS, Lewis SF, Sawka MN. Intermittent altitude exposures reduce acute mountain sickness at 4300 m. Clin Sci (Lond). 2004 Mar;106(3):321-8.</citation>
    <PMID>14561214</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sampson JB, Cymerman A, Burse RL, Maher JT, Rock PB. Procedures for the measurement of acute mountain sickness. Aviat Space Environ Med. 1983 Dec;54(12 Pt 1):1063-73.</citation>
    <PMID>6661120</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rock PB, Johnson TS, Cymerman A, Burse RL, Falk LJ, Fulco CS. Effect of dexamethasone on symptoms of acute mountain sickness at Pikes Peak, Colorado (4,300 m). Aviat Space Environ Med. 1987 Jul;58(7):668-72.</citation>
    <PMID>3619842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hughson RL, Yamamoto Y, McCullough RE, Sutton JR, Reeves JT. Sympathetic and parasympathetic indicators of heart rate control at altitude studied by spectral analysis. J Appl Physiol (1985). 1994 Dec;77(6):2537-42.</citation>
    <PMID>7896588</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bärtsch P, Maggiorini M, Ritter M, Noti C, Vock P, Oelz O. Prevention of high-altitude pulmonary edema by nifedipine. N Engl J Med. 1991 Oct 31;325(18):1284-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1922223</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scherrer U, Vollenweider L, Delabays A, Savcic M, Eichenberger U, Kleger GR, Fikrle A, Ballmer PE, Nicod P, Bärtsch P. Inhaled nitric oxide for high-altitude pulmonary edema. N Engl J Med. 1996 Mar 7;334(10):624-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8592525</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jensen LA, Onyskiw JE, Prasad NG. Meta-analysis of arterial oxygen saturation monitoring by pulse oximetry in adults. Heart Lung. 1998 Nov-Dec;27(6):387-408.</citation>
    <PMID>9835670</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hornbein TF, Townes BD, Schoene RB, Sutton JR, Houston CS. The cost to the central nervous system of climbing to extremely high altitude. N Engl J Med. 1989 Dec 21;321(25):1714-9.</citation>
    <PMID>2512483</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frey R, Mück W, Unger S, Artmeier-Brandt U, Weimann G, Wensing G. Single-dose pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics, tolerability, and safety of the soluble guanylate cyclase stimulator BAY 63-2521: an ascending-dose study in healthy male volunteers. J Clin Pharmacol. 2008 Aug;48(8):926-34. doi: 10.1177/0091270008319793. Epub 2008 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>18519919</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Slogoff S, Keats AS, Arlund C. On the safety of radial artery cannulation. Anesthesiology. 1983 Jul;59(1):42-7.</citation>
    <PMID>6859611</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frezza EE, Mezghebe H. Indications and complications of arterial catheter use in surgical or medical intensive care units: analysis of 4932 patients. Am Surg. 1998 Feb;64(2):127-31.</citation>
    <PMID>9486883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Valentine RJ, Modrall JG, Clagett GP. Hand ischemia after radial artery cannulation. J Am Coll Surg. 2005 Jul;201(1):18-22.</citation>
    <PMID>15978439</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mummery HJ, Stolp BW, deL Dear G, Doar PO, Natoli MJ, Boso AE, Archibald JD, Hobbs GW, El-Moalem HE, Moon RE. Effects of age and exercise on physiological dead space during simulated dives at 2.8 ATA. J Appl Physiol (1985). 2003 Feb;94(2):507-17. Epub 2002 Oct 11.</citation>
    <PMID>12391136</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 27, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Duke University Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Richard Moon</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Director, Duke Center for Hyperbaric Medicine and Environmental Physiology, Professor of Anesthesiology, Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Guanylate Cyclase</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Edema of Mountaineers</keyword>
  <keyword>Mountaineering</keyword>
  <keyword>Performance-Enhancing Substances</keyword>
  <keyword>Athletic Performance</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Altitude Sickness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Performance-Enhancing Substances</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
