<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="107730">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02101463</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NSH 997</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02101463</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MOSTEGRA TRIAL:MO-(Dified) STE-(nt) GRA(-ft): Surgeon-modified Fenestrated-branched Stent-grafts</brief_title>
  <acronym>MOSTEGRA</acronym>
  <official_title>Surgeon-Modified Fenestrated/Branched Stent-Grafts for Treatment of Complex Aortic Aneurysms in High-Risk Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northside Hospital, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northside Hospital, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial evaluates surgeon-modified fenestrated-branched stent-grafts (sm-FBSG) for
      Abdominal Aortic Aneurysms (AAA) that are custom-made intra-operatively with no waiting
      period by a qualified vascular surgeon.  In addition, aims to examine the alternative
      sm-FBSG for patients with restricted access to centers performing clinical trials with
      commercially available devices and those patients with aortic emergencies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Complex aortic aneurysms are those involving the renal, and visceral, arteries that require
      more extensive dissection, aortic clamping above the renal or mesenteric arteries, and
      possible reconstruction of aortic branches. Complex aortic aneurysms comprise two major
      entities, pararenal and thoracoabdominal aneurysms.

      Pararenal aneurysms represent the simplest form of complex aortic aneurysms that have no
      adequate neck between the renal arteries and the aneurysm and would require suprarenal
      clamping for open repair.

      Thoracoabdominal aortic aneurysms (TAAAs) involve dilatation of the descending thoracic
      aorta into the abdomen. The aneurysms may extend from the left subclavian artery to the
      iliac arteries. The most common etiology is from spontaneous degeneration of the aortic wall
      adventitia, but other causes of accelerated or secondary dilatation of the aortic wall
      include spontaneous aortic dissection, infection, trauma, and disorders of connective
      tissue, such as Marfan's, Turner's, and Ehlers-Danlos syndromes.

      Population studies have documented approximately 5.9 to 10.4 new TAAAs per 100,000
      person-years with nearly equal incidence in the sexes (males, 44%).The mean age at diagnosis
      is 63 to 65 years for men and 75 to 77 years for women. A study of deaths associated with
      TAAA captured by the Swedish National Bureau of Statistics and Swedish hospital records
      found that almost three quarters of TAAA ruptures occurred in women, mostly aged 70 to 84
      years. This dramatic difference in gender-associated rupture rates does not correlate with
      the incidence of TAAAs reported from single-center reports of treated TAAAs.

      The number of patients needed to treat thoracoabdominal aneurysms (TAAA) is estimated at
      two, making the benefit for patients undergoing repair of their TAAA obvious.
      Surgeon-modified fenestrated-branched stent-grafts (sm-FBSG) with branches for the visceral
      vessels in patients with complex aortic conditions could represent a therapeutic option for
      high-risk patients unfit for open surgery.  Open surgery for complex aneurysms of the
      abdominal aorta (AAA) including thoracoabdominal aortic aneurysms (TAAA) has greatly
      developed over the past decades to provide patients adequate management with good functional
      results and reduced perioperative morbidity and mortality.  However, despite much
      advancement in preoperative evaluation and perioperative care of patients with
      thoracoabdominal aortic aneurysms (TAAA), open surgical repair of TAAAs remains a formidable
      challenge for the vascular surgeon.  In a recent meta-analysis by Piazza and Ricotta of
      7,833 patients who underwent open surgical repair of TAAA between the years 2000 and 2010,
      the overall risk of death within 30 days was 7%, while in-hospital mortality was 10%. The
      30-day mortality was 5% for elective cases, with significant associated morbidity ranging
      from a 7.5% incidence of spinal cord ischemia, to 19% rate of renal failure and 36% rate of
      pulmonary dysfunction. The 30-day mortality for open repair of ruptured TAAA has been
      reported as high as 40%, with an average of 19% in this meta-analysis.

      Many high-risk patients with aneurysms of the abdominal aorta (AAA) and who have significant
      co-morbidities will not be good candidates for elective open surgery.  Endovascular aneurysm
      repair has been shown to be an effective alternative in treating uncomplicated infrarenal
      and thoracic aneurysms in both the elective and urgent setting, yet there is limited
      experience with this technology in complex conditions.  Fenestrated grafts have been
      developed as a minimally invasive treatment for patients with complex aortic aneurysms who
      are unfit for traditional open surgery. However, construction of these fenestrated grafts
      requires that they are custom-made to fit the specific anatomical requirements of each
      patient, and can take up to 12 weeks to manufacture. Restricted access to investigational
      devices and delays for device customization limit the treatment with these endografts to a
      small group of patients with relatively stable aneurysms.    Particularly in urgent cases,
      this time frame is not acceptable.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the safety and effectiveness of sm-FBSG for the treatment of complex aortic aneurysms in patients at high-risk for open surgical repair.</measure>
    <time_frame>30 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Major adverse events defined as:
All-cause death
Bowel ischemia
Myocardial infarction
Paraplegia
Renal failure
Respiratory failure
Stroke
Blood loss &gt;=1,000cc
Primary effectiveness endpoint is the proportion of treatment group subjects that achieve treatment success. Treatment success is a composite endpoint assessed at 12 months that requires all of the following criteria to be met in order for a patient to be considered a treatment success:
Technical Success, defined as successful delivery and deployment of the physician modified endovascular graft with preservation of those branch vessels intended to be preserved
Freedom from Type I &amp; III endoleak at 12 months
Freedom from stent graft migration at 12 months
Freedom from AAA enlargement at 12 months
Freedom from AAA rupture and conversion to open repair through 12 months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the risks and complications associated with sm-FBSG</measure>
    <time_frame>&gt;30 Days to 5 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate all serious and non-serious major adverse events quarterly
Evaluate device delivery and deployment with patency of all branches and aortic endografts without Type I/III endoleak post-operatively and in 6 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate postoperative mortality after repair with sm-FBSG</measure>
    <time_frame>&gt;30 Days to 5 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>• All-cause mortality, bowel ischemia, myocardial infarction, paraplegia, renal failure, respiratory failure, stroke, blood loss &gt;1,000cc</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate long-term survival and complications after repair of complex aortic aneurysms with sm-FBSG</measure>
    <time_frame>&gt;30 Days to 5 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Open surgical repair of the aortic aneurysm due to unsuccessful delivery or deployment of the stent graft, due to complications or other clinical situations that precluded successful endovascular treatment, or at any time following initial successful endovascular treatment for any reason
Examination of Internal bleeding or leaking of blood from the aneurysm subsequent to the index procedure
Non-diagnostic intervention after the index procedure intended to correct or repair an endoleak (device-related: Type I (proximal or distal), Type III, Type IV; non-device related: Type II), device migration, or other device defect.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Refine the device modification and procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>30 Days, 3 Months, 6 Months, and Years 1 to 5</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Patent luminal flow; absence of kinking, stenosis, occlusion, stent fracture, graft failure, or renal infarct &gt;30%
Change in aneurysm sac diameter from the first post-procedural measurement; incidence of endoleak; incidence of device migration; incidence of limb occlusion
Bifurcated and fenestrated stent graft patent luminal flow; absence of stent fracture or graft fatigue/failure
Renal Stent Graft Patency and Integrity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Optimize patient selection</measure>
    <time_frame>30 Days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Reduction in estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) &gt;30% from the preoperative value
Fluoroscopy time; contrast volume; estimated blood loss; % requiring transfusion; procedure time; ICU time; time to hospital discharge
Prior aortic surgery associated with a higher perioperative risk for repeat open repair
Hostile abdomen (&gt;=2 major abdominal procedures or described adhesions in previous laparotomy, laparoscopy with fragile small bowel loops adhered to each other or complicated with enterocutaneous fistulae. Patients status-post pancreatitis, peritoneal dialysis or other intraperitoneal condition that is associated with high risk of major adhesions)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Complex Aortic Aneurysms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>surgeon-modified fenestrated-branched stent-grafts (sm-FBSG)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>surgeon-modified fenestrated-branched stent-grafts (sm-FBSG)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>surgeon-modified fenestrated-branched stent-grafts (sm-FBSG)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: All patients must meet all of the following inclusion criteria to be
        eligible for enrollment into the study:

          -  Patients with complex aortic aneurysms (one of the following)

             o Juxta- or pararenal aneurysms with a maximal diameter at least 5.0cm and infrarenal
             aortic neck length &lt;10mm

               -  Aortic aneurysms involving the renal or mesenteric arteries with a maximal
                  diameter of at least 1.5 times the transverse dimension of an adjacent
                  non-aneurysmal aortic segment

               -  Thoracoabdominal aneurysms with a maximal diameter ≥5.5cm, including aneurysms
                  involving the distal aortic arch where there is &lt; 20mm of aortic neck length
                  distal to the left subclavian artery

               -  Rapid enlargement (&gt;0.5cm in 6 months) or rupture of any of the above aortic
                  aneurysms

               -  Juxta-, pararenal or thoracoabdominal aneurysm with unstable morphology (such as
                  saccular aneurysms) irrespective of size

          -  Patients presenting for elective or urgent repair of a complex aortic aneurysm

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  Patients who are male or non-pregnant female (females of child bearing potential must
             have a negative pregnancy test prior to enrollment into the study)

          -  No other investigational agents or devices while on protocol

          -  Patient or Legally Authorized Representative has signed an Institutional Review Board
             (IRB) approved Informed Consent Form

          -  Patient must be able and willing to comply with all follow-up exams

          -  Life expectancy of more than 1 year

        Additional to the above obligatory enrollment criteria one or more of the following
        inclusion criteria must apply for patients to participate in the study:

          -  Patients with medical conditions that would make them unfit for open repair (one or
             more of the following)

               -  American Society of anesthesiologists score ≥3

               -  Society of Vascular Surgery Score ≥ 8

               -  Patients requiring oxygen supplementation

               -  Pulmonary dysfunction with an FEV1 &lt;1.5 liter

               -  Recent myocardial infarction (&lt;6 months)

               -  Congestive heart failure (CHF) with an ejection fraction &lt;40%

               -  Symptomatic CHF

               -  Age &gt;79

               -  Previous CVA with profound deficit

               -  Coronary revascularization with bypass in past 6 months

               -  Coronary revascularization with angioplasty/stent in past 6 weeks

               -  Unstable angina

               -  Valvular heart disease requiring intervention

               -  Cancer with &lt;50% 5 year survival

               -  Renal insufficiency with creatinine &gt; 1.5 mg/dL

               -  Liver failure

          -  Prior aortic surgery associated with a higher perioperative risk for repeat open
             repair

          -  Hostile abdomen (≥ 2 major abdominal procedures or described adhesions in previous
             laparotomy, laparoscopy with fragile small bowel loops adhered to each other or
             complicated with enterocutaneous fistulae. Patients status-post pancreatitis,
             peritoneal dialysis or other intraperitoneal condition that is associated with high
             risk of major adhesions)

          -  Contraindication to stop clopidogrel or warfarin which is associated with
             significantly higher mortality for open repair.

        Exclusion Criteria: Patients that meet any exclusion criteria are not eligible for the
        study.

        General exclusion criteria

          -  Estimated life expectancy &lt;1 year

          -  Contraindication to angiography

          -  Active infection

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Patients with ruptured or contained ruptured aortic aneurysm who are persistently
             hemodynamically unstable at the time of presentation and require intensive fluid
             resuscitation, vasopressors to maintain pressure or cardiopulmonary resuscitation

          -  Known allergy to stainless steel, polyester, or gold

          -  History of anaphylactic reaction to contrast material with an inability to properly
             prophylax the patient appropriately

          -  Morbid Obesity with inability to visualize the aorta with available intraoperative
             imaging techniques

          -  Patient has other medical, social or psychological conditions that, in the opinion of
             the investigator, preclude them from receiving the pre-treatment, required treatment,
             and post-treatment procedures and evaluations

          -  Patient is currently participating in another investigational device or drug clinical
             trial

        Anatomic exclusion criteria

          -  Aortic diameter of true lumen that cannot accommodate a fenestrated endograft

          -  Angulation of &gt;90° in the paravisceral aorta

          -  Highly calcified and/or stenosed iliac arteries with a diameter &lt;6mm and concomitant
             contraindication to perform iliac conduit.

          -  Highly torturous iliac arteries and concomitant contraindication to perform iliac
             conduit.

        Comments on exclusion criteria:

          -  Patients with connective tissue disorder are not automatically excluded from the
             study, since the outcome of open repair in the setting of high-risk patients with
             complex aneurysm is as bad or even worse as for patients without connective tissue
             disorders.

          -  Patients with hypersensitivity or contraindication to anticoagulation such as
             patients with Heparin Induced Thrombocytopenia (HIT) are not automatically excluded
             from the study. Alternative forms of anticoagulation such as Argatroban or
             Bivalrudin, direct thrombin inhibitors, will be used in such cases.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph J. Ricotta, II, MD, MS, FACS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northside Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Margaret Wong, MBA, BSN, RN, CCRC</last_name>
    <phone>(404) 303-3529</phone>
    <email>margaret.wong@northside.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jen Cuvo, RN, BSN, CCRC</last_name>
    <phone>(404) 303-3523</phone>
    <email>jennifer.cuvo@northside.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northside Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30342</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nvs-ga.com/</url>
    <description>Northside Vascular Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 25, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>aortic</keyword>
  <keyword>sm-FBSG</keyword>
  <keyword>aneurysms</keyword>
  <keyword>fenestrated</keyword>
  <keyword>stent-grafts</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular</keyword>
  <keyword>Endovascular</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Aneurysm</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aortic Aneurysm</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
