<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="105704">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01661062</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2005.084</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HUM 757</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01661062</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study Using Cone Beam CT for Head and Neck Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of Tumor and Critical Normal Tissue Motion in Head and Neck Cancer Using Cone Beam CT</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cone beam CT (computed tomography) is a developing technology which allows CT images to be
      obtained while a patient is on the radiation treatment table.(A CT scan uses x-rays to
      produce detailed pictures of structures in the body.)  In this study, cone beam CT scans
      will be obtained before individual radiation treatment sessions for head and neck cancer.
      The information gathered from these scans will be used by the researchers to look at patient
      movement as well as changes in the amount of normal and tumor tissue throughout the course
      of radiation therapy.  The researchers will use this information to create hypothetical
      radiation treatment plans, which will be used as the basis for future research.  The cone
      beam CT scan data will not be used to alter the actual radiation treatment of any of the
      patients enrolled on the study. In addition, tests of salivary output and swallowing and
      questionnaires about quality of life will be made to assess how the doses of radiation
      affect them.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Movement of Normal Tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary outcome measure of this study is to characterize patient-specific target and normal tissue movement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of Image Quality</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Use acquired data to further improve cone beam CT reconstruction techniques and image quality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dosage of Radiation on Target Structures</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To characterize long-term changes in targets and normal tissues during the course of radiation therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation Between Xerostomia and Targeted Therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assess relationships between xerostomia and swallowing and the actually delivered doses to the relevant anatomical structures (salivary glands, swallowing structures) calculated from the CT scans performed during therapy. This will allow researchers to determine if targeted therapy decreases the effects of xerostomia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Head and Neck Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will be included in the treatment arm of this study. For the purposes of this study patients will get CT scans every day for the length of their radiation therapy (in order to assess if CT every day provides additional information compared with CT scans performed less frequently).  Although the exact amount of radiation patients get will be determined by their doctor, it is expected that they will get approximately 7 weeks, approximately 35 total cone beam CT scans.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cone Beam Computed Tomography (CT) Scan</intervention_name>
    <description>Cone beam CT scan is considered a noninvasive procedure (meaning that the procedure does not require breaking the skin or any tools that physically enter the body).  It will add a small amount of additional radiation dose (less than 1%) to the head and neck.  The increase in the amount of radiation is only a very small amount more than what patients who get standard daily imaging receive.  The amount of radiation from the cone beam CT scans is not significant (less than 1%) when compared to the amount of radiation generally received for treatment of head and neck cancer.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CBCT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients of all ages ≥18, both sexes, and all races will be included in this study.
             Pregnant females will be excluded.  No other special classes of subjects (i.e.,
             prisoners) will be entered.

          -  Patients must be diagnosed with biopsy-proven squamous cell carcinoma of the head and
             neck.

          -  Patients  must be recommended treatment with definitive radiation therapy with
             concurrent chemotherapy, but without prior surgical resection of the primary tumor or
             lymph nodes

          -  Patients must be recommended a treatment course of at least 30 radiation fractions

          -  Patients must sign an informed consent form approved for this purpose by the
             Institutional Review Board (IRB) of the University of Michigan Hospital indicating
             that they are aware that undergoing cone beam CT of the head and neck is voluntary
             and has potential risks.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must not have a history of prior radiation to the head or neck
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Avraham Eisbruch, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 30, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 26, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
