<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="132627">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01667978</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HS-12-00005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01667978</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Protease Inhibitors on the Pharmacokinetics of Oral Norethindrone Contraception</brief_title>
  <acronym>NET</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effect of Protease Inhibitors on the Pharmacokinetics of Oral Norethindrone Contraception</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Society of Family Planning</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern California</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to learn if women taking the atazanavir and ritonavir have
      lower levels of a birth control medication called norethindrone. Norethindrone (also called
      the mini pill) is an FDA (Food and Drug Administration) approved progestin-only birth
      control pill used to prevent pregnancy. Norethindrone is the standard medication used in
      women who take the progestin only pill to prevent pregnancy.  There are other birth control
      pills which contain different medications.  The investigators want to learn if HIV
      medications (atazanavir and ritonavir) make the blood level of this birth control pill
      higher or lower. If the levels of norethindrone are too low it may not work to prevent
      pregnancy. The investigators also hope to learn about changes in the vaginal fluids and
      cervical fluids when women are taking this birth control pill.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND/RATIONALE : It is recognized that there is a dearth of clinically applied,
      population based, empiric data to guide contraceptive recommendations in HIV + women on
      ARVs.(1) Protease inhibitors (PI) and non nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NNRTI
      ) induce micro enzyme systems such as CYP 3a4, which in turn alters the bio-availability and
      pharmacokinetics of other concurrently administered medications.(2) Empiric trials from
      small samples, often of 10-20 HIV negative subjects, have demonstrated that concurrent
      administration of combined oral contraceptives (COC) and a PI or a NNRTI have been
      associated with decreased plasma ethinyl estradiol (EE) levels. These pharmacokinetic
      findings have raised concern that decreased bio-availability of EE may result in decreased
      contraceptive efficacy, with possible increased unintended pregnancy. Some of these COC
      studies have demonstrated that there is no change in the serum levels of norethindrone (NET)
      on ARVs.(3-16) However, there are no published trials focused on oral NET or oral
      progestin-only pills (POP) to guide management in HIV+ women.(17)

      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary objective of this study is:

      To detect a ±40% difference in AUC of serum NET in HIV+ women taking ATV/RTV as compared to
      AUC of NET in HIV+ women taking an ARV regimen that has demonstrated no interaction with NET
      in the past.

      Primary endpoint: Natural log-transformed NET PK parameter AUC from 0 to 72 hours following
      oral administration, with multiple discrete serum data points for each subject on ATV/RTV.
      This will be compared to natural log-transformed NET PK AUC from 0 to 72 hours following
      oral administration, with multiple discrete serum data points for controls HIV+ women taking
      an ARV regimen that has demonstrated no interaction with NET in the past.

      The secondary objectives of this study are:

      To evaluate the effect of ATV/RTV on other PK exposure endpoints and parameters of NET (with
      natural log transformation). The sample and control groups mentioned above will again be
      compared. Endpoints include:

      minimum plasma concentration (Cmin), maximum plasma concentration (Cmax), time to Cmax
      (Tmax), and half-life (T1/2).

      SAMPLE SIZE: Recruitment of 16 participants in each arm, with the goal of attaining 32
      evaluable HIV-1-seropositive female subjects in total.

      POPULATION/STUDY ARMS: HIV-1-infected female subjects 18-44 years of age

      METHODOLOGY/INTERVENTIONS/FOLLOW-UP: A two-arm, open-label, prospective, steady state trial
      to characterize the pharmacokinetics (PK) of oral norethindrone (NET) as a progestin only
      contraceptive pill (POP) in HIV+ women receiving atazanavir and ritonavir therapy (ATV/RTV).
      The investigators will identify a control group of HIV+ women who are taking ARV regimens
      that have not significantly altered oral NET levels in prior trials. Subjects will be
      enrolled in the trial for approximately 4 weeks A 28 day continuous packet of NET 0.35 mg
      will be provided to all enrolled volunteers for 21 days of continuous administration. Women
      who participate in this study will demonstrate a means of continuing their ARV regimens for
      the duration of the study, ARV therapy will not be provided by this study. On day 22
      subjects will be admitted for serial pharmacokinetic (PK) specimens collection following the
      final study dose of NET.

      Subjects will be enrolled into one of the 2 arms based on their current ARV regimen.

      Study group: Women on stable ARV/RTV (300/100mg daily) with additional ARV regimens that
      have not significantly altered oral NET levels in prior trials. (n=12).

      Control group: Stable on current ARV, no protease inhibitors (PI), ARV regimens that have
      not significantly altered oral NET levels in previous research.

      OUTCOMES: Intensive PK sampling for NET will be performed in those in intervention and
      control arms after 21 days of NET administration. To determine side effect profile of NET by
      self-administered daily questionnaire during the 3-4 week study enrollment period

      STATISTICS: Area under the concentration-time curve (AUC), peak plasma concentration, and
      the lowest plasma concentration for NET in HIV+ women receiving this PI therapy will be
      determined and compared to similar values in HIV positive control subjects who are not
      taking PI therapy. Statistical consultation will be obtained from the USC Keck School of
      Medicine Department of Bio statistics and Laboratory of Applied Pharmacokinetics
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC norethindrone</measure>
    <time_frame>following 21 days of continuous ingestion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <condition>AIDS</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study group with PI: atazanavir ritonavir</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>o PI therapy, control group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Norethindrone acetate</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>PI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Both control and experimental group with take norethindrone.  However the experimental group will be taking a protease inhibitor: atazanavir and ritonavir</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Ages: 18-44 years Gender: female Accepts: healthy volunteers and HIV-1 infected women
        Acceptable medications include: no other medications, NRTI combinations, entry inhibitors,
        integrase inhibitors, and CCR5 agonists.  NRTI combinations may include but are not
        limited to: zidovudine (ZDV), lamivudine (3TC), emtricitabine (FTC), didanosine (ddl),
        stavudine (d4T), abacavir (ABC), and tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF).  NNRTI:
        etravirine, and rilpivirine.

        Exclusion criteria:

        History of bilateral oophorectomy, ovarian dysfunction or no regular periods. CD4+ cell
        count &lt;200 cells/mm3 No current or uncontrolled thyroid, liver, or renal disease BMI &lt;40
        kg/m^2 Current pregnancy, breastfeeding or pregnancy within 30 days of enrollment.
        Depomedroxyprogesterone acetate injection (DMPA) within 180 days prior to study entry.

        Other hormonal therapies (e.g. oral contraceptive agents, Provera, vaginal ring,
        contraceptive patch, monthly contraceptive injection, hormone replacement therapy,
        anabolic therapies, including nandrolone decanoate or megestrol acetate) within the 21
        days prior to study entry.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>44 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jessica M Atrio, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Southern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jessica M Atrio, MD</last_name>
    <phone>917-721-6155</phone>
    <email>jessicaatrio@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Blanca Ovalle</last_name>
    <phone>323-896-6115</phone>
    <email>blanca.ovalle@med.usc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Los Angeles County Hospital University of Southern California (LAC USC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033-1029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica M Atrio, MD</last_name>
      <phone>917-721-6155</phone>
      <email>jessicaatrio@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Los Angeles County University of Southern California</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033-1029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica M Atrio, MD</last_name>
      <phone>917-721-6155</phone>
      <email>jessicaatrio@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 11, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 15, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Southern California</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jessica Maria Atrio</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>contraception</keyword>
  <keyword>mini pill</keyword>
  <keyword>norethindrone</keyword>
  <keyword>atazanavir</keyword>
  <keyword>ritonavir</keyword>
  <keyword>norvir</keyword>
  <keyword>reyataz</keyword>
  <keyword>pregnancy prevent</keyword>
  <keyword>birth control</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS</keyword>
  <keyword>antiviral</keyword>
  <keyword>antiretroviral</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Norethindrone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Norethindrone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Protease Inhibitors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ritonavir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atazanavir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Protease Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
