<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="158184">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02057393</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>247374</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02057393</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Infrared Lymphangiography as a Method of Sentinel Node Identification</brief_title>
  <acronym>SPY SN</acronym>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The initial treatment for most people with melanoma involves wide excision of the skin and
      sentinel node biopsy. As with other cancers, the status of the sentinel node provides
      important prognostic information to the patient and physician. Sentinel node biopsy was
      first developed using only a blue dye. Technetium99, a radioactive protein, was added later
      and provides the ability to image the patient and identify relevant lymph node basins. For
      the last 15 years or so, the standard method of SLN localization includes both tech99 and
      blue dye. While the rates of localization overall are excellent, these methods each have
      drawbacks. We are investigating a new method of finding sentinel nodes that uses a green dye
      that has an infrared signal. Our hypothesis is that indocyanine green (ICG) and real time
      lymphangiography is equivalent to technetium99 and methylene blue in identifying sentinel
      nodes (SLN) in patients with melanoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Bio-equivalence Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Equivalence of ICG and real time lymphangiography to technetium99 and blue dye in localizing sentinel nodes</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary outcome measure is the ability of indocyanine green (ICG) and real time lymphangiography, technetium99 and methylene blue to identify sentinel nodes (SLN) in patients with melanoma, and to compare each dye to the others.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">89</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Sentinel Node</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Indocyanine Green</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single arm study, each subject receives 0.9ml ICG, methylene blue and technetium 99.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Indocyanine green</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects receive 0.9ml of ICG subcutaneously about the primary melanoma. The ICG has an infrared signal that is detected with the SPY Elite system (Lifecell). The ICG travels through the lymphatics to the sentinel node.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Indocyanine Green</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IC-Green</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Technetium99</intervention_name>
    <description>Technetium99 is a standard, widely used radiopharmaceutical that is injected subcutaneoulsy about the primary melanoma site. Lymphoscintigraphy is performed to identify the draining nodal basin, and a gamma probe is used in the operating room to track the radioactive signal and find the sentinel node.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Indocyanine Green</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Technetium99 sulfur colloid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methylene blue</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects receive 0.5-2ml of methylene blue subcutaneously about the primary melanoma at the time of surgery. The sentinel node should turn blue, which is visible with the naked eye.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Indocyanine Green</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed melanoma.

          -  All patients with melanoma of the arm, leg or trunk who qualify for a sentinel node
             biopsy based on the characteristics of their primary tumor are eligible to
             participate. Patients with melanoma that is T1b or greater are recommended to have a
             sentinel node biopsy.

          -  Age &gt;18 years.  Melanoma is extremely uncommon in children, this disease is not
             relevant in this age group.

          -  The effects of IC-Green on the developing human fetus at the recommended therapeutic
             dose are unknown.  For this reason women of child-bearing potential and men must
             agree to use adequate contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control;
             abstinence) prior to study entry and for the duration of study participation.  Should
             a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is
             participating in this study, the patient should inform the treating physician
             immediately.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
             document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with melanoma on the head or neck are excluded

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to IC-Green, sodium iodide or other agents used in the study.

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Colette Pameijer, MD</last_name>
    <phone>717-531-5272</phone>
    <email>cpameijer@hmc.psu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn State Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hershey</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Colette Pameijer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rogerio Neves, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anna Leung, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jain V, Phillips BT, Conkling N, Pameijer C. Sentinel lymph node detection using laser-assisted indocyanine green dye lymphangiography in patients with melanoma. Int J Surg Oncol. 2013;2013:904214. doi: 10.1155/2013/904214. Epub 2013 Dec 8.</citation>
    <PMID>24382997</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 24, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Colette Pameijer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Sentinel node biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Indocyanine green</keyword>
  <keyword>Real time lymphangiography</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Methylene Blue</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
