<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="38437">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01827722</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ORION</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01827722</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ozurdex Versus Ranibizumab Versus Combination for Central Retinal Vein Occlusion</brief_title>
  <acronym>ORION</acronym>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Valley Retina Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Valley Retina Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      CRVO occurs when the vessels in the back of the eye become blocked. This creates a dangerous
      condition because the vessels are weak and prone to leakage. This results in the development
      of macular edema.

      Previous studies have shown that inflammatory mediators and growth factors, such as vascular
      endothelial growth factor (VEGF), are elevated in patients with macular edema associated
      with CRVO.

      Ozurdex® is approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and is available by
      prescription for macular edema following CRVO and branch retinal vein occlusion (BRVO). It
      is also indicated for the treatment of non-infectious uveitis affecting the posterior
      segment of the eye. The approved dosage is 0.7 mg.

      Ranibizumab (Lucentis®) is approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and is
      available by prescription for other eye disorders, such as wet age-related macular
      degeneration (AMD), macular edema following CRVO or BRVO, and diabetic macular edema (DME).
      The approved dosage for wet AMD and macular edema following CRVO/BROV is 0.5 mg given
      monthly. The approved dosage for DME is 0.3 mg given monthly.

      Dr. Gonzalez is conducting an investigational study on the safety and effectiveness of
      treating CRVO-associated Macular Edema with a combination of 0.7 mg of Ozurdex® and 0.5 mg
      Lucentis®, given as separate injections into the eye.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Best Corrected Visual Acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>At week 24 the mean change in best corrected visual acuity from baseline will be compared between the three groups: Ozurdex alone, Ranibizumab alone, and Ozurdex/Ranibizumab combination.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Macular Edema Following Central Retinal Vein Occlusion</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ozurdex Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ozurdex intravitreal injection (combination with monthly sham injection) administered at a 16 week interval beginning on Day 1 and ending at Week 16.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ranibizumab Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ranibizumab injection (combination with sham injections beginning on Day 1 and Week 16) administered at monthly intervals beginning Day 1 and ending at Week 20.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Ozurdex with Ranibizumab PRN</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ozurdex intravitreal injection administered at 16 week intervals beginning on Day 1 and ending at Week 16 with an initial IV Ranibizumab injection administered at Day 1, then treated with Ranibizumab according to reinjection parameters assessed monthly (in combination with sham if reinjection parameters are not met).
Reinjection Parameters:
10 letter drop from best corrected visual acuity or a 100 µm increase in central retinal thickness according to optical coherence tomography (Spectralis HRA + OCT).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ozurdex</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Ozurdex Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ranibizumab</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Ranibizumab Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combination Ozurdex with Ranibizumab PRN</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Ozurdex with Ranibizumab PRN</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults greater than or equal to 18 years of age with foveal center involved macular
             edema secondary to CRVO diagnosed within 12 months before the screening visit (CRVO
             is defined as an eye with retinal hemorrhage or other biomicroscopic evidence of RVO
             [eg telangiectatic capillary bed] and a dilated [or previously dilated] venous system
             in at least 3 quadrants of the retina drained by the affected vein.

          -  Best corrected visual acuity (ETDRS) letter score of 73 to 24 inclusive (20/40 to
             20/320) in the study eye at Screening and at Day 1

          -  Mean central subfield thickness greater than or equal to 310 µm from 2 OCT
             measurements (Spectralis HRA + OCT) at Screening and Day 1

          -  Willing and able to comply with clinic visits and study-related procedures

          -  Ability to provide signed informed consent form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of vitreoretinal surgery in the study eye or anticipated within 12 months of
             Day 1

          -  Current bilateral manifestation of CRVO

          -  Decrease in VA due to causes other than CRVO in the study eye

          -  Prior episode of RVO in study eye

          -  Afferent pupillary defect, obvious and unequivocal

          -  Greater than 10 letter improvement in BCVA between Screening and Day 1

          -  History or presence of exudative or dry macular degeneration

          -  Panretinal scatter photocoagulation or sector laser photocoagulation within 3 months
             prior to Day 1 or anticipated within 4 months after Day 1

          -  Anticipated laser photocoagulation for macular edema within 4 months after Day 1

          -  History of or evidence on examination of any diabetic retinopathy in the study eye

          -  CVA or MI within 3 months prior to Day 1

          -  Prior anti-VEGF treatment in study or fellow eye within 3 months before day 1 or
             systemic anti-VEGF or pro-VEGF treatment within 6 months prior to Day 1

          -  Ocular or periocular infections including active or suspected viral diseases of the
             cornea and conjunctiva, active epithelial herpes simples keratitis (dendritic
             keratitis), vaccinia, varicella, mycobacterial infections, and fungal diseases

          -  Glaucoma or current ocular hypertension requiring more than 1 medication to control
             IOP in the study eye or a history of steroid induced IOP increase in either eye

          -  Prior Ozurdex treatment in study eye within 4 months prior to Day 1

          -  Aphakic eyes with rupture of posterior lens capsule

          -  Anterior chamber IOL and rupture of posterior lens capsule

          -  Hypersensitivity to any components of Ozurdex or Ranibizumab in either eye

          -  History of other disease, metabolic dysfunction, physical exam finding, including
             renal failure on dialysis which renders the patient at high risk from treatment
             complications based on the judgment of the Investigator's at his/her discretion.

          -  Sexually active men or women of childbearing potential who are unwilling to practice
             adequate contraception during the study (adequate contraceptive measures include
             stable use of oral contraceptives or other prescription pharmaceutical contraceptives
             for 2 or more menstrual cycles prior to screening; intrauterine device; bilateral
             tubal ligation; vasectomy; condom plus contraceptive sponge, foam, or jelly, or
             diaphragm plus contraceptive sponge, foam, or jelly).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Valley Retina Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>McAllen</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78503</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dina Garcia</last_name>
      <phone>956-631-8875</phone>
      <email>dgarcia@vritx.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jessica Herrera</last_name>
      <phone>956-631-8875</phone>
      <email>jh@vritx.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Victor H Gonzalez, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 4, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Valley Retina Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Victor H. Gonzalez, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Macular edema</keyword>
  <keyword>Central retinal vein occlusion</keyword>
  <keyword>CRVO</keyword>
  <keyword>Retinal vein occlusion</keyword>
  <keyword>RVO</keyword>
  <keyword>Ozurdex</keyword>
  <keyword>Dexamethasone intravitreal implant</keyword>
  <keyword>Lucentis</keyword>
  <keyword>Ranibizumab</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Edema</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Macular Edema</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinal Vein Occlusion</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone 21-phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
