<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="163010">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01750996</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CIHR# 103146</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01750996</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Strongest Families Finland Canada: Family-based Prevention and Treatment Program of Early Childhood Disruptive Behavior</brief_title>
  <acronym>Fin-Can</acronym>
  <official_title>Strongest Families Finland Canada: Family-based Prevention and Treatment Program of Early Childhood Disruptive Behavior</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>IWK Health Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research  (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>IWK Health Centre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: IWK Health Centre</authority>
    <authority>Finland: Turku University Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of the Strongest Families Finland Canada project is to help parents develop skills
      to strengthen their families and reduce disruptive behavior in their 4 year old children.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project will have two phases, described below. The first part will be development of
      the web based program, the second part will be the implementation of the program in Finland.
      All participants will be recruited in Finland and all research activities will take place in
      Finland, by the Finnish Consortium. The Canadian Consortium will assist in funding and
      provide expert support.

      Part 1: Website development:

      The Strongest families program provides evidence based psychological and behavioural
      interventions to families with children with mild to moderate mental health problems.
      Parents work through a handbook with exercises, watch instructional videos and participate
      in weekly phone calls from a trained 'coach' (paraprofessional) to provide support, respond
      to parents' questions and highlight the skills included in a handbook. The preliminary
      analysis of a Strongest Families effectiveness trial based at the IWK Health Centre
      (Projects #2234, and #2654) and effect size reports from the IWK Strongest families Service
      Program suggest that Strongest Families is an effective treatment for Oppositional Defiant
      Disorder (ODD).

      Strongest Families is an adaptation of the COPE program. COPE is a large-group parent
      training program (average 25 families per group)  that has been evaluated and used in many
      centres across Canada, the United States and Europe. It was developed at McMaster University
      by a team led by Dr. Charles Cunningham (one of the investigators on this submission). The
      groups use a coping modelling problem solving approach to skill acquisition which encourages
      parents to discuss the solution to common problems, collaborate in the formulation of child
      management strategies, share successes, and provide supportive feedback. Large group
      discussions may also provide more information regarding normal child development and a
      greater perspective on common child management difficulties than clinic/individual parent
      training .

      The benefits for parents participating in COPE group sessions are many, but the burden of
      traveling to receive services can impede attendance, especially for families in rural areas.
      One solution to this issue would be to adapt individualized Strongest Families to a more
      accessible mode.

      We propose to develop a web-based version of Strongest Families in preparation for a
      Randomized Control Trial (RCT) in Finland. All components of web site will be developed
      using a collaborative approach with active participation by all members of the research
      team. We will review each of the component as it is developed. We estimate a minimum of
      three rounds of testing for each component. The program will be evaluated using the
      user-interface so that we review the website and all its various features in a manner that
      simulates the actual parent experience. No qualitative or quantitative data will be recorded
      for this phase of the project. No participants will be recruited for this phase of the
      trial.

      The  web version of Strongest Families will have two components. First, is a personalized
      website that tracks and uses all activities and interactions to modify the Strongest
      Families intervention as the user progresses through the sessions. Interactions include
      questions, surveys, and polls which will be asked periodically throughout the program (for
      examples see Appendix A).  Second, the parenting skills curriculum will be based on our
      Strongest Families program, an approach derived from programs developed by members of this
      team18,19. Third,  parents , using pseudonyms, will participate in a discussion board/blog
      to exchange ideas. Pseudonyms will be chosen by the participant, but will not include any
      identifying elements.

      Part 2: Randomized trial  (Conducted in Finland, no Canadian recruitment)

      The centerpiece project will be a population-based RCT of high risk 4 year olds attending
      well-child clinics in Turku and environs. Families of children scoring at or above the 80th
      percentile on the BCFPI scale measuring ODD will be offered participation in a 2 arm trial.
      All data will be collected in Finland and stored at the University of Turku. All
      forms/scripts/ measures will be administered in Finnish or Swedish. This project has been
      approved by the Intermunicipal Hospital District of Southwest Finland. The Canadian team
      will provide expert and financial support.

      Treatment Group: Families randomized to Web-Enhanced Strongest Families (described above)
      will receive the website program described above.

      Control Group: Families randomized to enhanced Usual Care will receive a 45 minute
      intervention in the clinic from a trained nurse and a brochure describing positive parenting
      strategies and ways of managing parental stress.

      Randomization: (1:1 treatment: control) will be conducted using central electronic
      randomization. Participants will be stratified by clinic (to balance social class) and child
      sex.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Strengths &amp; Difficulties Questionnaire (To measure change from baseline to 5 &amp; 12 months)</measure>
    <time_frame>To measure change from baseline to 5 &amp; 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To measure child outcome change from baseline to 5 &amp; 12 months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale Short Form (DASS-21)- Finnish</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 5 &amp; 12months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Parental stress changes from baseline will be measured over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CHild Behaviour Checklist (to measure change from baseline)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measure change from baseline at 5 &amp; 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure of child behavioural change from baseline to 5 &amp; 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alabama Parenting Questionnaire (To measure change from baseline to 5 &amp; 21 months)</measure>
    <time_frame>To measure change from baseline to 5 &amp; 12 months post randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure parental parenting practice changes from baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Barkley's Quick-CHeck for Adult Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) (to measure change from baseline)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measure change from baseline to 5&amp;12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To measure parental ADHD symptom changes form baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child Behaviour Checklist- Teacher version (to measure change since baseline)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measure change from Baseline to 5 &amp; 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To measure child behaviour changes at daycare from baseline to 5 &amp; 12 months post randomization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction measure</measure>
    <time_frame>5-6months post randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To measure satisfaction with Intervention and website information</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Behaviour Disorders (Oppositional Defiance)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care control (Parenting tips)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to usual care will have access to a brief information website containing brief parenting tips but will not receive Strongest Families Intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Strongest Families</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Strongest Families intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Strongest Families</intervention_name>
    <description>Behavioural intervention</description>
    <arm_group_label>Strongest Families</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Child is 4 years old at time of recruitment

          -  Parent/guardian has access to a computer and the internet

          -  Parent/guardian is comfortable reading at a Grade 5 level

          -  Child meets  screening criteria (SDQ score of 4 or more with some problems per impact
             score)

               -  Child has had behavioural challenges for the last 6 months

               -  Parent has access to phone in home

               -  Parent speaks/writes Finnish

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  - Has received or is receiving behavioral treatment (parent training) before

          -  Diagnosis of:

               -  Autism or a Pervasive development disorder (PDD)

               -  Down's syndrome

               -  Fetal Alcohol Syndrome

               -  Mental retardation

               -  Genetic diagnosis that will lead to mental retardation

               -  Major mental health disorder (e.g., depression, psychosis)

          -  Child is not speaking using a sentence

          -  Child is deaf or blind
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick J McGrath, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>IWK Health Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>patricia Pottie, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>902-442-9521</phone>
    <email>ppottie@strongestfamilies.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Adam Cummins</last_name>
    <phone>902-470-7401</phone>
    <email>acummins@iwk.nshealth.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Turku, Finland</name>
      <address>
        <city>TUrku</city>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andre Sorander</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 11, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 14, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
