<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1309">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01664000</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CTIX 12-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12-151</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01664000</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Safety, Pharmacokinetic and Pharmacodynamic Study of Kevetrin in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Open-Label, Dose-Escalation, Safety, Pharmacokinetic and Pharmacodynamic Study of Kevetrin (Thioureidobutyronitrile) Administered Intravenously, in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cellceutix Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cellceutix Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In the laboratory, Kevetrin activates p53, a tumor suppressor protein that has an important
      role in protecting the body. p53 functions by activating proteins that repair DNA and kill
      cells that have genetic mutations such as in cancers. Research experiments showed that when
      cancer cells were treated with Kevetrin, it activated p53 which induced p21, a protein that
      inhibits cancer cell growth. p53 also induced PUMA (p53 up-regulated modulator of
      apoptosis), a protein that causes tumor cell death. Because of these activities, slowing
      cancer cell growth and causing cancer cell death, Kevetrin may help to treat tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Kevetrin was found to be effective in pre-clinical studies of human xenograft tumor models
      and was reasonably well-tolerated at therapeutic doses in the non-clinical animal studies.
      Kevetrin was also effective in multi-drug resistant tumor models; therefore, Kevetrin has
      the potential to treat tumors that have become resistant to standard chemotherapy. This
      trial will determine tolerance in humans and, possibly, efficacy with a Phase I, open-label,
      dose-escalation, safety, pharmacokinetic, and pharmacodynamic study of Kevetrin, in adult
      patients with solid tumors.

      The primary objectives are the following:

        -  To determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of Kevetrin.

        -  To determine the dose limiting toxicities (DLT) of Kevetrin.

        -  To establish a safe dose level of Kevetrin that can be used for future studies.

      The secondary objectives are to determine the following:

        -  The pharmacokinetics of Kevetrin in humans.

        -  Observe for evidence of antitumor activity following administration of Kevetrin.

        -  If Kevetrin induces changes in the biomarker p21 in peripheral blood lymphocytes.

        -  If there is a pharmacodynamic relationship between the plasma concentrations of
           Kevetrin and a clinical or cellular effect.

      During each 4 week cycle, each patient will receive three weekly doses of Kevetrin given as
      a 1 hour intravenous infusion followed by a 1 week off-treatment period. Following each
      dose, each patient will be monitored.  If the patients have acceptable safety and tolerance,
      Kevetrin will be given once weekly for a total of 3 weeks. During each cycle patients will
      be evaluated for safety, tolerance, and Dose-Limiting Toxicity (DLT) that occur during a
      cycle.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) of Kevetrin</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>A dose will be declared the MTD if at least 1 patient out of 6 patients experience a dose limiting toxicity (DLT) at the highest dose level below the maximally administered dose. Once an MTD has been established, up to 12 additional patients may be enrolled at the MTD dose level for confirmation of safety.
The maximally administered dose is if 1 or more of 6 patients experience a DLT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Limiting Toxicities (DLT) of Kevetrin.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The definition of dose limiting toxicity (DLT) is in accord with the NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events v4.0 (CTCAE).  Dose limiting toxicity will be defined as:
Grade 3 or 4 neutropenia complicated by fever, or greater than 38.5°C documented infection, or Grade 4 neutropenia of greater than 7 days duration
Grade 4 thrombocytopenia or grade 3 thrombocytopenia complicated by hemorrhage
Any grade greater than 3 non-hematologic toxicity unless there is clear alternative evidence that the adverse event (AE) was not caused by Kevetrin
Grade 3 diarrhea, nausea, or vomiting may be excluded from dose-limiting toxicities provided that the maximum time limit for supportive measures is 48 hours.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic Profile of Kevetrin</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1   Pre-dose, 30 minutes after starting the infusion, 1 hr, 1 hr 10 min, 1 hr 20 min, 1 hr 30 min, 1 hr 45 min, 2 hr, 2 hr 30 min, 3 hr, 4 hr, 5 hr, 7 hr, and 24 hr after the initiation of the infusion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The pharmacokinetics (PK) of Kevetrin will be determined for all patients enrolled in the study on Day 1 of Cycle 1 and Day 15 of Cycle 2. Blood samples will be obtained  before dosing, 30 minutes after starting the infusion, 1 hr, 1 hr 10 min, 1 hr 20 min, 1 hr 30 min, 1 hr 45 min, 2 hr, 2 hr 30 min, 3 hr, 4 hr, 5 hr, 7 hr, and 24 hr after the initiation of the infusion.
The pharmacokinetic profile will be analyzed by standard noncompartmental methods to provide estimated values of the pharmacokinetic parameters and associated variables, such as area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) and peak plasma concentration (Cmax) of Kevetrin. Associations between pharmacokinetic variables and drug-related toxicities will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic Profile of Kevetrin</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 15   Pre-dose, 30 minutes after starting the infusion, 1 hr, 1 hr 10 min, 1 hr 20 min, 1 hr 30 min, 1 hr 45 min, 2 hr, 2 hr 30 min, 3 hr, 4 hr, 5 hr, 7 hr, and 24 hr after the initiation of the infusion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The pharmacokinetics (PK) of Kevetrin will be determined for all patients enrolled in the study on Day 1 of Cycle 1 and Day 15 of Cycle 2. Blood samples will be obtained  before dosing, 30 minutes after starting the infusion, 1 hr, 1 hr 10 min, 1 hr 20 min, 1 hr 30 min, 1 hr 45 min, 2 hr, 2 hr 30 min, 3 hr, 4 hr, 5 hr, 7 hr, and 24 hr after the initiation of the infusion.
The pharmacokinetic profile will be analyzed by standard noncompartmental methods to provide estimated values of the pharmacokinetic parameters and associated variables, including area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) and peak plasma concentration (Cmax) of Kevetrin. Associations between pharmacokinetic variables and drug-related toxicities will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in tumor size</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in tumor size based on RECIST criteria version 1.1. using MRI, CT scan, and/or standard of care imaging</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in tumor size</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in tumor size based on RECIST criteria version 1.1. using MRI, CT scan, and/or standard of care imaging</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in tumor size</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in tumor size based on RECIST criteria version 1.1. using MRI, CT scan, and/or standard of care imaging</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in serum tumor marker</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 1 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A decrease in a tumor marker in the serum may also suggest evidence of anti-tumor efficacy. The following tumor markers will be evaluated: Carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA), Cancer Antigen 125 (CA125), Cancer Antigen 19-9 (CA19-9), Cancer Antigen 15-3 (CA15-3), Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA), or other appropriate markers.  The choice of the individual tumor markers will be based on the type of tumor of the patient and the testing that has preceded the patient's participation in this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in serum tumor marker</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 2 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A decrease in a tumor marker in the serum may also suggest evidence of anti-tumor efficacy. The following tumor markers will be evaluated: Carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA), Cancer Antigen 125 (CA125), Cancer Antigen 19-9 (CA19-9), Cancer Antigen 15-3 (CA15-3), Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA), or other appropriate markers.  The choice of the individual tumor markers will be based on the type of tumor of the patient and the testing that has preceded the patient's participation in this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in serum tumor marker</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A decrease in a tumor marker in the serum may also suggest evidence of anti-tumor efficacy. The following tumor markers will be evaluated: Carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA), Cancer Antigen 125 (CA125), Cancer Antigen 19-9 (CA19-9), Cancer Antigen 15-3 (CA15-3), Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA), or other appropriate markers.  The choice of the individual tumor markers will be based on the type of tumor of the patient and the testing that has preceded the patient's participation in this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in serum tumor marker</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A decrease in a tumor marker in the serum may also suggest evidence of anti-tumor efficacy. The following tumor markers will be evaluated: Carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA), Cancer Antigen 125 (CA125), Cancer Antigen 19-9 (CA19-9), Cancer Antigen 15-3 (CA15-3), Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA), or other appropriate markers.  The choice of the individual tumor markers will be based on the type of tumor of the patient and the testing that has preceded the patient's participation in this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in serum tumor marker</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 5 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A decrease in a tumor marker in the serum may also suggest evidence of anti-tumor efficacy. The following tumor markers will be evaluated: Carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA), Cancer Antigen 125 (CA125), Cancer Antigen 19-9 (CA19-9), Cancer Antigen 15-3 (CA15-3), Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA), or other appropriate markers.  The choice of the individual tumor markers will be based on the type of tumor of the patient and the testing that has preceded the patient's participation in this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in serum tumor marker</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A decrease in a tumor marker in the serum may also suggest evidence of anti-tumor efficacy. The following tumor markers will be evaluated: Carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA), Cancer Antigen 125 (CA125), Cancer Antigen 19-9 (CA19-9), Cancer Antigen 15-3 (CA15-3), Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA), or other appropriate markers.  The choice of the individual tumor markers will be based on the type of tumor of the patient and the testing that has preceded the patient's participation in this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the biomarker p21 in peripheral blood lymphocytes</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 7 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For biomarker analysis, p21 expression, assayed by qPCR, in peripheral blood lymphocytes after Kevetrin administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the biomarker p21 in peripheral blood lymphocytes</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For biomarker analysis, p21 expression, assayed by qPCR, in peripheral blood lymphocytes after Kevetrin administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Kevetrin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>thioureidobutyronitrile intravenous once/week for 3 weeks/ cycle</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>thioureidobutyronitrile</intervention_name>
    <description>Kevetrin (thioureidobutyronitrile)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Kevetrin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kevetrin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males or females, greater than or equal to 18 years of age, of any race or ethnicity,
             who can provide written Informed Consent.

          -  Patients with a life expectancy of at least 3 months.

          -  Pathologically confirmed solid tumor, locally advanced or metastatic, either
             refractory after standard therapy, or for which no effective curative or surgical
             treatment options are available

          -  Must have measurable disease on baseline imaging (e.g., CT scan, PET, MRI) per RECIST
             1.1 criteria to meet eligibility.

          -  ECOG performance status less than or equal to 1

          -  Acceptable liver function:

          -  Bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 times the upper limit of normal

          -  AST (SGOT), ALT (SGPT)less than or equal to 2.5 times the upper limit of normal, less
             than 5 times the upper limit if there are liver metastases.

          -  Acceptable renal function:

          -  Serum creatinine within normal limits, or calculated creatinine clearance greater
             than or equal to 60 mL/min/1.73m2 by the Cockcroft Gault equation or 24 hr urine
             creatinine clearance.

          -  Acceptable hematologic status:

          -  ANC greater than or equal to 1500 cells/mm3. To be eligible for a new cycle, ANC must
             be greater than or equal to 1000 cells/mm3

          -  Platelet count greater than or equal to 100,000/mm3. To be eligible for a new
             treatment cycle, platelet count must be greater than or equal to 75,000 /mm3.

          -  Hemoglobin greater than or equal to 9 g/dL

          -  Acceptable coagulation status:

          -  PT less than or equal to 1.5 times the upper limit

          -  PTT less than or equal to 1.5 times the upper limit

          -  All males in the study must agree to use condoms during sex to prevent spillage of
             semen for the duration of the study and for 3 months after the patient leaves the
             study.

          -  All females in the study must not be pregnant or breast feeding and not planning to
             become pregnant or breast feed for the duration of the study, and for at least three
             months after study completion.

          -  All women of childbearing potential must commit to using a double barrier method of
             contraception (e.g., diaphragm and condom), an intrauterine device (IUD), or sexual
             abstinence for the duration of the study and for at least three months after study
             completion.

          -  Serum pregnancy test for women of child bearing potential must be negative at entry
             into study.

          -  Written voluntary informed consent: the patient is capable of complying with the
             requirements of the written ICF and complying with protocol requirements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of significant disease that in the Investigator's opinion would put the
             patient at high risk on the trial.

          -  Cognitive impairment sufficient to render the patient incapable of giving informed
             consent.

          -  History of clinically significant psychiatric illness that would prevent the patient
             from providing a valid ICF and complying with protocol requirements.

          -  Unwillingness or inability to comply with procedures required in this protocol.

          -  History or presence of alcoholism or drug abuse within the past 2 years.

          -  Patients who have had a major surgical procedure within the past 6 weeks.

          -  History of HIV, hepatitis B, or hepatitis C.

          -  Active, uncontrolled bacterial, viral, or fungal infections requiring systemic
             therapy.

          -  Women of childbearing potential who are lactating, pregnant or there is the
             likelihood of becoming pregnant within the coming 12 months; a positive serum
             beta-hCG test at time of screening for entry into study.

          -  New York Heart Association Class III or IV, cardiac disease, myocardial infarction
             within the past 6 months, unstable arrhythmia, or evidence of ischemia on ECG.

          -  Patients with a mean QTc interval greater than 480ms are excluded. Avoid concomitant
             administration of agents that prolong the QT interval, except at the discretion of
             the investigator. If advised, patients should discontinue the use of these agents at
             least 2 weeks before the study begins. No uncontrolled arrhythmias.

          -  Patients who are currently receiving other investigational agents.

          -  Participation in a study of an investigational drug within 4 weeks prior to the
             planned first day of study drug administration.

          -  Patients who have undergone radiation within the past 4 weeks.

          -  Treatment with molecularly targeted agents within the past 3 weeks prior to planned
             first study drug administration. Patients who were receiving standard chemotherapy or
             experimental therapies must wait 4 weeks from their last dose prior to the planned
             first study drug administration. Patients treated with nitrosoureas or mitomycin C
             must wait 6 weeks from their last dose prior to the planned first study drug
             administration.

          -  Patients with known brain metastases may be excluded from this clinical trial because
             of their poor prognosis and because they often develop progressive neurologic
             dysfunction that would confound the evaluation of neurologic and other adverse
             events. However, patients may be eligible if scans show limited disease or repeat
             scans show stable disease in the opinion of the investigator and patients have no ill
             effect from the metastases.

          -  Herbal supplements, e.g., Saint John's Wort, Milk Thistle, are prohibited 1 week
             prior to the planned first study drug administration, during the clinical study, and
             up to the time that the patient is discharged from the study.  Use of Senekot is
             permitted.

          -  Patients who have been exposed to medications, herbal preparations, or foods known to
             be predominant CYP450 2C9, 2C19, 2D6, 3A4/5 substrates, strong inhibitors or inducers
             within 7 days of planned first study treatment day

          -  Patients who in the opinion of the Investigator would not be able to provide reliable
             study data or be available for study follow-up.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Krishna Menon, PhD VMD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Cellceutix Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber / Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center / Harvard Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrew Wolanski</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-6623</phone>
      <email>awolanski@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Geoffrey Shapiro, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James W Mier, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sara Tolaney, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nicole Chau, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leena Gandhi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Hilton, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrea Bullock, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Butrynski, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jason Luke, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Cleary, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 2, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>apoptosis</keyword>
  <keyword>p53</keyword>
  <keyword>p21</keyword>
  <keyword>Caspase3</keyword>
  <keyword>PARP</keyword>
  <keyword>MDM2</keyword>
  <keyword>PUMA</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
