<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="21530">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01686412</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HSL 2012/01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01686412</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Determination of Autonomic Responses to Exposure to Electromagnetic Fields With Low Energy Modulated Frequency</brief_title>
  <official_title>Determination of Autonomic Responses to Exposure to Electromagnetic Fields With Low Energy Modulated Frequency in Patients With Breast and Advanced Hepatocellular Cancer.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Sirio-Libanes</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Sirio-Libanes</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Brazil: National Committee of Ethics in Research</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an exploratory study, national, unicentric, double-blind, to be conducted at the
      Institute for Teaching and Research of the Hospital Sírio-Libanês in order to detect
      possible autonomic responses resulting from Exposure to Electromagnetic Fields of Low Energy
      (EEFLE) in healthy subjects and in patients with advanced hepatocellular carcinoma or in
      patients with advanced breast carcinoma. Autonomic responses have been described in patients
      with cancer during the exposure of EEFLE. This autonomic response, or biofeedback, due to
      exposure to EEFLE seems to be associated with a specific set of modulation frequencies when
      applied to patients with malignancies. Moreover, healthy individuals exposed to modulated
      EEFLE a specific set of frequency do not appear to autonomic response. Biofeedback is
      defined by a change in amplitude of the radial pulse during exposure to EEFLE, modulated
      according to a set of specific frequencies. This phenomenon is not yet fully elucidated. In
      exploratory survey of one patient was observed a change of the pressure pulse immediately
      after the start of and during exposure to EEFLE, modulated according to a set of specific
      frequencies recorded by digital photoplethysmography. This study aims to evaluate an
      autonomic response in individuals exposed in a single moment, by electromagnetic fields.
      This study does not intend to study a diagnostic or therapeutic procedure. For this reason,
      evolutive clinical data will not be considered during and after the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Health Services Research</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Autonomic response monitoring (blood pressure digital and manual monitoring)</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular electronic monitoring (digital photoplethysmography and electrocardiography)</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Baroreflex sensitivity (by the method of sequence)</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oncology patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Electromagnetic Fields of Low Energy (EEFLE)</intervention_name>
    <description>Are employed three sets of programs of different frequencies are modulated specifically for each group of patients in accordance with diagnostic (hepatocellular carcinoma, breast carcinoma and healthy subjects). These frequencies ranging between 0.1 and 114.000Hz.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Oncology patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Healthy volunteers:

          -  Should be considered healthy, with no known relevant comorbidity.

          -  Patients should not be suffering from active malignancy or history of malignancy in
             the past.

          -  Must be over 18 years.

          -  Must have ability to understand and provide a written informed consent.

        Patients with hepatocellular carcinoma:

          -  Patients must be diagnosed with inoperable HCC.

          -  Presence of primary tumor or metastatic at the time of the procedure.

          -  Patients with liver cirrhosis should be restricted to Child-Pugh A or B.

          -  Patients with AFP&gt; 400ng/ml and image feature does not require histopathological
             confirmation. However, in patients with active serology B virus, this value must be
             greater than AFP 4000 ng / ml. The remaining patients should have histological
             confirmation of HCC.

          -  Patients may be under observation or treatment in the presence of systemic or
             intra-hepatic.

          -  Must have ability to understand and provide a written informed consent.

        Patients with Ductal Carcinoma Breast

          -  Patients must have a diagnosis of breast ductal carcinoma inoperable.

          -  The presence of the primary tumor or metastatic during the procedure.

          -  Patients may be under observation or in the presence of systemic or hormonal
             treatment only.

          -  Must have ability to understand to provide a written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Can not stop antihypertensive medications or beta-blockers for at least 48 hours or
             being in possession of a pacemaker or other implantable device.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women.

          -  Smaller than 18 years.

          -  Patients undergoing radiotherapy treatment or up to 2 weeks of discontinuation.

          -  Inability to understand and provide written informed consent.

          -  Liver cirrhosis Child Pugh C.

          -  Patients without a definite diagnosis.

          -  Absence of the primary tumor or metastatic during the procedure.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Frederico Costa</last_name>
    <phone>+551131558800</phone>
    <email>frederico.costa@hsl.org.br</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Sírio-Libanês</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Frederico Costa</last_name>
      <phone>+551131558800</phone>
      <email>frederico.costa@hsl.org.br</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 2, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 12, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Sirio-Libanes</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Frederico Perego Costa</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Attending physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatocellular carcinoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
