<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35146">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01889420</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>INST 1304</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01889420</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase I Trial of Everolimus, Pomalidomide and Dexamethasone in Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Trial of Everolimus, Pomalidomide and Dexamethasone in Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New Mexico Cancer Care Alliance</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New Mexico Cancer Care Alliance</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being conducted to test the possibility that a combination of three drugs,
      pomalidomide and everolimus with dexamethasone, may improve patient responses when compared
      with use of either drug alone, with dexamethasone in refractory/relapsed multiple myeloma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Given that pomalidomide is an FDA approved drug for patients with relapsed or progressive
      myeloma, and everolimus has been shown to have single agent activity in relapsed myeloma, it
      seems reasonable to combine these two active drugs in patients with relapsed/refractory
      disease. Given that low dose dexamethasone dramatically improved the response rate of
      pomalidomide, this drug will be added to the combination.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dosage (MTD)(Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Our primary objective is to determine the Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) for combination therapy with pomalidomide, dexamethasone and everolimus in patients with refractory or relapsed multiple myeloma, in a maximum of 36 patients. This will be determined by first identifying the dose level at which &gt; 30% of patients experienced a Dose Limiting Toxicity (DLT) according to CTCAE v. 4.0, over a 28 day cycle. The dose combination (or MTD) subsequently used for the (confirmatory) extension portion of this study  will be defined as one dosage level below the DLT dosage combination. We will also prepare a descriptive assessment (using counts) of any therapeutic activity noted in our various Phase I cohorts. Activity will be measured by plasma concentrations of SPEP and free K/L light chains after each 28-day cycle</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity Profile</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the toxicity profile of pomalidomide, dexamethasone and everolimus in patients with myeloma in the phase 1 setting, as described by specific adverse event rates among patients experiencing &gt; grade 3 hematologic events (lasting &gt;7 days) or grades 3-5 non-hematologic adverse events, according to CTCAE v. 4.0, over a 28 day cycle. Specific events will be described as the numbers of patients experiencing them within each treatment cohort.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-tumor Effect</measure>
    <time_frame>3.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe the anti-tumor effect (&gt; partial response) of combination treatment with pomalidomide, everolimus and dexamethasone at initial dose levels (initial phase I cohorts), as measured by plasma concentrations of SPEP and free K/L light chains after each 28-day cycle. For this phase, since different dosing combinations will be used, we will use descriptive statistics for this measurement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate (RR)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine the overall response rate (RR), as defined by the ratio of patients with a &gt; Partial Responses (PR), in this phase 1 study in patients with relapsed or recurrent multiple myeloma who complete the extension portion of the trial and who were treated at equivalent dosages level combinations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma in Relapse</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Following determination of the maximum tolerated dosages in the phase I portion of this study, all patients enrolled in the extension portion will receive the predetermined dosage combination of pomalidomide, everolimus and dexamethasone. Cycles will span 28 days. Dosage schedules will be: 1.Everolimus daily for 28 days of a 28 day cycle; 2.	Pomalidomide daily for 21 days of a 28 day cycle and 3.Dexamethasone once weekly (d1,8,15,22) of a 28 day cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combination pomalidomide, everolimus and dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Pomalyst</other_name>
    <other_name>Affinitor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Age &gt; 18  years

        Relapsed or progressive multiple myeloma (Progressive Disease), defined as a 25 percent
        increase from the lowest response value in ANY of the following:

        Serum M-protein (abs increase ≥0.5 g/dL)

        Urine M-protein (abs increase of ≥200 mg/24 hours)

        Bone marrow plasma cell percentage (at least 10%absolute increase) in absence of
        measurable M protein

        Difference in kappa &amp; lambda FLC levels (ratio must be abnormal; absolute change must be
        &gt;10 mg/dL)

        Patients are also considered to have progressive disease when:

        New bone or soft tissue lesions (eg, plasmacytomas) are identified; or

        There is an unequivocal increase in the size of previously existing lesions; or

        The development of an otherwise unexplained serum calcium &gt;11.5 mg/dL is also a marker of
        PD

        Have received 1, but no more than 4 prior treatment regimens or lines of therapy for MM
        (Induction therapy followed by stem cell transplant &amp; consolidation/maintenance therapy
        will be considered as one line of therapy)

        ECOG Performance status 0 - 2

        Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks

        Evaluable multiple myeloma with, at least one of the following, assessed within 21 days
        prior to randomization:

        Serum M-protein ≥ 0.5 g/dL, or Urine M-protein ≥ 200 mg/24 hour, or

        In absence of detectable serum or urine M-protein, serum free light chain (SFLC) &gt; 100
        mg/L (involved light chain) and/or an abnormal kappa/lamda ratio  (&gt;4:1 or &lt;2:1), or

        Monoclonal plasma cells in a bone marrow biopsy/aspirate of &gt;5%

        Adequate organ and marrow function as defined below:

          -  Leukocytes   ≥ 2,500/mcL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets   ≥ 100,000/mcL

          -  Total bilirubin   &lt; 2  X ULN

          -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SPGT) ≤ 2.5 X ULN

          -  Creatinine   &lt; 1.5 X  ULN

        Contraception Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate
        contraception prior to study entry, for duration of study, and for 90 days after
        completion of therapy.

        A female of child-bearing potential is considered to be any woman (regardless of sexual
        orientation, having undergone a tubal ligation, or remaining celibate by choice) who meets
        the following criteria:

          -  No hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy; or

          -  Not naturally postmenopausal for at least 12 consecutive months (i.e., has had menses
             at any time in the preceding 12 consecutive months).

        Male patients must use an effective barrier method of contraception during study and for 3
        months following the last dose if sexually active with a female of child-bearing
        potential.

        No prior therapy with pomalidomide or everolimus.

        Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 4 weeks prior to entering the study or those
        who have not recovered from adverse events due to agents administered more than 4 weeks
        earlier.

        Receiving any other investigational agents. Minimum 4 week &quot;washout&quot; period is required.

        History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
        composition to pomalidomide, everolimus, or other agents used in the study.

        Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
        infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
        arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
        study requirements.

        Pregnant or nursing (due to the rick for congenital abnormalities and the potential of
        this regimen to harm nursing infants).

        Glucocorticoid therapy (prednisone &gt; 30 mg/day or equivalent) within 14 days prior to
        randomization.

        POEMS syndrome (polyneuropathy, organomegaly, endocrinopathy,  monoclonal protein, and
        skin changes).

        Plasma cell leukemia or circulating plasma cells ≥ 2 × 109/L.

        Waldenstrom's Macroglobulinemia.

        Patients with known amyloidosis.

        Focal radiation therapy within 7 days prior to randomization. Radiation therapy to an
        extended field involving a significant volume of bone marrow within 21 days prior to
        randomization (i.e., prior radiation must have been to less than 30% of the bone marrow).

        Immunotherapy within 21 days prior to randomization.

        Myelodysplastic syndrome

        Major surgery (excluding kyphoplasty) within 28 days

        Known cirrhosis.

        Significant neuropathy (Grades 3 to 4, or Grade 2 with pain) within 14 days

        Ongoing graft-vs-host disease.

        Using CYP3A4 inhibitors such as Ketoconazole, Ritonavir, Itraconazole, Erythromycin,
        Clarithromycin, Nelfinavir, Fluconazole, Amioderone, Cyclosporine, Diltiazem,
        nefazadone,fluvoxamine, verapamil, chloramphenicol, Indinavir or saquinavir within 7 days
        of treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ian Rabinowitz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of New Mexico Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ducinea D Quintana, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of New Mexico Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Valerie Parks, RN</last_name>
    <phone>505-925-0398</phone>
    <email>vparks@salud.unm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNM Cancer Research and Treatment Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <state>New Mexico</state>
        <zip>87131</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dulcinea Quintana, MD</last_name>
      <phone>505-925-0405</phone>
      <email>dcandelaria@salud.unm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Valerie Parks, RN</last_name>
      <phone>055-925-0390</phone>
      <email>vparks@salud.unm.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dulcinea Quintana, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ian Rabinowitz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.unm.edu</url>
    <description>UNM Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nmcca.org</url>
    <description>New Mexico Cancer Care Alliance</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 26, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>relapse</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory</keyword>
  <keyword>relapsed</keyword>
  <keyword>pomalidomide</keyword>
  <keyword>Pomalyst</keyword>
  <keyword>everolimus</keyword>
  <keyword>Affinitor</keyword>
  <keyword>dexamethasone</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone 21-phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
