<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="88855">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01662752</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C/32/2012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01662752</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lymphatic Mapping for Sentinel Node Identification and Analysis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study to Assess Near Infrared Laparoscopy With Indocyanine Green (ICG) for Intraoperative Lymphatic Imaging and Sentinel Lymph Node Identification During Standard Surgical Resection for Colonic Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>North West London Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Imperial College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main objective of this study is to determine whether the first (sentinel) lymph nodes in
      the drainage pathway of colonic tumour can be detected at the time of surgery using a new
      technique. The detection method is to inject a fluorescent dye (indocyanine green) adjacent
      to the tumour. The dye will then be seen as it fluoresces in the light form the near
      infrared spectrum that can be used at the time of the laparoscopic (keyhole) surgery. An
      endoscope is placed in the colon (colonoscopy) during surgery and the tracer fluorescent
      agent is injected around the tumour. The mesentery in which the lymph nodes draining the
      tumour are located will then be examined by laparoscopy as it is expected that fluorescence
      will be identified within approximately 5 minutes of the injection.  The first lymph node or
      nodes that take up the fluorescent dye will then be marked by placing a clip or a stitch by
      them. After the surgery has been completed and colon removed all lymph nodes can be examined
      microscopically by the pathologist, paying a particular attention to whether any tumour
      cells are present in the sentinel lymph nodes and whether the presence or the absence of
      tumour cells in that node accurately reflects the tumour status of the rest of the specimen.

      If this pilot demonstrates that sentinel lymph nodes can be reliably detected, we have
      developed a technique which allows us to remove a small area (less than 5 cm) of the colon.
      Using this procedure should decrease complications following traditional surgery. We however
      also need a method that allows accurate assessment of the lymph nodes draining the tumour.
      This pilot trial will examine our ability to detect such 'sentinel' lymph nodes so that we
      can use their status (positive for cancer cells or negative) to determine whether a smaller
      operation such as full thickness localised excision is adequate treatment for the patient
      and that they can avoid a larger operation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. BACKGROUND AND RATIONALE

      1.1. Colorectal cancer Colorectal cancer is the third commonest cancer and second highest
      cause of cancer death in the UK. Introduction of the National Bowel Cancer Screening Program
      and increasing awareness of symptoms of colorectal cancer will lead to an increase in
      numbers of cancers detected at an early stage of the disease.  Standard surgical management,
      however, remains unchanged and that is segmental colectomy with en bloc mesenteric resection
      of the regional lymph nodes as the metastatic status of these nodes remains the most
      important factor for determining adjuvant treatment.

      This of course was appropriate when the majority of the patients diagnosed with colorectal
      cancer presented with symptomatic, locally advanced disease. Our practice, however, needs to
      be reconsidered in the view of the recently published data from screening centres. Pilot
      results demonstrate a significant shift towards an earlier stage of the disease in the
      screened population and suggests that, in future, up to 50% of screen detected-cancers will
      be T1 or T2 (i.e. early stage disease) 1. Less than 15% of patients with T1 and T2 disease
      have nodal involvement 2 but current radiological techniques are not sensitive enough to
      identify these patients pre-operatively. Instead, major surgery is performed in all patients
      with T1 and T2 stage colonic cancer, and in up to 85%, en bloc mesenteric resection provides
      no therapeutic benefit, as they have node negative disease. Major resection also exposes
      patients to a significant risk of morbidity and mortality, along with late side effects.

      The concept of sentinel lymph node mapping (SLNM) in colorectal cancer is not new and
      although it has not had the same impact as in the clinical care of breast cancer, melanoma,
      and more recently gastric cancer 3-6, some expert centres have suggested that it may be
      clinically relevant 7, 8. The technique is based on the principle that the first possible
      sites of metastasis along the lymphatic drainage route from the primary lesion are known as
      sentinel lymph nodes (SLNs) and these can be detected using injection of dyes, radioisotopes
      or a combination of both. Therefore, evaluation of the SLNs can result in an accurate
      assessment of the nodal status in the entire lymphatic basin allowing a tailored surgical
      treatment. Although this technique has transformed surgical care for melanoma and breast
      cancer patients, its application in patients with colorectal cancer has been questioned due
      to discrepancies in the reported results caused by the heterogeneous study designs employed,
      variations in surgical experience and differing patient inclusion criteria 9-11.

      Detailed analysis of studies performed to date shows that tumour and patient
      characterisation as well as surgeons experience are key factors when assessing the utility
      of the technique 2, 12 and at least three nodes need to be found in order to maximise this
      13. The main research focus so far has been on optimising the technique itself. Initial
      research was performed using blue dye, radioactive colloid or both in combination but this
      failed to achieve the 95-97% identification rates found in breast cancer and was also
      accompanied by unacceptable false negative rates 14-17. Although many authors noted that
      their false negatives occurred predominantly in patients with advanced disease (T3 and T4
      cancers) 18-20, utilisation of those identification agents has proven frustrating to date.
      Radioactive colloids require involvement of a nuclear medicine physician, can be difficult
      to localise with a handheld camera and cause signal interference if the SLN(s) is too close
      to the injection site. Blue dyes however are difficult to localise in patients with a high
      body mass index (BMI), who unfortunately comprise the majority of our patient population,
      thus producing only limited (if any) visualisation of afferent lymphatic vessels and SLN(s).

      In order to re-examine extensive research that has been reported on SLNM, a secondary
      intention analysis of the two largest multicentre SLN databases was undertaken. This
      reported that in 225 patients with T1 or T2 disease, accurate detection of SLNs was possible
      in 95%, confirming that this staging technique should be most accurate in patients with
      early colonic cancer 2. This improved with operator experience and when tumour size was
      smaller than 35 mm in diameter. In 196 patients treated by experienced surgeons, 144
      (73.4%), would have correctly undergone localised full thickness resection if surgery had
      been based only on their SLNs status and 49 (25.0%), would have required conventional
      resection either because the SLNs were not identified, or due to detection of metastases.
      Only 3 patients (1.5%) would have been inappropriately predicted to be node negative.

      1.2. Investigational Agent To overcome the aforementioned issues, a number of researchers
      have utilized optical imaging using the near-infrared (NIR) fluorescence lymphatic tracer
      indocyanine green (ICG) which enables real-time intraoperative visualisation of lymphatic
      channels and SLNs. The technique performs as well as the combination of a radioactive tracer
      and blue dye in patients with breast cancer 21, and has also been validated in patients with
      early gastric cancer 4-6.

      ICG was initially recommended as a tattooing agent for colonic and pancreatic lesions to aid
      perioperative localization 22-24, as there were no reports of complications such as focal
      peritonitis, abscess formation, postoperative adhesions and ileus which had been seen with
      the use of India ink 25-27. However, its use as a tattooing agent is limited to patients
      undergoing surgery within 8 days after endoscopic injection, as the dye dissipates through
      lymphatic channels due to its small molecular size 22. More recently, its fluorescence
      properties have been utilised for intraoperative localisation of colorectal neoplasms and
      associated SLNs 28-32 in patients undergoing surgery using either charge-coupled device
      (CCD) or a NIR camera. Nagata et al. demonstrated that observation of ICG dye using a NIR
      camera was far superior to that by conventional laparoscopy with identification of SLNs
      being five times better 29.  These results suggest that a SLNM technique using NIR with a
      fluorescent tracer may be useful in patients with a high BMI who have large amounts of
      mesenteric adipose tissue. All authors reporting the NIR technique have noted its success in
      colorectal practice, without adverse effects with a comparable role to its use in early
      breast or gastric cancer.

      1.3. Rationale The ability to utilise this technique and confidently identify the SLNs has
      the potential to transform the surgical care of patients with colonic neoplasia. The focus,
      however, must be on patients with early disease, thus allowing those who have node negative
      disease to be considered for localised full thickness resection of their primary cancer as
      definitive surgical therapy. Unfortunately, studies published to date have included patients
      with T3 disease in their series 29, 31.

      This pilot trial aims to apply a well-described technique using a NIR camera and ICG as the
      tracer in order to clarify whether SLNs can be confidently identified in patients undergoing
      conventional resection (segmental colectomy and en bloc mesenteric resection) for T1 and T2
      colonic cancers. This protocol is based on extensive literature search of studies describing
      the technique in patients with early gastric and colorectal cancers 5, 6, 29-31, 33-36.
      Provided that the pilot trial is successful, and in order to obtain adequate power, a
      further large multicentre trial will be required to determine whether the nodes visualised
      by NIR mapping are representative of the patient's lymphatic basin metastatic status. Proven
      concordance between the pathology of the SLNs and that of the standard nodal resection would
      then justify a more limited surgical intervention, taking just the SLN(s), and allowing a
      more precisely tailored operative intervention.

      All patients in the pilot trial will undergo standard surgical treatment in addition to the
      NIR SLNM technique.

      1.3.1. Risk - benefit assessment

      Potential benefits This study is designed to assess the effectiveness of NIR mapping with
      ICG to identify SLNs in patients who are undergoing the current 'gold standard' treatment of
      segmental colectomy and en bloc mesenteric resection; all patients are therefore still
      receiving the current established standard of care for their condition. There will be no
      direct benefit to the participants in terms of any reduction in the extent of surgery which
      they receive, although this could potentially be a benefit of the imaging technique for
      future patients in the long term. However, the study design does provide some benefit to
      participants in that they will receive additional pathological scrutiny of their disease
      above that which is usually performed. In addition to routine standard pathological analysis
      of lymph nodes, the patients in this study will have ultra-analysis (including IHC) of the
      nodes identified in the mapping. While the significance of micrometastases detected by IHC
      is not entirely clear at present, this disease burden has been included in the TNM
      classification as an indication for considering additive postoperative therapy. Also, the
      addition of lymphatic mapping during the case can be expected to identify first order
      draining lymph nodes lying outside the field of standard operative resection and this is
      reported to occur in up to 14% of patients37. Excision and analysis of these nodes may
      result in upstaging of disease extent and thus allow the recommendation of adjuvant therapy
      leading to a potential improvement in prognosis.

      Potential risks and their management

      There are some small risks associated with the introduction of the additional imaging
      procedure. There is a documented risk of allergic (anaphylactic or anaphylactoid) reaction
      of less than 1 in 10, 000 to the tracer agent - all participants will be asked about any
      prior exposure to the agent or reaction to iodine dyes and shellfish. Case notes will also
      be thoroughly reviewed by a member of the research team. However, if allergic reaction
      occurs during or after administration of the ICG, standard hospital procedures will be
      followed and further active study procedures abandoned. The patient will however be followed
      up according to the protocol in order to collect the adverse event data until the adverse
      event is resolved. A pregnancy test will be performed in all women of childbearing potential
      and those who test positive will be excluded from the trial.

      Colonic perforation related to the endoscopy procedure occurs in 1/2000 cases. This
      procedure, however, is essential in order to inject the tracer agent. This risk will be
      minimized by ensuring that this examination is performed by an experienced endoscopist and
      it is significantly diminished with the use of bowel preparation that optimises the
      endoscopic view.

      Inclusion into the study will add 30 minutes to the total operative time which is thought to
      be acceptable by the senior members of the investigative team with minimal risk to the
      patient. Experienced clinicians will perform the surgical procedure and we expect that this
      added time will decrease significantly as experience is gained with the technique in
      question.

      Overall benefit-risk assessment

      In order to minimise the risks for potential participants, we will only use materials (ICG),
      equipment (NIR laparoscopy camera, Olympus) and methods (endoscopic injection) for which the
      risks are already known. Previously, the technique of sentinel node biopsy in colorectal
      cancer was used to enable a more intensive examination of the lymph nodes after the
      operation has taken place. Here, the proposal is that identification of the lymph nodes
      before or during the operation could help the surgeon decide exactly which operation to do.
      In this initial study we will use a single mapping agent and its fluorescence properties
      will allow enhanced sensitivity of detection at the time of surgery. Standard surgery will
      then be carried out. In choosing this agent, we have systematically studied the literature
      and previous empiric experience with non-fluorescent, non-radioactive agents (primarily
      methylene blue) and found this unsatisfactory in patients of average and above-average BMI.
      If the results of this 'optimised' technical study are satisfactory, further work will be
      proposed with a large multicentre study to assess sensitivity and specificity of the
      technique.

      ICG is routinely used in radiological and cardiac investigations and is well within safety
      recommendations for both patients and the staff entrusted with their care. The Olympus
      Infrared Laparoscopic System being used to detect the presence of the mapping agent in lymph
      nodes has been CE marked (European Community directive conformity). Therefore, we consider
      the overall risk to participants in  this study is minimal.

      In addition, there are also potential benefits from participating in the trial. Rather than
      undergoing standard pathological processing of their resected lymph nodes, patients in this
      study will have added intensive study of their sentinel nodes (all other nodes will be
      processed in the routine fashion). Aberrant nodes identified with the technique will also be
      removed and analysed for evidence of metastases. This will allow highly sensitive detection
      of tumour deposits (i.e. small micrometastases) that may be prognostically important in the
      nodes most likely to harbour such deposits. Using this technique we also hope to identify a
      proportion of patients with aberrant lymphatic drainage which will allow more accurate
      staging of the disease and reduce the risk of understaging and therefore avoid depriving
      patients of the benefits from adjuvant chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of subjects in which the SLN(s) are identified</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To establish whether it is possible to identify the first order draining mesocolic lymph nodes (sentinel lymph node(s) (SLNs) in patients with suspected T1 and T2 colonic cancer, using ICG, a fluorescent mapping agent, and a laparoscopic near infrared imaging (NIR) system</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity and specificity of tumour-bearing status of SLN(s) as a measure of lymph node status when assessed by standard techniques</measure>
    <time_frame>12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the extent to which that the tumour-bearing status of SLN(s) identified corresponds with lymph node status as assessed by standard methods (pathological examination of excised nodes using H&amp;E and immunohistochemistry)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency and tumour-bearing status of aberrant SLN(s</measure>
    <time_frame>12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To estimate the proportion of patients with aberrant nodal drainage.  i.e. the proportion with SLN(s) lying outside the standard resection field</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Indocyanine green</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Indocyanine green is used for intraoperative identification of sentinel lymph nodes in patients with early colonic cancer using near infrared laparoscopic imaging</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Indocyanine green</intervention_name>
    <description>Please see arm description</description>
    <arm_group_label>Indocyanine green</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the study

          2. Patients willing and able to comply with the study procedures

          3. Male or Female, aged 18 years or above

          4. Patients diagnosed with T1 or T2 colonic neoplasia on preoperative staging and
             require laparoscopic surgical excision

          5. If female, a negative pregnancy test for women of childbearing potential prior to
             surgery

          6. Patients who have clinically acceptable laboratory results pre-operatively with serum
             creatinine of &lt;110 mg/dL

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients diagnosed with T3 or T4 disease on preoperative imaging

          2. A patient who is pregnant, lactating or planning pregnancy during the course of the
             study

          3. Allergy to any of the compounds being used for lymphatic mapping including
             Indocyanine green or sodium iodide

          4. Patients with hyperthyroidism or those with thyroid adenomas

          5. Patients with renal insufficiency (serum creatinine of &gt;110 mg/dL)

          6. Patients in whom the use of ICG is contraindicated including development of adverse
             events when previously or presently administered

          7. Previous allergic reaction to shellfish
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robin Kennedy, FRCS, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Imperial College London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andrew Currie, MBChB, MRCS</last_name>
    <phone>+44 208 235 4225</phone>
    <email>slnmcc@imperial.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Robin Kennedy, FRCS, MS</last_name>
    <phone>+44 208 235 4108</phone>
    <email>robin.kennedy@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>North West London Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>UK</state>
        <zip>HA1 3UJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrew Currie, MBChB, MRCS</last_name>
      <phone>+44 208 869 5289</phone>
      <email>slnmcc@imperial.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Robin Kennedy, FRCS, MS</last_name>
      <phone>+44 208 235 4108</phone>
      <email>robin.kennedy@nhs.net</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 27, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 7, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Early colonic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Sentinel lymph node mapping</keyword>
  <keyword>Sentinel lymph node biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Near infrared imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Indocyanine green</keyword>
  <keyword>Laparoscopic</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Colonic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
