<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="161499">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01973595</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201300475</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01973595</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Almonds: Digestive Health and Immune Function of Adults and Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>Almonds: Digestive Health and Immune Function of Adults and Children</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Almond Board of California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether incorporating almonds into the diets of
      families with young children will induce beneficial changes in gastrointestinal function,
      the fecal microbiota profile, and immune and inflammatory processes of the adults and
      children resulting in improved quality of life. The investigators anticipate finding an
      increase in beneficial bacteria, improved intestinal function, increased antioxidant status,
      improved immune function, decreased inflammation, and decreased perceived stress during the
      almond intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, crossover study. After obtaining informed consent, healthy adults aged
      18-40 years with children aged 3-6 years will be randomized to either consume almonds and
      almond paste during the first arm of the study or during the second arm of the study. During
      the intervention period, adult participants will consume 1.5 ounces of almonds per day, and
      children will consume 0.5 ounces of almonds per day for 3 weeks. After a 4-week washout
      period, participants will be crossed to the other treatment (no almond consumption or almond
      consumption).

      Participants will complete daily questionnaires throughout the intervention period, and one
      week before and after each intervention period. Saliva samples will be collected from adults
      and children and blood samples will be collected from adults at the baseline and final time
      points of each intervention. Stool samples will be collected during the pre-baseline and
      final weeks of each intervention. Dietary intake will be assessed weekly during each
      intervention period. Gastrointestinal symptoms questionnaires will be completed weekly
      during each intervention, and a perceived stress questionnaire will be completed by adults
      at the beginning and end of each intervention period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gut microbiota community composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Final #1 (Week 4) to Final #2 (Week 14)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Microbiota at Week 4 and Week 14 will be compared, controlling for baseline levels.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gut microbiota community composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline #1 (Week 1) to Final #1 (Week 4)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in gut microbiota between baseline and final time points will be compared for each study arm.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gut microbiota community composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline #2 (Week 11) to Final #2 (Week 14)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in gut microbiota between baseline and final time points will be compared for each study arm.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammatory status</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Final in the Almond Intervention Arm</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Levels of inflammatory markers in the blood (adults only) will be compared between baseline and final time points during the almond intervention arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gastrointestinal function</measure>
    <time_frame>Final #1 (Week 4) to Final #2 (Week 14)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in gastrointestinal symptoms and bowel habits will be measured using the Daily Questionnaire and the Gastrointestinal Symptoms Response Scale, and results will be compared between treatment periods for each subject/group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune factors</measure>
    <time_frame>Final #1 (Week 4) to Final #2 (Week 14)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Levels of immune factors in the saliva and stool will be compared between treatment periods for each subject/group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diet Quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Final #1 (Week 4) to Final #2 (Week 14)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Four dietary recalls will occur per study arm, and each recall will be scored for quality. The quality scores will be averaged per arm and then compared between study arms for each subject/group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammatory status</measure>
    <time_frame>Final #1 (Week 4) to Final #2 (Week 14)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Levels of inflammatory markers in the blood (adults only) will be compared between treatment periods for each subject/group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gastrointestinal function</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Final in the Almond Intervention Arm</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in gastrointestinal symptoms and bowel habits will be measured using the Daily Questionnaire and the Gastrointestinal Symptoms Response Scale, and results will be compared between baseline and final time points during the almond intervention arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune factors</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Final in the Almond Intervention Arm (Week #4 or Week #14 depending on the randomization group)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Levels of immune factors in the saliva and stool will be compared between baseline and final time points during the almond intervention arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived stress</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Final in the Almond Intervention Arm (Week #4 or Week #14 depending on the randomization group)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in perceived stress levels will be measured using the Daily Questionnaire and the Perceived Stress Scale, and results will be compared between baseline and final time points during the almond intervention arm.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived stress</measure>
    <time_frame>Final #1 (Week 4) to Final #2 (Week 14)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in perceived stress levels will be measured using the Daily Questionnaire and the Perceived Stress Scale, and results will be compared between treatment periods for each adult subject and between groups.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">29</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Almonds</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Adults will consume 1.5 ounces of almonds or almond paste per day and children will consume 0.5 ounces of almonds or almond paste per day for 3 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No almond consumption</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>No almonds will be consumed by participants for 3 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Almonds</intervention_name>
    <description>Whole, raw almonds with skin, or whole, raw almonds with skin that have been ground into a paste.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Almonds</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No almond consumption</intervention_name>
    <description>No almonds will be consumed by participants for 3 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>No almond consumption</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        To participate in the study, adult participants must:

          -  Be 18 to 40 years old.

          -  Have a 3 to 6 year old child that you are willing to enroll in the study.

          -  Live with your child for on average at least 6 days of the week.

          -  Be willing and able to complete the Informed Consent Form in English.

          -  Not be currently pregnant or planning to become pregnant in the next 5 months.

          -  Be willing to consume 1.5 ounces of almonds (~43 nuts) each day for three weeks.

          -  Be willing to feed your child 0.5 ounces of almond paste (~2 tablespoons) per day for
             three weeks.

          -  Be willing monitor your child's daily intake over the course of the study.

          -  Be willing to provide 4 blood samples, 4 stool samples, and 4 saliva samples over the
             course of the study.

          -  Be willing to assist your child in providing 4 stool samples and 4 saliva samples
             over the course of the study.

          -  Be willing and able to complete daily and weekly questionnaires for you and your
             child regarding general wellness, bowel function, gastrointestinal symptoms, stress
             and anxiety, and dietary intake.

          -  Must be available for 14 consecutive weeks to participate in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        To participate in the study, adult and child participants:

          -  Must not have any known nut or tree nut allergies.

          -  Must discontinue any immune-enhancing dietary supplements (e.g., prebiotics and fiber
             supplements, probiotics, fish oil, vitamin E &gt;400% of the RDA or &gt;60 mg/day, and
             yogurts with live, active cultures).

          -  Must not be currently taking any medications for constipation or diarrhea on a
             regular basis.

          -  Must not be currently taking any large doses of anti-inflammatory drugs (i.e.,
             aspirin in doses &gt;600 mg/d) on a regular basis.

          -  Must not have received antibiotic therapy or a colonoscopy in the past two months.

          -  Must not be currently being treated for or have any of the following
             physician-diagnosed diseases or conditions:  HIV/AIDS; immune modulating diseases
             (autoimmune disease, hepatitis, cancer); kidney disease; pancreatitis; pulmonary
             disease; hepatic or biliary disease; or gastrointestinal diseases/conditions such as
             diverticulitis, ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease, Celiac disease, short bowel
             disease, ileostomy, or colostomy, but not including GERD; or have a central venous
             catheter.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bobbi Langkamp-Henken, PhD, RD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>almonds</keyword>
  <keyword>inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>immunity</keyword>
  <keyword>gut microbiota</keyword>
  <keyword>stress</keyword>
  <keyword>diet quality</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
