<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="129379">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01805076</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A011104</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ACRIN 6694</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA037447</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-02045</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01805076</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MRI and Mammography Before Surgery in Patients With Stage I-II Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Preoperative Breast MRI on Surgical Outcomes, Costs and Quality of Life of Women With Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alliance for Clinical Trials in Oncology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American College of Radiology Imaging Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alliance for Clinical Trials in Oncology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: NCI Central Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test whether patients undergoing a breast MRI (magnetic
      resonance imaging) before breast surgery will have better results after the surgery. Breast
      tumors are routinely evaluated using mammograms and ultrasound before surgery. This study
      would like to find out if using MRI in addition to mammography before surgery improves our
      ability to evaluate tumors and decide what kind of surgery is best for the patient.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized trial of preoperative breast MRI in patients deemed eligible for breast
      conserving surgery by conventional clinical criteria will provide important information
      about the clinical and biologic relevance of occult disease identified by MRI alone.
      Patients will be assigned to standard pre-operative breast cancer disease assessment without
      the addition of MRI prior to breast conserving surgery or standard pre-operative breast
      cancer disease assessment with the use of MRI prior to breast conserving surgery. The
      primary objective is to compare the rates of local-regional recurrence (LRR) following
      attempted breast conserving therapy in a cohort of women with triple negative or HER-2
      amplified breast cancer randomized to preoperative staging with mammography (control arm) or
      mammography plus breast MRI (MRI arm). The secondary objectives for this study are:

        1. To compare the re-operation rates following attempted breast conserving therapy between
           women assessed preoperatively with breast MRI to those assessed without the use of
           breast MRI

        2. To compare local recurrence rates between women who undergo BCT on the control arm to
           women who undergo BCT on the MRI arm

        3. To compare the conversion rate to mastectomy secondary to persistent positive margins
           or poor cosmesis within the first 6 months of attempting BCT (prior to the
           administration of RT) between women assessed preoperatively with breast MRI to those
           assessed without the use of breast MRI

        4. To compare the contralateral breast cancer rates in women randomized to preoperative
           breast MRI to those not receiving pre-operative breast MRI

        5. To compare the disease-free survival rates between women assessed preoperatively with
           breast MRI to those assessed without the use of breast MRI

        6. To compare breast cancer specific and overall survival outcomes of women assessed
           preoperatively with breast MRI to those assessed without the use of breast MRI

        7. To estimate the rate of MRI-guided localization assisted surgery

        8. To estimate the rate of multi-centric disease in the index breast for women in the MRI
           arm

        9. To evaluate the accuracy of index lesion characteristics and other factors in
           predicting multi-centricity in the cohort randomized to breast MRI

       10. To assess the positive predictive values (PPV) of MRI in detecting ipsilateral
           multi-centric disease and contralateral disease in women with breast cancer undergoing
           preoperative breast MRI

       11. To estimate the false positive rate for detection of multiple foci of breast cancer by
           MRI

      All registered patients will be monitored for relapse and survival for 5 years from the date
      of surgery. Patients will be followed a minimum of every 4 months for the first 2 years from
      diagnosis and a minimum of every 6 months during years 3-5. Patients will be monitored for
      local, regional, distant relapse and vital status.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Local-regional recurrence (LRR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Re-operation rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Conversion rate to mastectomy secondary to persistent positive margins or poor cosmesis</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the first 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to contralateral breast cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years post-randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival (DFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years post-randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years post-randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breast cancer specific survival will be measured</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years post-randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of MRI-guided localization assisted surgery (Arm B)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of women with MRI detected multiple foci disease (Arm B)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">536</enrollment>
  <condition>Estrogen Receptor-negative Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>HER2-negative Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>HER2-positive Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Progesterone Receptor-negative Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IA Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IB Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage II Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Triple-negative Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1 (control)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo a clinical breast examination and mammography with ultrasound of the breast and regional nodes followed by breast conserving surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2 (experimental)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo a clinical breast examination, mammography with ultrasound of breast and regional nodes and breast MRI followed by breast conserving surgery or mastectomy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Breast surgery</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1 (control)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2 (experimental)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Magnetic resonance imaging</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2 (experimental)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mammography</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1 (control)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2 (experimental)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  Female. Men are excluded from this study because the number of men with breast cancer
              is insufficient to provide a statistical basis for assessment of effects in this
             subpopulation of people with breast cancer.

          -  Pathologically confirmed diagnosis of breast cancer, clinical stage I-II (T1-3 N0 M0,
             T0-2 N1 M0). Diagnosis must be by needle biopsy; patients diagnosed by surgical
             excision are excluded.

          -  Patients must have either: 

               -  Estrogen receptor (ER) negative/progesterone receptor (PR) negative (&lt; 1% by
                  immunohistochemistry IHC staining) and HER-2 negative breast cancer OR 

               -  ER negative/PR negative (&lt; 1% by IHC staining) and HER-2 positive tumors

               -  HER-2 status will be determined as per the 2013 ASCO CAP guidelines:

                    -  HER-2 is considered positive if there is IHC 3+ staining or ISH positive
                       using either single probe ISH or dual probe ISH

                    -  HER-2 is considered negative if there is IHC 0 or 1+ staining or ISH
                       negative using either single probe ISH or dual probe ISH

          -  No patients with previous ipsilateral invasive breast cancer or ductal carcinoma in
             situ (DCIS)

          -  No patients with bilateral breast cancer

          -  No patients with known deleterious mutations in breast cancer (BRCA) genes

          -  No current history of receiving hormonal therapy, tamoxifen, and or aromatase
             inhibitors for therapeutic measures

          -  No history of chemotherapy for cancer within 6 months prior to registration

          -  No patients scheduled to receive neoadjuvant chemotherapy or partial breast
             irradiation following breast conserving surgery

          -  Eligible for BCT based on clinical examination, mammography and, if standard practice
             at a given institution, ultrasound and/or tomogram. Women who cannot be appropriately
             selected for BCT based on these standard imaging studies, and for whom additional
             imaging is recommended to clarify local disease extent, will not be eligible for this
             trial.

          -  Suitable to undergo MRI and receive the contrast agent gadolinium (exclusions
             follow): 

               -  No history of untreatable claustrophobia 

               -  No presence of metallic objects or implanted medical devices in body (i.e.,
                  cardiac pacemaker, aneurysm clips, surgical clips, prostheses, artificial
                  hearts, valves with steel parts, metal fragments, shrapnel, tattoos near the
                  eye, or steel implants) 

               -  No history of sickle cell disease 

               -  No contraindication to intravenous contrast administration 

               -  No known allergy-like reaction to gadolinium or moderate or severe allergic
                  reactions to one or more allergens as defined by the American College of
                  Radiology (ACR); patient may be eligible if willing to undergo pre-treatment as
                  defined by the institution's policy and/or ACR guidance 

               -  No findings consistent with renal failure, as determined by glomerular
                  filtration rate (GFR) &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73 m^2 based on a serum creatinine level
                  obtained within 7 days prior to registration 

               -  Weight lower than that allowable by the MRI table

          -  No prior MRI of study breast within the 12 months prior to registration

          -  No history of breast biopsy (including FNA) of the study breast within 6 months prior
             to the MRI

          -  Non-pregnant and non-lactating. Patients of child-bearing potential must have a
             negative pregnancy test within 7 days prior to registration. Perimenopausal patients
             must be amenorrheic &gt; 12 months to be considered not of child-bearing potential

          -  ≥ 18 years of age

          -  Signed study-specific informed consent prior to registration
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Isabelle Bedrosian, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Doctors Hospital of Laredo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Laredo</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gary Unzeitig, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>956-523-2000</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 24, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 24, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
