<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="121082">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01976871</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MGH - 2013P000968</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01976871</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Switching From Oral Dopamine Agonists to Rotigotine</brief_title>
  <acronym>SWITCH</acronym>
  <official_title>A Method to Switch From Oral Dopamine Agonists to Rotigotine in Patients With Restless Legs Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>John Winkelman, MD, PhD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective is to demonstrate safety and tolerability of switching patients with
      Restless Legs Syndrome (RLS) from an oral dopamine agonist to rotigotine.

      As a secondary objective, the investigators will evaluate control of RLS symptoms on
      rotigotine compared to the prior oral regimen.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will consist of 3 in-person visits and 4 scheduled telephone appointments over the
      course of approximately 6 weeks.  The first visit will be the screening visit during which
      eligibility will be confirmed and informed consent obtained.  After the first visit,
      subjects will continue their current oral dopamine agonist for a one-week baseline period
      during which they will record RLS symptoms daily.

      The second visit will be the baseline visit.  The IRLS scale, a commonly used measure of RLS
      symptoms, will be obtained. An individualized schedule for down-titration of oral dopamine
      agonist and concomitant up-titration of rotigotine will be provided. After the second visit,
      subjects will begin this cross-titration.  This will entail a pre-determined incremental
      taper of the oral medication and flexible up-titration of rotigotine according to symptoms.
      During this time, subjects will keep diaries of RLS symptoms and will speak with the
      investigator over the phone a total of 3 times (visits 2a-2c) to discuss dosing of
      rotigotine.

      After the titration is complete, subjects will enter the maintenance period, which will last
      28 days. There will be another phone contact (2d) one week after the titration is complete
      to adjust the dose of rotigotine as needed. The subject will then continue the chosen dose
      for the next 3 weeks of the maintenance period.  There will be one final phone contact (2e)
      1 week prior to the end of the maintenance period to remind subjects to resume RLS symptom
      diaries during the final week of the maintenance period.

      The third and final visit will take place at the end of the maintenance period. RLS symptoms
      will be discussed and the IRLS scale, Clinician Global Impression of Change (CGIC), Patient
      Global Impression of Change (PGIC), and Preference of Medication Scale (POMS) will be
      administered.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients completing the switch and their adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be monitored for the duration of the study, approximately 6-10 weeks depending upon scheduling of visits</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint will be the tolerability of switching from an oral dopamine agonist to rotigotine.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>International Restless Legs Scale (IRLS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Visit 3 (approximately 28 days after the last dose of oral dopamine agonist)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The IRLS will be used to determine the overall efficacy of RLS symptom control on rotigotine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>RLS-6 Scales</measure>
    <time_frame>Average of Baseline  week (approximately days 1-7 of the study) vs. Average of Final Treatment week (approximately days 21-28 of the maintenance period)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The RLS-6 scales will be used to determine the overall efficacy of RLS symptom control on rotigotine, calculated as a mean score for each scale during the final treatment week vs baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preference of Medication Scale (POM)</measure>
    <time_frame>Study visit 3 (approximately 28 days after the last dose of oral dopamine agonist)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The POM will be used to assess patient satisfaction with treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Patient Global Impression of Change scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Study visit 3 (approximately 28 days after the last dose of oral dopamine agonist)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Patient Global Impression of Change scale (PGIC) will be used to assess patient satisfaction with treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Clinician Global Impression of Change Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Study visit 3 (approximately 28 days after the last dose of oral dopamine agonist)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Clinician Global Impression of Change scale (CGIC) will be used to assess patient satisfaction with treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Restless Legs Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Ekbom Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Willis-Ekbom Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Dopamine Agonist to Rotigotine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>During the study, we will switch patients who are not satisfied with their current oral dopamine agonist to rotigotine. Cross-titration will allow determination of the lowest effective dose of rotigotine.  We will use as initial guidance the equivalence determined from the Parkinson's Disease trials, in which 1 mg rotigotine was shown to be approximately equivalent to 1-1.5 mg ropinirole or 0.25 -0.375 mg pramipexole. Tolerability, adverse events, and RLS symptom control will be evaluated.  These data will provide clinicians with practical guidance to optimize RLS treatment while minimizing adverse events.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rotigotine</intervention_name>
    <description>Rotigotine is FDA approved for the treatment of Restless Legs Syndrome at doses of 1 mg/24h, 2 mg/24h, and 3 mg/24h.  The prescribed dose of rotigotine may be achieved using single or multiple patches. Subjects will titrate the dose based on discussions with the investigator.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Dopamine Agonist to Rotigotine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Neupro</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A diagnosis of RLS, defined by International Restless Legs Study Group (IRLS)
             essential criteria:

               1. An urge to move the legs, usually accompanied or caused by uncomfortable and
                  unpleasant sensations in the legs.

               2. The urge to move or unpleasant sensations begin or worsen during periods of rest
                  or inactivity such as lying down or sitting.

               3. The urge to move or unpleasant sensations are partially or totally relieved by
                  movement, such as walking or stretching, at least as long as the activity
                  continues.

               4. The urge to move or unpleasant sensations are worse in the evening or night than
                  during the day or only occur in the evening or night.

        (Although some subjects may not meet these criteria on their current oral regimen, these
        symptoms must have been present prior to treatment.)

          -  Current treatment with either pramipexole (≤1 mg total daily dose) or ropinirole (≤4
             mg total daily dose) with unchanged dose for the past 30 days.  Patients also on
             other RLS medications will be allowed to participate if the dosing has been stable
             for the past 30 days and the subject agrees to maintain a stable dose for the
             duration of the trial.

          -  Inadequate symptom control or patient dissatisfaction with current oral regimen.

          -  Able to speak and read English.

          -  Able to provide informed consent.

          -  Able to learn and demonstrate appropriate patch application.

          -  Returns appropriately completed RLS symptom log at Visit 2.

          -  Confirms understanding of cross-titration schedule and is able to restate or
             summarize these instructions at Visit 2.

          -  Age ≥18 and ≤75.

          -  BMI ≥18 and ≤35

          -  History and/or clinical records document no change in medications active in the
             central nervous system (antidepressants, analgesics, antipsychotics, antiepileptics,
             hypnotics, etc.) for at least 30 days prior to visit 1.

          -  Able to understand study procedures and agrees to remain on stable medications during
             the period of the study.

          -  Women of childbearing potential must agree to use a medically accepted method of
             birth control. Acceptable forms of birth control include:

               1. Condom + spermicide

                    -  b. Diaphragm + spermicide

                    -  c. Oral contraceptive pills, hormone implants (like Norplant),or injections
                       (like Depo-Provera)

                    -  Intrauterine Device

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known secondary cause of RLS, including end-stage renal disease, severe iron
             deficiency (ferritin &lt;18), pregnancy.

          -  History of frequent symptomatic orthostatic hypotension.

          -  Current treatment with a dopamine antagonist medication.

          -  Another chronic pain syndrome that would, in the opinion of the investigator,
             interfere with evaluation of RLS symptoms or the response to the study medication.

          -  Plan to undergo a procedure that may require short or long-term opiates for pain
             control during the course of the trial.

          -  Women who are pregnant, lactating, or planning to become pregnant.

          -  Shift work or other commitments that do not allow for regular sleep at night.

          -  Known hypersensitivity or intolerance to rotigotine.

          -  Known allergy to sulfite-containing drugs.

          -  History of problematic skin hypersensitivity to adhesives.

          -  Previous or current clinically significant impulse control disorder, as determined by
             clinical interview.

          -  Anticipated change in psychiatric or neurologic status likely to require adjustment
             of CNS-active medications during the study period.

          -  Unwillingness of subject to remain on stable doses of CNS-active medications.

          -  Unwillingness of subject to refrain from as-needed use of RLS medications.

          -  Significant risk for suicide by clinical interview.

          -  History of severe mental illness or psychosis

          -  Current unstable medical illness.

          -  Any medical or psychiatric condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would
             interfere with participation in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John W. Winkelman, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>617-643-9101</phone>
    <email>JWWINKELMAN@PARTNERS.ORG</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John W. Winkelman, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>JWWINKELMAN@PARTNERS.ORG</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John W. Winkelman, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 25, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>John Winkelman, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief, Sleep Disorders Clinical Research Program</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Restless Legs Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Ekbom Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Willis-Ekbom Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Rotigotine</keyword>
  <keyword>Neupro</keyword>
  <keyword>Dopamine Agonist</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Restless Legs Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychomotor Agitation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dopamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dopamine Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>N 0437</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dopamine Agonists</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
