<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="61929">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01672736</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PMHOSI906-MM001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01672736</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Trial of ASP7487 (OSI-906) in Combination With Bortezomib for the Treatment of Relapsed Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1/2 Trial of ASP7487 OSI-906)in Combination With Bortezomib and Dexamethasone for the Treatment of Relapsed or Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Multiple Myeloma Research Consortium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Astellas Pharma Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, open-label, non-randomized study.  Patients will receive ASP7487
      (OSI-906) in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone. Phase 1 involves dose escalation
      of the combination, whereas Phase 2 involves the expansion of ASP7487 (OSI-906) combined
      with bortezomib and dexamethasone at the MTD to establish the ORR.  This trial will accrue
      patients with relapsed or relapsed/refractory MM - a disease state for which bortezomib is
      approved to treat by the FDA and Health Canada. The combination of ASP7487 (OSI-906) with
      bortezomib is supported by pre-clinical work in MM in which the combination with an IGF1-R
      inhibitor enhances anti-tumor activity of bortezomib.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Phase 1 portion of the study will determine the MTD and DLTs of bortezomib administered
      on days 1, 4, 8 and 11 of a 21-day cycle combined with ASP7487 (OSI-906) dosed twice daily
      orally continuously. The combination of ASP7487 (OSI-906) with bortezomib has not previously
      been tested. The active agent bortezomib will be used during Cycle 1 - 8 at the recommended
      treatment dose of 1.3 mg/m2 days 1, 4, 8 and 11 and Cycles 9+ on days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a
      5-week cycle and ASP7487 (OSI-906) will be dose escalated form 75 mg to 150mg utilizing 3+3
      design
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose of the combination of ASP7487 (OSI-906) with Velcade and Dexamethasone</measure>
    <time_frame>It is estimated that it will take approximately 3-5 months determine MTD.   The efficacy analysis could take upto  2.5 years after the activation date of the study to be completed.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Phase 1: To determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of ASP7487 (OSI-906)  administered in combination with the recommended dose and schedule of bortezomib and dexamethasone;
Phase 2: To evaluate the antitumor activity of ASP7487 (OSI-906) in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone at the MTD established from the Phase 1 component.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ASP7487,  Velcade,  Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ASP7487 administered orally 75, 100 and 150 mg) BID continuously for each cycle. Bortezomib administered at 1.3 mg/m2 twice weekly for the first 8 21 day cycles and once weekly beyond cycle 9 for 35 day cycles. Dexamethasone is administered on bortezomib administration days at 20 mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ASP7487, Velcade, Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>ASP7487- Oral (75, 100, 150 mg)BID Bortezomib- 1.3 mg/m2 IV on days 1, 4, 8, 15 of each 21 day cycle up to cycle 8 and days 1, 5, 15, 22 of each 35 day cycle beyond cycle 9 Dexamethasone- 20 mg on the day of Bortezomib administration</description>
    <arm_group_label>ASP7487,  Velcade,  Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ASP7487</other_name>
    <other_name>Bortezomib</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexamethasone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males or females, age 18 years or older.

          2. A diagnosis of MM and documentation of relapsed or relapse/refractory status
             following at least 1 prior therapy and a maximum of 4 prior regimens.

          3. Patients with measurable disease defined as at least one of the following these
             baseline laboratory studies for determining eligibility must be obtained within 21
             days prior to enrollment):

               1. Serum M-protein ≥ 0.5 g/dl (≥ 5 g/l)

               2. Urine M-protein ≥ 200 mg/24 h

               3. Serum free light chains (FLC) assay: Involved FLC level ≥ 10 mg/dl  (≥100 mg/l)
                  and an abnormal serum free light chain ratio (&lt; 0.26 or &gt; 1.65)

               4. Biopsy proven plasmacytoma (should be measured within 28 days of first study
                  drug administration). Prior biopsy is acceptable.

               5. If the serum protein electrophoresis is unreliable for routine M-protein
                  measurement, quantitative immunoglobulin levels on nephelometry or turbidimetry
                  will be followed.

          4. Patient has an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) ≤ 2 OR Karnofsky

               -  60% performance status (PS) (Appendix 13-2).

          5. Predose mean QTc ≤ 450 msec or mean QTc Fridericia's Correction (QTcF)on Day 1(cycle
             1 or cycle 0 if applicable) must be ≤ 450 msec.

          6. Females of childbearing potential (FCBP):  a female of childbearing potential is a
             sexually mature woman who: 1) has not undergone a hysterectomy or bilateral
             oophorectomy; or 2) has not been naturally postmenopausal for at least 24 consecutive
             months).  Pregnancy status in women of childbearing potential must be confirmed by
             serum β-hCG at screening. Pregnancy testing is not required for post-menopausal or
             surgically sterilized women. FCBP must use acceptable forms of birth control or agree
             to abstain from heterosexual intercourse while participating in the study and for 90
             days following the last dose of study drug. Men must agree to use a latex condom
             during sexual contact with a FCBP even if they have had a successful vasectomy while
             participating in the study and for 90 days following the last dose of study drug.

          7. Voluntary, written informed consent before performance of any study-related procedure
             not part of routine medical care with the understanding that consent may be withdrawn
             by the patient at any time without prejudice to future medical care.

          8. Ability to understand the purpose and risks of the study and provide signed and dated
             informed consent and authorization to use protected health information (in accordance
             with national and local patient privacy regulations).

          9. Must be able to take and retain oral medications.

         10. Inclusion Clinical Laboratories Criteria The following laboratory results must be met
             within 7 (+3 days if necessary for holiday/scheduling conflicts) days of first study
             drug administration:

               1. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,000 cells/dL (1.0 x 10^9/L) (Growth factors
                  cannot be used within 14 days of first study drug administration);

               2. Platelet count ≥ 50,000 cells/dL (50 x 109/L);

               3. Hemoglobin ≥ 8.0 g/dL (4.96 mmol/L);

               4. Serum AST or ALT within normal limits;

               5. Total bilirubin within normal limits;

               6. Creatinine clearance ≥ 30 mL/min (Cockcroft-Gault calculation);

               7. Serum creatinine ≤1.5 x ULN (correction with hydration and re-testing is
                  permitted)(values ≥ 1.5 X ULN may be acceptable if improved to &lt; 1.5 x ULN, with
                  hydration and/or attributable to progressing MM);

               8. Serum calcium (ionized or corrected for albumin) ≥ 2.0 mmol/L (8.0 mg/dL or 1.0
                  mmol/L ionized calcium) to ULN. Treatment of hypercalcemia or hypocalcemia is
                  allowed and patient may enroll if serum calcium returns to &gt; 2.0 mmols/L to ULN
                  with standard treatment

               9. Serum potassium and magnesium within normal limits (correction with
                  supplementation is permitted);

              10. HgbA1c of ≤ 7%;

              11. Fasting glucose of ≤126 mg/dL (7.0 mmol/L). A diagnosis of Type II diabetes
                  mellitus is permitted if &gt; 4 weeks since diagnosis and well controlled.
                  Concurrent non-insulinotropic antihyperglycemic therapy is permitted if the dose
                  has been stable for 8 weeks.

         11. Resolution of prior toxicities associated with a prior treatment to

               -  grade 1.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients refractory or intolerant to bortezomib are not permitted (Refractory =
             non-responsive/progressed on therapy or within 60 days of bortezomib) on phase 2 part
             of the study only.

          2. Diagnosed or treated for another malignancy within 3 years of enrollment, with the
             exception of complete resection of basal cell carcinoma or squamous cell carcinoma of
             the skin, an in situ malignancy, or low-risk prostate cancer after curative therapy.

          3. Patient has received other investigational drugs or chemotherapy within 21 days or
             approved anti-myeloma therapy including steroid therapy within 14 days prior to first
             study drug administration.

          4. History (within the last 6 months) of significant cardiovascular disease unless the
             disease is well-controlled. Significant cardiac disease includes but is not limited
             to second/third degree heart block; clinically significant ischemic heart disease;
             superior vena cava (SVC) syndrome; poorly controlled hypertension; congestive heart
             failure of New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class II or worse. History of arrhythmia
             (multifocal premature ventricular contractions [PVCs], bigeminy, trigeminy,
             ventricular tachycardia, or uncontrolled atrial fibrillation) that is symptomatic or
             requires treatment (≥ grade 3), left bundle branch block (LBBB), or asymptomatic
             sustained ventricular tachycardia are not allowed. Patients with atrial fibrillation
             controlled by medication are not excluded;

          5. Mean QTc interval ≥ 450 msec or QTcF interval &gt; 450 msec at screening;

          6. Prior autologous, peripheral stem cell transplant within 12 weeks of the first dose
             of study drug;

          7. Daily requirement for corticosteroids (except for inhalation corticosteroids);

          8. Patients with evidence of mucosal or internal bleeding and/or platelet transfusion
             refractory (i.e., unable to maintain a platelet count ≥ 50,000 cells/dL);

          9. Known active infection requiring parenteral or oral anti-infective treatment.

         10. Serious psychiatric illness, active alcoholism, or drug addiction that may hinder or
             confuse follow-up evaluation.

         11. Use of any medical conditions that, in the Investigator's opinion, would impose
             excessive risk to the patient. Examples of such conditions include any pre-existing
             kidney disease (acute or chronic, unless renal insufficiency is felt to be secondary
             to MM), hypertension, active seizure disorder or pulmonary diseases that would impose
             excessive risk to the patient.

         12. Patient has hypersensitivity to any of the components of study drugs;

         13. Known HIV or active hepatitis B or C viral infection;

         14. Diabetes mellitus currently requiring insulin or insulinotropic therapy or prior
             history of steroid induced diabetes ;

         15. History of cerebrovascular accident (CVA) within 6 months prior to registration or
             that is not stable;

         16. Prior therapy with an IGF-1R inhibitor;

         17. Use of drugs that have a risk of causing QT interval prolongation and/or have a known
             risk of causing Torsades de Pointes (TdP) before 14 days or the recommended 5
             half-life washout period elapses (as indicated in Appendix 13-6), which ever is
             longer prior to Cycle 1 Day 1 dosing;.  Drugs that have a known risk of causing TdP
             can be found on (www.azcert.org/medical- pros/drug-lists/bycategory.cfm);

         18. Use of strong/moderate CYP1A2 inhibitors such as ciprofloxacin and fluvoxamine. Other
             less potent CYP1A2 inhibitors/inducers are not excluded (see appendix 13-9)

         19. Gastrointestinal abnormalities, including bowel obstruction, inability to take oral
             medication, requirement for intravenous (IV) alimentation, active peptic ulcer or
             prior surgical procedures or bowel resection or other poorly controlled
             gastrointestinal disorders that could affect the absorption of study drug (eg,
             Crohn's disease or ulcerative colitis);

         20. Peripheral neuropathy ≥ grade 2;

         21. Significant liver disease or metastatic disease to the liver;

         22. History of amyloid, plasma cell leukemia or CNS involvement.

         23. Prior radiation therapy or major surgical procedure within 4 weeks of the first dose
             of study treatment (this does not include limited course of radiation used for
             management of bone pain).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Suzanne Trudel, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UHN-PMH</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University Winship Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kenisha Barron</last_name>
      <phone>404-778-5144</phone>
      <email>kbarron@emory.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jonathan Kaufman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Of Chicago Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathryn McDonnell, BS</last_name>
      <phone>773-702-1835</phone>
      <email>kmcdonnell@bsd.uchicago.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrzej Jakubowiak, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Elizabeth II Health Sciences Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Halifax</city>
        <state>Nova Scotia</state>
        <zip>B3H2Y9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Donna Mann, RN</last_name>
      <phone>(902) 429-2597</phone>
      <email>Donna.mann@cdha.nshealth.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Darrell White, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Health Network-Princess Margaret Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Engin Gul, HBSc</last_name>
      <phone>416 946 4501</phone>
      <phone_ext>2608</phone_ext>
      <email>engin.gul@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Suzanne Trudel, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sir Mortimer B. Davis-Jewish General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3T 1E3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Caroline Lambert, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>514-340-8222</phone>
      <phone_ext>4599</phone_ext>
      <email>clambert@jgh.mcgill.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Martin Gyger, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Maisonneuve-Rosemont</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H1T 2M4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nathalie Lachapelle, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>514-252-3400</phone>
      <phone_ext>4471</phone_ext>
      <email>nlachapelle.hmr@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard LeBlanc, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 18, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 1, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Relapsed or relapse/refractory Multiple Myeloma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone 21-phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bortezomib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
