<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="14834">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01737008</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>XDC-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01737008</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Dacomitinib With Radiotherapy With and Without Cisplatin in Patients With Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Head and Neck</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Trial of Dacomitinib Concomitant With Radiotherapy With and Without Cisplatin in Patients With Locally Advanced Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Head and Neck</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 1 study of investigational drug dacomitinib with radiotherapy and with or
      without chemotherapy in patients with advanced squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck
      (SCCHN).

      There are proteins found on the surface of cells called receptors that receive signals and
      send signals to the cell to grow or to die. Dacomitinib is an oral drug that blocks a
      receptor called the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) which is found to be too active
      in SCCHN patients. By blocking the signals for the cancer cells to grow, it is believed to
      stop or slow the growth of tumor cells. The treatment of SCCHN usually includes chemotherapy
      and radiation.

      This study will have two phases: a dose escalation phase and a dose expansion phase. The
      dose escalation phase will find the best dose as well as determine the safety of dacomitinib
      when given with radiotherapy and with or without chemotherapy.The dose expansion phase will
      further test the best dose determined in the dose escalation phase for safety and
      effectiveness.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (in mg) of Dacomitinib</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of Dacomitinib in the Blood (Pharmacokinetics) in Combination with Cisplatin and Radiation</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 8, 22 and 43 (+2 day window) after initial dose</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants and Length of Time That Participants are Disease Free</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants who are Alive after 6 and 12 Months Post Completion of Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants and Length of Time That Participants do not Experience Distant Metastasis</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Head and Neck</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dacomitinib with Radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dacomitinib, 15mg to 45mg orally, once daily.  Radiotherapy, once daily (Monday to Friday) over six weeks.One day on weeks 2 to 6 the participants will receive treatment twice daily (bid).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dacomitinib and Chemoradiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dacomitinib: 15mg to 45mg orally, once daily. Radiotherapy: Once daily (Monday to Friday) over seven weeks. Twice daily (bid) treatments may be introduced to compensate for treatment days missed due to statutory holidays, or machine maintenance. Cisplatin: 100mg/m2 intravenously; weeks 1, 4, and 7.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dacomitinib</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Dacomitinib with Radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dacomitinib and Chemoradiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PF-00299804</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Dacomitinib with Radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dacomitinib and Chemoradiotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Dacomitinib and Chemoradiotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed written and voluntary informed consent provided.

          -  Patient must be willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan,
             pharmacokinetic assessments, laboratory tests and other study procedures.

          -  Age ≥ 18 years, male or female.

          -  Dose escalation phase: Arm A: patients with local or locally advanced, histologically
             or cytologically confirmed SCCHN, candidates for radical radiotherapy might be
             eligible. Arm B: previously untreated patients, with locally advanced, histologically
             or cytologically confirmed SCCHN candidates for radical concurrent cisplatin-based
             chemoradiation will be eligible.

          -  Dose expansion phase: previously untreated patients, with locally advanced,
             histologically or cytologically confirmed SCCHN, HPV-negative determined by lack of
             p16 immunohistochemical staining, candidates for radical concurrent cisplatin-based
             chemoradiation will be eligible. Note: Patients with primary tumors of head and neck
             in nasopharynx, skin, or unknown are excluded.

          -  Prior treatment with biological agents targeted to the epidermal growth factor
             receptor is not allowed.

          -  Prior chemotherapy or radiotherapy for the treatment of the current neoplasm is not
             allowed

          -  Patient must not have received any prior anti-neoplastic treatment within the past 2
             years.

          -  Any treatment-related acute toxicity, including laboratory abnormalities, must have
             recovered to CTCAE Grade 1 (NCI CTCAE v.4.0) or baseline, except toxicity not
             considered a safety risk.  Chronic dysphagia or xerostomia or other local effect
             resulting from prior surgery will not be considered an exclusion criterion.

          -  ECOG performance status of 0-1.

          -  Patient must have adequate organ function as determined by the following criteria
             for:

               -  Renal function: Estimated creatinine clearance of ≥ 50 mL/min using the
                  following formula: Creatinine clearance = [(140-age) x wt (kg) x Constant] /
                  creatinine (µmol/L)  [Constant = 1.23 for men and 1.04 for women]

               -  Bone marrow function  (without hematopoietic growth factors or transfusion):
                  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 109/L; Leukocytes &gt; 3.0 x 109/L;
                  Hemoglobin &gt; 80 g/L (or &gt; 8 g/dL); Platelets ≥ 100 x 109/L

               -  Liver function: Total bilirubin ≤ ULN; AST (SGOT) and ALT (SGPT) ≤ 2.5 x ULN

               -  Cardiac function: 12-Lead electrocardiogram (ECG) with normal tracing, or
                  clinically non-significant changes that do not require medical intervention.
                  QTc interval &lt; 480 msec, and without history of Torsades de Pointes or other
                  symptomatic QTc abnormality.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient cannot be concurrently enrolled on another clinical trial while enrolled on
             this study.

          -  Prior investigational drug therapy within 30 days or 5 half-lives preceding the first
             dose of study medication (whichever is longer).

          -  Requirement for treatment with drugs that are highly dependent on CYP2D6 for
             metabolism since dacomitinib is a potent CYP2D6 inhibitor in in vitro assays. [See
             Appendix B: prohibited medication list; Appendix C: use with caution medication
             list].

          -  Patients currently taking drugs that are generally accepted to have a risk of causing
             Torsades de Pointes

          -  Any acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition or laboratory abnormality that
             could increase the risk associated with trial participation or trial drug
             administration or could interfere with the interpretation of trial results and, in
             the judgment of the investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for entry in
             the trial.  This includes:

               -  History of interstitial lung disease;

               -  Uncontrolled hypertension, unstable angina, myocardial infarction or symptomatic
                  congestive heart failure within the past 12 months or serious uncontrolled
                  cardiac arrhythmia, diagnosed or suspected congenital long QT syndrome;

               -  Patients with minimally symptomatic cardiovascular (e.g. ischemic heart disease,
                  congestive cardiac failure, arrhythmia) or vascular disease (e.g. stroke, deep
                  venous thrombosis) who had anti arrhythmic therapy and/or significant changes to
                  medical care within 6 months to enrolment;

               -  Active bacterial, fungal or viral infection including hepatitis B (HBV),
                  hepatitis C (HCV), and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).  Serological testing
                  will not be required at baseline for patients who have no symptoms suggestive of
                  infection.

               -  History of significant bleeding disorder, or concurrent medications that are
                  felt in the opinion of the investigator to potentially lead to unacceptable
                  coagulation function  during perioperative interval, including:

               -  Diagnosed congenital bleeding disorders (e.g., von Willebrand's disease);

               -  Diagnosed acquired bleeding disorder within one year (e.g., acquired anti-factor
                  VIII antibodies).

               -  Other serious uncontrolled medical disorder or active infection that would
                  impair the ability to receive study treatment as determined by the investigator.

               -  Dementia or significantly altered mental status that would limit the ability to
                  obtain informed consent and compliance with the requirements of this protocol.

          -  Female patients who are breastfeeding or pregnant are excluded.  All female patients
             with reproductive potential must have a negative pregnancy test (serum/urine) within
             72 hours prior to starting treatment.  Female patients of reproductive potential
             include any female who has experienced menarche and who has not undergone successful
             surgical sterilization (hysterectomy, bilateral tubal ligation or bilateral
             oophorectomy) or is not postmenopausal (defined as amenorrhea &gt;12 consecutive months;
             or women on hormone replacement therapy (HRT) with documented serum follicle
             stimulating hormone (FSH) level &gt;35 mL.U/mL).

          -  Female patients of reproductive potential or their partners must agree to use
             effective contraception while receiving trial treatment and for at least 3 months
             thereafter.  The definition of effective contraception will be based on the judgment
             of the principal investigator or designated associate.

          -  Inability or lack of willingness to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plans,
             protocol assessments or laboratory tests.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lillian Siu, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Princess Margaret Cancer Centre/University Health Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Meghan Perry, B.Sc.Hons.</last_name>
    <phone>416-946-4501</phone>
    <phone_ext>3181</phone_ext>
    <email>meghan.perry@uhn.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princess Margaret Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lillian Siu, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 21, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 26, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Head and neck</keyword>
  <keyword>Squamous cell carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase 1</keyword>
  <keyword>Dacomitinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiation</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemoradiation</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemoradiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Cisplatin</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Maximum tolerated dose</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Human epidermal growth factor receptor</keyword>
  <keyword>Previously Untreated</keyword>
  <keyword>Local or Locally Advanced</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
