<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="82156">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01715948</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDHA-RS/2013-118</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01715948</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of BAHA and CROS Hearing Aid in Single-Sided Deafness</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of BAHA and CROS Hearing Aid in Single-Sided Deafness</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Manohar Bance</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dalhousie University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Capital District Health Authority, Canada</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      People with single-sided deafness (SSD) have significant hearing loss in one ear and normal
      or near normal hearing in the other ear.  Those living with SSD experience several
      communication difficulties, particularly when listening to speech in the presence of
      background noise.  This problem is worse in situations where the noise is on the side of the
      good ear and the speech is on the side of the poor ear.

      The Bone-Anchored Hearing Aid (BAHA) and the Contralateral Routing of Signals (CROS) hearing
      aid are two devices designed to improve hearing in people who have significant hearing loss
      in one ear only.  The BAHA is a surgically implanted device which also includes an external
      processor; sounds from the poor ear are transmitted to the good ear through skull
      vibrations. The CROS does not involve surgery; instead a hearing aid is fitted behind each
      ear, and the sounds on the side of the poor ear are wirelessly transmitted to the good ear.

      The majority of previous studies comparing the BAHA to the CROS have used older CROS models
      with basic technology and a wire along the neck to send sounds from the poor ear to the good
      ear.  There is a lack of studies comparing newer digital wireless CROS hearing aids to the
      BAHA. The current research will compare the effect of the BAHA and CROS hearing aid on
      speech perception scores when listening to speech in quiet and in noise. The research will
      also investigate patients' reported benefits with each device during everyday situations. In
      order to compare the BAHA and CROS, individuals who already have been implanted with a BAHA
      will be given a trial period with a new wireless digital CROS hearing aid.

      The research hypothesis states that the CROS hearing aid will be as equally beneficial or
      greater than the BAHA in improving hearing and patient benefit. If the findings support the
      hypothesis that the CROS offers just as much benefits as the BAHA, or is an even better
      alternative, more patients may choose to avoid surgery and decide to receive a CROS hearing
      aid instead.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Users of BAHA will be given a 2-week trial period with the Unitron Tandem CROS hearing aid.
      Participants will be randomly assigned to wear either their BAHA for two weeks or the trial
      CROS for two weeks. There will be a total of three visits made to the clinic.

      During each visit:

        -  Participants' hearing will be tested (either with the BAHA, the CROS, or without
           wearing any device).

        -  Speech perception ability will be tested in quiet and in noise conditions (either while
           wearing the BAHA, the CROS, or no device).

        -  Participants will be asked to complete two standardized questionnaires on the perceived
           benefits that the BAHA or the CROS provides.

      In addition, participants will be asked to fill out a short diary form every day, for a
      two-week period, to report the situations in which they wore the device.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Speech-in-noise (QuickSIN) test scores</measure>
    <time_frame>The QuickSIN will be administered unaided (no device) during the first visit to the clinic, and will be administered again at the end of a two-week trial with the CROS and at the end of a two-week use of the BAHA.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The QuickSIN is a speech in noise test. Participants are asked to repeat sentences while listening in multi-talker background noise.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bern Benefit in Single-Sided Deafness Questionnaire (BBSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Will be administered at the end of a two-week trial with the CROS and at the end of a two-week use of the BAHA.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The BBSS is a 10-item questionnaire that measures participants' perceived benefit from their BAHA or CROS hearing aid.  The items examine different situations in which participants score the benefit derived from their device with ratings that range from -5 (&quot;Much Easier Without the Aid&quot;) to +5 (&quot;Much Easier With the Aid&quot;).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Speech Spatial Qualities Questionnaire (SSQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Will be administered at the end of a two-week trial with the CROS and at the end of a two-week use of the BAHA.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Speech Spatial Qualities Questionnaire describes 49 scenarios in which participants may experience difficulty hearing.  For both the BAHA and CROS, participants will be asked to rate their perceived hearing ability for all scenarios on a 10-point scale, ranging from &quot;Not at all&quot; to &quot;Perfectly&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Unilateral Hearing Loss</condition>
  <condition>Unilateral Deafness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CROS hearing aid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who have been implanted with a BAHA over the past three years will be given a two-week trial period with a CROS hearing aid. The CROS uses two hearing aids that fit behind each ear. The hearing aid fitted on the side of the poor ear houses a microphone and a transmitter. The hearing aid fitted on the normal ear side houses a receiver that is connected to an open ear tip.  Sounds on the side of the poor ear are picked up by the microphone and transmitted to the opposite normal ear, overcoming the head shadow effect that presents with unilateral deafness.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CROS hearing aid</intervention_name>
    <description>BAHA users will be fitted with the CROS hearing aid for a two-week trial period. Their hearing abilities with the CROS hearing aid will be compared to their hearing abilities with their BAHA over a two-week period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CROS hearing aid</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Unitron Tandem 4 CROS hearing aid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults with unilateral deafness (hearing loss in only one ear) who received BAHA
             surgery less than 3 years ago

          -  Severe to profound hearing loss in the poor ear and normal hearing in the good ear

          -  English speaking

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults who underwent BAHA surgery more than 3 years ago

          -  Adults with hearing loss in both ears

          -  Adults who received a BAHA to treat a condition other than unilateral deafness (such
             as bilateral conductive hearing loss)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Manohar Bance, FRCS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Capital Health, Canada</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rachel Caissie, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dalhousie University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer Finbow, B.Sc.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dalhousie University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer Finbow, B.Sc.</last_name>
    <phone>902-266-6320</phone>
    <email>jennifer.finbow@dal.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>School of Human Communication Disorders</name>
      <address>
        <city>Halifax</city>
        <state>Nova Scotia</state>
        <zip>B3J 1Y6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer Finbow, B.Sc.</last_name>
      <phone>902-266-6320</phone>
      <email>jennifer.finbow@dal.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jennifer Finbow, B.Sc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 28, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 23, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Capital District Health Authority, Canada</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Manohar Bance</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Staff Physician Division of Otolaryngology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CROS hearing aid</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone-anchored hearing device</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Deafness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss, Unilateral</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
