<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="111054">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02030665</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NIDA-12728-11</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02030665</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Marijuana Treatment Project 4</brief_title>
  <acronym>MTP4</acronym>
  <official_title>Individualized Assessment and Treatment for Marijuana Dependence: Treatment Mechanisms</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Connecticut Health Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Connecticut Health Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Marijuana is the most commonly used illicit drug in the US, but treatment for marijuana
      dependence is not fully effective. In the current proposal we are exploring the idea that
      more tailored teaching of coping skills may result in improved outcomes for
      marijuana-dependence than those seen thus far.Participants will be 275 men and women meeting
      criteria for marijuana dependence and randomly assigned to 9 sessions of treatment in one of
      4 treatment conditions: Standardized MET plus CB (SMET-CB); SMET+ CM (SMET-CB-CM); IATP; or
      IATP + CM (IATP-CM).  Patients in all treatments will engage in ES via cell-phone for two
      weeks prior to treatment, for a weekly period during treatment, for another week after
      treatment has ended, and for two weekly periods at months 8 and 14. In the IATP conditions,
      the information gathered from the pretreatment and during-treatment ES periods will provide
      data for a functional analysis of patients' drug use and urges to use. It is hypothesized
      that IATP conditions will yield significantly better coping skills acquisition than SMET-CB
      conditions, both at posttreatment and at extended follow-ups, and that change in coping
      skills will predict better outcomes for the IATP conditions
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Marijuana is the most commonly used illicit drug in the US, but treatment for marijuana
      dependence is not fully effective. The most effective treatments to date have employed
      motivational enhancement (MET) plus cognitive-behavioral coping skills treatment (CB) and
      contingency management (CM) for abstinence. This proposal is a competitive renewal of our
      recently completed study to enhance coping and self-efficacy to improve marijuana outcomes
      in the long term.  In the current proposal we are exploring the idea that more tailored
      teaching of coping skills may result in improved outcomes for marijuana-dependence than
      those seen thus far. The Individualized Assessment and Treatment Program (IATP) for
      marijuana dependent patients will employ experience sampling (ES) to determine the strengths
      and weaknesses of each patient in drug-use situations so that treatment can be tailored
      accordingly. Results from a pilot study indicated that IATP for alcohol dependent patients
      yielded better drinking outcomes at posttreatment than a packaged CB program (PCBT), that
      IATP patients reported greater use of coping skills than PCBT participants, and that
      posttreatment reports of coping skills were related to posttreatment drinking.
      Participants will be 275 men and women meeting criteria for marijuana dependence and
      randomly assigned to 9 sessions of treatment in one of 4 treatment conditions: Standardized
      MET plus CB (SMET-CB); SMET+ CM (SMET-CB-CM); IATP; or IATP + CM (IATP-CM).  Patients in all
      treatments will engage in ES via cell-phone for two weeks prior to treatment, for a weekly
      period during treatment, for another week after treatment has ended, and for two weekly
      periods at months 8 and 14. In the IATP conditions, the information gathered from the
      pretreatment and during-treatment ES periods will provide data for a functional analysis of
      patients' drug use and urges to use. Therapists will use the information to address specific
      cognitions, affects, and behaviors that are adaptive and maladaptive, and will tailor a
      specific coping skills program with the patient. During-treatment experience sampling will
      allow adjustment of the treatment goals and procedures, making the treatment adaptive. In
      the SMET-CB conditions the experience sampling data will not be used in therapy, but will
      still provide in-vivo measures of drinking and coping skills. It is hypothesized that IATP
      conditions will yield significantly better coping skills acquisition than SMET-CB
      conditions, both at posttreatment and at extended follow-ups, and that change in coping
      skills will predict better outcomes for the IATP conditions.  It is further predicted that
      the addition of CM to both IATP and SMET-CB will enhance short-term and long-term outcomes.
      The results will have implications for improved tailoring of treatment to patients' strength
      and deficits, and for the validity of the training of coping skills for relapse prevention.
      The data collected will shed light on the ways in which patients in treatment use coping
      skills in real-time contexts. Finally, the use of repeated ES periods will allow us to
      determine how treatment impacts thoughts, feelings and behaviors, and how these in turn
      affect outcome in the long and short term.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Factorial Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Marijuana Use</measure>
    <time_frame>every 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Marijuana use measured in terms of Days of use in every 90-day period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Coping Skills</measure>
    <time_frame>every 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Coping Skills measured using the Coping Skills Survey, administered every 3 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">275</enrollment>
  <condition>Marijuana Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standardized MET plus CB (SMET-CB)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Motivational Enhancement plus Cognitive-Behavioral treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SMET+ CM (SMET-CB-CM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Motivational Enhancement plus CB treatment plus contingency management</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IATP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individualized Assessment and Treatment Program; Cognitive-Behavioral  Treatment based on in-depth field monitoring of patient behavior</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IATP + CM (IATP-CM).</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individualized Assessment and Treatment plus Contingency Management</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Contingency Management</intervention_name>
    <description>Reinforcement provided contingent upon demonstration of negative drug tests</description>
    <arm_group_label>SMET+ CM (SMET-CB-CM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>IATP + CM (IATP-CM).</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Positive Reinforcement</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Individualized Assessment &amp; Treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Tailored Cognitive-Behavioral Treatment based on detailed records of patient behavior</description>
    <arm_group_label>IATP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>IATP + CM (IATP-CM).</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IATP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive-Behavioral Treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard psychoeducational approach  to coping skills training</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standardized MET plus CB (SMET-CB)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CBT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  at least 18 yrs old

          -  meet DSM-IV criteria for Cannabis Dependence

          -  be willing to accept random assignment to any of the 4 treatment conditions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  acute medical/psychiatric problems that require inpatient treatment (e.g., acute
             psychosis, severe depression, suicide/homicide risk)

          -  reading ability below the fifth grade level

          -  lack of reliable transportation

          -  excessive commuting distance.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark D Litt, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Connecticut Health Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elise Kabela-Cormier, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Connecticut Health Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark D Litt, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>860-679-4680</phone>
    <email>Litt@nso.uchc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elise Kabela-Cormier, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>860-679-2657</phone>
    <email>kabela@uchc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Connecticut Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Farmington</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://marijuanatreatment.uchc.edu</url>
    <description>Link to Public Project Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 7, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Marijuana Dependence</keyword>
  <keyword>Individualized treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Motivational Enhancement Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive-Behavioral Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Contingency Management</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Marijuana Abuse</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
