<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="134653">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02123979</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-000723</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>112101 668916</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02123979</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Assess Dopamine Receptor Modulation With Rotigotine to Enhance Morphine Analgesia in the Dental Model</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Randomized Parallel Group Study to Assess Dopamine Receptor Modulation With Rotigotine to Enhance Morphine Analgesia in the Dental Model of Acute Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>East Carolina University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>East Carolina University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Based on our established laboratory data demonstrating that the spinal dopamine system, via
      the D3 receptor signaling cascade controls opioid responsiveness, the investigators
      hypothesize that patients provided a continuous release of an approved D3 agonist will
      achieve pain relief with lower doses of morphine, reducing the potential for tolerance and
      addiction. The investigators predict that the investigators can improve the pain control
      provided by morphine and effectively prevent morphine tolerance in the treatment of pain
      with adjuvant manipulation of the D3 receptors. The investigators specifically aim to assess
      the translational potential of D3 receptor modulation in human subjects experiencing painful
      conditions as a means to enhance morphine analgesia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Inclusion Criteria:

        -  Male and female patients aged 18 and over scheduled to undergo elective oral surgery
           for the removal of impacted third molars

        -  Indicated for the removal of 3-4 third molars, at least two of which are categorized as
           partial-boney or full-boney impactions

        -  Self-report of moderate or severe pain on a categorical scale with a minimum of 5 out
           of 10 on the numerical rating scale following the offset of local anesthesia

      Exclusion Criteria:

        -  History or intolerance to rotigotine

        -  Current or history of mental disorder or substance abuse

        -  Allergy or intolerance to opioids or local anesthetics

        -  Concurrent or recent use of agents that may confound the sedative effects of the study
           drug (opioids, benzodiazepines) over the previous 7 days or alcohol ingestion in the
           previous 24 hours

        -  Chronic or recent use of medications that might confound the effects of rotigotine,
           e.g., antihistamines, prescription or over-the-counter NSAIDs (Nonsteroidal
           anti-inflammatory drugs), acetaminophen, steroids, antidepressants, muscle relaxants.

        -  Concurrent or history of chronic diseases, e.g., diabetes, rheumatoid arthritis, liver
           disease, cancer, hypertension or obesity (body mass index &gt;35).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sum of pain intensity difference scores</measure>
    <time_frame>up to six months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary outcome measure will be the SPID (sum of pain intensity difference scores) over the 3-hour observation period for MS(morphine sulfate)+Nuepro versus MS.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Analgesic tablets taken postoperatively</measure>
    <time_frame>December 2014</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of analgesic tablets taken over the first 48 hours postoperatively will be compared between the two groups as a secondary measure of the ability of the D3 agonist to potentiate opioid analgesia as a surrogate indicator of reduced potential for tolerance development.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>assess pain</measure>
    <time_frame>up 48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>assess the translational potential of what has been demonstrated in the lab to human subjects experiencing painful conditions that require control with morphine. We hope to provide proof of concept for a treatment strategy that will allow opiates to maintain their effectiveness at low doses without the emergence of tolerance and other side effects, even with prolonged use.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-op Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo patch</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Neupro®  transdermal patch/placebo randomly allocated like a flip of a coin applied to your skin at the dose of 8 mg/day or a matching placebo patch after the oral surgery procedure is completed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neupro®  transdermal patch</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Neupro®  transdermal patch/placebo randomly allocated like a flip of a coin applied to your skin at the dose of 8 mg/day or a matching placebo patch after the oral surgery procedure is completed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neupro®  transdermal patch/placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>8mg  transdermal patch Neupro®  transdermal patch/placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>placebo patch</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Neupro®  transdermal patch</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>also known as rotigotine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  • Male and female patients aged 18 and over scheduled to undergo elective oral
             surgery for the removal of impacted third molars

               -  Indicated for the removal of 3-4 third molars, at least two of which are
                  categorized as partial-boney or full-boney impactions

               -  Self-report of moderate or severe pain on a categorical scale with a minimum of
                  5 out of 10 on the numerical rating scale following the offset of local
                  anesthesia

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History or intolerance to rotigotine

               -  Current or history of mental disorder or substance abuse

               -  Allergy or intolerance to opioids or local anesthetics

               -  Concurrent or recent use of agents that may confound the sedative effects of the
                  study drug (opioids, benzodiazepines) over the previous 7 days or alcohol
                  ingestion in the previous 24 hours

               -  Chronic or recent use of medications that might confound the effects of
                  rotigotine, e.g., antihistamines, prescription or over-the-counter NSAIDs,
                  acetaminophen, steroids, antidepressants, muscle relaxants.

               -  Concurrent or history of chronic diseases, e.g., diabetes, rheumatoid arthritis,
                  liver disease, cancer, hypertension or obesity (body mass index &gt;35).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raymond Dionne, DDS, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>School of Dental Medicine, East Carolina University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>School of Dental Medicine At East Carolina University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greenville</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27834</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Raymond Dionne</last_name>
      <phone>252-744-2108</phone>
      <email>dionner@ecu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raymond Dionne, DDS, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>East Carolina University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Raymond Dionne</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Raymond A. Dionne, DDS, PhD Research Professor Department of Pharmacology &amp; Toxicology Brody School of Medicine Department of Foundational Sciences School of Dental Medicine East Carolina University Greenville, NC 27834-4354</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dopamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>N 0437</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
