<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="137922">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01975181</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>372910-6</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01975181</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cardiovascular Prevention Program Registry</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cardiovascular Prevention Program Registry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Walter Reed National Military Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Walter Reed National Military Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Cardiovascular Prevention Program (CPP) Registry seeks to improve the cardiovascular
      disease (CVD) risk profile of subjects through therapeutic lifestyle change using an
      integrative model of medicine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Through improvements in lifestyle choices regarding diet, exercise, sleep and stress
      management, the CPP Registry expects to find improvements in calculated risk for heart
      disease and stroke.

      Upon entry to the CPP Registry, subjects are given a detailed assessment of CVD risk through
      their reported past medical history, family history, review of systems, physical
      examination, laboratory data including lipid profile and glucose metabolism,
      electrocardiogram and/or exercise stress test, and carotid ultrasound for intima-medial
      thickness. Framingham risk score is calculated and in combination with other factors, a
      global score for CVD risk is appraised.

      Subjects then attend a half-day workshop on heart healthy behaviors including a cooking
      demonstration that promulgates a Mediterranean Diet. At approximately monthly intervals,
      subjects consult in 20 minute appointments with a dietician, exercise physiologist, and
      stress management coach to work on behavioral improvements to encourage heart health.

      At program's end, typically 6 to 8 months after enrollment in the Registry, subjects repeat
      their CVD risk assessment to receive a personal report card detailing the results of their
      therapeutic lifestyle changes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>3 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in Cardiovascular Disease Risk Score</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A cardiovascular disease risk score is calculated using the Framingham Risk Score PLUS other factors including family history, body mass index, diastolic blood pressure, high sensitivity C-reactive protein, low-density lipoprotein, triglyceride and lipoprotein(a).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in Dietary Score using the Rate-Your-Plate Dietary Assessment Tool</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Specific dietary behaviors are surveyed using the Rate-Your-Plate Dietary Assessment Tool with scores for each behavior ranging from 0 to 3. A high score indicates a healthy dietary behavior. All individual scores are added to calculate an overall score for healthful eating.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) score</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Using the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ), subjects report how much continuous exertional activity they accomplish each week.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in Perceived Stress Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Using the Perceived Stress Scale, subjects report on subjectively experienced stress levels over the several weeks prior to the measurement date.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subjects complete the questionnaire (PSQI) to have a global assessment of their sleep quality for the time period including a month before the questionnaire completion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic Lifestyle Change Arm</arm_group_label>
    <description>All subjects entering the Registry will receive therapeutic lifestyle change interventions for diet, exercise, stress management and sleep improvement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diet</intervention_name>
    <description>In receiving recommendations for a Mediterranean-style diet, subjects are encouraged to get protein predominantly from fish and legumes, fat from olive oil or other sources high in omega-3 oils, to eat whole grains and complex carbohydrates while avoiding highly processed foods. Subjects are also coached on portion control, stress-eating and snacking, aiming for adequate water intake, and eating meals including breakfast with regularity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic Lifestyle Change Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mediterranean-style diet</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>After assessing safety of exercise with a supervised, graded exercise tolerance test, subjects are given a prescription for exercise with activities tailored to their preferences and physical limitations aiming for at least 150 minutes of continuous aerobic exercise per week.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic Lifestyle Change Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stress Management</intervention_name>
    <description>In supervised coaching sessions and with assigned homework behaviors, subjects learn to use a &quot;tension tamer&quot; with visualized imagery, deep breathing, and progressive muscle relaxation to live with lower levels of stress.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic Lifestyle Change Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Stress Reduction</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sleep Improvement</intervention_name>
    <description>After evaluation of treatment of sleep pathologies such as obstructive sleep apnea and periodic limb movement disorder, subjects are taught to employ &quot;tension tamer&quot; techniques and pursue daily exercise to improve sleep latency and sleep continuity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic Lifestyle Change Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adult Military Health-Care Beneficiaries
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: The CPP Registry is a clinical program available to any adult (age 18
        years or older) military health care beneficiary. Subjects who present to the CPP for
        evaluation and participation may be self-referred or be referred by a provider. A majority
        of participants are free of cardiovascular disease symptoms. Participants elect to enroll
        in order to learn about healthy lifestyle choices that can help prevent the development of
        cardiovascular disease.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Less than 18 years of age.

          2. Individuals unable or unwilling to participate or give informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Randolph E Modlin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Walter Reed National Military Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marina N Vernalis, DO</last_name>
    <phone>301-400-1111</phone>
    <email>marina.n.vernalis.ctr@health.mil</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Integrative Cardiac Health Project, Walter Reed National Military Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20889</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lydia Hill, BA</last_name>
      <phone>301-400-1111</phone>
      <email>lydia.hill@med.navy.mil</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Christa A Caporiccio, BA</last_name>
      <phone>301-400-1111</phone>
      <email>christa.a.caporiccio.ctr@health.mil</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marina N Vernalis, DO</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mariam D Kashani, DNP</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Arn H Eliasson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 16, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cardiovascular disease risk factors</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiovascular disease prevention</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
