<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="119465">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02060370</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-0944</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02060370</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sunitinib Scheduling in Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma (mRCC)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Alternative Sunitinib Scheduling in Patients With Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma (mRCC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The standard method for giving sunitinib is 4 weeks in which the patient receives the drug
      every day, followed by 2 weeks in which the patient receives no drug.  These 6 week cycles
      are then repeated.  However, side effects are often seen to increase and get worse during
      the 4 weeks of treatment, especially during the last 2 weeks.  Researchers want to learn if
      shortening the treatment cycles can help to decrease the frequency and severity of side
      effects.

      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn more about the safety of giving
      sunitinib to patients with metastatic kidney cancer for 2 weeks followed by 1 week in which
      they receive no drug.  The side effects from and effectiveness of this dosing schedule will
      be studied and compared to those of the standard.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Drug Administration:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will take sunitinib capsules
      by mouth every day for 2 weeks, followed by 1 week in which you do not receive any study
      drug.  This will then be repeated every 3 weeks.

      Every 6 weeks will be 1 study cycle.

      If you have any side effects tell the study doctor right away.  The study doctor may change
      your dose of the study drug.

      Study Visits:

      Every day during the first week, and then at least 1 time each week during the study, your
      blood pressure will be checked (either at home, at the clinic, or by your local doctor).
      You will need to write down your blood pressure in a blood pressure diary each time you
      check it and bring the diary with you to each clinic visit.

      On Day 1 of Cycle 1:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 3-4 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine and biomarker testing.

        -  You will fill out a questionnaire about the quality of your life and about how you are
           feeling.  This should take about 5 minutes.

      On Day 35 of every cycle:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 3-4 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      On Day 35 of every even-numbered cycle (Cycles 2, 4, 6, and so on):

        -  You will have a CT scan of your chest, abdomen, and pelvis.

        -  Blood (about 1 tablespoon) will be drawn to check your thyroid function.

        -  Blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for biomarker testing. (Cycles 2 , 4, and 6
           only)

        -  You will fill out the questionnaire about the quality of your life and about how you
           are feeling. (Cycles 2 , 4, and 6 only)

      At any time that the doctor thinks it is needed, additional blood (about 1 tablespoon) may
      be drawn to check your thyroid function, and you may need to have a bone scan and CT scan or
      MRI of the brain to check the status of the disease.

      Length of Study:

      You may continue taking the study drug for as long as the study doctor thinks it is in your
      best interest.  You will be taken off study if the disease gets worse, intolerable side
      effects occur, or if you are unable to follow study directions.

      Your participation in this study will be over after the follow-up visit.

      End-of-Treatment Visit:

      After you are no longer receiving the study drug, you will have an end-of-treatment visit
      and blood (about 3-4 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine and biomarker testing.

      Follow-Up Visit:

      About 30 days after your end-of-treatment visit you will have a follow-up visit and blood
      (about 3-4 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      This is an investigational study.  Sunitinib is FDA approved and commercially available to
      treat advanced kidney cancer.  The dosing schedule being used on this study is
      investigational.

      Up to 60 participants will be enrolled in this study.  Up to 15 will take part at MD
      Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Composite rate of toxicity defined as percentage of patients who experience one or more of the following ≥grade 3 toxicities using CTCAE version 4.03 criteria that are possibly, probably, or definitely related to study therapy: fatigue, hand-foot syndrome (HFS), or diarrhea.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 35 of second, 12 week cycle</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Progression-free survival (PFS) defined as time from treatment initiation to disease progression using Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) Version 1 or death. PFS measured from the date of initiation of treatment to the first of documented progression or death; and estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Genitourinary Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Kidney Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sunitinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sunitinib starting dose 50 mg by mouth daily given for 2 weeks &quot;on&quot; followed by 1 week &quot;off&quot;.  1 cycle is 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sunitinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Starting dose: 50 mg by mouth daily given for 2 weeks &quot;on&quot; followed by 1 week &quot;off&quot;. 1 cycle is 6 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sunitinib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sunitinib Malate</other_name>
    <other_name>SUO11248</other_name>
    <other_name>Sutent</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>Questionnaire completion on Day 1 of Cycle 1, and on Day 35 of Cycles 2, 4, and 6.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sunitinib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Survey</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically or cytologically-confirmed metastatic renal cell carcinoma of clear
             cell histology

          2. Age &gt;/=18 years

          3. Measurable or evaluable metastatic disease per RECIST v 1

          4. ECOG performance status 0-1 or Karnofsky's performance score &gt;/= 70

          5. Normal organ and bone marrow function as defined by: Serum aspartate transaminase
             (AST) or serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT) and serum alanine
             transaminase (ALT) or serum glutamic pyruvic transaminase (SGPT) &lt;/= 2.5 x laboratory
             upper limit of normal (ULN); Total serum bilirubin &lt;/= 2.0 x ULN; Absolute neutrophil
             count (ANC) &gt;/= 1500/µL; Platelets &gt;/= 100,000/µL; Hemoglobin &gt;/= 9.0 g/dL
             (transfusion permitted); Serum calcium &lt;/= 12.0 mg/dL; Serum creatinine &lt;/= 2.5 mg/dL

          6. Subjects must have the ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written
             informed consent document

          7. Prior nephrectomy is not a requirement for eligibility

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior treatment with sunitinib or any other systemic therapy in the metastatic
             setting (prior neo/adjuvant therapy will be allowed if completed &gt; 6 months prior to
             registration and therapy not discontinued for toxicity)

          2. Uncontrolled hypertension (defined as blood pressure &gt;140/90 mm Hg not controlled
             with anti-hypertensives)

          3. Prior intrabdominal, intrathoracic, vascular, spinal or intracranial surgery or
             radiation therapy within 4 weeks of starting treatment

          4. History of or known brain metastases, spinal cord compression, or carcinomatous
             meningitis

          5. New York Heart Association (NYHA) grade II or greater congestive heart failure

          6. Current treatment on another therapeutic clinical trial

          7. Any of the following within the preceding 6 months- myocardial infarction,
             severe/unstable angina, severe peripheral vascular disease (claudication) or
             procedure on peripheral vasculature, coronary/peripheral artery bypass, graft,
             cerebrovascular accident or transient ischemic attack, clinically significant
             bleeding

          8. Pregnant or breastfeeding women are excluded from this study because there is an
             unknown, but potential risk for adverse events in nursing infants secondary to
             treatment of the mother with sunitinib. Breastfeeding must be discontinued if the
             mother is treated with sunitinib

          9. Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or acquired immunodeficiency syndrome
             (AIDS)-related illness

         10. HIV-positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible because of
             the potential for pharmacokinetic interactions with sunitinib. In addition, these
             patients are at increased risk of lethal infections when treated with marrow
             suppressive therapy

         11. Patients with a history of deep venous thromboembolism or pulmonary embolism on
             treatment with anticoagulation are eligible for the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eric Jonasch, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eric Jonasch, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-2830</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lineberger Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27514</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic Taussig Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fox Chase Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19111-2497</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 30, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 10, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Genitourinary Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Kidney Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>mRCC</keyword>
  <keyword>Sunitinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Sunitinib malate</keyword>
  <keyword>SUO11248</keyword>
  <keyword>Sutent</keyword>
  <keyword>Questionnaire</keyword>
  <keyword>Survey</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urogenital Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sunitinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
