<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35276">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02075320</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LCCC1337</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02075320</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Lung Nodule Sensitivity of Stationary Chest Tomosynthesis in Patients With Known Lung Nodules</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Lung Nodule Sensitivity of Stationary Chest Tomosynthesis Versus Chest Radiographs in Patients With Known Lung Nodules</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose: The proposed research, if successfully implemented, will result in a low-dose,
      low-cost, and highly effective method for screening of lung cancer, leading to reduction of
      the lung cancer mortality rate. Using the s-DCT system the imaging dose for a full
      tomosynthesis scan is expected to be only 10% of that from a low-dose CT. The targeted
      imaging time of 2s is 1/5 to 1/3 of that from a current commercial DCT system at the same
      imaging dose. Beyond lung cancer screening, the low-dose and sensitive 3D lung imaging
      modality will likely to find applications in areas such as monitoring of pediatric cystic
      fibrosis patients where reduction of imaging dose is critical.

      Participants: One hundred (100) patients undergoing a clinical non-contrast CT for their
      lung nodules will be asked to have this procedure (scan) within 2 weeks (+/- 1 week) of
      their clinical CT and chest radiograph, with no intervening procedures or therapies.

      Procedures (methods): The purpose and endpoint of this study is to compare the sensitivity
      of the s-DCT system to the conventional chest  radiographs with non-contrast chest CT as the
      reference standard. One hundred (100) patients undergoing a clinical non-contrast CT for
      their lung nodules will be asked to have this procedure (scan) within 2 weeks (+/- 1 week)
      of their clinical CT and chest radiograph, with no intervening procedures or therapies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a one arm study of 100 patients with one or more lung nodules based on standard
      imaging (chest CT) at UNC Hospitals that consent to undergo an experimental s-DCT to
      characterize the number and extent of lung nodules. Most patients will also have undergone a
      SOC CR. The sensitivity of the CR and of the experimental s-DCT will be estimated
      separately, using the CT as the gold-standard. The sensitivities of the CR and the s-DCT
      will then be compared. In the event that CRs are not included in the SOC imaging or are
      unusable (outside of acceptable window (i.e. do not accommodate s-DCT within 2 weeks) or
      poor quality), the scout image acquired by CT will be used in place of a CR. The scout image
      is a preliminary radiograph that is taken prior to performing a definitive CT.

      Working in collaboration with the UNC Multi-Disciplinary Thoracic Oncology (MTOP) group, the
      investigators plan to inform patients that they may be contacted to participate in this
      study to evaluate the sensitivity of the s-DCT system, using the SOC CR and chest CT for
      comparison. CRs are included to provide a basis for comparing system sensitivity,
      representing a minimum standard.

      Once a patient has been referred, or the investigators have collaborated with the treating
      clinic regarding the eligibility of a subject, the patient will be approached by a
      coordinator from Radiology to assess interest in participation. The coordinator will either
      go to the treating clinic, or will call the patient at home, after he/she have been apprised
      of the study by his/her treating physician/nurse.

      If the patient is interested in participation, he/she will be consented either then (in
      their treatment clinic) or when he/she arrives to have his/her s-DCT, but prior to any study
      procedures. Review of the consent will take place in the privacy of an exam room, or when
      possible, a sample consent form will be sent to the patient via email prior to arriving for
      the scan to allow for ample review. Once the patient has consented, women of child bearing
      potential (WCBP) will be given a urine pregnancy test in order to ensure that they are not
      pregnant. If a urine pregnancy test shows a result positive for pregnancy, the patient will
      be excluded from the study per the exclusion criteria because the investigators cannot, in
      good conscience, expose a fetus to unnecessary radiation exposure. If the urine pregnancy
      test shows that the patient is not pregnant, she may participate in the study.

      The study scan, s-DCT, will be performed within two weeks of his/her clinical evaluations by
      chest CT and CR. There cannot be any intervening therapies or procedures (i.e. biopsy or
      excision of lesions) done in between the SOC imaging and the s-DCT. In the event that CRs
      are not included in the SOC imaging or are unusable (outside of acceptable window or poor
      quality), the scout image acquired by CT will be used in place of a CR.

      Images will be acquired by a trained radiologist technologist. The technologist will
      comfortably position the patient in the supine position on the imaging table. Then, all
      patients will have a breath held s-DCT scan in an anterior-posterior direction. Images will
      be reconstructed off-line and transferred for review on conventional PACS workstations.
      Images will be reviewed by radiologists.

      A secondary objective of this study is to determine the specificity of the s-DCT system in
      determining malignancy. In order to assess this objective each patient will be followed for
      up to 1 year following study imaging. If a known nodule is biopsied, the malignancy will be
      determined as indicated by the pathology report. If the nodule is followed but not biopsied
      within 1 year, the nodule will be considered to be not malignant for the purposes of this
      research study. However, some instances may occur in which nodules are not biopsied and are
      considered malignant. In these instances, subsequent CTs and clinical reports will be used
      to determine malignancy during this 1 year follow-up period.

      A reader study will be performed after all patients have been accrued. Each of the 3 scans
      per patient will be de-identified. As reading of all tests will take place after the patient
      has undergone clinical decision making (treatment versus following), the results of this
      study will not affect patient care. A total of 5 radiologist readers, with at least two
      years of CT experience will serve as readers. Each reader will separately interpret the CR
      and s-DCT study for all patients. For each lesion, readers will measure a cranial caudal
      (CC) diameter, to evaluate the system's ability to reproduce CT size measurements. Lesion
      identification and averaged measurement of the CC diameter by Thoracic Radiology
      subspecialists measured on conventional CT with clinical interpretation will serve as
      reference standard for the study.

      Each reader will separately interpret CR and s-DCT images in random order at two different
      reading sessions with a one month wash-out period in between reads. The radiologists will
      identify lesions, measure the CC size of the lesion and rate their confidence in deciding a
      lesion is present based on radiographic features evaluation, specifically the identification
      of lesions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Screening</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Specificity (percentage)</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Sensitivity for our study is defined as the ability of s-DCT or CR to detect a lung lesion known to exist based on non-contrast CT (the gold standard)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specificity of s-DCT (percentage)</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Specificity for this objective is defined as the ability of the s-DCT system to identify a lesion as non-malignant over the course of 1 year post s-DCT.  The gold standard will vary depending on the clinical situation as follows:
In the subset of who undergo a biopsy of a suspicious lesion, the pathology report will be the gold standard.
If a biopsy is not performed, but CT scan is performed within the 1 year timeframe, and a diagnosis of malignancy based on this nodule is made, the CT scan will be the gold standard.
If a biopsy or CT scan is not performed, but the clinical records indicate the lesion is malignant (within the one year timeframe), this will be the gold standard.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reader preference (arbitrary units)_</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate radiologists confidence in evaluating specific lesion characteristics in suspicious lung lesions. Readers will be scored from -3 to +3.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Signs and Symptoms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stationary Digital Chest Tomosynthesis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will be included in the experimental group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stationary Digital Chest Tomosynthesis</intervention_name>
    <description>The study scan, s-DCT, will be performed within two weeks of his/her clinical evaluations by chest CT and CR.  There cannot be any intervening therapies or procedures (i.e. biopsy or excision of lesions) done in between the SOC imaging and the s-DCT.  In the event that CRs are not included in the SOC imaging or are unusable (outside of acceptable window or poor quality), the scout image acquired by CT will be used in place of a CR.
Images will be acquired by a trained radiologist technologist.  The technologist will comfortably position the patient in the supine position on the imaging table.  Then, all patients will have a breath held s-DCT scan in an anterior-posterior direction.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stationary Digital Chest Tomosynthesis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥18 years of age

          -  Known lung lesion(s) based on SOC non-contrast CT

          -  Negative urine pregnancy test in women of child-bearing potential (WCBP) within 1
             week prior to s-DCT

          -  Undergone a non-contrast chest CT in a time frame that will accommodate experimental
             imaging (s-DCT) within 2 weeks

          -  IRB written informed consent obtained and signed

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to provide consent

          -  Pregnant or lactating

          -  BMI &gt; 35 (Patients who may not fit on a 35 x 35 detector)

          -  Planned procedures or therapies in between SOC scans and study scan on s-DCT, e.g.,
             biopsy or excision of lung lesion
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yueh Lee, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Terry Hartman S Hartman, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>919-843-3670</phone>
    <email>terry_hartman@med.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shanah R Kirk</last_name>
    <phone>919-966-6957</phone>
    <email>shanah_kirk@med.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNC Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Terry S Hartman, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>919-843-3670</phone>
      <email>terry_hartman@med.unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Shanah R Kirk</last_name>
      <phone>919-966-6957</phone>
      <email>shanah_kirk@med.unc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yueh Lee, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>M Patricia Rivera, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Katherine Birchard, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Benjamin Haithcock, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Molina, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Otto Zhou, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jianping Lu, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dongling Zeng, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 28, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 26, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CT</keyword>
  <keyword>Chest</keyword>
  <keyword>Lung</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Signs and Symptoms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
