<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="93996">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01782755</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>28012013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01782755</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Probiotics: Prevention of Severe Pneumonia and Endotracheal Colonization Trial (PROSPECT): A Feasibility Clinical Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>PROSPECT</acronym>
  <official_title>Probiotics: Prevention of Severe Pneumonia and Endotracheal Colonization Trial (PROSPECT): A Feasibility Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>McMaster University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research  (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McMaster University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Ethics Review Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Probiotics are commercially available live bacteria thought to have health benefits when
      ingested. A literature review of probiotic studies in the intensive care unit (ICU) found
      that in patients who receive probiotics, there is a 25% reduction in lung infection, known
      as ventilator-associated pneumonia (VAP). There is also an 18% reduction in the chance of
      developing any infection in the ICU. However, the studies reviewed were small and not well
      done.  Therefore, whether probiotics are really helpful or not is unclear. Before a large
      carefully performed study is done to evaluate the effects of probiotics in critically ill
      patients, a pilot trial is needed. The investigators plan to study the feasibility of such a
      trial in mechanically ventilated ICU patients in 11 ICUs in Ontario, investigating whether
      orally ingested L. rhamnosus GG (a common probiotic) prevents VAP and other infections. The
      4 goals of the pilot study will be to ensure that we can successfully enrol patients; follow
      the protocol faithfully; make sure patients don't receive additional probiotics, and
      estimate how much pneumonia exists in these patients. In a separate substudy, the
      investigators will evaluate the effects of probiotics on lower lung infiltration with
      potential harmful bacteria, stool bacteria, markers of immunity called cytokines, and
      markers of infection called endotoxin levels. The investigators plan to enroll 150 adults
      admitted to ICU and receiving mechanical ventilation. Following informed consent, patients
      will be randomized to either L. rhamnosus GG group or an identical placebo. Twice daily,
      patients will receive probiotics or placebo in a feeding tube. The investigators will record
      all infections and other important outcomes in the ICU. This study is very important in the
      ongoing search for more effective strategies to prevent serious infection during critical
      illness. Probiotics may be an easy-to-use, readily available, inexpensive approach to help
      future critically ill patients around the world.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:Probiotics are live microorganisms thought to have health benefits when ingested.
      Randomized controlled trials (RCTs) have documented favourable impact on a range of clinical
      problems, including prevention of upper respiratory tract infections, antibiotic-associated
      diarrhea, Clostridium difficile-associated diarrhea, and irritable bowel syndrome. Our
      recent meta-analysis of probiotic RCTs in the intensive care unit (ICU) also suggests 25%
      lower rates of ventilator-associated pneumonia (VAP) and 18% lower infection rates overall
      when administered to critically ill mechanically ventilated patients. However, these
      estimates arise from small, modest quality single-center RCTs yielding imprecise estimates
      of effect and uncertain generalizability, and require confirmation in a large
      methodologically rigourous RCT. Before such a trial is launched testing whether probiotics
      confer benefit, harm, or have no impact on infectious and non-infectious outcomes, a pilot
      trial is needed to confirm feasibility.

      Specific Aim: To determine the feasibility of performing a large RCT in mechanically
      ventilated critically ill patients adequately powered to investigate whether orally ingested
      L. rhamnosus GG prevents VAP, based on metrics of successful timely pilot trial recruitment;
      high adherence to protocol; and minimal contamination and cross-overs. We hypothesize that a
      full scale RCT will be feasible.

      Setting: 11 ICUs in Ontario.

      Methods: 150 patients 18 years of age or older, admitted to ICU and receiving mechanical
      ventilation for &lt;48 hrs, with an anticipated duration of ventilation of ≥72 hs will be
      included. Exclusion criteria are patients at increased risk of iatrogenic probiotic
      infection, strict contraindication or inability to receive enteral medications, known or
      suspected pregnancy, hopeless prognosis or intent to withhold or withdraw advanced life
      support, prior history of mechanical ventilation during current hospital stay, previous
      enrolment in this or a related infection prevention trial. Following informed consent,
      patients will be randomized in variable unspecified block sizes of 4-6 in a fixed allocation
      ratio of 1:1, stratified by ICU. Twice daily, patients will receive either 1x1010 colony
      forming units (CFU) of L. rhamnosus GG (Culturelle, Locin Industries Ltd) in 1 capsule or an
      identical placebo capsule. Both will be suspended in sterile water administered via
      nasogastric tube. Research Nurses will notify local Study Pharmacists after informed consent
      is obtained. Study Pharmacists will obtain the allocation from the PROSPECT website. Only
      the Database Manager and Study Pharmacists, who have no role in the clinical care of
      patients, will have access to the randomization schedule. Thus, all other members of the
      research team, the clinical team, patients and families will be blinded. Patients will
      receive the trial intervention from the first administration until:1) first extubation
      sustained &gt;24 hrs or unsupported breathing &gt;24 hrs in patients with tracheostomy; 2) death;
      or 3) isolation of Lactobacillus spp. cultured from a sterile site, or if cultured as the
      sole or predominant organism from a non-sterile site. Analysis of feasibility, clinical and
      mechanistic outcomes will be by a blinded biostatistician, conducted according to the
      intention to treat principle.

      Pilot Trial Outcomes: The primary outcomes relate to feasibility: 1) recruitment success in
      one year; 2) &gt;90% adherence to the probiotic administration protocol; and 3) &lt;5% cross-overs
      and contamination. Clinical outcomes of VAP, other infections, and diarrhea will also be
      measured.

      Mechanistic Sub-Study: In a separate funded sub-study of this pilot, we will examine
      endotracheal aspirates, stool and serum to determine the impact of orally ingested L.
      rhamnosus GG on lower respiratory tract (LRT) and lower gastrointestinal (GIT) colonization
      with potential pathogens; and we will examine immune effects measured by serum cytokines and
      endotoxin levels.

      Full Trial Outcomes:VAP, other ICU-acquired infections, diarrhea (total, antibiotic
      associated and Clostridium-difficile associated diarrhea), ICU and hospital mortality.

      Relevance: Despite clinical uptake of some existing VAP prevention strategies, the ongoing
      morbidity, mortality and cost of VAP underscore the need for further cost-effective
      interventions to reduce its impact. When rigorously evaluated, probiotics may have salutary
      effects decreasing nosocomial infections; alternatively, probiotics may have no demonstrable
      effect, or actually cause infections in critically ill patients with impaired immune
      function.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pilot Trial - Feasibility</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Is it feasible to perform a large RCT in mechanically ventilated critically ill patients to investigate whether orally ingested L. rhamnosus GG prevents VAP, based on successful and timely pilot trial recruitment; high adherence to protocol; minimal contamination; and an acceptable VAP rate?</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Ventilator Associated Pneumonia (VAP)</condition>
  <condition>Infection</condition>
  <condition>Antibiotic-Associated Diarrhea</condition>
  <condition>C-Difficile</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients allocated to the intervention group will receive 1x1010 colony forming units (CFU) of Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG (Culturelle, Locin Industries Ltd) in 1 capsule suspended in sterile water, administered through a nasogastric, nasoduodenal, percutaneous gastrostomy or percutaneous jejunal tube twice daily while patients are mechanically ventilated until 24 hours of spontaneous breathing.  The first dose will be within 48 hours of intubation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients allocated to the placebo group will receive a capsule identical in appearance to the L. rhamnosus GG capsule, but containing microcrystalline cellulose.  The placebo will also be suspended in sterile water and similarly administered twice a day.  When suspended in water, the placebo has identical appearance and consistency as the probiotic.  The placebo will be prepared by the manufacturer of L. rhamnosus GG, Culturelle, and has been used successfully in a recent RCT in the ICU population</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>L. rhamnosus GG  - Probiotic</intervention_name>
    <description>Twice daily, patients will receive either 1x1010 colony forming units (CFU) of L. rhamnosus GG (Culturelle, Locin Industries Ltd) in 1 capsule or an identical placebo capsule</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Culturelle Probiotic</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adults ≥ 18 years of age;

          2. Admitted to any ICU &lt; 48 hours and receiving mechanical ventilation for &lt;48 hours;

          3. Anticipated ventilation of ≥72 hours at the time of enrolment, as per the ICU
             physician.

          4. Nasogastric or nasoduodenal feeding tube in situ

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients at potential increased risk of iatrogenic probiotic infection including
             specific immunocompromised populations (HIV &lt;200 CD4 cells/μL, those receiving
             chronic immunosuppressive medications, prior organ transplant or hematological
             transplant, current or recent malignancy requiring active follow-up), patients at
             risk for endovascular infection (history of rheumatic heart disease, congenital heart
             defect, mechanical valves, history of endocarditis, endovascular grafts, permanent
             endovascular devices such as permanent [not short-term] hemodialysis catheters or
             pacemakers), patients with anatomic/mucosal GI tract defects  (gastroesophageal or
             intestinal injury, foregut surgery and/or oropharyngeal mucosal injury, ischemic gut)
             and severe acute pancreatitis (Ranson score ≥4, [Ranson 1974]);

          2. Strict contraindication or inability to receive enteral medications;

          3. Patients with percutaneous gastric or percutaneous jejuna feeding tubes already in
             situ

          4. Known or suspected pregnancy - although L. rhamnosus GG has been studied in
             pregnancy, their safety in critically ill pregnant women is unknown;

          5. Intent to withhold or withdraw advanced life support as per the ICU physician;

          6. Prior history of mechanical ventilation during current hospital stay;

          7. Previous enrolment in this or a potentially confounding trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Deborah J Cook, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>McMaster University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Deborah J Cook, MD</last_name>
    <phone>905-522-1155</phone>
    <phone_ext>35325</phone_ext>
    <email>debcook@mcmaster.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nicole L Zytaruk, Reg. N</last_name>
    <phone>905-522-1155</phone>
    <phone_ext>35325</phone_ext>
    <email>zytaruk@mcmaster.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Paul's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V6Z1Y6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter Dodek, MD</last_name>
      <phone>604-806-9023</phone>
      <email>pedodek@interchange.ubc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Betty-Jean Ashley</last_name>
      <email>bjashley@mail.cheos.ubc.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Dodek, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vancouver General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V5Z 1M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>William Henderson, MD</last_name>
      <phone>604-875-5949</phone>
      <email>william.henderson@vch.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Denise Foster, RN</last_name>
      <phone>604-875-4111</phone>
      <phone_ext>68336</phone_ext>
      <email>Denise.Foster@vch.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William Henderson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8N 4A6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Deborah Cook, MD</last_name>
      <phone>905-522-1155</phone>
      <phone_ext>35325</phone_ext>
      <email>debcook@mcmaster.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nicole Zytaruk, Reg. N</last_name>
      <phone>905-522-1155</phone>
      <phone_ext>35325</phone_ext>
      <email>zytaruk@mcmaster.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Deborah Cook, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hamilton Health Science - Hamilton General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8L 2X2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maureen Meade, MD</last_name>
      <phone>905-527-7077</phone>
      <email>meadema@HHSC.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lori Hand, RRT</last_name>
      <phone>905-972-1294</phone>
      <email>handlori@hhsc.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maureen Meade, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hamilton Health Science - Jurvinski Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8V 1C3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maureen Meade, MD</last_name>
      <phone>905-527-7077</phone>
      <email>meadema@hhsc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>France Clarke, RRT</last_name>
      <phone>905-522-1155</phone>
      <phone_ext>33633</phone_ext>
      <email>clarkef@mcmaster.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maureen Meade, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ottawa Research Institute - General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1H 8L6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laurlyn McIntyre, MD</last_name>
      <phone>613-737-8899</phone>
      <phone_ext>73231</phone_ext>
      <email>lmcintyre@ottawahospital.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Irene Watpool, RN</last_name>
      <phone>613-737-8724</phone>
      <email>iwatpool@ottawahospital.on.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lauralyn McIntyre, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute - Civic Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1H 8G7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lauralyn McIntyre, MD</last_name>
      <phone>613-737-8899</phone>
      <phone_ext>73231</phone_ext>
      <email>lmcintyre@ottawahospital.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Tracy McArdle, RN</last_name>
      <phone>613-798-5555</phone>
      <phone_ext>17076</phone_ext>
      <email>tmcardle@ottawahospital.on.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lauralyn McIntyre, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 1X5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sangeeta Mehta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>416-586-4679</phone>
      <email>samehta@mtsinai.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Brittany Giacomino, RN</last_name>
      <phone>416-586-4800</phone>
      <phone_ext>2549</phone_ext>
      <email>BGiacomino@mtsinai.on.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sangeeta Mehta, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Michael's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5B 1W8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Marshall, MD</last_name>
      <phone>416-864-6060</phone>
      <phone_ext>3538</phone_ext>
      <email>marshallj@smh.toronto.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Orla Smith, Reg. N</last_name>
      <phone>416-864-6060</phone>
      <phone_ext>3179</phone_ext>
      <email>smitho@smh.toronto.on.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Marshall, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Health Network - Toronto Western Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Margaret Herridge, MD</last_name>
      <phone>416-340-4800</phone>
      <phone_ext>3057</phone_ext>
      <email>dr.margaret.herridge@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Andrea Matte, RRT</last_name>
      <phone>416-340-4800</phone>
      <email>Andrea.Matte@uhn.on.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Margaret Herridge, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital de l'Enfant Jesus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quebec City</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>G1J 1Z4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Francois Lauzier, MD</last_name>
      <phone>418-649-0252</phone>
      <email>francois.lauzier@med.ulaval.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sara-Judith Breton, RN</last_name>
      <phone>418-649-0252</phone>
      <email>sarah-judith.breton.cha@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francois Lauzier, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.prospectpilottrial.com</url>
    <description>PROSPECT Pilot Trial</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Probiotics</keyword>
  <keyword>Ventilator Associated Pneumonia (VAP)</keyword>
  <keyword>Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Antibiotic-Associated Diarrhea</keyword>
  <keyword>C-Difficile</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia, Ventilator-Associated</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
