<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="19967">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01851811</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00000359</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01851811</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Correlation Between CPAP Compliance and Food Intake Timing</brief_title>
  <acronym>TLMECC</acronym>
  <official_title>To Examine the Correlation Between Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) and the Timing of Last Meal Before Bed Time.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hackensack University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hackensack University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite widespread agreement that continuous positive airway pressure is effective therapy
      for obstructive sleep apnea, it is estimated that 50% of patients recommended for therapy
      are noncompliant 1 year later. Nasal continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) is the most
      definitive medical therapy for obstructive sleep apnea (OSA). Many patients have difficulty
      tolerating nasal CPAP due to nasal airway problems, mouth leak, and general discomfort from
      the mask and headgear. Interventions to improve compliance in such patients have not been
      studied. The investigators plan to further evaluate the usage of CPAP and identify if the
      timing of last meal before bedtime affects the compliance and tolerance of CPAP.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OSA is a chronic disorder characterized by frequent reduction and/or cessation of
      inspiratory airflow during sleep, with resulting hypoxemia and hypercapnia that are
      terminated by arousals. This pattern of repetitive arousals and nocturnal hypoxemia leads to
      disruption of sleep architecture and daytime hyper-somnolence as well as a multitude of
      neurobehavioral and cardiopulmonary derangements. All patients diagnosed with OSA should be
      instructed to undergo behavioral changes such as weight loss, avoidance of alcohol and
      sedatives, sleeping on the side and improvement in sleep hygiene, such as keeping a regular
      sleep schedule and getting an adequate amount of sleep. Continuous Positive Airways Pressure
      (CPAP) is currently considered to be the cornerstone of therapy for sleep apnea (OSA).
      However compliance with this treatment is frequently poor, which may lead to ongoing
      symptoms of sleep disruption, daytime sleepiness and poor waking cognitive function.
      Mechanical and psychological/educational interventions have been proposed to try to increase
      the hours of use of CPAP therapy. In older male patients with OSA, compliance with CPAP
      therapy is associated with attendance at a patient CPAP education and support group.
      Resolution of symptoms with therapy also appears to be associated with enhanced compliance.
      Some studies suggest that there is no direct causal relationship between OSA and gastro
      esophageal reflux disease (GERD). The investigators hypothesize that the compliance and
      tolerance to CPAP is affected with the timing of last meal before bedtime and this may also
      affect the symptoms of GERD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Retrospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) and the timing of last meal before bed time</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Questionnaires will be used to determine correlation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients in the HUMC who are diagnosed with sleep apnea will be determined through
        screening charts.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed with Obstructive Sleep Apnea.

          -  Patients on CPAP therapy

          -  Patients older than 21 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -Patients not on CPAP therapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan Zafarlotfi, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hackensack University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hackensack University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 7, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>OSA</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
