<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="40233">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01971723</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HSC#: 2013.10364</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01971723</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multi-ingredient Supplement for Strength and Power</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Impact of T+ Supplementation on Anabolic Hormone Profile and Performance in Power Athletes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Florida State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>East Carolina University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Florida State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      It has been suggested that high amounts of total serum testosterone levels correlate with
      higher lean body mass, lowered fat mass, greater muscle strength, and faster recovery. These
      suggestions drive athletes and body builders to find ways to raise their testosterone
      levels. Many athletes and bodybuilders look to alternative methods to anabolic steroids in
      order increase their testosterone levels without legal repercussions or physiological side
      effects. Herbs and other plant extracts have been introduced as a possible source to
      naturally boost testosterone levels. Research supporting the use of herbs and plant extracts
      has been shown to be equivocal. However, evidence in studies with hypogonadal men suggests
      that longjack root may naturally boost testosterone levels. (Tambi M.I. et al).

      Onnit Labs, LLC has packaged this supplement (T+) which claims it can naturally boost
      testosterone and lower estrogen levels and subsequently improve performance. This product is
      a powder (11g) that is mixed with 16 oz of water and consumed 20 minutes prior to anaerobic
      workouts, such as high intensity weight training.

      T+ is a multi-ingredient supplement that consists of vitamins B5 and B6, magnesium aspartic
      acid, mucuna pruriens, longjack root, nettle root, red clover luteolin, resveratrol, beta-
      alanine, branch chain amino acids, L- glutamine, Bioperine, and Fibersol 2.

      The active ingredients purported to boost plasma testosterone levels are mucuna pruriens,
      longjack root, and magnesium aspartic acid. The active ingredients claimed to lower plasma
      estrogen concentrations are red clover, luteolin, resveratrol and nettle root. All other
      ingredients (Branch Chain Amino Acids and Beta-Alanine) have been documented to improve
      exercise performance.

      It is hypothesized that there will not be any physiological changes after supplementation of
      T+. It is also hypothesized that performance will not be affected by the supplementation of
      T+.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to examine the physiological and performance effects of T+ on
      power athletes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Basic Science</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Performance outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks from start of study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurement of one repetition maximums strength for all competition lifts included in a standard, ungeared, powerlifting competition (squat, bench and deadlift). This testing will take place before the supplementation of either T+ or placebo and at the end of the four-week training period. During the four weeks, the volume ((weight x reps)set 1+(weight x reps)set 2+ (weight x reps)set 3….. ) will be calculated and measured for each exercise in each lifting session.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physiological Outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month from Completion of Study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurements of insulin, blood lipid panel, glucose, testosterone, estrogen, insulin-like growth factor-I, creatine kinase, total testosterone, free testosterone and dihydrotestosterone (DHT) on three occasions: prior to the start of supplementation and training, at the end of two weeks, and finally at the end of training.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Supplement</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>T+ Supplement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm requires the participants to take a prescribed dose of the T+ supplement for 4 weeks while completing an exercise regiment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm requires the participants to take a prescribed dose of a calorie matched placebo for 4 weeks while completing an exercise regiment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>T+ Supplement</intervention_name>
    <description>Randomized, placebo-controlled, double blind protocol with two treatment groups (matched by lean body mass). Group 1 will receive the recommended serving of one scoop (11g) of T+ supplement. This serving will be taken 45 minutes before the beginning of working out on an empty stomach (&gt;1 hour after meal). On non-training days, the participants will also take a serving at the same time as on training days. This will continue for four weeks (28 days).</description>
    <arm_group_label>T+ Supplement</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>The placebo group will consume a calorie-match placebo in the same manner as the supplement group (one serving 45 minutes prior to work outs on an empty stomach). The placebo group will also follow the same supplementation patterns and workout as their counterparts in the supplement group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must be familiar with the three main powerlifting movements (squat, bench and
             deadlift)

          -  Must have one month training with a designated strength coach to understand the
             expectations of the strength coach and movement patterns for performance

          -  Have no pre-existing musculoskeletal disorders

          -  Participate in the three-week supplement wash out prior to beginning the experiment
             (except for basic protein supplements and multivitamins)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Female
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael J Ormsbee, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Florida State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tallahassee</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32306</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 18, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 27, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Testosterone</keyword>
  <keyword>Estrogen</keyword>
  <keyword>Insulin</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood Lipid</keyword>
  <keyword>Glucose</keyword>
  <keyword>Creatine Kinase</keyword>
  <keyword>Strength</keyword>
  <keyword>Power Athlete</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
