<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="122544">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01685372</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-0829</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01685372</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunogenicity of Fluzone High Dose in Immunocompromised Children and Young Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immunogenicity and Efficacy of High-dose Trivalent Inactivated Seasonal Influenza Vaccine(Fluzone High Dose) in Immunocompromised Children and Young Adults.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Colorado Clinical &amp; Translational Sciences Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether Fluzone High Dose increases the immune
      response to the influenza antigens contained in the vaccine compared to standard-dose
      Fluzone in immunocompromised children and young adults.  Safety and efficacy data will also
      be collected.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 10  months after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Gathering data on influenza-like-illness during the influenza season for which the subject was vaccinated in the study.  Influenza season typically lasts January through May.  Compare rates of diagnosed influenza and rates of reported Influenza Like Illness (ILI) from Questionnaires #2 and #3 and also obtained from medical records between the high-dose and standard-dose recipients within each patient group for each influenza season included in the study. We will obtain 3 sets of data related to influenza/ILI and analyze combinations of them.
Polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-proven diagnosis of influenza performed at Children's Hospital Colorado (CHC)
Diagnosis of influenza by non-PCR rapid-influenza test (diagnosed outside of main-campus CHC)
Diagnosis of ILI (from questionnaires #2 and #3).  [Centers for Disease Control (CDC) definition of ILI: Fever ≥ 100°F AND cough or sore throat in the absence of another known cause other than influenza for the illness.]</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Seroprotection</measure>
    <time_frame>blood draw at 10-45 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure hemagglutinin inhibition (HAI) on blood samples #1 and #2 for all subjects, which is the sample drawn at the &quot;peak&quot; of the immune response. Compare percentage reaching HAI ≥ 1:32 (or 1:40) between the high-dose and standard-dose recipients within each patient group between timepoint 0 (pre-vaccination) and blood draw #2.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>0-14 days after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Compare proportion of adverse events reported within the 14 days after vaccination by each subject. Compare types and rates of adverse events between the high-dose and standard-dose recipients within each patient group.  Subjects will keep a Safety Diary for the 14 days post-vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Seroconversion</measure>
    <time_frame>10-45 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure HAI on blood samples #1 and #2 for all subjects. Compare percentage reaching a four-fold increase in antibody level between the high-dose and standard-dose recipients within each patient group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>10-45 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>For other immunogenicity: Compare results of blood draw #1 and #2 between the high-dose and standard-dose recipients for each patient group for the following: antibody avidity, microneutralization, T-cell interferon, T-cell IL-2, B-cell Immunoglobulin G  (IgG) and B-cell Immunoglobulin A (IgA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>End of season seroprotection</measure>
    <time_frame>at least 5 months post vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measure HAI on blood sample #3, to be drawn May-September following vaccination. Compare percentage who still have HAI ≥ 1:32 (1:40) between the high-dose and standard-dose recipients within each patient group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in disease status after vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluate disease status changes reported by subject on Questionnaire #3 as well as changes reported in clinic notes over the course of the influenza season. Statistical analysis will compare rates of progress or improvement of disease within the 2 months after vaccination and then within 6 months after vaccination between the high-dose and standard-dose recipients within each patient group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Will survey subjects at day 30-45 regarding any unplanned health care visit
Will have on-going passive surveillance of adverse events (AEs)/serious adverse events (SAEs) throughout course of influenza season of enrollment.  Data collection will stop in September following enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">420</enrollment>
  <condition>Rheumatologic Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV)</condition>
  <condition>Bone Marrow Transplant(BMT)</condition>
  <condition>Hemodialysis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fluzone High Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fluzone High Dose 0.5 mL intramuscularly (IM) given once</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fluzone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fluzone 0.5mL IM given once</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluzone High Dose</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Fluzone High Dose</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>high-dose influenza vaccine</other_name>
    <other_name>influenza vaccine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluzone</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Fluzone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>influenza vaccine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 5 years and ≤ 35 years

          -  Receiving influenza vaccination in Children's Hospital Colorado (CHC) clinic as part
             of routine clinical care

          -  Only supposed to receive one dose of influenza vaccine

          -  Rheumatology patients: must be on some type of immunosuppressive or immunomodulatory
             medication at the time of immunization and considered at least moderately
             immunosuppressed in the opinion of the primary rheumatologist. Basic guidelines for
             rheumatology patients: (1) Any patient receiving monoclonal antibody therapy (i.e.,
             infliximab, etanercept, tocilizumab, anakinra) must also be taking another
             immunosuppressive/immunomodulatory medication; (2) Patients taking steroids as
             monotherapy must be on a dose of ≥ 2mg/kg/day OR ≥ 20mg/day; (3) Patients on
             combination therapy where the dose of a single drug may not be very high, but the
             combination is considered moderately or severely immunosuppressive will be eligible.

          -  Bone Marrow Transplant patients: all patients in clinic eligible

          -  Oncology patients: must be on some type of chemotherapy

          -  Hemodialysis patients: must be on dialysis

          -  Child Health Immunodeficiency Program (CHIP) patients: must have a known diagnosis of
             HIV

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Rheumatology patients: if receiving any of the monoclonal antibodies, etanercept,
             infliximab, adalimumab, tocilizumab, atlizumab, or anakinra, must also be taking at
             least one other immunosuppressive/immunomodulatory medication

          -  Unable to come for scheduled follow-up appointments

          -  History of anaphylaxis reaction to influenza vaccination in the past

          -  Severe allergic reaction to any component of the vaccine, including egg protein, or
             after previous dose of any influenza vaccine

          -  History of Guillain-Barre syndrome ever in the past in the subject or in a parent or
             a sibling of the subject

          -  Allergy to latex

          -  Intravenous immuneglobulin (IVIG) within in 4 weeks preceding any blood draw

          -  Receiving an investigational agent as part of another study or other medical
             treatment (investigational = not-FDA approved for any indication)

          -  Subject not enrolled in other studies that prohibit him/her from enrolling in this
             study

          -  Blood draw contraindicated

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Breastfeeding

          -  Received a polysaccharide vaccine (pneumovax) w/in 3 weeks of the vaccination

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt; 500/uL at the time of vaccination or could
             potentially have ANC 500/uL during the 5 days after vaccination

          -  Platelet count &lt; 50,000/uL at the time of vaccination

          -  If a subject has a temperature ≥ 100.4°F at the time of enrollment, then the subject
             must choose to not enroll or delay immunization until afebrile.

          -  Receiving influenza vaccination past December 15 of influenza season.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Donna Curtis, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Colorado, University of Colorado Denver School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Donna Curtis, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>720-777-2808</phone>
    <email>donna.curtis@childrenscolorado.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Colorado</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donna Curtis, MD,MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 27, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Collagen Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
