<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="99081">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01827358</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09-0065</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>MRSA CVD 1000</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01AI80057C</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01827358</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of Intranasal and Topical Mupirocin in Eradicating Colonization With Staphylococcus Aureus (SA) in Critically Ill Infants - a Phase 2, Multi-Center, Open Label, Randomized Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety and Efficacy of Intranasal and Topical Mupirocin in Eradicating Colonization With Staphylococcus Aureus (SA) in Critically Ill Infants - a Phase 2, Multi-Center, Open Label, Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To examine the safety and effectiveness of mupirocin in eradicating colonization with SA
      (MRSA or MSSA) and preventing the occurrence of invasive and other clinically significant SA
      infections among infants in the ICU. To evaluate the safety and clinical acceptability of a
      5-day course (15 applications) of topical mupirocin applied every 8 hours (+/= 2 hours)
      daily to the nares, umbilicus and perianal area of infants residing in the ICU. Infants less
      than 24 months of age will be recruited from among those admitted to the NICU or ICU at one
      of the participating centers. Study duration is 36 months. Enrolled infants will continue to
      receive medical care as they otherwise would if they were not enrolled in the trial.  The
      study will be powered toward the primary endpoint with 126 participants. Enrollment may
      continue up to a maximum of 500 participants to inform the secondary and exploratory
      endpoints and to help design any subsequent study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 2, open label, multi-center, randomized trial to determine the safety and
      efficacy of mupirocin in eradicating colonization with Staphylococcus aureus (SA) and
      preventing the occurrence of invasive and other clinically significant SA infections among
      critically ill infants in the ICU. Infants hospitalized in an ICU at any one of the 6
      participating centers with a positive nasal culture for SA will be eligible to enroll.
      Infants will be stratified by birth gestational age (&lt; 28 weeks and &lt;8 weeks of post-natal
      life or &gt;/= 28 weeks / &lt; 28 weeks and &gt;/=8 weeks of post-natal life) and colonizing strain
      Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) or Methicillin-sensitive Staphylococcus
      aureus (MSSA) and then randomized 1:1 to receive a 5 day course of mupirocin applied to the
      nares, umbilicus and perianal (NUP) areas every 8 hours (+/= 2 hours) vs. no treatment.
      (Stratification by birth gestational age is performed to minimize bias that could result
      from a higher risk for developing infection due to prematurity or prolonged length of stay
      due to prematurity.)  Each participant will be enrolled for up to 12 weeks (Day 85) or until
      the time of discharge from the hospital, death or withdrawal from further participation,
      whichever occurs first. It is anticipated that it will take at least 2 years to enroll all
      participants. Study duration is 36 months. Enrolled infants will continue to receive medical
      care as they otherwise would if they were not enrolled in the trial.  The study will be
      powered toward the primary endpoint with 126 participants. Enrollment may continue up to a
      maximum of 500 participants to inform the secondary and exploratory endpoints and to help
      design any subsequent study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary decolonization efficacy:  Proportion of infants in the treatment and control groups who have no detectable S. aureus (SA) on direct cultures obtained on day 8</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Persistent decolonization efficacy: Proportion of infants in the treatment and control groups who have no detectable SA on direct cultures on days 8 and 22</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 8 and 22</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety: Frequency of solicited adverse events(AEs), moderate and severe unsolicited AEs (that are not otherwise considered pre-defined trial endpoints),  serious adverse events (SAEs) during days 1-7 and related SAEs until Day 85</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 through 85</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Protective efficacy and median time to occurrence of clinical SA infection in the treatment compared to the control group during days 1-22 or until discharge, whichever occurs first.</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 through 22</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">126</enrollment>
  <condition>Staphylococcal Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receive a 5-day course of mupirocin calcium ointment 2 % 20 mg intranasally applied every 8 hours and a topical skin application (umbilical and perianal area) of mupirocin calcium cream 2% 20 mg   applied every 8 hours for a total of 15 doses</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mupirocin cream</intervention_name>
    <description>Mupirocin calcium cream 2% applied topically to umbilicus and perianal area every 8 hours for 5 days, for a total of 15 applications</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mupirocin ointment</intervention_name>
    <description>Mupirocin calcium ointment 2% will be applied intranasally every 8 hours for 5 days, for a total of 15 applications</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently admitted to a NICU or ICU at a participating site

          -  Chronological age less than 24 months

          -  Evidence of colonization with SA (MRSA or MSSA) based on a positive nasal
             surveillance culture.  Randomization must occur within 120 hours of receipt of the
             nasal surveillance swab by the laboratory

          -  The attending neonatologist/ intensivist anticipates that the infant will remain in
             the ICU for a minimum of 14 days after enrollment

          -  Infant has never been discharged home since birth

          -  Parent or legal guardian agrees that the infant will not participate in a research
             trial involving the administration of an investigational drug for 14 days following
             enrollment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Receipt of an investigational drug as part of a research trial within the past 14
             days

          -  Previously enrolled and participated in this trial

          -  Has an active or previous SA infection or previous SA colonization

          -  Currently receiving topical or intranasal mupirocin

          -  Has a rash in an area to which mupirocin will be directly applied

          -  Has any of the following congenital abnormalities:

               -  A congenital skin disorder (i.e. - epidermolysis bullosa, icthyosis)

               -  An opened neural tube defect

               -  Confirmed or suspected choanal atresia

               -  Any of the following abdominal wall defects: wound dehiscence, gastroschisis,
                  open abdominal wound (small abdominal wall defects such as ostomy sites or
                  peritoneal drain sites are not exclusionary)

          -  Is nasally intubated

          -  Known hypersensitivity to the trial product or its constituents

          -  Known or suspected immune deficiency. Infants born to HIV-seropositive mothers with
             the following risk factors for intrapartum transmission will not be eligible to
             participate:

               -  Mother's most recent viral load within the past 3 months was &gt; 1,000 copies/ml
                  or

               -  Mother's viral load is not known or has has not been measured in the past 3
                  months.

          -  Any other condition(s) that in the opinion of the investigator would jeopardize the
             safety or rights of a participant or would render the participant unable to comply
             with the protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karen L Kotloff</last_name>
    <phone>(410) 706-5328</phone>
    <email>kkotloff@medicine.umaryland.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University Hospital Midtown - Neonatal Intensive Care Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30308-2208</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland Medical Center - Children's Hospital - Neonatal Intensive Care Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201-1595</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Mercy Hospital and Clinics - Infectious Diseases</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>64108-4619</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint Louis University School of Medicine - Cardinal Glennon Children's Medical Center - NICU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63104-1003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center - Infectious Diseases</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229-3026</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University - Pediatric - Vanderbilt Vaccine Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232-2573</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 29, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 4, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Staphylococcus aureus, colonisation, prevention, mupirocin,critically ill, infants, children, antibacterial agent</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Staphylococcal Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mupirocin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
