<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="100718">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01754259</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012P002537</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01754259</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Ranolazine on Coronary Flow Reserve in Symptomatic Diabetic Patients and CAD</brief_title>
  <acronym>RAND-CFR</acronym>
  <official_title>Effects of Ranolazine on Coronary Flow Reserve in Symptomatic Patients With Diabetes and Suspected or Known Coronary Artery Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham and Women's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Coronary vascular dysfunction is highly prevalent among patients with known or suspected
      Coronary Artery Disease (CAD)1, increases the severity of inducible myocardial ischemia
      (beyond the effects of upstream coronary obstruction)2, and identifies patients at high risk
      for serious adverse events, including cardiac death1, 3-5. Diabetic patients without known
      CAD with impaired coronary vascular function show a risk of cardiac death comparable to, and
      possibly higher, than that for non-diabetic patients with known CAD10. In the setting of
      increased oxygen demand, coronary vasodilator dysfunction can upset the supply-demand
      relationship and lead to myocardial ischemia, subclinical left ventricular dysfunction
      (diastolic and systolic), and symptoms.

      The significance of microvascular coronary dysfunction is increasingly recognized as
      invasive and non-invasive (PET) methods of quantifying CFR become available.

      Importantly, current treatment strategies for obstructive CAD, such as percutaneous coronary
      intervention with angioplasty and stenting, are not helpful in microvascular disease.
      Similarly, mortality-altering treatments for systolic heart failure, such as angiotensin
      converting enzyme inhibitors, have not been beneficial in treating diastolic dysfunction.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Ranolazine is a novel anti-anginal agent which inhibits the late sodium current in
      cardiomyocytes, decreasing sodium and calcium overload. In ischemia, excess of intracellular
      calcium may impair myocyte relaxation and contribute to ventricular diastolic stiffness,
      which in turn affects myocardial contractility and perfusion. Ranolazine is FDA-approved for
      treatment of chronic angina. In three randomized, placebo-controlled trials of patients with
      stable angina, it was shown to increase exercise time free of angina and ST-segment
      depression, increase exercise capacity and decrease angina when used in combination with
      established antianginal agents including diltiazem, amlodipine or atenolol, and reduce the
      frequency of angina on  patients on maximum doses of amlodipine.Similarly, in a large
      population of patients with acute coronary syndromes, ranolazine also decreased exertional
      angina symptoms and incidence of arrhythmias, with no effect on mortality. Interestingly, in
      this same study, it significantly improved hemoglobin A1c and recurrent ischemia in patients
      with diabetes mellitus, and reduced the incidence of increased hemoglobin A1c in patients
      without known prior hyperglycemia.

      Although the anti-ischemic effect of ranolazine is thought to be mediated in part by
      increased myocardial blood flow,there is currently limited evidence for such an effect on
      tissue perfusion. A previous study in women without overt CAD did not detect improved
      myocardial blood flow after treatment with ranolazine. In that study, however, coronary
      hyperemia was elicited with adenosine (which uncouples blood flow from cardiac work, and
      reflects predominantly endothelial-independent vasodilation) rather than exercise, which
      triggers a more complex interplay between metabolic demand, coronary hemodynamics, and
      vasodilator response. Thus, there is a need for additional investigation of whether the
      beneficial effects of ranolazine on exertional symptoms are directly related to improved
      global tissue perfusion. Such evidence would support the use of ranolazine as an
      anti-ischemic therapy in the challenging population of symptomatic patients with evidence of
      microvascular dysfunction without obstructive CAD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in post-exercise coronary vasodilator reserve</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change (from baseline) in post-exercise coronary vasodilator reserve, as measured by PET imaging at 4 weeks post randomization.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in symptoms of exertional angina and/or dyspnea</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in symptoms of exertional angina and/or dyspnea on the Seattle Angina 	Questionnaire and Rose Dyspnea Scale Questionnaire at 4 weeks post randomization;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in left ventricular systolic function</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change (from baseline) in left ventricular systolic function, reflected primarily in 	LV global longitudinal strain, at 4 weeks post randomization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in post-exercise global myocardial blood flow</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change (from baseline) in post-exercise global myocardial blood flow (in 	mL/min/g) at 4 weeks post randomization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in post-exercise global coronary vascular resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change (from baseline) in post-exercise global coronary vascular resistance (in 	mm Hg/mL/min/g) at 4 weeks post randomization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in serum biomarkers of myocardial strain</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in serum biomarkers of myocardial strain (ultrasensitive  troponin I 	(usTnI), N-terminal pro-B-type natriuretic peptide (NTproBNP), and the interleukin 	family member (ST2)), as well as glycosylated hemoglobin (A1c) at 4 weeks post 	randomization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between multimodality imaging parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>varies</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Correlation between multimodality imaging parameters  (in PET, echo, and 	angiography) characterizing extent of  coronary vascular reactivity, myocardial 	dysfunction and patterns of atherosclerotic disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in LV diastolic function</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change (from baseline) in LV diastolic function reflected primarily in mitral 	annular early diastolic relaxation velocity (E') at 4 weeks post randomization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes, Type I</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes, Type II</condition>
  <condition>Angina</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ranolazin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subject will receive labeled bottles containing tablets with ranolazine 500 mg or a matching placebo provided by the sponsor.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subject will receive labeled bottles containing tablets with ranolazine 500 mg or a matching placebo provided by the sponsor.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ranolazine</intervention_name>
    <description>Subject will receive labeled bottles containing tablets with ranolazine 500 mg or a matching placebo provided by the sponsor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ranolazin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Pill</intervention_name>
    <description>Subject will receive labeled bottles containing tablets with ranolazine 500 mg or a matching placebo provided by the sponsor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. type 1 or 2 diabetes mellitus

          2. anginal symptoms and/or exertional dyspnea;

          3. ability to exercise and achieve an exercise tolerance of at least 3 METS but not
             higher than 9 METS either on a treadmill or bicycle exercise tolerance test;

          4. perfusion sum stress score (SSS) ≤ 6, as assessed by initial PET

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. patients not fulfilling inclusion criteria

          2. patients with evidence of unprotected left main coronary artery stenosis &gt;50%

          3. patients with evidence of new obstructive CAD not on optimal medical therapy

          4. evidence of angiographic disease and/or inducible myocardial ischemia on stress
             testing planning to undergo revascularization within the following 3 months

          5. history of cardiomyopathy (LVEF &lt;40%) or significant valvular heart disease

          6. uncontrolled hypertension (SBP &gt;180 mm Hg at screening)

          7. gait instability, lower extremity amputations preventing exercise

        9. significant liver dysfunction (LFTs &gt;3x upper limits of normal), including cirrhosis
        10. prolonged QT (QTc &gt;450 and &gt;470 ms for men and women, respectively) or concomitant use
        of drugs that prolong QT interval (including methadone and antiarrhythmics such as
        sotalol, amiodarone, and quinidine) 11. use of drugs that inhibit CYP3A such as
        ketoconazole, itraconazole, fluconazole, clarithromycin, erythromycin, diltiazem,
        verapamil, nefazodone, nelfinavir, ritonavir, lopinavir, ritonavir, indinavir, and
        saquinavir 12. use of drugs that induce CYP3A such rifampin, rifabutin, rifapentine,
        phenobarbital, phenytoin, carbamazepine, and St. John's wort 13. atrial fibrillation /
        inability to hold breath for ≥ 10 seconds (in patients in whom CTA will be performed) 14.
        eGFR &lt; 50 ml/min or end stage renal disease on dialysis 15. allergy to intravenous
        contrast 16. pregnant or lactating women, or women of childbearing potential not using an
        acceptable form of birth control (negative pregnancy test also required) 17. inability to
        fit safely in PET/CT scanner
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marcelo Di Carli, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marcelo Di Carli, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-525-8322</phone>
    <email>mdicarli@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Masha Gaber, ALM</last_name>
    <phone>617-732-4237</phone>
    <email>mgaber@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 8, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 12, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marcelo F. Di Carli, MD, FACC</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief, Division of Nuclear Medicine-PET</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>type 1 diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>type 2 diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>exertion angina</keyword>
  <keyword>suspected CAD</keyword>
  <keyword>known CAD</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ranolazine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
