<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="121076">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01962571</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BMBF251</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01962571</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Optic Neuritis With Erythropoietin</brief_title>
  <acronym>TONE</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase 2 Randomized, Double-blinded, Placebo Controlled Multi-center Trial Determining the Efficacy of i.v. Erythropoietin by Measurements of Retinal Nerve Fibre Layer Thickness and Low Contrast Visual Acuity 6 Months After Optic Neuritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Eye Hospital, Freiburg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Eye Hospital, Freiburg</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This clinical trial aims at preventing visual dysfunction and optic nerve degeneration
      associated with autoimmune optic neuritis by systemic i.v. administration of 33.000 IU
      erythropoietin over 3 days. The primary objective is the determination of the efficacy of
      erythropoietin compared to placebo given as add-on to methylprednisolone as assessed by
      measurements of retinal nerve fibre layer thickness and low contrast visual acuity 6 months
      after acute optic neuritis. The ultimate goal is the establishment of a direct
      neuroprotective therapy for optic neuritis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      INTRODUCTION

      Neurodegeneration is the structural correlate of functional impairment in multiple sclerosis
      (MS). Available therapies, however, target the immune response, but exert only limited
      direct neuroprotection. Optic neuritis (ON) is one of the most frequent manifestations of MS
      and leads to degeneration of retinal ganglion cell axons with consecutive visual impairment.
      Due to their correlation with brain atrophy, these changes allow conclusions to be drawn
      about inflammation-associated neurodegeneration on a more global level. Various substances
      that interfere with pathways related to apoptosis and regeneration represent potential
      candidates for protecting retinal ganglion cell axons. Among these, erythropoietin (EPO) is
      one of the most potent drugs as shown in inflammatory and non-inflammatory disease models.
      In a clinical pilot trial, we have demonstrated that EPO is safe and efficacious in
      preserving retinal ganglion cell axons after optic neuritis. Hence, we plan to administer
      EPO intravenously to patients with ON and to evaluate its effect on visual function and
      retinal nerve fibre layer preservation in a prospective, double blind, placebo-controlled,
      multi-center phase II trial.

      DESIGN

      The study is designed as a prospective, double blind, randomized controlled trial with 24
      participating departments (Departments of Ophthalmology and Neurology) located at 12
      different German University Medical Centers. Main selection criterion for the study sites
      has been a reputation for treating large numbers of patients with MS, ON and other optic
      nerve diseases. The trial will have 2 parallel arms, one with 3 infusions of 33.000 IU human
      recombinant EPO, spread over 3 days, and one with placebo infusions administered in an equal
      fashion. In both arms, patients receive 1 g methylprednisolone i.v. for 3 days in accordance
      to national guidelines.

      The treatment and follow-up of each patient will extend over a period of 6 months. An
      unblinded post-trial follow-up of 24 months will yield information about long-term visual
      function and clinical disease course. For each patient, a treating and an evaluating
      neurologist (separated to maintain a blinded trial) as well as an ophthalmologist and a
      neurophysiologist will be involved.

      OUTCOME MEASURES

      This clinical trial will employ two primary outcome measures in hierarchical order, 1st a
      morphologic one (retinal nerve fibre layer thickness, RNFLT) and a 2nd functional one (low
      contrast visual acuity, LCVA). Both are important as the morphologic measures are
      characterized by high precision and reproducibility and the functional measures by relevance
      for the individual patient affected by ON or MS thereafter. Morphologic parameters have
      lower variability than functional parameters, because the variability of patients'
      subjective cognition does not add to the overall variance when measuring morphologic
      parameters. We consider both parameters important, as relevant neuroprotection is expected
      to not only limit functional deterioration, but also reduce nervous tissue loss, especially
      in the light of possible recurrences of ON.

      The 1st primary outcome measure is RNFLT in the affected eye after 6 months. RNFLT became a
      standard measure for neurodegeneration over the recent years and can be precisely measured
      by OCT. It allows thickness measurements of the peripapillary RNFL consisting of retinal
      ganglion cells axons. Using time domain OCT, thinning of the RNFL from 100 μm to 78 μm
      (means, p=0.0001) was seen in the majority of ON patients (74%) within 6 months. RNFLT
      decline reaches a plateau around 4 months. Several investigations have established that
      RNFLT measurement by OCT is a robust tool for the quantification of optic nerve axons and
      the degree of optic atrophy, especially after ON. The recent introduction of the spectral
      domain OCT technique allows for more precise detection and quantification of the RNFL, in
      particular using the Spectralis®-System which incorporates eye tracking for substantially
      better retest variability (variation coefficient of 0.6%, as compared to 5% using time
      domain OCT). RNFLT will be determined along a ring of 3.4 mm diameter concentrically laid
      around the optic disc using the Spectralis®-OCT (Heidelberg Engeneering, Heidelberg).

      The 2nd primary outcome measure is LCVA in the affected eye after 6 months. While high
      contrast visual acuity (VA) recovers well after ON, contrast sensitivity (CS), however, is
      most likely to remain subnormal: 22% of cases with fully recovered visual acuity revealed
      subnormal CS. LCVA correlates well with health-related quality of life and correlates
      significantly with RNFLT in MS patients after previous ON. LCVA will be recorded by 1.5%
      low-contrast Sloan letter charts.

      Secondary outcome measures: Since acute ON may lead to RNFL oedema, we will primarily
      compare RNFLT at 6 months among both treatment groups. However, 4 additional OCT analyses
      will be performed to increase the likelihood in capturing axonal changes: a) unaffected
      fellow eye RNFLT at baseline minus affected eye RNFLT at 6 months, b) decrease of RNFLT from
      baseline to follow-up at 6 months, RNFLT in the papillomacular bundle and d) macular
      thickness of the ganglion cell layer plus inner plexiform layer after 6 months. The other
      functional endpoints VA and CS will be assessed using standard ETDRS-charts and Mars-charts.
      Visual fields (VF) will be recorded on automated, static perimeters (Octopus perimeter,
      Haag-Streit, Switzerland) using the newly developed GATE strategy (German Adaptive Threshold
      Estimation) within the entire 90° VF in a threshold determining manner. Visually evoked
      potential (VEP) amplitudes and latencies will be measured by standard electrophysiological
      equipment in accordance with the International Society for Clinical Electrophysiology.
      Vision related qualitiy of life (VRQOL) shall be assessed using the validated German version
      of 25-item National Eye Institute Visual Functioning Questionnaire. Its overall score as
      well as its 12 subscores will be analysed. Further, relapse rates of ON will be documented
      and analysed.

      READING CENTRES

      The &quot;Bern Photographic Reading Center&quot; located at the Klinik und Poliklinik für
      Augenheilkunde, Universität Bern, Switzerland, will serve as the reading center for OCT. It
      shall further provide external quality control. The &quot;Visual Field Reading Center&quot; located at
      the Fachhochschule Aalen, Germany, will serve as the reading center for VF testing.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retinal nerve fiber layer thickness</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured by SD-OCT along a 3.4 mm scan circle concentric to the optic nerve head as defined by the center of Bruchs membrane opening</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Low contrast visual acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determined by 2.5% contrast Sloan charts</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Retinal nerve fiber layer thickness at the temporal sector of the optic nerve head</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Retinal nerve fiber layer thickness in the papillo-macular bundle</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Macular volume</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured by SD-OCT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured by ETDRS-charts</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Contrast sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured by Mars charts</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual field</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured in the entire visual field using the fast GATE algorithm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vision related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Determined by NEI-VFQ 25</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visually evoked potentials</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Optic Neuritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Erythropoietin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>33.000 IU erythropoietin i.v. on 3 consecutive days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>1,5 ml saline i.v. on 3 consecutive days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Erythropoietin</intervention_name>
    <description>This intervention will be administered in parallel to the standard treatment of 1 g methylprednisolone / day i.v. for 3 consecutive days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Erythropoietin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>EPO</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>This intervention will be administered in parallel to the standard treatment of 1 g methylprednisolone / day i.v. for 3 consecutive days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Optic neuritis

          -  First symptoms less than 10 days ago

          -  Visual acuity of ≤ 0.5 (decimal system)

          -  Able to provide written informed consent, to follow instructions and to make the
             required visits

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Refractive anomalies: Hyperopia &gt; 5 dpt, myopia &gt; 7 dpt, astigmatism &gt; 3 dpt

          -  Media opacity

          -  Papillitis

          -  Previous ON

          -  Any other optic nerve disease, any retinal disease or ocular hypertension

          -  Pre-existing MS or any other neurological disease

          -  Any significant illness interfering with the study parameters, such as autoimmune
             diseases, severe cardiovascular disease, or poorly controlled diabetes

          -  Thrombophilia, hypertension, any malignancy, epilepsy, or any other contraindications
             to EPO

          -  Performing semi-professional or professional sport activities

          -  Pre-treatment with immunosuppressive or immunomodulatory agents

          -  Pre-treatment with corticosteroids or EPO during the last 60 days
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wolf A. Lagrèze, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Eye Hospital, Freiburg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ricarda Diem, Prof. (Deputy)</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dep. Neurooncology, University Hospital Heidelberg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wolf A Lagrèze, Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>+49 761 270</phone>
    <phone_ext>40010</phone_ext>
    <email>wolf.lagreze@uniklinik-freiburg.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ricarda Diem, Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>+49 6221 563</phone>
    <phone_ext>7774</phone_ext>
    <email>ricarda.diem@med.uni-heidelberg.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital, Deps. Ophthalmology / Neurology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Freiburg</city>
        <state>Baden-Wuerttemberg</state>
        <zip>79106</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wolf A. Lagrèze, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 761 270</phone>
      <phone_ext>40010</phone_ext>
      <email>wolf.lagreze@uniklinik-freiburg.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nikolai Gross, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 761 270</phone>
      <phone_ext>40524</phone_ext>
      <email>nikolai.gross@uniklinik-freiburg.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wolf A. Lagrèze, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nikolai Gross, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fanni Molnar, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital, Deps. Neurooncology / Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <state>Baden-Wuerttemberg</state>
        <zip>69120</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ricarda Diem, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 6221 56</phone>
      <phone_ext>37774</phone_ext>
      <email>ricarda.diem@med.uni-heidelberg.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Michael Platten, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 6221 56</phone>
      <phone_ext>6804</phone_ext>
      <email>michael.platten@med.uni-heidelberg.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ricarda Diem, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Platten, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital, Deps. Ophthalmology / Neurology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tuebingen</city>
        <state>Baden-Wuerttemberg</state>
        <zip>72076</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Helmut Wilhelm, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 7071 29</phone>
      <phone_ext>84766</phone_ext>
      <email>helmut.wilhelm@med.uni-tuebingen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Felix Tonagel, Dr.</last_name>
      <email>felix.tonagel@med.uni-tuebingen.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Helmut Wilhelm, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Felix Tonagel, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital, Deps. Neurology / Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Erlangen</city>
        <state>Bayern</state>
        <zip>91054</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ralf A Linker, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0)9131 85</phone>
      <phone_ext>32187</phone_ext>
      <email>ralf.linker@uk-erlangen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>De-Hyung Lee, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0)9131 85</phone>
      <phone_ext>34466</phone_ext>
      <email>de-hyung.lee@uk-erlangen.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ralf A Linker, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>De-Hyung Lee, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital, Deps. Ophthalmology / Neurology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Munich</city>
        <state>Bayern</state>
        <zip>81377</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathrin Hartmann, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 89 5160</phone>
      <phone_ext>3811</phone_ext>
      <email>Kathrin.Hartmann@med.uni-muenchen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kathrin Hartmann, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Center, Deps. Neurology / Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Goettingen</city>
        <state>Niedersachen</state>
        <zip>37099</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Katharina Hein, PD Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 551 39</phone>
      <phone_ext>8484</phone_ext>
      <email>k.hein@uni-goettingen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Katharina Hein, PD Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital, Deps. Neurology / Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duesseldorf</city>
        <state>Nordrhein-Westfalen</state>
        <zip>40225</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Corinna Peters, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 211 81</phone>
      <phone_ext>19296</phone_ext>
      <email>MS-Studien@med.uni-duesseldorf.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Corinna Peters, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital, Deps. Neurology / Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Essen</city>
        <state>Nordrhein-Westfalen</state>
        <zip>45147</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Oliver Kastrup, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 201 723</phone>
      <phone_ext>6501</phone_ext>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Oliver Kastrup, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Center of the Johannes Gutenberg University, Deps. Neurology / Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mainz</city>
        <state>Rheinland-Pfalz</state>
        <zip>55131</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Frauke Zipp, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 6131 17</phone>
      <phone_ext>5697</phone_ext>
      <email>frauke.zipp@unimedizin-mainz.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Volker Siffrin, Prof.</last_name>
      <email>volker.siffrin@unimedizin-mainz.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Frauke Zipp, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Volker Siffrin, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Carl Gustav Carus, Deps. Neurology / Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dresden</city>
        <state>Sachsen</state>
        <zip>1307</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tjalf Ziemssen, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 351 458</phone>
      <phone_ext>4465</phone_ext>
      <email>Tjalf.Ziemssen@uniklinikum-dresden.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tjalf Ziemssen, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charité, Deps. Neurology / Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10117</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Friedemann, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 30 450</phone>
      <phone_ext>539-705</phone_ext>
      <email>friedemann.paul@charite.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Friedemann, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.tone-studie.de</url>
    <description>Study information and useful links in German language</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sühs KW, Hein K, Sättler MB, Görlitz A, Ciupka C, Scholz K, Käsmann-Kellner B, Papanagiotou P, Schäffler N, Restemeyer C, Bittersohl D, Hassenstein A, Seitz B, Reith W, Fassbender K, Hilgers R, Heesen C, Bähr M, Diem R. A randomized, double-blind, phase 2 study of erythropoietin in optic neuritis. Ann Neurol. 2012 Aug;72(2):199-210. doi: 10.1002/ana.23573.</citation>
    <PMID>22926853</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 9, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 30, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Optic neuritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Multiple Sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinically isolated syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Erythropoietin</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neuritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Optic Neuritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epoetin Alfa</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
