<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="8067">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01692704</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ONK-USZ-003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01692704</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Downsizing of Unresectable Cholangiocarcinoma by Combined Intravenous and Intra-arterial Chemotherapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Downstaging of Unresectable Intrahepatic or Hilar Cholangiocellular Carcinoma by Selective Intra-arterial Floxuridine and Systemic Cisplatin and Gemcitabine. A Dose Finding Single Center Phase IIa Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Zurich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Zurich</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Switzerland: Swissmedic</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An open label, prospective, non-randomized single arm study. Combination of two treatment
      modalities - HAI with FUDR and systemic chemotherapy with cisplatin and gemcitabine.

      Definition of the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of intravenous gemcitabine in combination
      with intravenous cisplatin and intra-arterial FUDR. Definition of safety and toxicity of
      this combined regional and systemic treatment approach. Definition of the response rate
      after 3 months of hepatic intra-arterial chemotherapy with continuous infusion FUDR with or
      without ligation of the right or left portal vein, in combination with 3 months of systemic
      cisplatin and gemcitabine in patients with unresectable intrahepatic or hilar CCC.

      A total of 9-18 patients are required. 3-6 patients per dose level. A maximum of three dose
      levels (1 - 3) has been defined.

      Statistical Methodology: Traditional 3+3 dosing algorithm to find MTD.

        -  Trial with medicinal product
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose limiting toxicities (DLT) of intravenous gemcitabine with concomitant administration of FUDR-HAI and intravenous cisplatin.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Dose limiting toxicities will be assessed to define the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of gemcitabine in combination with fixed doses of cisplatin and FUDR. DLTs are per protocol prespecified AE or laboratory abnormalities observed during the first 6 weeks of study treatment. The MTD is one dose level below the dose level that caused DLTs in ≥ one third of patients (2 or more in a cohort of 6 patients), as determined by a traditional 3+3 algorithm.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Cholangiocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Selective intra-arterial floxuridine and systemic gemcitabine and cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Intra-arterial floxuridine:0.2 mg/KG/day for 14 days, repeated day 29. Overall 3 applications.
Systemic cisplatin: 25 mg/m2 at days 1 and 8, repeated day 22. Overall 8 applications.
Systemic gemcitabine: Three different dose levels will be tested; 600 mg/m2, 800 mg/m2, or 1000 mg/m2, at days 1 and 8, repeated day 22. Overall 8 applications.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically proven cholangiocellular carcinoma including
             gallbladder cancer.

          -  Non-resectable cholangiocellular carcinoma as judged within an interdisciplinary
             tumor-board including senior hepatobiliary surgeons. Non- resectability is based on
             insufficient remnant liver volume.

          -  Patient is not a candidate for liver transplantation

          -  WHO Performance Score 0 or 1

          -  No extrahepatic tumor, as evaluated by PET/CT scan of the chest and the
             abdomen/pelvis with the exception of potentially resectable small lung nodules or
             hilar lymph node involvement.

          -  The assessment is done within 21 days before registration.

          -  Adequate liver function or kidney function tests, including any of the following:

               -  Bilirubin &lt; 2 x ULN

               -  Aspartate-Aminotransferase (AST) &lt; 5 x ULN

               -  Alanine-Aminotransferase (ALT) &lt; 5 x ULN

               -  Alkaline phosphatase &lt; 5 x ULN

               -  Estimated creatinine clearance &gt; 60 ml/min (using the Cockcroft formula)

          -  Adequate hematological values:

               -  Hemoglobin &gt; 80 G/L

               -  Leucocytes &gt; 3.00 G/L,

               -  Neutrophils &gt; 1.00 G/Ll

               -  Platelets &gt; 100 G/L

          -  Signed written informed consent

          -  Patient age &gt;/= 18 years

          -  Presentation of the case at the interdisciplinary tumor-board attended by
             hepatobiliary surgeons, oncologists, hepatologists and radiologists

          -  Women who are not breastfeeding and are using effective contraception if sexually
             active, who are not pregnant and agree not to become pregnant during the 12 months
             thereafter. A negative pregnancy test before inclusion into the trial is required for
             women &lt; 50 years.

          -  Men who agree not to father a child during participation in the trial or during the
             12 months thereafter.

          -  Patient compliance and geographic proximity allow proper staging and follow- up.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Anatomic variant in arteriogram which prevents selective delivery of the chemotherapy
             to the liver

          -  Life expectancy &lt; 3 months

          -  Severe medical or psychiatric co-morbidity prohibiting the planned treatment or the
             giving of informed consent

          -  Any man or woman of childbearing age in case of inadequate contraception

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding woman

          -  Known hypersensitivity to trial drugs or hypersensitivity to any other component of
             the trial drugs.

          -  Treatment in clinical trial within 30 days prior to trial entry.

          -  Active heart disease defined as congestive heart failure &gt; NYHA class 2

          -  Past or current history (within the last 2 years prior to treatment start) of other
             malignancies except basal and squamous cell carcinoma of the skin or in situ
             carcinoma of the cervix

          -  Inability or unwillingness to comply with the study protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Panagiotis Samaras, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Zurich, Department of Oncology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Panagiotis Samaras, MD</last_name>
    <email>panagiotis.samaras@usz.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Zurich, Department of Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zurich</city>
        <state>ZH</state>
        <zip>8091</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 6, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholangiocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Floxuridine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
