<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="148147">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02086487</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RC12/052</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02086487</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety Assessment of NIlotinib in Patients With Suboptimal Response on Imatinib Therapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>NISRI</acronym>
  <official_title>Efficacy and Safety Assessment of NIlotinib in Patients With Suboptimal Response on Imatinib Therapy (NISRI)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>King Abdullah International Medical Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>King Abdullah International Medical Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Saudi Arabia: Saudi Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      whether Nilotinib at the two sequential dosage forms will induce quicker and deeper response
      in those patients, and if FISH on PB (Peripheral blood) would be an effective way to monitor
      response compared to conventional cytogenetics on bone marrow (BM) sample
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter, open label trial which will be conducted within Kingdom of saudi
      Arabia for which CML (Chronic Myeloid Leukemia) patients who meet eligibility criteria and
      showing sub optimal response to Imatinib therapy as per European leukemia Net ELN 2009
      guidelines will be recruited and switched to Nilotinib 300 mg twice a day therapy.

      Efficacy assessments of hematologic and cytogenetic response and disease progression, will
      be performed every 6 months at a minimum, including hematologic analysis, bone marrow
      cytogenetics, and molecular studies to ensure that nilotinib is being provided to patients
      who were responding and that patients who progressed could discontinue therapy.

      Safety assessments include evaluation of adverse events, hematologic assessment, biochemical
      testing, cardiac enzyme assessment, serial electrocardiogram evaluation, and physical
      examination. Adverse events are graded according to the National Cancer Institute Common
      Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events Version 4.0. Survival will be dated from start of
      nilotinib therapy until death from any cause and censored at last follow-up for patients who
      were alive.

      The data will be summarized with respect to demographic and baseline characteristics,
      efficacy evaluation, and safety observations and measurements.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary efficacy variable of this study is the overall Major molecular response at 12 month after starting Nilotinib 300mg twice daily for patient who suboptimally responded to Imatinib as per the ELN guidelines</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of cytogenetic response (complete cytogenetic response CCyR and Major cytogenetic response MCyR) and Major molecular response MMR at 3, 6 and 12 months of starting Nilotinib in patients who had a suboptimal response on Imatinib.</measure>
    <time_frame>12Months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of CCyR at 6 months and MMR at 6 and 12 months from Nilotinib dose escalating to 400 mg BID.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate and duration of Complete Hematologic Response CHR.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of CMR at 12 months of Nilotinib.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of FISH results with conventional cytogenetics at 3, 6 &amp; 12 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mutational analysis for the patients with suboptimal response at the pre defined end points as per the ELN guidelines.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">98</enrollment>
  <condition>Myeloid Leukemia, Chronic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nilotinib 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients diagnosed with chronic myeloid leukemia receiving treatment of Imatinib 400 mg but show sub-optimal response on Imatinib  therapy as per the ELN 2009 guidelines will be switched to Nilotinib 300 mg and then will be assessed for therapy response. ELN guidelines 2009 states as:
No cytogenetics response at 3 months; BCR-ABL1 (Fusion gene from BCR and ABL/Protein product from BCR-ABL) transcript &gt; 10% at 3 months; less than a partial cytogenetic response at 6 months; BCR-ABL1 transcript &gt; 1% at 6 months less than a complete cytogenetic response at 12 months; less than a major molecular response at 18 months; or loss of major molecular response or development of partially imatinib-sensitive BCR-ABL mutation at any time</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nilotinib 300 mg.</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients diagnosed with chronic myeloid leukemia receiving treatment of Imatinib 400 mg once a day but are determined to be sub-optimally responding to Imatinib therapy as per the ELN 2009 guidelines will be switched to Nilotinib 300 mg BID and then will be assessed for therapy response. ELN guidelines 2009 for imatinib therapy response states as:
No cytogenetics response at 3 months; BCR-ABL1 transcript &gt; 10% at 3 months; less than a partial cytogenetic response at 6 months; BCR-ABL1 transcript &gt; 1% at 6 months less than a complete cytogenetic response at 12 months; less than a major molecular response at 18 months; or loss of major molecular response or development of partially imatinib-sensitive BCR-ABL mutation at any time</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nilotinib 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tasigna 300 mg</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent prior to any study procedures being performed.

          -  Age 18 or above of male or female CML patients in chronic phase.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group ECOG Performance status 0, 1 or 2

          -  Sub-optimal response on Imatinib therapy as determined by any of the following
             criteria:

               1. No cytogenetics response at 3 months; (i.e Ph+ metaphases in BM&gt;95%)

               2. BCR-ABL1 transcript &gt; 10% at 3 months;

               3. less than a partial cytogenetic response at 6 months; (i.e Ph+ metaphases in
                  BM&gt;35%)

               4. BCR-ABL1 transcript &gt; 1% at 6 months

               5. less than a complete cytogenetic response at 12 months; (i.e Ph+ metaphases in
                  BM&gt;0%)

               6. less than a major molecular response at 18 months; i.e (BCR-ABL1 &gt;0.1%)

               7. loss of major molecular response or development of partially imatinib- sensitive
                  BCR-ABl mutation at any time.

          -  Normal serum levels &gt; LLN (lower limit of normal) or corrected to within normal
             limits with supplements, prior to the first dose of study medication, of potassium,
             magnesium and calcium;

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase AST and Alanine aminotransferase ALT &lt; 2.5 x ULN

          -  Alkaline phosphatase &lt; 2.5 x ULN (upper limit of normal)

          -  Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 x ULN;

          -  Serum amylase &lt; 1.5 x ULNPerformance status ECOG 0,1,2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous Exposure to Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor (TKI) other than Imatinib for more
             than 2 weeks

          -  Pregnant or lactating females

          -  Patients with prolonged QT intervals

          -  Patient with history of pancreatitis

          -  Previously documented T315I mutations;

          -  Uncontrolled congestive heart failure or hypertension;

          -  Myocardial infarction or unstable angina pectoris within past 12 months;

          -  Significant arrhythmias, including history or presence of clinically significant
             ventricular or atrial tachyarrhythmias, clinically -significant bradycardias, long QT
             syndrome and/or corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt; 450 msec on screening ECG.  Patients
             with complete LBBB (Left Bundle Branch Block);

          -  Patients concurrently on strong cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) inhibitors as listed in
             appendix XI;

          -  Other concurrent uncontrolled medical conditions (e.g. uncontrolled diabetes, active
             or uncontrolled infections, acute or chronic liver and renal disease) that could
             cause unacceptable safety risks or compromise compliance with the protocol;

          -  Impaired gastrointestinal function or GI disease that may alter the absorption of
             study drug (e.g. ulcerative disease, uncontrolled nausea, vomiting and diarrhea,
             malabsorption syndrome, small bowel resection or gastric by-pass surgery);

          -  Patients with another primary malignancy that is currently clinically significant or
             requires active intervention.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dr. Ahmad S. Alaskar, MD,FACP,FRCP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>King Abdulaziz Medical City</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Guard Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Riyadh</city>
        <zip>11426</zip>
        <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 18, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 27, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>NIlotinib ,  Suboptimal Response ,  Imatinib</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Imatinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
