<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="119528">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02148770</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>646/2013BO2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02148770</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurofeedback and Eating</brief_title>
  <official_title>Modulating Functional Connectivity Between Eating-related Brain Areas by Neurofeedback</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Tuebingen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Tuebingen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Neuroimaging has becoming increasingly common to investigate the neural networks underlying
      eating behaviour and food preference in normal-weight and obese humans. It has been observed
      that obese in comparison to lean individuals display altered activation patterns in
      reward-processing brain areas. Interestingly, obese individuals who prove to be capable of
      losing weight appear to have a stronger connectivity between areas related to food value and
      to the control of eating behaviour. The same areas are also associated with healthy food
      choices. Based on these neural differences, brain-related intervention strategies to support
      weight loss and long-lasting weight maintenance are of particular interest. Such
      interventions can also be assumed to interact with sleep behaviour against the background of
      recent findings showing that short or impaired sleep favours increases in food intake and
      compromises memory functions. Hence, the investigators want to examine the effect on eating
      behaviour of neurofeedback training-induced up-regulation of functional connectivity between
      reward- and impulse-related brain areas, with a particular focus on the influence of sleep
      behaviour on this effect.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: (i) The investigators want to investigate whether neurofeedback training-induced
      up-regulation of the functional connectivity between the dorsal medial frontal and ventral
      medial prefrontal cortex reduces food intake in obese humans. (ii) The investigators want to
      examine whether the strength of this effect depends on regular sleep between training
      sessions.

      Study design: Two groups of subjects, i.e., carriers and non-carriers of the obesity-risk
      associated FTO-allele, will participate in four experimental conditions according to a
      randomized parallel design. Half of the subjects in each group will learn to up-regulate the
      functional connectivity between the two brain areas, while the other subjects will
      participate in sham-training sessions. In each group, half of the subjects that underwent
      the up-regulation and half of the subjects who underwent the sham-regulation condition will
      enjoy regular night sleep. The other subjects will have a night of complete sleep
      restriction. Adherence to experimental conditions will be assigned randomly, based on the
      subjects' enrolment in the study.

      Study population: 120 overweight and obese (BMI 25-40 kg/m2), but otherwise healthy men,
      18-65 years old.

      Intervention: All subjects will participate in a pre-test day, followed by four
      neurofeedback-sleep session days and a post-test day. During each neurofeedback-sleep
      session, subjects will undergo a 45 min real-time-fMRI-brain-computer-interface scan in
      order to learn to regulate the functional connectivity between the respective two brain
      areas. Nocturnal sleep after each training session will be kept normal or be restricted in
      the sleep laboratory.

      Main study parameters/endpoints:

        1. The ability to regulate functional connectivity.

        2. Respective effects on eating behaviour.

        3. The effect of sleep restriction on parameters 1 and 2. Nature and extent of the burden
           and risks associated with participation, benefit and group relatedness: Participants
           will be scanned 6 times (fMRI). Functional MRI is a safe and non-invasive technique.
           Additionally blood will be drawn. This procedure will have a low risk in healthy
           people.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurofeedback and eating behaviour</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>We want to determine if the training-induced up-regulation of the functional connectivity between the ventral prefrontal medial cortex and the dorsal prefrontal cortex inhibits eating behaviour. This will outcome will be determined by the ability to regulate functional connectivity (brain activity measured during training) and respective effects on eating behaviour (food choice task during regulation at end of the training).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>neurofeedback and sleep</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine if sleep is essential for the effects of neurofeedback training to emerge.  We will study the differences in ability to up-regulate the functional connectivity and its effect on eating behaviour (food choice task).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>8</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Self-regulation</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Sleep</condition>
  <condition>Eating Behaviour</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+SHNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects are FTO+ carriers: carriers of FTO-allele which is associated with risk for obesity.
Neurofeedback training: Sham regulation of functional connectivity between vmPFC and DLPFC.
Normal Sleep after neurofeedback training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+SHSD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects are FTO+ carriers: carriers of FTO-allele which is associated with risk for obesity.
Neurofeedback training: Sham regulation of functional connectivity between vmPFC and DLPFC.
Sleep deprivation after neurofeedback training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+UPNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects are FTO+ carriers: carriers of FTO-allele which is associated with risk for obesity.
Neurofeedback training: Up-regulation of functional connectivity between vmPFC and DLPFC.
Normal sleep after neurofeedback training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+UPSD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects are FTO+ carriers: carriers of FTO-allele which is associated with risk for obesity.
Neurofeedback training: Up-regulation of functional connectivity between vmPFC and DLPFC.
Sleep deprivation after neurofeedback training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-SHNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects are FTO non-carriers (FTO-allele which is associated with risk for obesity).
Neurofeedback training: sham-regulation of functional connectivity between vmPFC and DLPFC.
Normal sleep after neurofeedback training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-SHSD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects are FTO non-carriers (FTO-allele which is associated with risk for obesity).
Neurofeedback training: sham-regulation of functional connectivity between vmPFC and DLPFC.
Sleep deprivation after neurofeedback training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-UPNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects are FTO non-carriers (FTO-allele which is associated with risk for obesity).
Neurofeedback training: Up-regulation of functional connectivity between vmPFC and DLPFC.
Normal sleep after neurofeedback training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-UPSD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects are FTO non-carriers (FTO-allele which is associated with risk for obesity).
Neurofeedback training: Up-regulation of functional connectivity between vmPFC and DLPFC.
Sleep deprivation after neurofeedback training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neurofeedback</intervention_name>
    <description>Networks involved in eating behaviour can be modified by neurofeedback training. We will perform a neurofeedback task using the technology of fMRI-based Brain Computer Interface (BCI). BCI approaches based on real-time fMRI (rtfMRI) allow voluntary regulation of brain regions. For the rtfMRI, a well-established setup will be used which translates the blood oxygen level dependent (BOLD) signal of a specific brain region of interest into a visual signal (e.g. moving bar) in real time using brain voyager® and matlab. The study will include 4 training-sessions spread over 2 weeks. Two training-session days have to be at least 3 days apart. In the up-regulation condition subjects will learn to up regulate their functional connectivity between vmPFC and dlPFC. In the sham-condition subjects are get the same instructions, however they will receive sham feedback.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+SHNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+SHSD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+UPNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+UPSD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-SHNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-SHSD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-UPNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-UPSD</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BCI</other_name>
    <other_name>Neurofeedback training</other_name>
    <other_name>rtfMRI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sleep Deprivation</intervention_name>
    <description>Half of the participants will have regular night sleep, whereas the other half will undergo complete sleep deprivation after every neurofeedback training session. First all participants will fill in several memory questionnaires and perform computer reaction time tests. Afterwards participants can enjoy a normal night of sleep, or be kept awake the whole night under the supervision and in the company of the experimenter. During the night a sleep EEG is registered. The next morning all participants will again fill in the memory questionnaires and perform a computer reaction time tests.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+SHSD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+UPSD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-SHSD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-UPSD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Normal Sleep</intervention_name>
    <description>Half of the participants will have regular night sleep, whereas the other half will undergo complete sleep deprivation after every neurofeedback training session. First all participants will fill in several memory questionnaires and perform computer reaction time tests. Afterwards participants can enjoy a normal night of sleep, or be kept awake the whole night under the supervision and in the company of the experimenter. During the night a sleep EEG is registered. The next morning all participants will again fill in the memory questionnaires and perform a computer reaction time tests.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+SHNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+UPNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-SHNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-UPNS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fMRI-based Brain Computer Interface (BCI)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+SHNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+SHSD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+UPNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO+UPSD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-SHNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-SHSD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-UPNS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO-UPSD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy male subjects

          -  Age 18-65 years at start of the study

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) between 25 and 40 kg/m2

          -  Right-handedness

          -  Non-smokers

          -  Informed consent to study protocol

          -  Willingness to be informed about chance findings of pathology and approval of the
             disclosure of this information to the general physician (see Informed Consent)

          -  Fulfilment of the criteria for blood donors according to the &quot;Richtlinien zur
             Gewinnung von Blut und Blutbestandteilen und zur Anwendung von Blutprodukten&quot;, in
             particular Hb ≥ 135 g/l (8,37 mmol/l; Bundesärztekammer 2010)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who have a non-removable metal object in or at their body, such as, for
             ex-ample:

               -  Heart pace-maker

               -  Artificial heart valve

               -  Metal prosthesis

               -  Metallic implants (screws, plates from operations, etc.)

               -  Metal splinters / grenade fragments

               -  Non-removable dental braces

               -  Acupuncture needles

               -  Insulin pump

               -  Intraport, etc.

               -  In field strengths of over 1.0 T also: tattoos, eye lid-shadow

          -  Current weight loss regimens

          -  Limited temperature perception and/or increased sensitivity to warming of the body

          -  Pathological hearing ability or an increased sensitivity to loud noises

          -  Claustrophobia

          -  Lack of ability to give informed consent

          -  Operation less than three month ago

          -  Simultaneous participation in other studies

          -  Acute illness or infection during the last 4 weeks

          -  Neurological disorder or injury

          -  Moderate or severe head injury

          -  Severe psychotic illness

          -  Intake of antidepressants / antipsychotics

          -  Participation in other studies with blood withdrawals or blood donation in previous
             and subsequent 2 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Manfred Hallschmid, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+49 7071 29-8825</phone>
    <email>Manfred.Hallschmid@uni-tuebingen.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Maartje Spetter, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+49 7071 29-81193</phone>
    <email>Maartje.Spetter@med.uni-tuebingen.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UKT and MPI</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tuebingen</city>
        <zip>72076</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Manfred Hallschmid, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+49 7071 29-8825</phone>
      <email>Manfred.Hallschmid@uni-tuebingen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maartje Spetter, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Manfred Hallschmid, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ralf Veit, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.braintrainproject.eu/</url>
    <description>Overview of main project. This study is a pilot from for the larger studies decribed on this website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weiskopf N, Scharnowski F, Veit R, Goebel R, Birbaumer N, Mathiak K. Self-regulation of local brain activity using real-time functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI). J Physiol Paris. 2004 Jul-Nov;98(4-6):357-73. Epub 2005 Nov 10. Review. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>16289548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sitaram R, Caria A, Veit R, Gaber T, Rota G, Kuebler A, Birbaumer N. FMRI brain-computer interface: a tool for neuroscientific research and treatment. Comput Intell Neurosci. 2007:25487. doi: 10.1155/2007/25487. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>18274615</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 27, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>rt-fmri</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
