<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="73886">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01933243</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TAANA-287112</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01933243</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Anxiety and Anorexia Nervosa in Adolescents</brief_title>
  <acronym>TAANA</acronym>
  <official_title>Treatment of Anxiety and Anorexia Nervosa in Adolescents</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nationwide Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nationwide Children's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Adolescents with anorexia nervosa frequently have associated anxiety, and standard
      medications used for anxiety are unhelpful when patients are malnourished. This is a 12 week
      trial examining the safety, tolerability, and effectiveness of fish oil nutritional
      supplements for anxiety in adolescents with anorexia nervosa. In addition, investigators are
      studying the effectiveness of a 4 week trial of massage therapy in these patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Anorexia nervosa (AN) is an eating disorder characterized by a morbid fear of weight gain
      and a perception of being overweight despite objective evidence of weight loss and
      malnutrition. It has been estimated that almost 0.9% of women will suffer form AN at some
      point in their lives, and most cases of AN arise during adolescence. Even with appropriate
      treatment, only about half of patients with AN will have a full recovery, 30% partial
      recovery, and 20% will progress to having a chronic illness. Earlier, more aggressive
      treatment with appropriate nutritional recovery during adolescence offers the best chance of
      a full recovery.  Treatment of AN is complicated by the high rate of comorbid psychiatric
      diagnoses, the physical and cognitive effects of the attendant malnutrition, and the lack of
      effective pharmacologic interventions. Approximately 75% of patients with AN have a comorbid
      psychiatric illness, including depression, obsessive compulsive disorder, and anxiety.
      Anxiety disorders in particular share attributes with AN, including perfectionism, rigidity,
      compulsivity, and harm avoidance in addition to trait anxiety. Complicating treatment, the
      risk and severity of patients' anxiety is enhanced by a lower body mass index (BMI), and
      this low BMI is the likely reason why standard medication treatments for generalized
      anxiety, such as selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors are ineffective. In order to
      address these treatment challenges, we propose to study the tolerability, feasibility and
      efficacy of two non-pharmacologic interventions for anxiety in adolescents with AN: omega-3
      polyunsaturated fatty acid (PUFA) supplementation and massage therapy (MT).

      Over the past 15 years, there has been an interest in possible associations between fish oil
      and affective illness, particularly depression. Low plasma levels of docosaheaenoic acid, an
      essential fatty acid found in fish oil, are associated with low concentrations of
      cerebrospinal fluid 5-hydroxyindolacetic acid (5-HIAA), a marker of central nervous system
      serotonin turnover. Epidemiologically, those populations with higher fish oil consumption
      tend to have lower rates of depression,  and reported low levels of fish consumption have
      been associated with a greater risk of depression in women. It has been hypothesized that
      omega-3 PUFAs alter brain phospholipid composition and enhance membrane fluidity, and this
      is supported by evidence that supplementation with omega-3 PUFAs decreases brain water
      proton transverse relaxation times in patients with bipolar disorder.  The association with
      depression and the proposed mechanism of action elicited some interest regarding
      associations between omega-3 PUFAs and anxiety disorders.  Supplementation trials have shown
      mixed results, with no effects for obsessive compulsive disorder in patients taking maximum
      doses of selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors, and another showing decreased anxiety
      symptoms in 22 patients enrolled in a substance abuse treatment program. Recently,
      Kiecolt-Glaser and colleagues described a decrease in test-related anxiety symptoms in a
      non-clinical sample of medical students related to supplementation with omega-3 PUFAs.
      Although there has been some interest in the use of omega-3 PUFA supplementation as an
      adjunctive treatment for anorexia nervosa, there have been no systematic trials.

      MT is broadly defined as the manipulation of soft tissue with the intention of promoting
      health and well being. Single-dose MT has been used as a treatment for state anxiety,
      negative mood, and immediate pain, and multiple-dose MT has been used for trait-anxiety,
      depression, and delayed pain, with the effects most prominent for relief of state anxiety
      symptoms.  MT is a standard component of the protocol for inpatient medical stabilization of
      patients with AN at Nationwide Children's, and there have been multiple anecdotal reports
      from patients and parents regarding subjective decreases in food-related anxiety. However,
      there is little empirical evidence to support the use of MT in the treatment of AN. Thus
      far, there has only been one small trial involving a total of 19 adult patients in treatment
      for AN that demonstrated lower self-reported anxiety and stress levels as well as lower
      cortisol levels immediately after MT. After receiving MT twice weekly for 5 weeks, those
      patients who received MT also had lower scores on a standard eating disorder symptom
      inventory.

      Given the lack of efficacy of standard treatments for anxiety in AN, investigators are
      conducting a tolerability, feasibility, and efficacy study of the two interventions noted
      above: omega-3 PUFAs taken daily for 12 weeks and MT administered 3 times weekly for 4 weeks
      for the treatment of anxiety in adolescents with AN. Investigators will also assess the
      utility of measuring HRV, salivary α-amylase, and cortisol as assessments of stress
      responses in this population.

      Experimental Design and Methods Study Design: This pilot study utilizes a 2-stage
      randomization design to assess the feasibility, tolerability, and efficacy of omega-3 PUFA
      supplementation and MT for the treatment of trait anxiety in adolescents with AN.
      Participants are initially randomized into 2 study arms: omega-3 PUFAs or placebo. After 8
      weeks, participants in each group are then randomized to either receive MT or not, while
      continuing taking their daily omega-3 PUFAs or placebo.

      Recruitment:

      Recruitment takes place within the Nationwide Children's Hospital Eating Disorders Program
      (EDP). Potential participants are identified by the EDP nurse when arriving for care. If a
      patient and family are interested in learning more about the research study, program staff
      provide written information, and the study coordinator contacts the family to arrange formal
      consenting and study intake procedures.

      Study protocol:

      Phase 1 (Omega-3 PUFA lead-in), 8 weeks:

      Group 1 (PUFA): 20 participants will be administered omega-3 PUFAs [2085 mg of
      eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and 348 mg of docosahexaenoic acid (23)] in capsule form once
      daily.

      Group 2 (Control): 20 participants will take a placebo capsule once daily as described
      above.

      Phase 2 (Addition of MT), 4 weeks:

      In phase 2, half of the participants in groups 1 and 2 will be randomized to receive MT.
      During this phase, participants will continue taking either omega-3 PUFAs or placebo
      capsules. The massage intervention consists of one massage given by a licensed massage
      therapist three times weekly for 4 weeks. A standardized massage therapy protocol based on
      principles of Swedish massage will be used to ensure consistency in methods. The massage
      will include 30 minutes of gentle friction, kneading, stroking, and passive touch on the
      adolescent's upper extremities, lower extremities, head, face, and back. Standard
      hospital-provided, unscented lotion will be used, and massage will be accompanied by
      participant's choice of music. Massage sessions will be provided in a private examination
      room in the Clinical Research Services unit, equipped with a massage table. To ensure
      integrity of the intervention, an experienced licensed massage therapist not providing the
      study intervention will observe massage technique of each of the intervention therapists
      throughout the course of the study to test delivery consistent with agreed upon protocol.
      These observations will occur randomly with 20% of the 240 massages to be delivered.

      All participants will continue to receive standard clinical care as determined by the
      clinical care team in the Nationwide Children's Hospital Eating Disorders Program. This
      standard care includes regular medical appointments, psychotherapy appointments, and
      nutritional counseling as well as group and family therapy sessions.

      Statistical Analysis A total of 40 subjects will be recruited into the study.  Mean score on
      the 8-item tolerability scale, in addition to descriptive statistics of reported side
      effects and frequencies, will be used to assess tolerability of omega-3 fatty acid
      supplementation.  Feasibility of massage therapy will be assessed by appointment compliance
      (total attended/total scheduled x 100).  For assessment of improvement in anxiety, the main
      outcome measure will be change in trait anxiety from baseline to 8 weeks as measured by the
      Beck Anxiety Inventory-Trait (BAIT). For this analysis, investigators will focus on
      comparing changes in the BAIT between subjects randomized to receive omega-3 PUFAs (n = 20)
      and those receiving placebo (n = 20).  Analysis of Covariance (ANCOVA) will be used to
      compare the 8-week BAIT scores between treatment groups adjusting for baseline scores and
      potential confounders.  Based on published data, investigators anticipate a mean difference
      in BAIT score of 4-6 points between groups with a standard deviation of 6.0.  Assuming a
      mean difference of 5 between groups, there will be 75.02% power to detect this difference
      between groups with a standard deviation of 6.

      The secondary anxiety outcome measure will be change in trait anxiety from 8 weeks to 12
      weeks as measured by the BAIT.  For this analysis, subjects randomized to receive massage
      during this 4-week interval (n = 20) will be compared to those not receiving massage (n =
      20).  The same assumptions as above hold for this analysis.  Analysis of Covariance (ANCOVA)
      will be used to compare the 12-week BAIT scores between treatment groups adjusting for week
      8 scores and potential confounders.  Investigators will also conduct sub-group analyses of
      subjects receiving massage with and without omega-3 to explore for any interaction between
      these two therapies in the ANCOVA model, although inferences from these sub-group analyses
      will be limited by small sample sizes.  Physiologic measures of stress and anxiety (salivary
      cortisol, α-amylase, and HF HRV) will also be described for all subjects, at each time point
      and by treatment group. Potential confounders which will be included in our analyses will
      include current BMI, and differences in EAT-26 scores reflective of eating disorders
      symptomatology.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability of fish oil supplementation in adolescents with anorexia nervosa.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Mean score on the 8-item fish oil tolerability scale, in addition to descriptive statistics of reported side effects and frequencies, will be used to assess tolerability of omega-3 fatty acid supplementation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in trait anxiety in subjects receiving a combination of omega-3 PUFA supplementation and massage therapy plus standard of careas compared to subjects receiving standard of care treatment alone (controls).</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in BAIT scores between weeks 0, 8, and 12</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of physiologic measures of anxiety (salivary α-amylase, salivary cortisol, high frequency heart rate variability) to assess anxiety and the trajectory of stress responses over time in adolescents with anorexia nervosa.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Compliance with saliva collection protocol.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of incorporating massage therapy into the outpatient treatment of adolescents with anorexia nervosa.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Feasibility of massage therapy will be assessed by appointment compliance (total attended/total scheduled x 100).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Anorexia Nervosa</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fish oil, massage therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fish oil for 12 weeks plus massage therapy for 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fish oil, no massage therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fish oil for 12 weeks but no massage therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo pill, massage therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo pills for 12 weeks plus massage therapy for 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo pill, no massage therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo pills for 12 weeks, no massage therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fish oil</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will take 2 capsules daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fish oil, massage therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fish oil, no massage therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ProEPA Xtra soft gel capsules</other_name>
    <other_name>Eicosapentaenoic acid (2120mg)/ docosahexaenoic acid (600mg)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Massage therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>30 minutes of modified Swedish massage three times weekly for 4 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fish oil, massage therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo pill, massage therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo pill</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will take 2 capsules daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo pill, massage therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo pill, no massage therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Clinical diagnosis of AN BMI less than 10th percentile for age and gender.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Symptoms for greater than 1 year

          2. inability to take pills

          3. co-morbid medical conditions affecting appetite and weight (e.g., inflammatory bowel
             disease, cancer, cystic fibrosis)

          4. co-morbid psychiatric conditions affecting appetite and weight (e.g., bipolar
             disorder, substance abuse)

          5. current treatment with psychiatric medications, including selective serotonin
             reuptake inhibitors, benzodiazepines, and neuroleptic medications

          6. Currently taking fish oil supplements

          7. inability to participate in study for 12 consecutive weeks.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Terrill Bravender, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nationwide Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Terrill Bravender, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>614-722-2458</phone>
    <email>terrill.bravender@nationwidechildrens.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jules Arthur, MS</last_name>
    <phone>(614) 722-2656</phone>
    <email>julianne.arthur@nationwidechildrens.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nationwide Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Terrill Bravender, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>614-722-2458</phone>
      <email>terrill.bravender@nationwidechildrens.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Terrill Bravender, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 28, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>Anorexia nervosa</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescents</keyword>
  <keyword>Fish oil</keyword>
  <keyword>Massage therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anorexia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anorexia Nervosa</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
