<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="105775">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01759862</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>24280</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01759862</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Perioperative Aminophylline to Improve Early Kidney Function After a Kidney Transplant</brief_title>
  <acronym>RTphylline</acronym>
  <official_title>Perioperative Aminophylline to Improve High Risk Renal Graft Outcome- a Double Blinded, Placebo Controlled, Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to evaluate whether peri-transplant administration of a drug named
      aminophylline to children undergoing a kidney transplant from deceased donors improves early
      graft function and also projects on long term graft function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Double-blinded, placebo-controlled, randomized, clinical trial to evaluate whether
      administration of aminophylline starting pretransplant until post-transplant day 5 improves
      early kidney function and projects also on long term graft function.

      Study Arms and intervention: On admit to the hospital prior to transplant, patients will be
      randomized into treatment or control arms. The randomization will be based on age groups
      1-5y, 5-12y and 12-18y Treatment arm: Patients will receive aminophylline loading dose
      5mg/kg prior to transplant and will continue to receive aminophylline 1.8mg/kg Q6h for a
      total of 20 doses.

      Control arm: Patients will receive placebo infusion of normal saline, pre-transplant,
      followed by normal saline infusions matched by volume and frequency to treatment arm for a
      total of 20doses.

      The only difference between the two arms will be the study intervention. Other than that all
      patients will receive the same standard of care for patients undergoing a kidney transplant.

      Theophylline drug levels will be monitored every morning from all patients for the first 4
      days post- transplant. Theophylline levels will be reported independently by the laboratory
      in a faxed research report directly to the pharmacist who will perform dose adjustments,
      according to the following table.

      Theophylline Level (mcg/ml) Dose Adjustment &lt;2 Increase subsequent doses by 50% 2-2.9
      Increase subsequent doses by 33% 3-3.9 Increase subsequent doses by 25% 4-4.9 Increase
      subsequent doses by 15% 5-7 (goal) Target Level; No dose adjustment 7.1-8.4 Decrease
      subsequent doses by 10% 8.5-9.9 Decrease subsequent doses by 15% 10-12.4 Decrease subsequent
      doses by 25% 12.5-14.9 Decrease subsequent doses by 50% 15-19.9 Decrease subsequent doses by
      67% &gt;19.9 Discontinue all aminophylline doses. Contact Medical Monitor

      All involved personnel will be blinded to the patient's allocation and to the drug level
      results.

      The investigators will also collect a urine sample for NGAL (Neutrophil
      gelatinase-associated lipocalin)levels from all patients at 12 hours post-transplant.

      Primary outcome will be calculated Glomerular Filtration Rate(GFR) on postoperative day 5.
      The investigators will determine whether patients in the aminophylline group had improved
      GFR compared to control group.

      The investigators will also determine whether patients who received aminophylline had lower
      urinary NGAL levels compared to control group indicating a lesser degree of kidney injury.
      Urinary NGAL (Neutrophil gelatinase-associated lipocalin) is a biomarker of kidney injury.
      Elevated urinary NGAL levels post-transplant were found to be predictive of delayed graft
      function and the need for dialysis post-transplant.

      At the investigators' center all patients undergo routine kidney protocol biopsies at 6
      months post- transplant. After the slides are read by the pathologist the investigators will
      use the same tissue blocks to quantify the amount of fibrosis using computerized image
      analysis of Sirius Red-stained biopsies. The amount of fibrosis seen on 6 months protocol
      biopsies was proven to be correlated with expected graft survival.

      An independent medical monitor will be assigned to manage toxic theophylline levels
      &gt;20mcg/mL. The laboratory will report directly to the medical monitor, who will discontinue
      aminophylline and remove the patient from the study.

      The trial will be also be monitored with a Data Safety Monitoring Board (DSMB) unrelated to
      the study. The DSMB will meet after enrollment of 20 patients to assess for drug safety and
      monitor for adverse events of the drug.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Calculated estimated Glomerular Filtration rate (eGFR)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The investigators will measure blood creatinine on post-operative day 5 and using the Schwartz equation will calculate estimated glomerular filtration rate (GFR) to determine kidney function.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary NGAL (Neutrophil gelatinase-associated lipocalin) levels</measure>
    <time_frame>12 hours post transplant</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>urinary NGAL(Neutrophil gelatinase-associated lipocalin) is a biomarker for kidney injury. NGAL levels 12h post-transplant were found to be a marker for development of delayed graft function and need for dialysis post-transplant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Degree of fibrosis measured on protocol biopsy</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The investigators will use the same cores that are obtained during routine 6 months protocol biopsies to quantify the amount of fibrosis using computerized image analysis of Sirius Red-stained biopsies. The degree of fibrosis at 6 months was found to correlate with graft survival.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Function of Renal Transplant</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aminophylline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive aminophylline loading dose 5mg/kg prior to transplant and will continue to receive aminophylline 1.8mg/kg Q6h for a total of 20 doses.
Theophylline drug levels will be monitored daily for 4 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive placebo infusion of normal saline, pre-transplant, followed by normal saline infusions matched by volume and frequency to treatment arm for a total of 20 doses.
Drug levels will be monitored daily for 4 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aminophylline</intervention_name>
    <description>Aminophylline loading dose 5mg/kg prior to transplant and will continue to receive aminophylline 1.8mg/kg Q6h for a total of 20 doses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aminophylline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Theophylline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Theophylline drug levels</intervention_name>
    <description>Theophylline drug levels will be monitored every morning from all patients for the first 4 days post- transplant.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aminophylline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive placebo infusion of normal saline, pre-transplant, followed by normal saline infusions matched by volume and frequency to treatment arm for a total of 20 doses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Normal saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Pediatric kidney transplant recipients less than 21 years of age

          2. Patients undergoing deceased donor (DD) kidney transplants

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Known history of non-sinus tachycardia

          2. Multiple organ transplants recipients

          3. Severe liver dysfunction
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul C Grimm, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Medical director, Pediatric Kidney Transplant Program Department of Pediatric Nephrology , Lucile Packard Children's hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lucile Packard Children's Hospital at Stanford</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305-5208</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Orly Haskin, MD</last_name>
      <phone>650-723-7903</phone>
      <email>orlyh@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Paul C Grimm, MD</last_name>
      <phone>6507237903</phone>
      <email>pgrimm@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Orly Haskin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Grimm, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grenz A, Baier D, Petroktistis F, Wehrmann M, Köhle C, Schenk M, Sessler M, Gleiter CH, Fandrich F, Osswald H. Theophylline improves early allograft function in rat kidney transplantation. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 2006 May;317(2):473-9. Epub 2006 Jan 12.</citation>
    <PMID>16410406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhat MA, Shah ZA, Makhdoomi MS, Mufti MH. Theophylline for renal function in term neonates with perinatal asphyxia: a randomized, placebo-controlled trial. J Pediatr. 2006 Aug;149(2):180-4.</citation>
    <PMID>16887430</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jenik AG, Ceriani Cernadas JM, Gorenstein A, Ramirez JA, Vain N, Armadans M, Ferraris JR. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of the effects of prophylactic theophylline on renal function in term neonates with perinatal asphyxia. Pediatrics. 2000 Apr;105(4):E45.</citation>
    <PMID>10742366</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McLaughlin GE, Abitbol CL. Reversal of oliguric tacrolimus nephrotoxicity in children. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2005 Jul;20(7):1471-5. Epub 2005 Apr 19.</citation>
    <PMID>15840666</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 30, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>kidney transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Aminophylline</keyword>
  <keyword>pediatric</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Aminophylline</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Theophylline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
