<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="92583">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02132754</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4166-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02132754</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of MK-4166 in Participants With Advanced Solid Tumors (MK-4166-001)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 1 Trial of Single Agent MK-4166 in Subjects With Advanced Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a 3-part dose-escalation study to determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD)/maximum
      administered dose (MAD) of MK-4166 in participants with advanced solid tumors. In Part A,
      the doses will be escalated quickly in successive cohorts and based on safety events may
      progress to Part B, in which the preliminary MTD will be identified; based on safety events
      the study may progress to Part C in which the MTD will be confirmed. The primary study
      hypothesis is that single agent MK-4166 has acceptable safety and tolerability.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants experiencing dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 (up to 21 days)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants experiencing adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants discontinuing study drug due to adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 84 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive MK-4166 at assigned dose, intravenously over 30 minutes, on Day 1 of each 21-day cycle, for up to 4 cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-4166</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>All Participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Participant has histologically- or cytologically-confirmed metastatic or locally
             advanced solid tumor that has failed to respond to standard therapy or progressed
             despite standard therapy, or participant is not a candidate for standard therapy or
             unwilling to undergo standard therapy, or there is no available therapy that may
             convey clinical benefit

          -  Measurable disease by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) version
             1.1

          -  Performance status of 0 or 1 on the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG)
             Performance Scale

          -  Adequate organ function

          -  Female participants of childbearing potential must have a negative urine or serum
             pregnancy test and must be surgically sterile or willing to use 2 methods of birth
             control or abstain from heterosexual activity for the course of the study through 30
             days after last dose of study drug

          -  Male participants must agree to use an adequate method of contraception during sexual
             contact with females of childbearing potential starting with the first dose of study
             medication through 180 days after the last dose of study drug

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Chemotherapy, radiation, or biological cancer therapy within 4 weeks prior to the
             first dose of study therapy, or who has not recovered to Common Terminology Criteria
             for Adverse Events (CTCAE) Grade 1 or better from the adverse events due to cancer
             therapeutics administered more than 4 weeks earlier

          -  Currently participating or has participated in a study of an investigational agent or
             using an investigational device within 28 days of administration of MK-4166

          -  Expected to require any other form of antineoplastic therapy while on study

          -  On chronic systemic steroid therapy in excess of replacement doses, or on any other
             form of immunosuppressive medication

          -  History of a malignancy for which potentially curative treatment has been completed,
             with no evidence of malignancy for 5 years excepting successful definitive resection
             of basal cell carcinoma of the skin, superficial bladder cancer, or in situ cervical
             cancer.

          -  Known active central nervous system (CNS) metastases and/or carcinomatous meningitis

          -  Severe hypersensitivity reaction to treatment with another monoclonal antibody

          -  Active autoimmune disease or a documented history of autoimmune disease, except
             vitiligo or resolved childhood asthma/atopy

          -  Active infection requiring therapy

          -  Active, non-infectious pneumonitis

          -  Prior stem cell or bone marrow transplant

          -  Positive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), Hepatitis B, or Hepatitis C

          -  Known psychiatric or substance abuse disorders that would interfere with cooperation
             with the requirements of the trial.

          -  Regular user (including &quot;recreational use&quot;) of any illicit drugs or recent history
             (within the last year) of substance abuse (including alcohol)

          -  Symptomatic ascites or pleural effusion

          -  Pregnant, breastfeeding, or expecting to conceive or father children within the
             projected duration of the study

          -  Clinically significant heart disease

          -  Major surgery in the past 16 weeks

          -  Received a live vaccine within 30 days prior to first dose
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Toll Free Number</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-577-8839</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 5, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 5, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
