<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="110761">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01662765</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MK-003-UPS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01662765</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Conservative Versus Surgical Treatment of Umbilical Pilonidal Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Conservative Versus Surgical Treatment of Umbilical Pilonidal Sinus Disease: A Prospective, Randomised, and Multicenter Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical Park Gaziantep Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Zeugma Saglik Hizmetleri San. Tic. Ltd. Sti.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical Park Gaziantep Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Turkey: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Investigator's information in the Responsible Party data elements is not properly
      formatted. Please provide the investigator's &quot;Official Title&quot; (e.g., Director, Head of
      Otolaryngology, Principal Investigator, Clinical Professor).Pilonidal sinus disease is a
      common health problem. It is seen most frequently in the sacrococcygeal region. However, it
      can also observed in the umbilicus. Although rare, umbilical pilonidal sinus (UPS) disease,
      is still poorly understood both in terms of diagnosis or pathophysiology and the best
      treatment options. The incidence and the prevelance of the disease is thought to be 0.6% and
      %0.1, respectively, and is more common in males.

      Pilonidal sinus disease of the umbilicus is caused by hair penetrating the skin, causing a
      foreign-body reaction and development of a sinus lined with granulation tissue. Most of the
      patients complain of pain, discharge or bleeding from the umbilicus when symptoms develop.
      It can be diagnosed with a careful examination, in which hairs can be seen deep in the
      umbilicus and usually protrude from a small sinus.

      The first article, which can be considered as umbilical pilonidal sinus disease was first
      published by Dr. Warren in 1854, and he described the removal of a sprinkle of hair from the
      umbilicus. But the term &quot;umbilical pilonidal sinus&quot; was first described and used by Williams
      and Patey in 1956. Since this initial reference to umbilical pilonidal sinus there have been
      approximately only 30 reports in the literature. Most of them are case reports and remaining
      consists of small case series. But until now no prospective randomised studies have been
      published related to UPS.

      UPS is one of the most neclected disease that few reported studies and lack of the
      prospective randomised studies in the literature, and no cosensus about the treatment of the
      disease  supports this idea. However, it may be actually more common than thought and may be
      found more frequently if sought specifically.

      The aim of the study was to compare the results of conservative and surgical treatment, to
      create an algorithm for the management of the disease, and gain more information about the
      etiologiy, pathogenesis, and course of the disease. The investigators hypothesise that
      surgical treatment of UPS will be better than conservative management in terms of recurrence
      rate, healing time, patient comfort and satisfaction, and cost effectiveness.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>cure rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year after initial treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Primary outcome was the cure rate. Absence of recurrence within two year after the first treatment was considered as a cure. In contrast, a recurrence was defined as the appearance of a new, active discharging sinus or granulation tissue with/without a bit of hairs in the deep of the umbilicus within two years after therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>healing time</measure>
    <time_frame>two year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>the time form initial treatment to healing the wound and/or sinus and/or granulation tissue and no any sign of drainage with no longer need for dressing and wound care in either treatment arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>complications</measure>
    <time_frame>two years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>formation chronic non-healing wound, bleeding, and infection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>patient satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>two years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>it will evaluated in five categories as follow: very satisfied, satisfied, not bad, unsatisfied, worst</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>costs</measure>
    <time_frame>two year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>from initial treatment to the complete healing, all kind of cost will be calculated.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">84</enrollment>
  <condition>Pilonidal Sinus</condition>
  <condition>Sinus; Dermal, Pilonidal</condition>
  <condition>Umbilical Granuloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Circulary incision 2-3 mm below the skin level in the umbilicus through the subcutaneos fat towards the linea alba. Dissection of the subcutaneous tissue within the umbilicus and its deep connection to preperitoneal fat through the linea alba. Excision of the umbilical complex containig pilonisal cyst 3 mm below the umbilical ostium.
Approximation of the subcutaneous tissue with a single purse-string absorbable suture. The specimen, including the umbilical complex (pilonidal cyst, and involved skin and subcutaneos tissue), was transferred to department of pathology for histopathological examination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conservative</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Conservative treatment described as follow:
Under local anesthesia, extracting all protruding hair, and curetting the granulation tissue and pilonidal cyst deep in the umbilicus.
postoperative management include antibiotic treatment with ampicilline plus sulbactam and ornidazole, shaving surrounding skin, washing twice daily, and keeping umbilicus dry.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>modified umbilectomy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgery</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>umbilectomy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>conservative</intervention_name>
    <description>this treatment will include conservative procedures under local anesthesia for patient comfort.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conservative</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>non-surgical management</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  all patients willing to participate to the study with the diagnosis of umbilical
             pilonidal sinus

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  no informed consent

          -  serious coagulation abnormalities

          -  known allergy to local anesthetics

          -  pregnancy, or women who refused contraception at the time of treatment

          -  other concomitant umbilical pathologies such as umbilical hernia, granuloma, dermoid
             cyst

          -  the patients who diagnosed with urachal and omphalomesenteric anomalies through
             radiological investigation

          -  patients who underwent umbilical operation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mehmet KAPLAN, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical Park Gaziantep Hospital, Gaziantep, Turkey</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Park Gaziantep Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gaziantep</city>
        <zip>27090</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dr.Ersin Arslan State Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gaziantep</city>
        <zip>27100</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Şehitkamil State Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gaziantep</city>
        <zip>27100</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hatem Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gaziantep</city>
        <zip>27090</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>25 Aralık Familiy Physician Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gaziantep</city>
        <zip>27100</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.medicalpark.com.tr</url>
    <description>main study center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 9, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 8, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical Park Gaziantep Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mehmet Kaplan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Umbilical pilonidal sinus</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Conservative</keyword>
  <keyword>Investigational treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>After care</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Granuloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pilonidal Sinus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
