<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="78927">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01905046</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A211102</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA031946</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00995</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01905046</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Metformin Hydrochloride in Patients With Atypical Hyperplasia or In Situ Breast Cancer to Placebo in Decreasing Atypical Cells in Patients With Atypical Hyperplasia or in Situ Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Testing for Atypia in Random Periareolar Fine Needle Aspiration (RPFNA) Cytology After 12 Months Metformin (1,1-Dimethylbiguanide Hydrochloride) Chemoprevention Versus Placebo Control in Premenopausal Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alliance for Clinical Trials in Oncology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alliance for Clinical Trials in Oncology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized phase III trial studies metformin hydrochloride to see how well it works
      compared to placebo in decreasing atypical cells in patients with atypical hyperplasia or in
      situ breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment groups. Patients will receive metformin
      hydrochloride 850 mg by mouth (PO) twice daily (BID) for 24 months on Arm I, which includes
      a 4-week ramp up of 850 mg PO QD. Patients will receive placebo 850 mg PO BID for 12 months
      on Arm II, which includes a 4-week ramp up of 850 mg PO QD. Patients initially randomized to
      the placebo (Arm II) may crossover to the metformin hydrochloride treatment group (Arm I)
      for months 13-24.  The primary and secondary objectives are described below.

      Primary Objective:

      • Test for the presence or absence of cytological atypia in random periareolar fine needle
      aspiration (RPFNA) bilateral aspirates for women receiving metformin versus placebo control.

      Secondary Objectives:

        -  Use the Masood Cytology Index Score to test for the presence of cytological atypia or
           disappearance of cytological atypia in RPFNA bilateral aspirates.

        -  Compare Masood Cytology Score values in the right and left breasts from the same
           individual in the metformin and placebo groups.

        -  Test the reproducibility of reverse phase protein microarray (RPPM) in duplicate RPPM
           determinations from individual RPFNA specimens.

        -  Correlate baseline RPPM values with presence of atypia (as measured by Masood Cytology
           Index Score).

        -  Determine the change in percent breast density.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Test for the presence or absence of atypia in RPFNA after 12 months and 24 months. Month 24 is optional for the placebo group for those patients who remain on the placebo arm and will not receive metformin (Metformin versus placebo control).</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Test for the Masood Score and the presence of atypia or disapperance of atypia in RPFNA after 12 months (for both arms) and 24 months for Metformin arm.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Test the reproducibility of RPPM in duplicate RPPM determination from single bilateral RPFNA specimen.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the change in percent breast density from prior to the initiation of metformin or placebo treatment through therapy (ie, Months 12 and 24) and following therapy (Months 36 and 48).</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 48 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare Masood Cytology Score value at 0, 12 and 24 months in right and left breast from the same individual in the metformin and non-metformin group.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlate baseline RPPM values with presence of atypia at Month 12 and Month 24.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Atypical Ductal Breast Hyperplasia</condition>
  <condition>BRCA1 Mutation Carrier</condition>
  <condition>BRCA2 Mutation Carrier</condition>
  <condition>Ductal Breast Carcinoma in Situ</condition>
  <condition>Lobular Breast Carcinoma in Situ</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I: metformin hydrochloride</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive metformin hydrochloride tablet 850 mg PO BID for 24 months on Arm I, which includes a 4-week ramp up of 850 mg PO QD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II: placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive placebo tablet PO QD BID for 12 months which includes a 4-week ramp up of 850 mg PO QD. Patients initially randomized to the placebo group (Arm II) may crossover to the metformin group (Arm I) for months 13-24.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>metformin hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I: metformin hydrochloride</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>1,1 - dimethylbiguanide hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>657-24-9</other_name>
    <other_name>N, N - dimethylimidodicarbonimidic diamide monohydrochloride</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II: placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PLCB</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Pre-Registration Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Must be at increased risk for breast cancer, defined as at least one of the following
             four criteria: 

               -  Having had a prior biopsy demonstrating atypical hyperplasia, lobular carcinoma
                  in situ (LCIS), or ductal carcinoma in situ (DCIS) 

               -  A Gail Model Risk of  ≥1.66% over 5 years 

               -  A strong family history of breast and/or ovarian cancer as defined in the study
                  protocol.

               -  Known breast cancer (BRCA)1 or BRCA2 mutation carrier providing that the woman
                  has:  

                    -  Met with a genetic counselor to review genetic testing results, and  

                    -  Has been offered the opportunity to undergo prophylactic mastectomy and
                       oophorectomy

          2. Pre-menopausal women as defined as four menstrual cycles within the last six months
             prior to pre-registration. Women with less than 4 menses within 6 months prior to
             pre-registration or women who have had a hysterectomy with ovaries intact will be
             considered premenopausal if follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) level is &lt; 20. Women
             who are using hormonal contraceptives that cause amenorrhea (e.g. injectable and
             extended oral contraceptives, Hormone-containing contraceptive ring, or
             hormone-containing intrauterine device) will be considered eligible if they had a
             minimum of 4 menstrual cycles within the last six months prior to starting on the
             contraceptive.

          3. Digital mammogram within 180 days prior to pre-registration.

          4. Mammographic density ≥ 25% or mammogram evaluated by a radiologist as scattered fibro
             glandular density.

          5. Mammograms must be read as not suspicious for breast cancer (American College of
             Rheumatology [ACR] class I-III). Subjects with a class IV mammogram may be enrolled
             once they have been evaluated by a breast surgeon and there is no evidence of
             invasive malignancy.

          6. Must be non-pregnant and non-lactating for at least one year prior to
             pre-registration.

          7. If currently menstruating, subjects must use a reliable method of birth control.

          8. Willing to provide RPFNA and blood samples for correlative research purposes.

          9. Women with core biopsy or excisional biopsy containing DCIS, LCIS or atypia are
             eligible for this study.

         10. Women eligible to take tamoxifen must be offered tamoxifen prevention as part of
             their clinical care and have refused tamoxifen treatment.

         11. Age 25-55 years.

        Pre-registration Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Other active malignancy ≤ 5 years prior to pre-registration. EXCEPTIONS:
             Non-melanotic skin cancer or carcinoma-in-situ of the cervix. NOTE: If there is a
             history of prior malignancy, they must not be receiving other specific treatment,
             i.e., other hormonal therapy, for their cancer.

          2. Body mass index (BMI) &lt; 25.

          3. Receiving warfarin.

          4. Bilateral breast implants or autologous breast flap reconstruction.

          5. Active diagnosis of alcoholism.

          6. Contraindication to metformin prevention such as acute hypersensitivity or allergic
             reaction to metformin.

          7. Receiving tamoxifen or raloxifene.

          8. Administration of any investigational agent ≤ 30 days prior to pre-registration.

          9. Radiation to both breasts.

         10. Co-morbid systemic illnesses or other severe concurrent disease which, in the
             judgment of the investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for entry into
             this study or interfere significantly with the proper assessment of safety and
             toxicity of the prescribed regimens.

         11. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

         12. Receiving pyrimethamine, cimetidine, rifampin or cephalexin.

         13. Women who have a core biopsy or excisional biopsy containing invasive cancer.

        Registration/Randomization Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Qualifying cytological atypia in RPFNA, Masood score of 14-17.

          2. Required laboratory values obtained no more than 30 days prior to
             registration/randomization.

               1. Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL.

               2. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1500/mm^3.

               3. Platelet count ≥ 75,000/mm^3.

               4. Creatinine ≤ 1.5 mg/dL or creatinine clearance (CrCl) &gt;= 30 mL/min.

               5. Total bilirubin ≤ 3.0 mg/dL.

               6. Aspartate trasaminase (AST) ≤ 3 x upper limit of normal (ULN).

               7. Alanine transaminase (ALT) ≤ 3 x ULN.

          3. Negative pregnancy test done ≤ 7 days prior to registration /randomization, for women
             of childbearing potential only.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Victoria Seewaldt, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University School of Medicine - Department of Pharmacology and Cancer Biology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 18, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 16, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma in Situ</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Intraductal, Noninfiltrating</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Ductal, Breast</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Lobular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
