<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="161295">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01709695</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCO 09-1825</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HSM:10-00415</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01709695</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurobiological Basis of Response to Guanfacine Extended Release in Children and Adolescents With ADHD</brief_title>
  <official_title>Neurobiological Basis of Response to Guanfacine Extended Release in Children and Adolescents With Attention-deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD): an Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging(fMRI) Study of Brain Activation Pre and Post Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study proposes to evaluate the effects of guanfacine extended release on brain
      activation during fMRI in children and adolescents with ADHD between the ages 8-15 and ADHD
      subjects randomized to placebo treatment.

      This study also proposes to collect DNA on study participants, to examine the genetic
      underpinning of the observed fMRI activation profiles at baseline and in response to
      treatment. The purpose is to examine polymorphisms of the adrenergic 2A gene (and other
      related targets) for genetic biomarkers in association with the fMRI findings of this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study proposes to evaluate the effects of guanfacine on brain activation during fMRI in
      12 children and adolescents ages 8 - 15 with ADHD treated with once-daily INTUNIV(TM)
      (guanfacine; GXR) extended release tablets and 12 ADHD subjects randomized to placebo
      treatment. Children will be comprehensively assessed using a variety of clinical and
      neuropsychological measures. They will be scanned at baseline while performing both the
      go/no-go task (a well validated task for measuring inhibitory control (Durston et al., 2002,
      2003)) and the Stay Alert task - a new task designed to measure the arousal component of
      attention, which was used successfully in a recent fMRI study of guanfacine in healthy
      adults (Clerkin et al., 2009). They will then be treated with GXR or placebo for 6 - 8 weeks
      in accordance with titration and dosing strategies used in recent Phase III dose
      optimization trials (e.g., up to 4 mg/day), and re-scanned while performing the same two
      tasks. The fMRI scans will be conducted using a dedicated research 3.0 T Siemens scanner.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacodynamics Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fMRI activation from pre to post treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>At screening and at 6-8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in fMRI activation from pre to post treatment in medication treated subjects in comparison to placebo treated subjects who are scanned while performing a go/no-go task.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impressions</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Physician rated scales of overall clinical impairment (CGI-O), severity of clinical impairment (CGI-S), and clinical improvement (CGI-I)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Atomoxetine Stimulant Side Effects Rating Scale (ASSERS)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Side effects rating scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychological assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Neuropsychological assessments: Digit Span, Finger Windows, Continuous Performance Test, Attentional Network Task (ANT), and fMRI behavioral task data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder Rating Scale IV (ADHDRS IV)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Norm referenced parent interview to assess severity and frequency of ADHD symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>ADHD</condition>
  <condition>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>guanfacine hydrochloride XR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Flexible dose titration of guanfacine extended release (Intuniv; active medication). The medication is titrated in doses from 1 - 4 mg once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Flexible dose titration of placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Guanfacine Hydrochloride XR</intervention_name>
    <description>Weekly adjustments based on parent ratings of symptoms, side effects, and health status per vital signs up to 4mg maximum dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>guanfacine hydrochloride XR</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>INTUNIV non-stimulant medication</other_name>
    <other_name>GXR</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Weekly adjustments based on parent ratings of symptoms, side effects, and health status per vital signs up to 4mg maximum dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of any subtype of ADHD

          -  Normal findings on physical exam, laboratory studies, vital signs, and ECG

          -  Weight = 60 kgs or less

          -  Able to complete study procedures and swallow capsules;

          -  Willing to commit to the entire visit schedule

          -  Off treatment or have been discontinued from their previous medication for two weeks.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Psychiatric comorbidity except Oppositional Defiant Disorder [ODD], Simple Phobia,
             and dysthymia (unless ongoing medication treatment is required);

          -  Currently a suicide risk, has previously made a suicide attempt or has a prior
             history of suicidal behavior;

          -  Has failed treatment with an adequate trial of an alpha-2 adrenergic agonist;

          -  Known or suspected allergy, hypersensitivity, or clinically significant intolerance
             to guanfacine hydrochloride.

        Children may not:

          -  be treated with systemic medication for a medical or psychiatric illness that have
             CNS effects or affect cognitive function;

          -  have a known history or presence of structural cardiac abnormalities,
             exercise-related cardiac events, or clinically significant bradycardia;

          -  have orthostatic hypotension or a known history of hypertension;

          -  have an abnormal ECG that is deemed clinically significant;

          -  have a history of alcohol or other substance abuse or dependence within the last 6
             months;

          -  use any medications that affect BP or heart rate (excluding the subject's current
             ADHD medication at screening);

          -  use another investigational medicinal product or participation in a clinical study
             within 30 days prior to the baseline visit;

          -  be significantly overweight based on Center for Disease Control and Prevention Body
             Mass Index (BMI)-for-age gender specific charts;

          -  have body weight of less than 25kg;

          -  have a clinically important abnormality on urine drug and alcohol screen (excluding
             the subject's current ADHD stimulant, if applicable);

          -  be female and currently pregnant or lactating;

          -  have symptoms indicative of a primary sleep disorder.

          -  have braces or other metal permanently placed within their body.

          -  be too anxious to tolerate the fMRI procedure, or be claustrophobic.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>15 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Newcorn, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Beth Krone, MS</last_name>
    <phone>212-241-8012</phone>
    <email>beth.krone@mssm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Beth Krone, MS</last_name>
      <phone>212-241-8012</phone>
      <email>beth.krone@mssm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Newcorn, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 22, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 30, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jeffrey Newcorn</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intuniv</keyword>
  <keyword>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>fMRI</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Guanfacine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
