<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="157899">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01664793</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1 U01 IP000321-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01664793</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>From Innovation to Solutions: Childhood Influenza Vaccination Planning</brief_title>
  <official_title>From Innovation to Solutions: Autodialers, Use of Early Autumn Physicals and Vaccination Assessment as a Vital Sign to Increase Childhood Influenza Vaccination in Diverse Settings</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States:  University of Pittsburgh Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to increase childhood influenza vaccination rates using the FDA
      licensed vaccine according to national guidelines in a cluster randomized study in which
      offices are randomized to intervention or control with the control set becoming the
      intervention sites in Year 2.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will conduct a stratified, randomized cluster trial of 20 diverse
      practices to compare vaccination rates in intervention and control sites. Intervention sites
      will use a package of newly developed and evidence-based techniques that will be tailored to
      their practice structure and culture, called 4 Pillars Toolkit, in addition to early season
      vaccination. Usual care practices will not receive such assistance.

      In the second year, the 10 control practices from the first year will become intervention
      sites using 4 Pillars toolkit of packaged evidence-based techniques that were used in the
      intervention sites the previous year, in addition to early season vaccination.  A new set of
      controls will be obtained for Year 2, for comparative purposes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The main outcome variable is vaccination rates for each of the sites</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary outcomes to be measured</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately up to three years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Missed opportunities for vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary outcomes to be measured</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately up to three years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vaccination rates by demographic characteristics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary outcomes to be measured</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately up to three years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Acceptability and perceived usefulness of the online training program. This will be measured through an online survey to be completed by those who complete the online training program. This voluntary online training program will be sent to every office engaged in the intervention and will be distributed via the office manager to all clinical and non-clinical staff.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary outcomes to be measured</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately up to three years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinic specific fidelity to the 4 pillars toolkit. Fidelity of implementation will be assessed by using a modified Delphi technique. The investigators will be asked to distribute 100 points across the identified measures which will be averaged to create a fidelity point system. This fidelity point system will then by used to weight those survey questions (that each intervention clinic's head doctor and nurse/practice manager will complete at the end of the season)that assess measures of the intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary outcomes to be measured</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately up to three years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Types of interventions used</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary outcomes to be measured</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately up to three years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Perceptions of intervention usefulness. This will be measured by an online survey of the head physician and nurse/office manager and through end of the season site debrief sessions lead by the Co-Investigator and conducted with all clinic staff.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza Vaccination Rates</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group Year 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>10 diverse pediatric and family medicine based clinic sites - Intervention sites will use a package of newly developed techniques and evidence-based techniques called the 4 Pillars toolkit along with early season vaccination..</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group Year 1 &amp; Intention Group Year 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>10 diverse pediatric and family based clinics - Control sites will not receive assistance with increasing influenza vaccination in Year 1, they will follow guidelines for usual care.  In Year 2, they will receive the 4 Pillars Toolkit and early season vaccination</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group Year 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Control group of family medicine and pediatric practices for Year 2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>4 Pillars Toolkit for increasing childhood influenza vaccination rates</intervention_name>
    <description>Pillar 1 Convenient Vaccination Services:
Extend Vaccination Season:  Use August &amp; September physicals; extend the season beyond January Express Vaccination Services:  Influenza vaccination clinics, Open access vaccine scheduling, or Dedicated vaccination station
Pillar 2:  Patient notification about the importance of vaccination and availability of convenient services Notify when convenient services are available by email, autodialer , &quot;On-hold&quot; messages, social media
Pillar 3  Enhanced Office Systems Assessment of influenza vaccination by staff routinely: EMR prompts, review  Immunization tab, or check as part of vital signs Empower staff to vaccinate by standing orders programs,  per protocol without the need for an individual physician order.
Order a sufficient supply
Pillar 4:  Motivation: Office immunization champion tracks progress towards a goal Set a goal that is a 20% to 25% increase, Monitor and share progress weekly (doses given) Encourage competition</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group Year 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Practice staff and children in 20 diverse pediatric and family medicine clinical sites
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  For health care workers: health care worker at the selected sites - includes all
             members of the staff at participating practices.

        For children: attendance at the selected health care center within the last year and age
        &gt;/=6 months thru 18 years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  For health care workers: none.

        For children: Severe egg allergy or allergy to influenza vaccine
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Zimmerman, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh, School of Medicine, Department of Family Medicine and Clinical Epidemiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chyongchiou Lin, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh, School of Medicine, Deparment of Family Medicine and Clinical Epidemiology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.immunizationed.org/PracticeImprovement/</url>
    <description>Childhood Influenza Vaccination Study Toolkit</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 10, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 2, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Richard Zimmerman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>influenza</keyword>
  <keyword>vaccination</keyword>
  <keyword>strategies</keyword>
  <keyword>children/adolescents</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
