<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="55170">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01689532</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR100876</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CNTO136ARA3001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01689532</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of CNTO 136 (Sirukumab) Administered Subcutaneously in Japanese Patients With Active Rheumatoid Arthritis Unresponsive to Methotrexate or Sulfasalazine</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Randomized, Double-blind, Parallel Group Study of CNTO 136 (Sirukumab), a Human Anti-IL-6 Monoclonal Antibody, Administered Subcutaneously as Monotherapy, in Japanese Subjects With Active Rheumatoid Arthritis Unresponsive to Methotrexate or Sulfasalazine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen Pharmaceutical K.K.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline, PLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen Pharmaceutical K.K.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Pharmaceuticals and Medical Devices Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of sirukumab as a single
      therapy in Japanese patients with moderately to severely active rheumatoid arthritis (RA)
      who have not responded to treatment with methotrexate (MTX) or sulfasalazine (SSZ).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized (patients will be assigned to treatment by chance), double-blind (study
      personnel and patients will not know what treatments are being given), multicenter study.
      The expected duration of the study is 68 weeks. This will include 52 weeks of treatment with
      study agent with dosing every 2 weeks and 16 weeks of safety follow-up after the last dose.
      Disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs (DMARDs), including MTX and SSZ, are not permitted
      from 4 weeks before the first dosing with study agent until Week 24. The use of DMARDs is
      discouraged at or any time after Week 24; however, patients who have less than 20%
      improvement from baseline in both swollen and tender joint counts at Week 24 will be allowed
      to take DMARDs. At or any time after Week 16, the initiation and/or adjustment of oral
      corticosteroids will be allowed for patients who have less than 20% improvement from
      baseline in both swollen and tender joint counts at Week 16.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of patients with adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neutrophil count</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Platelet count</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hepatobiliary laboratory abnormalities</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Lipid parameter abnormalities</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of patients who achieve ACR 20 response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>American College of Rheumatology (ACR) 20 response is at least a 20% improvement in rheumatoid arthritis (RA) symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of patients who achieve ACR 50 response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>ACR 50 response is at least a 50% improvement in RA symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of patients who achieve ACR 70 response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>ACR 70 response is at least a 70% improvement in RA symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of patients who achieve ACR 90 response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>ACR 90 response is at least a 90% improvement in RA symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major clinical response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Major clinical response is achieving ACR 70 for 6 continuous months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent improvement from baseline in ACR components</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of patients with DAS28 (CRP) response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Disease Activity Index (DAS28, using CRP [C-reactive protein]) is a measure of tender and swollen joints (28 joints each) and the patient's assessments of disease activity. A score of higher than 5.1 indicates high disease activity, and a score below 3.2 indicates low disease activity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of patients with DAS28 (CRP) remission</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>DAS28 (CRP) remission is defined as a value of &lt;2.6 at a visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in DAS28 (CRP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of patients with SDAI-based ACR/EULAR remission</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Simplified Disease Activity Index (SDAI) is a derived score combining tender joints (28 joints), swollen joints (28 joints), Patient's Global Assessment of Disease Activity (GH), Physician's global assessments of disease activity (PGH), and CRP. SDAI-based ACR/EULAR remission is defined as a SDAI value of ≤ 3.3 at the visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of patients with Boolean-based ACR/EULAR remission</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Boolean-based ACR/EULAR remission is defined as meeting all of the following 4 criteria at a visit: Tender joint count (68 joints) ≤ 1; Swollen joint count (68 joints) ≤ 1; CRP ≤ 1 mg/dL; Patient's Global Assessment of Disease Activity on VAS ≤ 1 on a 0 to 10 scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in SDAI</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in CDAI</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Clinical Disease Activity Index (CDAI) score is a derived score combining tender joints (28 joints), swollen joints (28 joints), GH, and PGH. Scores range from 0 (remission) to 76 (high activity).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in HAQ-DI score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Health Assessment Questionnaire - Disability Index (HAQ-DI) assesses the degree of difficulty a person has in accomplishing tasks in 8 functional areas (dressing, arising, eating, walking, hygiene, reaching, gripping, and activities of daily living). Responses in each functional area are scored from 0, indicating no difficulty, to 3, indicating inability to perform a task in that area.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC of change from baseline in HAQ-DI score from Week 0 through Week 24 and from Week 0 through Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 52 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>AUC is &quot;area under the curve,&quot; an assessment of blood concentration of study agent over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of HAQ-DI responders (ie, those who have a change from baseline of &gt; 0.22 in HAQ-DI score)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of HAQ-DI responders in sirukumab treatment groups who maintain a change from baseline of &gt; 0.22 in HAQ-DI score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in duration of morning stiffness</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in physical and mental component scores and in domain scores of SF-36</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>36-Item Short Form Questionnaire (SF-36) is 8 multi-item scales that are scored from 0 to 100 with higher scores indicating better health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in EQ VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The EuroQoL Group visual analogue scale (EQ VAS) is a self-rated health assessment. Scores range from 0 (worst health imaginable) to 100 (best health imaginable).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in EQ-5D index</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The EQ-5D is a standardized measure of health status with 3 levels: 1=no problems, 2=some problems, and 3=extreme problems.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">122</enrollment>
  <condition>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sirukumab 100 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sirukumab 50 mg and Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sirukumab 100 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Sirukumab 100 mg subcutaneous (SC) injection, at Weeks 0, 2, and every 2 weeks through Week 52.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sirukumab 100 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sirukumab 50 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Sirukumab 50 mg SC at Weeks 0, 4, and every 4 weeks through Week 52.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sirukumab 50 mg and Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Between sirukumab injections, placebo SC at Weeks 2, 6, and every 4 weeks through Week 52.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sirukumab 50 mg and Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Be a Japanese man or woman with a diagnosis of rheumatoid arthritis (RA), according
             to the revised 1987 criteria of the American Rheumatism Association, for at least 3
             months before screening

          -  Has moderately to severely active RA with at least 6 of 68 tender joints and 6 of 66
             swollen joints, at screening and at baseline

          -  Has been unresponsive to adequate treatment with methotrexate (MTX), sulfasalazine
             (SSZ), or combination of MTX or SSZ with other disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs
             (DMARDs) at screening due to lack of benefit after at least 12 weeks of marketed dose
             of MTX or SSZ, as assessed by the treating physician. Documented lack of benefit may
             include inadequate improvement in joint counts, physical function, or overall disease
             activity

          -  If using oral corticosteroids, must be on a stable dose equivalent to &lt;=10 mg/day of
             prednisolone for at least 2 weeks prior to first dosing with study agent. If
             currently not using corticosteroids, the patient must not have received oral
             corticosteroids (by mouth) for at least 2 weeks prior to first dosing with study
             agent

          -  If using nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) or other analgesics (pain
             relievers) for RA, must be on a stable dose for at least 2 weeks prior to first
             dosing with study agent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has a history of intolerance to at least 2 or inadequate response to at least one
             anti-tumor necrosis factor-alpha (anti-TNF-alpha) agent after 3 months of therapy;
             has received anti-TNF-alpha (eg, infliximab, golimumab, adalimumab, or etanercept)
             within 3 months of first study agent dosing

          -  Has a history of intolerance to tocilizumab that precluded further treatment with it,
             or inadequate response to 3 months of tocilizumab (anti-IL-6 receptor) therapy; has
             used B-cell-depleting therapy (eg, rituximab) within 7 months of first study agent
             dosing  or has evidence during screening of abnormally low B-cell level caused by
             previous B-cell depletion therapy; has used any other biologic therapy for the
             treatment of RA within 3 months of first study agent dosing; has a history of
             sirukumab use

          -  Has received intra-articular (IA), intramuscular (IM), or intravenous (IV)
             corticosteroids for RA, including adrenocorticotrophic hormone during the 4 weeks
             prior to first study agent dosing

          -  Has received leflunomide within 24 months before first study agent dosing and has not
             undergone a drug elimination procedure, unless the M1 metabolite is measured and is
             undetectable. Drug elimination procedure must be completed prior to obtaining
             informed consent

          -  Has a history of cyclophosphamide or cytotoxic agent use; has received cyclosporine
             A, azathioprine, tacrolimus, mycophenolate mofetil, oral or parenteral gold, or
             D-penicillamine within 4 weeks of first study agent dosing; has received an
             investigational drug (including investigational vaccines) or used an investigational
             medical device within 3 months or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer, before first
             study agent dosing
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen Pharmaceutical K.K., Japan Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen Pharmaceutical K.K.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Asahikawa</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuoka</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Hiroshima</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Hitachinaka</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kagoshima</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kirishima</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kitakyushu</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kobe</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kumamoto</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Matsumoto</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Miyagi</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Oita</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Sapporo</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Sendai</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Shinjuku</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Shizuoka</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Yokohama</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 18, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Active Rheumatoid Arthritis Unresponsive to Methotrexate or Sulfasalazine</keyword>
  <keyword>Sirukumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Human Anti-IL-6 Monoclonal Antibody</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sulfasalazine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
