<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="99323">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02145858</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CL2014001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02145858</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevention of Retained-Blood Outcomes With Active Clearance Technology</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prevention of Retained-Blood Outcomes With Active Clearance Technology. ACT Registry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ClearFlow, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Vanderbilt University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ClearFlow, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Postoperative bleeding is a common consequence after heart surgery which can significantly
      impact outcomes and costs [Wynne R, Christensen MC, Dixon B]. When bleeding occurs, reliable
      postoperative blood evacuation of the pleural, mediastinal and pericardial spaces with chest
      tubes is imperative to facilitate pulmonary reexpansion and mediastinal decompression as the
      patient recovers. When post operative blood evacuation is inadequate, retained blood
      complications can result (herein described as the Retained Blood Complications (RBC). RBC is
      the presence of post-operative pericardial and/or pleural fluid or blood that is diagnosed
      and may necessitate drainage in the acute or subacute setting. The need for treatment and
      interventions for these conditions represents an impediment to patient recovery and involves
      both resource and economic consumption for a heart program and the healthcare system at
      large.  Clinically, Retained Blood Complications (RBC) can be recognized  acutely or
      subacutely. When it presents acutely, it is usually fresh thrombus around the heart or lungs
      presenting as tamponade or hemothorax.  When it presents subacutely, it results in bloody
      pleural or pericardial effusions [Light RW, Light RW, Light RW, Ikaheimo MJ]. These
      effusions are often driven by the breakdown of remaining thrombus. Once RBC occurs,
      subsequent procedures may be needed to remedy it.  A recent review of the literature
      indicated that additional procedures for RBC are demonstrated in approximately 15% to 20% of
      patients after heart surgery. In a prospectively collected United States Nationwide
      Inpatient Sample (NIS) data from 2010, RBC could be demonstrated in 17% of patients.  In
      this analysis, mortality was doubled from 4% to 8%, length of stay was increased by 5 days,
      and average costs were 55% higher.  Patients with RBC, therefore, represent an increased at
      risk population for complications and costs.

      Postoperative obstruction of conventional chest tubes with blood and other fibrinous
      material in the setting of postoperative bleeding contributes to RBC.(Shalli) In a recent
      study of postoperative cardiac surgery patients at the Cleveland Clinic, 36% of patients
      were found to have evidence of chest tube obstruction [Karimov JH].  Active Clearance with
      PleuraFlow has been shown to prevent chest tube clogging, and reduce RBC. (Shiose, Arakawa,
      Perrault) The purpose of this registry is to evaluate the effectiveness of PleuraFlow
      System, a commercial Class II (US), Class IIb (Canada, Europe, and Australia), in the
      management of blood evacuation after cardiac surgery. Additionally, the purpose is to
      educate about the incidence of complications and post-surgical interventions consistent with
      Retained Blood Complications (RBC) after adult cardiac surgery. The purpose of this registry
      is also to collect post-market surveillance data on PleuraFlow ACT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective multicenter observational registry with a retrospective component.
      The registry has two tracks. One track--ALL-ACT-- is for sites enrolling a consecutive
      cohort of all cardiac surgery patients (Track A). The second track--VAD-ACT-- is for sites
      enrolling patients post ventricular assist device (VAD) surgery (Track B). There are two
      conditions for participation in this registry:

      First, sites are required to enter into the registry database anonymized matched historical
      data elements from a cohort of cardiac surgery patients done over the preceding 12 to
      24-month period (Phase 0). These retrospective data elements will be used as baseline
      information for the purpose of comparative analyses with the prospective data sets collected
      during the prospective enrollment phase.

      Second, sites are required to participate in a roll-in phase (Phase 1).  The purposes of the
      roll-in phase are to allow the users at participating sites to familiarize themselves with
      the product use and with ACT.  To implement clinical use protocols provided by ClearFlow,
      Inc. to all commercial users as part of product training, and; to demonstrate consistency
      and compliance with the clinical use protocols.

      Phase 0 and phase 1 can be executed in parallel. Participating sites may start prospective
      enrollment (Phase 2) after completion of phase 0 and 1.

      Investigators shall report PleuraFlow-related serious injuries to Sponsor as soon as
      becoming aware of the injury and no later than 48 hours.

      Investigators shall report deaths to both the Sponsor and Regulatory authorities in
      compliance with their applicable State, Country and conditions imposed by the reviewing
      Ethical Committee. The three main guidance documents for reporting recall and vigilance
      procedure of medical devices are, 21 CFR, Part 806, MEDDEV 2.12/1 rev8 Guidelines on a
      Medical Devices Vigilance System, and Health Canada Medical Device Regulations SOR/98-282.

      Vanderbilt University will create a REDCap database specific to this study and administer
      it.  The Vanderbilt database study administrator will control database access, oversee data
      entry and data transfer from each participating site. Database manager will monitor the
      REDCap database and ensure data completeness and security.  The database manager will
      maintain contact will the data entry personnel from each site and ensure whether data
      capture is occurring and determine the number of patients expected to be enrolled in the
      Registry at the end of the study period. Sponsor will not have access to REDCap once the
      study is complete. The REDCap database is secure and HIPAA compliant.

      Descriptive statistics for categorical variables will be reported as percentages, and
      continuous variables will be reported as mean ± standard deviation (SD).  Categorical
      variables will be compared using the chi-square test.  Continuous variables will be compared
      using a Student's t-test as appropriate.

      Database study administrator will coordinate the generation of data reports and statistical
      outputs. Sponsor will not have access to REDCap once the study is complete.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>1 Month</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Retained Blood Complications (RBC)</measure>
    <time_frame>surgery to post-operative 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The incidence of RBC as defined by a composite endpoint of specific interventions and diagnoses.  Any patient that has a record of any of the following interventions or diagnosis post-operative including post discharge has RBC.
Interventions
Reoperation for bleeding, tamponade or washout of retained blood
Pericardial window
Chest tube placement/replacement
Pericardiocentesis
Placement of pericardial drain
Thoracotomy
Thoracoscopy
Thoracentesis
Diagnoses
Pleural effusion
Pericardial effusion
Hemothorax
Pneumothorax
Pericardial tamponade</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <condition>Hemorrhage, Postoperative</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood drainage post cardiac surgery using PleuraFlow System</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects 18 years or older who received a PleuraFlow System following heart surgery (Track
        A) or VAD surgery (Track B)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or Female subjects 18 years or older who received a PleuraFlow System following
             heart surgery (Track A) or VAD surgery (Track B)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any condition deemed inappropriate for inclusion by the investigators.

          -  Infants, children and adolescents under the age of 18.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Simon Maltais, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Vanderbilt Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232-8802</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mary E Davis, MS</last_name>
      <phone>615-343-9195</phone>
      <email>mary.beth.davis@Vanderbilt.Edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Simon Maltais, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wynne R, Botti M, Copley D, Bailey M. The normative distribution of chest tube drainage volume after coronary artery bypass grafting. Heart Lung. 2007 Jan-Feb;36(1):35-42. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>17234475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Christensen MC, Dziewior F, Kempel A, von Heymann C. Increased chest tube drainage is independently associated with adverse outcome after cardiac surgery. J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth. 2012 Feb;26(1):46-51. doi: 10.1053/j.jvca.2011.09.021. Epub 2011 Nov 18. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>22100857</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dixon B, Santamaria JD, Reid D, Collins M, Rechnitzer T, Newcomb AE, Nixon I, Yii M, Rosalion A, Campbell DJ. The association of blood transfusion with mortality after cardiac surgery: cause or confounding? (CME). Transfusion. 2013 Jan;53(1):19-27. doi: 10.1111/j.1537-2995.2012.03697.x. Epub 2012 May 11. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>22574710</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Light RW. Pleural effusions following cardiac injury and coronary artery bypass graft surgery. Semin Respir Crit Care Med. 2001 Dec;22(6):657-64. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>16088710</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Light RW. Pleural effusions after coronary artery bypass graft surgery. Curr Opin Pulm Med. 2002 Jul;8(4):308-11. Review. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>12055394</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Light RW, Rogers JT, Cheng D, Rodriguez RM. Large pleural effusions occurring after coronary artery bypass grafting. Cardiovascular Surgery Associates, PC. Ann Intern Med. 1999 Jun 1;130(11):891-6. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>10375337</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Light RW, Rogers JT, Moyers JP, Lee YC, Rodriguez RM, Alford WC Jr, Ball SK, Burrus GR, Coltharp WH, Glassford DM Jr, Hoff SJ, Lea JW 4th, Nesbitt JC, Petracek MR, Starkey TD, Stoney WS, Tedder M. Prevalence and clinical course of pleural effusions at 30 days after coronary artery and cardiac surgery. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2002 Dec 15;166(12 Pt 1):1567-71. Epub 2002 Oct 11. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>12406850</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ikäheimo MJ, Huikuri HV, Airaksinen KE, Korhonen UR, Linnaluoto MK, Tarkka MR, Takkunen JT. Pericardial effusion after cardiac surgery: incidence, relation to the type of surgery, antithrombotic therapy, and early coronary bypass graft patency. Am Heart J. 1988 Jul;116(1 Pt 1):97-102. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>3260740</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karimov JH, Gillinov AM, Schenck L, Cook M, Kosty Sweeney D, Boyle EM, Fukamachi K. Incidence of chest tube clogging after cardiac surgery: a single-centre prospective observational study. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2013 Dec;44(6):1029-36. doi: 10.1093/ejcts/ezt140. Epub 2013 Mar 21. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>23520232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shalli S, Boyle EM, Saeed D, Fukamachi K, Cohn WE, Gillinov AM. The active tube clearance system: a novel bedside chest-tube clearance device. Innovations (Phila). 2010 Jan;5(1):42-7. doi: 10.1097/IMI.0b013e3181cf7ce3. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>22437275</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shiose A, Takaseya T, Fumoto H, Arakawa Y, Horai T, Boyle EM, Gillinov AM, Fukamachi K. Improved drainage with active chest tube clearance. Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg. 2010 May;10(5):685-8. doi: 10.1510/icvts.2009.229393. Epub 2010 Feb 23. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>20179137</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arakawa Y, Shiose A, Takaseya T, Fumoto H, Kim HI, Boyle EM, Gillinov AM, Fukamachi K. Superior chest drainage with an active tube clearance system: evaluation of a downsized chest tube. Ann Thorac Surg. 2011 Feb;91(2):580-3. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2010.10.018. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>21256318</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perrault LP, Pellerin M, Carrier M, Cartier R, Bouchard D, Demers P, Boyle EM. The PleuraFlow Active Chest Tube Clearance System: initial clinical experience in adult cardiac surgery. Innovations (Phila). 2012 Sep-Oct;7(5):354-8. doi: 10.1097/IMI.0b013e31827e2b4d. PubMed</citation>
    <PMID>23274869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 21, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chest tube, chest drainage, chest tube clogging, retained blood complications, hemothorax, tamponade, heart surgery, pleural effusion, intensive care</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postoperative Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
