<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="35167">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01933620</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130180</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-CC-0180</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01933620</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Human Microbiome in Clinical Center Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Studies of the Human Microbiome in Clinical Center Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - The intestines, mouth, and skin all contain billions of bacteria and some fungi. Every
      person   s body contains microorganisms like these. They normally do not make people sick.
      Researchers are interested in how these microorganisms change when a person is hospitalized.
      They want to find out if changes take place because of the hospitalization (such as
      treatments used or changes in medical condition) or because of a person   s biology (such as
      their immune system).

      Objectives:

      - To understand which microorganisms are most likely to spread through hospitals and what
      affects that spread.

      Eligibility:

      - People over 2 years of age who are going to be inpatients at the National Institutes of
      Health Clinical Center (NIHCC) for at least 1 week.

      Design:

      - Clinicians will take samples from participants up to once a day for as long as they are
      hospitalized at NIHCC.

      &lt; TAB&gt; - Blood will be taken from a needle in the arm. This will be done only once, unless
      the participant gets a certain infection.

        -  Swabs will be taken with a cotton swab, from the rectal area, groin, throat, and
           armpit, and possibly other areas.

        -  Participants may give a stool sample or be asked to spit into a cup.

        -  Clinicians will collect some information from participants    medical records. They may
           request some samples of tissue that are left over from procedures already scheduled at
           NIHCC.

        -  After participants leave the NIHCC, samples may be taken when they return for follow-up
           visits from their hospitalization, for up to 2 years. They will not have to return as a
           follow-up for this study only.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this protocol is to explore changes to microbial communities during the course
      of hospital care, and to determine the extent to which these alterations affect whether
      hospitalized patients become colonized with nosocomial bacteria. The study enables
      collection of clinical specimens and associated medical data to evaluate the natural
      history, epidemiology, and genomics of patients who are expected to be hospitalized for at
      least seven days. Biological specimens including blood, stool, sputum, and swabs will be
      taken from CC inpatients at least 2 years of age as frequently as daily through discharge,
      and at follow-up visits for up to 2 years from the date of enrollment. To understand the
      dynamics of the fecal and other microbiota of hospitalized patients, this protocol will
      assess the full complement of the microbial-host-environmental contributions including: (1)
      microbial genome and community; (2) patient   s genotype, underlying medical condition,
      medical treatment; and (3) hospital practices and environment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary endpoint is to accumulate a sufficiently robust body of intestinal microbiome data and clinical and epidemiological metadata to characterize fully the changes in the human microbiota that occur during the course of hospitalization an...</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Multidrug Resistance</condition>
  <condition>Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</condition>
  <condition>Neutropenia</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Individuals must meet the following inclusion criteria to participate in the study:

          -  Be inpatients in the NIH CC with an expected hospitalization of at least 7 days
             beyond the date of referral.

          -  Be 2 years of age or older

          -  Allow storage of blood and tissue samples for future analyses.

          -  Allow genetic testing of blood, body fluids, and tissue specimens.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        A patient will not be eligible if he/she has any condition which, in the investigator   s
        opinion, places the patient at undue risk by participating in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tara N Palmore, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tara N Palmore, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 594-6818</phone>
    <email>tpalmore@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-CC-0180.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klevens RM, Edwards JR, Richards CL Jr, Horan TC, Gaynes RP, Pollock DA, Cardo DM. Estimating health care-associated infections and deaths in U.S. hospitals, 2002. Public Health Rep. 2007 Mar-Apr;122(2):160-6.</citation>
    <PMID>17357358</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hidron AI, Edwards JR, Patel J, Horan TC, Sievert DM, Pollock DA, Fridkin SK; National Healthcare Safety Network Team; Participating National Healthcare Safety Network Facilities. NHSN annual update: antimicrobial-resistant pathogens associated with healthcare-associated infections: annual summary of data reported to the National Healthcare Safety Network at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 2006-2007. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2008 Nov;29(11):996-1011. doi: 10.1086/591861. Erratum in: Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2009 Jan;30(1):107.</citation>
    <PMID>18947320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonten MJ, Weinstein RA. The role of colonization in the pathogenesis of nosocomial infections. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 1996 Mar;17(3):193-200. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8708364</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multidrug Resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Neutropenia</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neutropenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
