<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="149512">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01696188</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12D.328</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01696188</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study Comparing Two Methods of Placing an Interscalene Nerve Catheter for Postoperative Pain Control in Patients Who Undergo Open Shoulder Surgery.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of In-Plane vs. Out-of-Plane Ultrasound-Guided Approach for Interscalene Nerve Catheters: a Prospective, Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Thomas Jefferson University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Thomas Jefferson University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double-blinded, prospective study designed to compare two approaches
      (in the plane of the ultrasound beam and out of the plane of the ultrasound beam) to placing
      an interscalene nerve block and catheter for pain control after open shoulder surgery. Both
      approaches have been used successfully but neither has been proven to be superior. Our
      endpoints are pain scores, time for block placement, and catheter dislodgements. We
      hypothesized that patients with the out-of-plane approach would have decreased pain and
      fewer catheter dislodgements.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Interscalene nerve block is an effective method of analgesia for surgery of the upper
      extremity. Perineural interscalene catheters offer the advantage of extended pain relief up
      to 48 hours after shoulder surgery. This is a prospective, randomized trial designed to
      compare two approaches (posterior and anterolateral) to interscalene continuous nerve
      catheter placement for analgesia after open shoulder surgery (open rotator cuff repair,
      total shoulder arthroplasty or revision, hemi-arthroplasty, or proximal humerus open
      reduction internal fixation). Specifically, the objectives of this study are to compare
      measured pain scores, opioid consumption, and catheter dislodgements. We hypothesize that
      the anterolateral approach will produce lower pain scores, less opioid consumption, and
      fewer catheter dislodgements.

      All patients undergoing open shoulder surgery will be recruited and enrollment in the study
      will not deviate from the current standard of care at Thomas Jefferson University Hospital.
      All nerve blocks will be placed by a regional anesthesiologist or a fellow in regional
      anesthesia. Patient medical history will be obtained and blocks will be placed per usual
      protocol. Block efficacy will be assessed by physical exam immediately after placement by
      the anesthesiologist and another member of the research team. Operative details, including
      medications given, will be recorded.

      Patient pain scores and medications given in the PACU will be recorded. Supplementary
      analgesics will be available. Pain scores, medications given, and sensory examinations will
      be recorded for 48 hours postoperatively. Data will be analyzed both at the conclusion of
      the study and at several interims before that.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>VAS Pain Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Catheter dislodgements</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Inspect the peripheral nerve catheters at 48 hours postoperatively and assess for being in-place or not.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>opioid consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Calculate the total amount of opioid consumed in the first 48 hours after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>time for block placement</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately post-procedure</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Calculate the time to perform the nerve block procedure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Shoulder Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>In-plane group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive an interscalene catheter placed with in-plane approach.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Out-of-plane group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive an interscalene catheter with an out-of-plan approach.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>interscalene nerve catheter</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>In-plane group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Out-of-plane group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Peripheral nerve catheter kit, B Braun (Bethlehem, PA)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  speaks English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  children,

          -  neuropathy in operative arm
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kishor Gandhi, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>215-955-6161</phone>
      <email>kishor.gandhi@jefferson.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Eric S Schwenk, MD</last_name>
      <phone>215-955-6161</phone>
      <email>eric.schwenk@jefferson.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kishor Gandhi, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fredrickson MJ, Ball CM, Dalgleish AJ. Posterior versus anterolateral approach interscalene catheter placement: a prospective randomized trial. Reg Anesth Pain Med. 2011 Mar-Apr;36(2):125-33.</citation>
    <PMID>21425511</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Antonakakis JG, Sites BD, Shiffrin J. Ultrasound-guided posterior approach for the placement of a continuous interscalene catheter. Reg Anesth Pain Med. 2009 Jan-Feb;34(1):64-8.</citation>
    <PMID>19258990</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mariano ER, Loland VJ, Ilfeld BM. Interscalene perineural catheter placement using an ultrasound-guided posterior approach. Reg Anesth Pain Med. 2009 Jan-Feb;34(1):60-3.</citation>
    <PMID>19258989</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 13, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Interscalene</keyword>
  <keyword>nerve block</keyword>
  <keyword>nerve catheter</keyword>
  <keyword>in-plane</keyword>
  <keyword>out-of-plane</keyword>
  <keyword>anterolateral approach</keyword>
  <keyword>posterior approach</keyword>
  <keyword>shoulder surgery</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Shoulder Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
