<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="151311">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01850589</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01850589</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Conservative and Aggressive Smoking Cessation Treatment Strategies in a Vascular Surgery Office Practice</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Conservative and Aggressive Smoking Cessation Treatment Strategies in a Vascular Surgery Office Practice</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>North Shore Long Island Jewish Health System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>North Shore Long Island Jewish Health System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The use of Bupropion with consulting works better than counseling alone for patients to quit
      smoking. Overall, there was a small percentage of patients who quit smoking all together.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objective of the current investigation is to evaluate the effectiveness of an intensive
      verses conservative smoking cessation program in patients with peripheral arterial disease
      in an outpatient setting.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Use of bupropion with counseling works better to help patients quit smoking.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>March 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A Change in Smoking Cessation Survey Results</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months, 6 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will complete the questionnaire provided to them by the Vascular Surgery attending/fellow during voluntary, free outpatient visits at the Vascular Surgery Office at Staten Island University Hospital.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A Change in Expired Carbon Monoxide (CO) Monitor</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months, 6 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patient's carbon monoxide level will be measured using an expired carbon monoxide monitor during initial visit and at outpatient follow up visits at the Vascular Surgery Office at Staten Island University Hospital. Results will be recorded in each patient's medical record.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking Cessation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conserative Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be counseled by the vascular attending/fellow during their office appointment to stop smoking. Counseling will consist of a self-help materials including &quot;Smart Move: A Stop Smoking Guide&quot; from the American Cancer Society and a brief educational discussion on the benefits of smoking cessation. Patients randomized to Group 1 will be offered adjunctive treatment with nicotine replacement therapy at no cost.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aggressive Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>An 8 week comprehensive smoking cessation and pharmacotherapy program consisting of eight weekly one hour group counseling sessions conducted with up to four other smokers focusing on patient education and behavior modification. Behavior modifications will include cue recognition; coping skills; stress management; and relapse prevention skills. Counseling will include information on nutrition, exercise, and chemical dependency. All counseling sessions will be held by the Director of the Staten Island Tobacco Cessation Program at 256C Mason Avenue. Pharmacotherapy adjuncts offered at no cost are as follows: Chantix (varenicline) GlaxoSmithKline, Zyban (bupropion) Pfizer,and Nicoderm/Nicorette (nicotine nasal spray, inhaler, transdermal patches and gum) GlaxoSmithKline.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacotherapy  Chantix (varenicline), Zyban (bupropion),and Nicoderm/Nicorette (nicotine nasal spray, inhaler, transdermal patches and gum)</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmacotherapy adjuncts offered at no cost are as follows: Chantix (varenicline) GlaxoSmithKline, Zyban (bupropion) Pfizer,and Nicoderm/Nicorette (nicotine nasal spray, inhaler, transdermal patches and gum) GlaxoSmithKline.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aggressive Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GlaxoSmithKline, Zyban,Nicoderm/Nicroette GlaxoSmithKline.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. All patients with confirmed peripheral arterial disease (PAD), defined as at least
             one of the following criteria, during the initial Vascular Surgery Office exam and
             review of the patient's medical record:

               1. Ankle-brachial index of &lt;.90 in at least 1 lower extremity.

               2. Toe-brachial index of &lt;.60

               3. Objective evidence of arterial occlusive disease in 1 lower extremity by duplex
                  ultrasonography, magnetic resonance angiography or computed tomographic
                  angiography

               4. prior leg arterial revascularization or amputation due to PAD

          2. Patients have to smoke with a minimum of 10 cigarettes per day for a minimum of 5
             years.

          3. Patients must be able to give informed written consent and be at least 18 years of
             age.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant women: Smoking Cessation Program medication Chantix (varenicline), Zyban
             (bupropion) has been shown to cause decreased fertility and decrease fetal weight in
             animal study offspring.

          2. Patients less than 18 years of age: Safe and effective use in children has not been
             established with Chantix (varenicline) and Zyban (bupropion). These medications are
             not approved for use in individuals less than 18 years of old.

          3. Patients with a history of a seizure disorder. Zyban (bupropion) is contraindicated
             in patients with preexisting seizure disorder.

          4. Patients with a history of anorexia nervosa or bulimia nervosa. Patients with these
             eating disorders have been shown to have an increased incidence of seizures and Zyban
             (bupropion) is contraindicated in patients with a history or anorexia nervosa and
             bulimia nervosa.

          5. The use bupropion concomitantly with monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs), including
             drugs with MAOI-like activity is contraindicated. Studies with animals indicate that
             bupropion-induced adverse reaction and toxicity appear to be enhanced by these
             medications.

          6. Patients with renal insufficiency;defined as having a Creatinine Clearance (CrCl)
             &lt;=50mL/min. Chantix is substantially excreted by the kidneys and the risk of toxic
             reactions are greater in patients with impaired renal function. Creatinine Clearance
             =[(140-age(yr)]*weight(kg)]/[72*serumCr(mg/dL)].

          7. Patients with hepatic insufficiency; defined as having elevated liver function tests
             (serum aminotransferases) greater than 1.5 baseline. Zyban is metabolized in the
             liver. Half-lives of bupropion and/or its major metabolites are prolonged in patients
             with liver disease.

          8. Patients with vascular pathology other than PAD (Carotid atherosclerosis, abdominal
             aortic aneurysms, venous insufficiency).

          9. Subjects with a history of psychiatric illness requiring current treatment with
             psychoactive medications, a history of dependence on alcohol or non nicotine
             substance in the past year or current use of tobacco products other than cigarettes.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jonathan Deitch, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>North Shore- LIJ (SIUH)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 8, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 8, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>North Shore Long Island Jewish Health System</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jonathan Deitch</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Program Director, Vascular Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Smoking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Nicotine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nicotine polacrilex</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Varenicline</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bupropion</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
