<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="168021">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01709799</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>179-2010</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01709799</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Village Interactive Training and Learning Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>VITAL</acronym>
  <official_title>The Village Interactive Training and Learning Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to help scientists and health care providers learn
      more about preventing dementia and brain disease in older adults.  There is an urgent need
      to develop strategies to prevent or slow down memory loss and brain function decline in the
      elderly.

      In this study, the investigators hope to learn how physical exercise and a brain training
      program work together to improve thinking and memory in older adults.  Specifically, these
      aims include:

        -  Learning whether physical activities (like biking or treadmill walking or Wii Fit
           games) will help improve the benefits of a brain training program.  Based on
           preliminary results and that in the literature, the investigators anticipate greater
           cognitive benefits in the Exercise + Cognitive training groups than the Cognitive
           Training alone group.

        -  To determine whether the benefits of adding exercise will occur quickly or develop more
           gradually over time. The investigators suspect that a major benefit of exercise
           pre-dosing will occur by the 12th week of the program.

        -  To examine whether Wii-Fit exercise games cause similar effects on brain training as
           traditional exercise programs such as biking or walking. Although several recent
           studies have raised questions about the true aerobic benefit of exergames such as
           Wii-Fit Plus, other evidence suggests that these weaker aerobic benefits may be offset
           by the greater novelty and interest level afforded by exergames.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Research Participants take part in a 16 week Wellness Program, which includes either
      traditional physical exercise with brain training(Group A), Wii exergaming with brain
      training(Group B) or brain training alone (Group C).  Participants are randomly assigned to
      groups.

      A comprehensive battery of neuropsychological tests, surveys and assessments are given prior
      to start of the intervention, at completion of the 16 weeks, and again 3 months post
      completion.

      The program involves 4 days of physical activity each week for groups A &amp; B.  The physical
      exercise/activity portion will involve warm up stretching and then either Group
      A-traditional exercise (like riding a stationary recumbent bicycle or walking on a
      treadmill), Group B- playing Nintendo Wii Exergames with a television based video game, or
      Group C- NO exercise at all.

      Every 4th week the 16 week intervention period, all participants in all three groups will
      also complete 80 minutes of brain training activities each day of the week.  This is in
      addition to the previously assigned physical activity for Groups A &amp; B.  The brain training
      regimen consists of Posit Science Insight computer based brain games.

      The Insight program consists of five different modules that focus on visual processing,
      attention, and memory.  Each of the modules are described below:

        1. Bird Safari: This module involves identifying and ordering simple visual stimuli that
           flash on a screen. The goal is to improve ability to respond quickly to visual stimuli
           and to segment rapidly changing visual pictures.

        2. Jewel Diver: This module involves tracking objects as they become hidden by
           distractors. The goal is to improve ability of visual system to rapidly identify and
           discriminate objects in the visual periphery.

        3. Master Gardener: This module involves visual working memory and matching pairs of
           pictures.

        4. Road Tour: This is a simulated driving exercise that involves divided attention to
           oncoming cars and road signs. The goal is to improve ability of visual system to
           continuously track multiple objects against a field of distractors.

        5. Sweep Seeker: In this exercise, participants identify complex moving visual stimuli.
           The goal is to improve rapid, sequential eye movements to salient visual targets,
           process relevant information and then make rapid decisions to identify, discriminate
           and classify targets.

      Questionnaires regarding the participants mood before and after the brain training weekly
      are administered. In addition, brief questionnaires on attention and memory are given to
      measure thinking and memory progress.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change scores on five subtests of the PositScience Insight Program (Bird Safari, Master Gardener, Road Tour, Jewel Diver, Sweep Seeker)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Weeks 4-8-12-16-28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Multiple time frames are selected because outcome change from baseline to week 28 is assessed.  A trajectory approach (looking and slope of change from beginning to end) is used; hence there are  multiple occasions. The Insight Program has 5 self contained subtests or assessments for the brain training activity.  These include assessments for Jewel Diver, Bird Safari, Master Gardener, Road Tour, Sweep Seeker.
The Insight scores measure the presentation time needed by participants to make correct perceptual judgments.  Reduction in presentation time needed over the course of the study is an index of improvement (increased perceptual efficiency).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Everyday Functions as Measured with Activities of Daily Living Assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 16 &amp; 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Timed Activities of Daily Living assessments are administered, such as making change, finding a name in the phone book, reading labels on a can, reading prescription labels, and identifying common food items in a cabinet.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">112</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Older Adults</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Training plus Traditional Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Physical exercise will be achieved using traditional methods of aerobic exercise.  Participants may choose between walking on a treadmill or riding on a stationary bike (Choices include recumbent or traditional sit-up bike.)
Every 4th week, participants will add 80mins./day of Insight gaming for cognitive training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Training plus Exergames</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Physical exercise in this group will be achieved using the Nintendo Wii Sports Resort and Wii Sports video games. A standardized gaming plan will be used for all participants, with play starting at 15 mins. and increasing 5 mins each week after, up to a maximum of 40 play minutes.
Every 4th week, participants will add 80mins./day of Insight gaming for cognitive training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>There is no physical training for this group.  Participants will complete 80 mins/day during the 4th, 8th, 12th and 16th weeks of the intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Traditional Physical Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will do physical activity that raises heart rate to a target heart rate (THR)zone which is pre-calculated using the Karvonen Formula:
(THR={(max. heart rate- rest heart rate) x %intensity} + resting heart rate
Participants begin exercise regimen starting at 50% THR for intensity and gradually increase by 5% up to a maximum of 75% THR.
Activity duration begins at 10 mins./day and increases 5 mins. every week following to a maximum of 40 mins. Polar Heart Rate monitors are used to measure THR and save resulting data.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Training plus Traditional Exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nintendo Wii Exergames</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants experience Wii Video Games in a standardized format, beginning with 15 mins of seated play per day on week one, and then increasing 5 mins./week on each week following up to a maximum of 40mins. of play.
Participants are made aware of the Target Heart Rate Zone for the week, but are not required to reach that zone during play.  The THR is calculated by the Karvonen Formula:
THR={(max. heart rate- rest heart rate) x %intensity} + resting heart rate
Polar Heart Rate monitors are used to measure THR and save resulting data.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Training plus Exergames</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Posit Science INSIGHT program games are used for all cognitive training.  Participants are exposed to (2) forty minute game sessions per day, for the cognitive training weeks #4,8,12,16.
INSIGHT Assessments are done at baseline, the start of each training week and at week 28.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Training plus Traditional Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Training plus Exergames</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 60+

          -  Generally Healthy

          -  On stable does of medications

          -  Absence of significant behavioral or cognitive dysfunction

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Significant cognitive or behavioral problems or symptoms

          -  History of falls &gt;2 in the past month

          -  Unstable medical conditions such as uncontrolled diabetes, uncontrolled     cardiac
             disease, uncontrolled hypertension, or other that would increase risk of side effects
             performing physical activity

          -  History of substance abuse in last 6 months

          -  Known structural brain abnormality, previous major debilitating strokes or seizures,
             traumatic brain injury

          -  Had complete neuropsychological testing in the last 6 months

          -  Previous participation in cognitive or exercise training study within last 3 months

          -  Currently engaging in moderate to heavy exercise &gt;125 mins. week at 75% Target Heart
             Rate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>95 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dawn Bowers, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida- PHHP, CHP</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael M Marsiske, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida, PHHP, CHP</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Village Retirement Community</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32653</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 22, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 18, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cognitive Training</keyword>
  <keyword>Aging</keyword>
  <keyword>Seniors</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
