<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="149625">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01833988</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013p000561</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01833988</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Summer Camp Study: Blood Glucose Control With a Bi-Hormonal Bionic Endocrine Pancreas</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Summer Camp Study: Feasibility of Outpatient Automated Blood Glucose Control With a Bi-Hormonal Bionic Endocrine Pancreas in a Pediatric Population at the Clara Barton Diabetes Camps</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boston University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will test the hypothesis that a wearable automated bionic pancreas system that
      automatically delivers both insulin and glucagon can improved glycemic control vs. usual
      care for young people with type 1 diabetes 12-20 in a diabetes camp environment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in average blood glucose (BG) between closed-loop and open-loop periods as determined from all scheduled HemoCue measurements with mean evenly weighted across the daytime and nighttime hours.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in the percentage of the above subset of BG values less than 70 mg/dl.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in average BG as determined from all HemoCue measurements taken during the day/nighttime including all extra measurements taken before meals, taken during exercise, and taken for hypoglycemia monitoring.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in percentage of the above subset of BG values less than 70 mg/dl.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in average BG as determined from the pre-meal, pre-snack, before bed, 12:00 AM, and 3:45 AM HemoCue measurements (nine measurements per day)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in the percentage of the above subset of BG values between the closed-loop control and usual care periods less than 70 mg/dl.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in percentage of subjects with mean BG &lt; 154 mg/dl</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in the percentage of study days with mean BG &lt; 154 mg/dl over the duration of the closed-loop period vs. the usual care period</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in number of hypoglycemic events as determined from HemoCue measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in fraction of time spent within glucose ranges (&lt; 70 mg/dl, 70-120 mg/dl, 70-180 mg/dl, &gt; 180 mg/dl, &gt; 250 mg/dl)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in mean BG during exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in number of hypoglycemic episodes and nadir BG during exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in mean BG and likelihood of hypoglycemia on nights after a period of exercise &gt; 30 minutes vs. nights after days without exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference of outcome measures on day 1 vs. remaining days (days 2-5) and on day 1-2 vs. on remaining days (days 3-5) in closed-loop and usual care periods</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in mean continuous glucose monitoring glucose (CGMG)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in number of  CGMG events &lt; 70 mg/dl (episodes separated by &lt; 15 minutes will be considered a single episode) and nadir for each</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in fraction of time spent within CGMG ranges (&lt; 70 mg/dl, 70-120 mg/dl, 70-180 mg/dl, &gt; 180 mg/dl, &gt; 250 mg/dl)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in area over the curve and below 70 mg/dl (measure of total hypoglycemia exposure)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in area over the curve and below 50 mg/dl (measure of total hypoglycemia exposure)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in percentage of subjects with mean CGMG &lt; 154 mg/dl</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in percentage of study days with mean CGMG &lt; 154 mg/dl</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in mean CGMG in the four hour period following meals</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in mean CGMG during exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in number of incidents of  hypoglycemia and nadir CGMG during exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in standard deviation of CGMG values (glycemic variability)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in standard deviation of CGMG values at night (11:00 PM to 7:00 AM)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in average BG as determined from all HemoCue measurements taken during the daytime including all extra measurements taken before meals, taken during exercise, and taken for hypoglycemia monitoring.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in average BG as determined from all HemoCue measurements taken during the nighttime including all extra measurements taken for hypoglycemia monitoring.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in percentage of the above subset of BG values at night less than 70 mg/dl.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in number of hypoglycemic events at night as determined from HemoCue measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in fraction of time at night spent within glucose ranges (&lt; 70 mg/dl, 70-120 mg/dl, 70-180 mg/dl, &gt; 180 mg/dl, &gt; 250 mg/dl)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in mean CGMG at night</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in number of  CGMG events &lt; 70 mg/dl (episodes separated by &lt; 15 minutes will be considered a single episode) and nadir for each during nighttime hours</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in fraction of time spent within CGMG ranges (&lt; 70 mg/dl, 70-120 mg/dl, 70-180 mg/dl, &gt; 180 mg/dl, &gt; 250 mg/dl) at night</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in area over the curve and below 70 mg/dl (measure of total hypoglycemia exposure) at night</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in area over the curve and below 50 mg/dl (measure of total hypoglycemia exposure) at night</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in standard deviation of CGMG values (glycemic variability) at night</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in number of carbohydrate interventions for hypoglycemia</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in number of carbohydrate interventions for hypoglycemia at night</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in total number of grams of carbohydrate taken for hypoglycemia</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in total number of grams of carbohydrate taken for hypoglycemia at night</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mean absolute relative deviation (MARD) of CGMG vs. scheduled HemoCue BG measurements in closed-loop and usual care periods</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between closed-loop and open-loop in mean insulin total daily dose</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Fraction of time bionic pancreas not functioning properly due to: system crash, communication problem (continuous glucose monitor), communication problem (pumps), pump malfunction, tubing occlusion, infusion set failure)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Difference of outcome measures on day 1 vs. remaining days (days 2-5) and on day 1-2 vs. on remaining days (days 3-5) for both closed-loop and usual care</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 1 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bi-hormonal Bionic Pancreas</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bi-hormonal Bionic Pancreas</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual Care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bi-hormonal Bionic Pancreas</intervention_name>
    <description>Automated blood glucose control via a closed-loop bionic pancreas device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bi-hormonal Bionic Pancreas</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Boston University Bionic Pancreas</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Comparator week to closed-loop control, utilizing usual camp care and the subject's own insulin pump.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 12-20 years with type 1 diabetes for at least one year.

          -  Diabetes managed using an insulin infusion pump and rapid- or very-rapid-acting
             insulins including insulin aspart (NovoLog), insulin lispro (Humalog), and insulin
             glulisine (Apidra) for at least three months prior to enrollment.

          -  Otherwise healthy (mild chronic disease such as asthma will be allowed if well
             controlled that do not require medications that result in exclusion).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to provide informed assent

          -  Unable to comply with study procedures.

          -  Current participation in another diabetes-related clinical trial other than one that
             is primarily observational in nature.

          -  Total daily dose (TDD) of insulin that is &gt; 2 units/kg.

          -  Pregnancy (positive urine HCG), plan to become pregnant in the immediate future, or
             sexually active without use of contraception

          -  Hypoglycemia unawareness (self-reported or legal guardian report of consistent lack
             of hypoglycemia symptoms when BG is &lt; 50 mg/dl)

          -  End stage renal disease on dialysis (hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis).

          -  History of prolonged QT or arrhythmia

          -  History of congenital heart disease or current known cardiac disease

          -  Acute illness (other than non-vomiting viral illness) or exacerbation of chronic
             illness other than type 1 diabetes at the time of the study.

          -  Seizure disorder or history of hypoglycemic seizures or coma in the last five years

          -  Untreated or inadequately treated mental illness (indicators would include symptoms
             such as psychosis, hallucinations, mania, and any psychiatric hospitalization in the
             last year), or treatment with second generation anti-psychotic medications, which are
             known to affect glucose regulation.

          -  Electrically powered implants (e.g. cochlear implants, neurostimulators) that might
             be susceptible to radiofrequency interference.

          -  Use non-insulin, injectable (e.g. exenatide, pramlintide) or oral (e.g.
             thiazolidinediones, biguanides, sulfonylureas, meglitinides, dipeptidyl peptidase-4
             inhibitors, acarbose)anti-diabetic medications.

          -  History of adverse reaction to glucagon (including allergy) besides nausea and
             vomiting.

          -  Unwilling or unable to completely avoid acetaminophen during the usual care and
             closed-loop BG control portions of the study.

          -  History of eating disorder such as anorexia, bulimia, &quot;diabulemia&quot; or omission of
             insulin to manipulate weight

          -  History of intentional, inappropriate administration of insulin leading to severe
             hypoglycemia requiring treatment

          -  Any factors that, in the opinion of the principal investigator, would interfere with
             the safe completion of the study procedures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>20 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven J Russell, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bionicpancreas.org</url>
    <description>Information about this and related studies</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 11, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 13, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Steven J. Russell, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>bionic pancreas</keyword>
  <keyword>artificial pancreas</keyword>
  <keyword>insulin</keyword>
  <keyword>glucagon</keyword>
  <keyword>continuous glucose monitoring (CGM)</keyword>
  <keyword>outpatient</keyword>
  <keyword>insulin pump</keyword>
  <keyword>pediatrics</keyword>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <keyword>camp</keyword>
  <keyword>summer camp</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancrelipase</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
