<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="158206">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02085993</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20120269</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02085993</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Patients With ITP Estimating the Proportion Administering Romiplostim Correctly After Receiving Home Admin Training</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Cross-sectional Study of Patients With Immune Thrombocytopenic Purpura and Caregivers to Estimate the Proportion Who Administer Romiplostim Correctly After Receipt of Home Administration Training Materials</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Amgen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Austria: Ethikkommission</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>Netherlands:  Independent Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>France: Comité consultatif sur le traitement de l'information en matière de recherche dans le domaine de la santé</authority>
    <authority>Greece: National Organization of Medicines</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cross-sectional study, observation made by healthcare professionals of subjects or
      caregivers, administering romiplostim at their first standard-of-care visit 4 weeks after
      training with the home administration training pack. Further observations can also be
      recorded in the study if made within 16 weeks of enrolment. Data will be collected from the
      subjects' dose diary at their first standard of care visit to ensure there were no problems
      with administration while not at the clinic.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This cross-sectional study involves direct observation by a healthcare professional of a
      series of subjects and caregivers in the act of administering romiplostim at their first
      standard-of-care visit occurring 4 weeks after training with the HAT pack. Further
      observations, if they occur, will also be recorded in the study if made within 16 weeks of
      enrolment. (Additional observations are voluntary and are not required for study
      participation; they occur only if the healthcare professional requests them.) Additionally,
      data will be collected from the subjects' dose diary at the first standard of care visit to
      ensure there were no problems with administration while not at the clinic.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case-Only, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Successful self administration of romiplostim</measure>
    <time_frame>First Standard of Care visit post Home Administration Training (range 2-8 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>to estimate the proportion of subjects and caregivers who administer romiplostim correctly after being trained with the HAT pack.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>successful reconstitution of romiplostim</measure>
    <time_frame>First Standard of Care visit post Home Administration Training (range 2-8 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To estimate the proportion of subjects and caregivers who reconstitute romiplostim correctly.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Accuracy in administering the prescribed dose of romiplostim</measure>
    <time_frame>First Standard of Care visit post Home Administration Training (range 2-8 weeks)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A yes/no indicator of whether the subject or caregiver injects romiplostim successfully with the difference between the prescribed and administered dose expressed as a %</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Successful administration of romiplostim at follow up visits</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 16 weeks post enrolment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A Yes/No indicator for whether the subject or caregiver administers romiplostim correctly at any follow up visits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Immune Thrombocytopenic Purpura</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        ITP patients being treated with romiplostim will be approached for possible study
        participation. At each participating site, patients that meet the following criteria will
        be  enrolled as a study subject.  Adult ITP patients, treated per EU Summary of product
        characteristics (SmPC), or caregiver new (or at least a 3 month gap) to administering
        romiplostim, that has received HAT pack training and is available at a standard-of-care
        medical visit 4 weeks (range 2 to 8 weeks) after HAT pack training, the patient provides
        informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  (1) adult ITP patient, treated per EU Summary of product characteristics (SmPC), or
             caregiver new (or at least a 3 month gap) to administering romiplostim,

          -  (2) has received HAT pack training,

          -  (3) available at standard-of-care medical visit 4 weeks (range 2 to 8 weeks) after
             HAT pack training,

          -  (4) patient provides informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Amgen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amgen Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>866-572-6436</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.amgentrials.com</url>
    <description>AmgenTrials clinical trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 25, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 11, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>romiplostim,</keyword>
  <keyword>Nplate,</keyword>
  <keyword>immune thrombocytopenic purpura</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Purpura</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Purpura, Thrombocytopenic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Purpura, Thrombocytopenic, Idiopathic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
