<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="46840">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01778127</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ZAMZEE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01778127</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Web-Based Physical Activity Intervention in Adolescent Survivors of Childhood Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Web-Based Physical Activity Intervention in Adolescent Survivors of Childhood Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Five year survival following a diagnosis of childhood cancer has reached 83%, making long
      term health outcomes among survivors an important concern. The growing population of
      survivors is at an increased risk of physical inactivity and associated adverse health
      outcomes. Regular physical activity is associated with better cardiovascular and
      musculoskeletal health.  Despite the known benefits of physical activity, nearly half of all
      childhood cancer survivors do not meet recommended guidelines for physical activity.

      Researchers at St. Jude Children's Research Hospital (SJCRH) want to determine if a
      rewards-based physical activity intervention delivered via an interactive website among
      young adolescent childhood cancer survivors, aged 11 through 14 years, will increase
      physical activity levels and improve cardiovascular and musculoskeletal health. The
      investigators also want to learn if this rewards-based intervention is effective. To achieve
      this goal the investigators have designed a three-arm prospective, randomized study with two
      reward-based intervention groups and a control group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE:

        -  To compare changes in levels of moderate and vigorous physical activity over 24 weeks.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVE:

        -  To compare changes in cardiorespiratory fitness, muscular strength and flexibility over
           24 weeks.

      Participants will be randomized to one of three groups.  Participants in the control group
      will receive an activity monitor and educational materials, but will not have access to the
      interactive website. Participants randomized to the two intervention groups will be given
      access to a rewards program delivered via an interactive website, an activity monitor, and
      educational materials. Individual physical activity data can be viewed by study participants
      after uploading information from their monitors to the interactive website. One intervention
      group will receive minimal rewards, while the other group will receive immediate incentives
      as well as the minimal rewards as they move from one level to the other on the website.

      After 24 weeks, changes in cardiorespiratory fitness, muscular strength, flexibility, and
      physical function will be compared between the two intervention groups and the control
      group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in daily average of moderate and vigorous physical activity (MVPA) levels between groups</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12 and Week 24</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The impact of the intervention will be assessed at the end of 24 weeks by comparing physical activity levels at baseline, week 12, and week 24 in each group.  Data will be collected each time a participant accesses the website (or connects the accelerometer - for the control group) over the entire 24 week period, resulting in access to data on daily levels of physical activity over a 24 week period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cardiovascular function between groups over 24 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>VO2 max will be used as the marker for physical fitness. Differences between groups will be evaluated with an F-test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in muscular strength between groups over 24 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Means and standard deviations and the estimated change in grip strength (kilograms), knee extension strength 60 degrees per second (Newton meters), ankle dorsiflexion strength 30 degrees per second (Newton meters), and strength subtest (Bruininks-Oseretsky Test of Motor Proficiency) will be compared between baseline and 24 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in flexibility between groups over 24 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Means and standard deviations of active plantar flexion, active dorsiflexion, and sit and reach will be compared between baseline and 24 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A: Minimal Rewards</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants use an activity monitor and the interactive website.  They will receive minimal rewards based on their physical activity levels.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B: Immediate Incentives</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants use an activity monitor and the interactive website.
In addition to minimal rewards, participants will receive immediate incentives as they move from one level to the other on the website.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group C: Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the control group will receive an activity monitor and educational materials, but will not have access to the interactive website. No rewards will be offered for their participation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Activity Monitor</intervention_name>
    <description>Measurement of physical activity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A: Minimal Rewards</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B: Immediate Incentives</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group C: Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tri-Axial Accelerometer</other_name>
    <other_name>Zamzee</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interactive Website</intervention_name>
    <description>Zamzee is a meter that measures activity and a website that makes moving fun.  Parents of participants can set activity goals.  Activity is uploaded to the website where participants track progress and earn rewards by increasing their level of activity.  Participants can view leaderboards and check how other participants are doing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A: Minimal Rewards</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B: Immediate Incentives</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zamzee Website</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Educational Materials</intervention_name>
    <description>All participants will receive educational handouts about physical activity.  Participants will receive the educational handouts again via mail three and five months into the study to reinforce the importance of physical activity and maintain compliance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A: Minimal Rewards</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B: Immediate Incentives</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group C: Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Educational Brochure</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Previously treated for childhood cancer at St. Jude Children's Research Hospital
             (SJCRH)

          -  11 through 14 years of age

          -  Not undergoing active treatment for cancer

          -  Medical clearance from participant's attending physician via email

          -  Does not meet the Centers for Disease Control (CDC) physical activity guidelines.
             CDC guidelines for children age 11 to 14 are defined as 60 minutes or more per day of
             physical activity, seven days a week

          -  Internet access and a computer that has software that is compatible with the study
             device (Windows XP, Windows Vista, Windows 7, Mac OSX 10.5 and Mac OSX 10.6)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Global cognitive impairment (Full Scale Intelligence Quotient &lt; 70) that prevents use
             of the interactive website

          -  Pregnant female

          -  Inability to read and write English
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>11 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kirsten K. Ness, PT, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kirsten K. Ness, PT, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>866-278-5833</phone>
    <email>info@stjude.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kirsten K. Ness, PT, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>866-278-5833</phone>
      <email>info@stjude.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kirsten K. Ness, PT, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stjude.org</url>
    <description>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 12, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 18, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cancer Survivor</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical Activity</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Outcomes</keyword>
  <keyword>Rewards-Based Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Musculoskeletal Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
