<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="46879">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01871727</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E7777-G000-302</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01871727</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Trial of E7777 in Persistent and Recurrent Cutaneous T-Cell Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Clinical Study to Demonstrate Safety and Efficacy of E7777 (Denileukin Diftitox) in Persistent or Recurrent Cutaneous T-Cell Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eisai Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eisai Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this trial is to assess the efficacy and safety of E7777 (improved purity
      ONTAK [denileukin diftitox]) in patients with persistent and recurrent cutaneous T-cell
      lymphoma. A Lead-in dose-finding part will be used to determine the dose of E7777 that
      should be used to test efficacy and safety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Objective Response Rate is defined as the proportion of subjects with best response of complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) using the Global Response Score of the consensus International Society for Cutaneous Lymphomas/ European Organization of Research and Treatment of Cancer (ISCL/EORTC) criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Persistent or Recurrent Cutaneous T-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>E7777</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>E7777</intervention_name>
    <description>administered by intravenous (i.v.) infusion over 60 minutes (± 10 minutes) on 5 consecutive days during every cycle of 21 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>E7777</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION

        Subjects must meet all of the following criteria to be included in the study:

          1. Age ≥18 years.

          2. Histopathologic diagnosis of CTCL (mycosis fungoides [MF] or Sézary Syndrome [SS]),
             confirmed by skin biopsy, or lymph node, or blood assessment, of current disease.

          3. CD25 assay-positive tumor, defined as detectable CD25 on ≥ 20% of total lymphoid
             infiltrate in biopsied skin lesions by immunohistochemistry, assessed by central
             pathology laboratory. A recent or archival skin biopsy (≤ 6 months) can be used.
             Re-biopsy is required if the subject had disease progression or relapse since the
             last biopsy, or had received anticancer therapy since the last biopsy.

          4. CTCL disease stage as follows, according to ISCL/EORTC (Olsen 2011).

               -  Lead-In part: Stage IA - IV, except Stage IVB with visceral or CNS involvement
                  (bone marrow involvement is not considered visceral involvement but rather an
                  extension of blood involvement [B2], and is allowed).

               -  Main Study: Stage IA - III.

          5. History of prior therapies for CTCL as follows:

               -  Lead-In part: must have had prior therapy; any number of prior therapies
                  allowed.

               -  Main Study: must have had prior therapy; ≤ 3 prior therapies allowed. Topical
                  treatments (except topical chemotherapy) and steroids are not considered as
                  prior therapies. Prior therapies allowed are: cytotoxic chemotherapy,
                  combination cytotoxic chemotherapy, electron beam radiotherapy (EBRT),
                  phototherapy (e.g., PUVA or UVB), photophoresis, interferon, topical
                  chemotherapy (e.g., carmustine, nitrogen mustard), systemic retinoids,
                  cyclosporin A (≥4 mg/kg/d for ≥1 month), or histone deacetylase inhibitors
                  (vorinostat or romidepsin). Repeated use of the same agent counts as one
                  therapy, unless it is part of a different combination regimen.

          6. A minimum washout period of 4 weeks after previous CTCL therapy is recommended before
             the first dose of E7777. Subjects must have recovered from any adverse effects from
             any previous CTCL therapy before starting study drug. A shorter washout may be
             allowed if a subject is experiencing progressive disease despite ongoing treatment.

          7. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0, 1, or 2 in the
             Lead-In part and performance status of 0 or 1 in the Main Study.

          8. Life expectancy ≥ 3 months in the Lead-In part and ≥ 12 months in the Main Study.

          9. Adequate bone marrow reserves as evidenced by:

               -  platelets ≥ 100,000/mm3 (100×109/L)

               -  clinically stable hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL (90 g/L) and hematocrit ≥ 27% without
                  transfusion support

         10. Normal hepatic function as evidenced by:

               -  bilirubin ≤ 1.5 × the upper limit of normal (ULN) and alkaline phosphatase ≤ 3.0
                  × the ULN.

               -  aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT)

                  ≤ 3.0 × the ULN.

               -  albumin ≥ 3.0 g/dL (30 g/L). If AST or ALT values are elevated, a second
                  determination may be made ≥ 4 days later; if the values obtained upon the retest
                  meet the above criteria, then the subject is considered to have met this
                  criterion for entry.

         11. Adequate renal function as evidenced by serum creatinine ≤ 1.8 mg/dL (158 μmol/L) OR
             calculated creatinine clearance ≥ 50 mL/min (per the Cockcroft-Gault formula) with &lt;
             2+ protein OR 24-hour urine creatinine clearance ≥ 50 mL/minute with 24-hour urine
             protein &lt; 1g.

         12. Willing and able to comply with all aspects of the protocol.

         13. Provide written informed consent prior to any study-specific screening procedures.

         14. Females may not be lactating or pregnant at Screening or Baseline (as documented by a
             negative beta-human chorionic gonadotropin [ß-hCG] test with a minimum sensitivity of
             25 IU/L or equivalent units of ß-hCG). A separate baseline assessment is required if
             a negative screening pregnancy test was obtained more than 72 hours before the first
             dose of study drug.

         15. All females will be considered to be of childbearing potential unless they are
             postmenopausal (amenorrheic for at least 12 consecutive months, in the appropriate
             age group, and without other known or suspected cause) or have been sterilized
             surgically (i.e., bilateral tubal ligation, total hysterectomy, or bilateral
             oophorectomy, all with surgery at least 1 month before dosing).

         16. Females of childbearing potential must not have had unprotected sexual intercourse
             within 30 days prior to study entry and must agree to use a highly effective method
             of contraception (e.g., total abstinence, an intrauterine device, a double-barrier
             method [such as condom plus diaphragm with spermicide], a contraceptive implant, an
             oral contraceptive, or have a vasectomized partner with confirmed azoospermia)
             throughout the entire study period and for 30 days after study drug discontinuation.
             If currently abstinent, the subject must agree to use a double-barrier method as
             described above if she becomes sexually active during the study period or for 30 days
             after study drug discontinuation. Females who are using hormonal contraceptives must
             have been on a stable dose of the same hormonal contraceptive product for at least 4
             weeks prior to dosing and must continue to use the same contraceptive during the
             study and for 30 days after study drug discontinuation.

         17. Male subjects must have had a successful vasectomy (confirmed azoospermia) or they
             and their female partner must meet the criteria above (i.e., not of childbearing
             potential or practicing highly effective contraception throughout the study period
             and for 30 days after study drug discontinuation).

        Exclusion Criteria

        Subjects who meet any of the following criteria will be excluded from the study:

          1. CTCL Stage IVB disease with visceral or CNS involvement (bone marrow involvement is
             considered an extension of blood involvement [B2] and is not considered visceral
             involvement)

          2. Prior denileukin diftitox therapy

          3. Use of topical steroids within 14 days of Day 1 of initial therapy is not allowed,
             with the following exception: Topical steroids or systemic low dose steroids (≤ 10
             mg/day prednisone) are allowed in subjects with erythroderma who have been on
             corticosteroids for a prolonged period of time and where discontinuation may lead to
             rebound flare in disease. The concomitant steroid medication is allowed as long as
             the type of steroid, route of administration, and steroid dose remain the same as
             what the subject had been receiving for a prolonged period of time.

          4. Prior malignancy other than CTCL within past 5 years (except nonmelanoma skin cancer
             or carcinoma in situ of the cervix)

          5. Serious intercurrent illness

          6. Significant cardiac disease requiring ongoing treatment, including congestive heart
             failure (CHF), severe coronary artery disease (CAD), cardiomyopathy, uncontrolled
             cardiac arrhythmia, unstable angina pectoris, or myocardial infarction (MI) (within 6
             months of study enrollment)

          7. Significant pulmonary symptoms or disease

          8. History of uncontrolled seizure disorder or active central nervous system disease

          9. Need for treatment with a drug that contains a warning for hepatotoxicity or
             nephrotoxicity in its labeling

         10. Major surgery within 2 weeks of study enrollment

         11. Significant or uncontrolled infections requiring specific anti-infective therapy

         12. Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection; known active hepatitis B or
             hepatitis C infection

         13. Females who are pregnant (positive urine test) or breastfeeding

         14. Any history of a medical condition or a concomitant medical condition that, in the
             opinion of the investigator, would compromise the subject's ability to safely
             complete the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chean Eng Ooi</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Eisai Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eisai Medical Services</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-422-4743</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 7, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, T-Cell, Cutaneous</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
