<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="134589">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02043379</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IVIG after CPB in Infants</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>F13114002</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02043379</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intravenous Immunoglobulin for Early Prevention of Cardiopulmonary Bypass Induced Hypogammaglobulinemia in Infants and Neonates</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Grifols Biologicals Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama at Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study protocol is to determine if administering Intravenous
      Immunoglobulin (IVIG) for treatment of cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB) induced
      hypogammaglobulinemia in the early post-operative period can impact post-surgical outcomes
      (i.e., infection, fluid overload, and associated morbidities).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The intense post-CPB systemic inflammatory response syndrome (SIRS) is well described in
      neonates and infants.  Increased production and release of pro-inflammatory cytokines,
      including Tumor Necrosis Factor, Interleukin1-B, and Interleukin-6 may suppress myocardial
      contractility, induce capillary leak, and activate complement and the clotting cascade -
      together leading to potential organ injury and death. SIRS is also frequently accompanied by
      impairment of the humoral immune response. One potential reason for this acquired
      immunodeficiency after cardiac surgery is the removal of immunoglobulins (Ig)s from the
      vascular space into other compartments where they are either sequestered or lost from the
      body altogether. We recently demonstrated that such Ig depletion from the intravascular
      compartment occurs in neonates following cardiac surgery. In a retrospective study of 53
      children &lt;3 months of age, we showed that plasma Immunoglobulin G (IgG) concentration drops
      precipitously after cardiac surgery and does not return to preoperative levels by 7 days;
      51% of patients had hypogammaglobulinemia.

      An important question is whether post-CPB low IgG has clinical consequence. IgG plays an
      essential role in the humoral immune system, activating complement and inducing the
      phagocytic system to neutralize pathogens. IgG deficiency is a known risk factor for
      infections in other pediatric populations.  We were the first to demonstrate that post-CPB
      hypogammaglobulinemia is associated with worse clinical outcomes, including increased
      secondary infections (37% vs.12% in those without low IgG, p&lt;0.05). These novel findings are
      paramount in that they identify a potential modifiable risk factor to improve outcomes after
      pediatric cardiac surgery with CPB.  Additionally, low IgG is accompanied by fluid overload
      and prolonged mechanical ventilation.  Igs constitute an important component of plasma
      oncotic pressure, so hypogammaglobulinemia may exacerbate anasarca, prolonging postoperative
      convalescence and increasing the morbidities associated with increased ICU length of stay.9

      Igs have an increasingly recognized role in modulating the innate immune response.  Present
      use of IVIG exceeds mere antibody replacement and extends to the treatment of autoimmune and
      inflammatory conditions. In fact, more than 75% of IVIG use in the U.S. today is for the
      treatment of inflammatory conditions, where proposed mechanisms include reduction of
      pro-inflammatory cytokine and adhesion molecule expression, superantigen neutralization,
      restoration of glucocorticoid responsiveness, and blockade of complement fragment
      deposition. It is plausible that IVIG could benefit neonates after cardiac surgery not only
      via restoration of humoral opsonization capacity, but also as a modulator of innate immunity
      and SIRS.  According to this model, tissue injury, CPB, and shock trigger SIRS, leading to
      hypogammaglobulinemia and resultant increased susceptibility to inflammatory dysregulation
      which might be ameliorated via administration of IVIG.

      In an adult study, IVIG failed to benefit postoperative cardiac patients with severe SIRS.
      However, the dose of IVIG given was relatively small compared with that typically given for
      autoimmune and inflammatory conditions. Neonates and infants may be more susceptible to the
      harmful effects of acquired hypogammaglobulinemia than adults as they may be unable to
      generate adequate quantities of antibodies in response to pathogens, relying mainly on
      maternal Igs until around the 4th to 6th month of life.  In addition, they display an
      exaggerated inflammatory response to CPB as compared with older children and adults, so they
      might stand to benefit more from IVIG as an immunomodulator.

      Because of the increased vulnerability to acquired infection and other morbidities in the
      setting of hypogammaglobulinemia as result of enhanced SIRS and immune dysfunction, it is
      feasible that normalization of IgG concentration in the neonatal and infant population may
      improve clinical outcomes via restoration of the humoral immune system, modulation of the
      innate immune system, and restoration of intravascular oncotic pressure.  The appropriate
      IgG level threshold for treatment and optimal plasma IgG level to target after
      administration of IVIG are presently unknown.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-Operative Infections</measure>
    <time_frame>Hospital Discharge</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint of this study is incidence of post-operative infections through hospital discharge</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal variables</measure>
    <time_frame>24 &amp; 48 hours post CPB</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Plasma albumin &amp; plasma total protein will be assessed at 24 and 48 hours. Maximum plasma creatinine within the first 48 hours will also be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fluid Overload Variables</measure>
    <time_frame>24 and 48 hours post-CPB</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The following fluid overload variables will be assessed at 24 and 48 hours post-cardiopulmonary bypass: blood product and albumin administration, chest tube output, urine output, peritoneal dialysis output, net fluid balance, and percent fluid overload.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemodynamic variables</measure>
    <time_frame>first 48 hours post-CPB</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The maximum and average inotrope score will be calculated, the incidence of low cardiac output syndrome will be recorded, and the maximum plasma lactic acid will be recorded for the the specified time frame.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory variables</measure>
    <time_frame>hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Alive, ventilator free days and duration of oxygen therapy will be recorded at hospital discharge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>From admit to the Pediatric cardiac intensive care unit until discharge from the hospital in days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Immunoglobulins</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days post-op</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Plasma Immunoglobulin levels will be checked pre-operatively, 12 hours post-op and 5 days post-op</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma cytokine levels</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post-op</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Plasma cytokine levels:Interferon-gamma, Interleukin-10, Interleukin-12p70, Interleukin-1b, Interleukin-6, Interleukin-8, Tumor Necrosis Factor a will be measured preoperatively, immediately postoperatively and 4, 12, and 24 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunoglobulin concentration in fluid loss</measure>
    <time_frame>12 hours post-op</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Immunoglobulin concentration will be measured from chest tube, peritoneal drain, and urine outputs every 4 hours for first 12 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Incidence of mortality from admit to Pediatric cardiac intensive care unit post-operatively until hospital discharge .</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intensive Care Unit Length of Stay</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The majority of the subject's enrolled into this protocol (complex neonates) are discharged home from the Pediatric Cardiac Intensive Care unit (PCICU). All others enrolled in the study are usually discharged from the PCICU within a week after surgery. This is measured in days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypogammaglobulinemia</condition>
  <condition>Congenital Heart Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IVIG</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Those randomized to the study arm will receive a dose of IVIG 1 gram/kg at 12 hours post-cardiopulmonary bypass. This is a one time only dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subject's randomized into the placebo arm of the study will receive a volume of normal saline that is comparative to that if they were to receive IVIG. This will be at 12 hours post-cardiopulmonary bypass. This volume is to ensure blinding of study drug.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IVIG</intervention_name>
    <description>Those randomized to the study arm will receive a one time dose of IVIG at 12 our post-Cardiopulmonary bypass. This is significantly early than our current standard of care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>IVIG</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gamunex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>If the subject is randomized to the placebo group they will receive a volume of normal saline that is equivalent to the volume of IVIG to be administered based on their weight.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Normal Saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Infants &lt;6 months old

          -  Successfully weaned off cardiopulmonary bypass after cardiac surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Requirement of extra corporeal membrane oxygenation in the operating room

          -  Known immune deficiency

          -  Current Do Not Resuscitate or limitation of care order

          -  Current enrollment in another interventional clinical study

          -  Refusal of parental consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Alten, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham Pediatric Cardiac Critical Care</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Alten, MD</last_name>
    <phone>205-975-3123</phone>
    <email>jalten@peds.uab.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Krissie Hock, RN, BSN, BS</last_name>
    <phone>205-996-3313</phone>
    <email>khock@peds.uab.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's of Alabama</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Alten, MD</last_name>
      <phone>205-975-3123</phone>
      <email>jalten@peds.uab.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Krissie Hock, RN, BSN, BS</last_name>
      <phone>205-353-2553</phone>
      <email>khock@peds.uab.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Alten, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 21, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 14, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>congenital heart disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiopulmonary Bypass</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypogammaglobulinemia</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Agammaglobulinemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Defects, Congenital</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins, Intravenous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rho(D) Immune Globulin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
