<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="112488">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01723566</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PANORAMA 2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01723566</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PANORAMA 2 Observational Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Panorama 2 Medtronic CRDM Implantable Cardiac Device Long Term Registry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medtronic Bakken Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medtronic Bakken Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>NA: No oversight authorities involved</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Understanding the clinical practice of treatment of cardiac rhythm disorders all over the
      world and understanding the clinical outcomes of the treatment with its cardiac rhythm
      products in real world patient population is essential for Medtronic to be able to
      effectively develop new products and adjust existing products. In addition Medtronic is
      committed to monitor the safety of its products throughout the entire life cycle to ensure
      maximum product reliability.

      The Panorama 2 registry will enable Medtronic to increase data collection of clinical
      practice with Medtronic implantable Cardiac Rhythm and Disease Management (CRDM) devices in
      various regions across the world and on product reliability of its CRDM devices.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Describe region-specific clinical practice of CRDM device use</measure>
    <time_frame>2012-2019</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To describe the region-specific current clinical practices associated with the device treatment of patients receiving implantable Medtronic CRDM devices by collecting information on the patient characteristics (demographics, medical history and cardiovascular status), the type of Medtronic CRDM devices used, the indication for the use of the Medtronic CRDM devices and the clinical outcomes of the treatment with the Medtronic CRDM devices (all deaths, cardiovascular hospitalizations, Serious Adverse Device Effects and NYHA class).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8500</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Rhythm Disorders</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients that have a Medtronic implantable CRDM Device implanted (including Vitatron),
        which is commercially available at the start of the registry or becomes commercially
        available during the course of the registry, and used within its intended use, may be
        included.

        These products are:

          -  Pacemaker systems: Implantable Pulse Generators (IPG) and cardiac leads

          -  Defibrillation systems: Implantable Cardioverter Defibrillators (ICD) and cardiac
             leads

          -  Resynchronization systems: Cardiac Resynchronization Therapy (CRT):

               -  Cardiac Resynchronization Therapy - Pacemaker (CRT-P) and cardiac leads

               -  Cardiac Resynchronization Therapy - Defibrillator (CRT-D) and cardiac leads

          -  Implantable Loop Recorders (ILR)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Patient is 18 years of age or older (lower age limit dependent on local law: to be
             specified in country-specific addendum to the clinical investigational plan, if
             applicable)

          -  Patient or Legally Authorized Representative provides signed and dated authorization
             and/or consent per institution and local requirements

          -  Patient will be treated with a commercially available implantable Medtronic CRDM
             device/ Vitatron device within maximally 30 days after enrollment or within 3 days
             prior to enrollment

        Exclusion criterion:

        • Patient has exclusion criteria per local law (to be specified in country-specific
        addendum to the clinical investigational plan, if applicable)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cairo University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Abdelwahhab</last_name>
      <email>amirabdelwahab@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amir Abdelwahab, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 28, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 6, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
