<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="129614">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02119676</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>INCB18424-267</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02119676</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Ruxolitinib in Colorectal Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind Study of Ruxolitinib or Placebo in Combination With Regorafenib in Subjects With Relapsed or Refractory Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Incyte Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Incyte Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if ruxolitinib, in combination with regorafenib,
      is safe and effective in the treatment of metastatic colorectal cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study consists of an open-label, Part 1 safety run-in (consisting of 1 to 3 cohorts of 9
      subjects each), to confirm the safety of the regorafenib/ruxolitinib combination in subjects
      with relapsed or refractory metastatic colorectal cancer (CRC). If determined to be
      tolerable, Part 2 will proceed as a randomized, double-blind study evaluating ruxolitinib or
      placebo in combination with regorafenib in subjects with relapsed or refractory metastatic
      CRC previously treated with fluoropyrimidine, oxaliplatin, and/or irinotecan based
      chemotherapy, an anti-VEGF therapy and if KRAS wild type an anti-EGFR therapy.

      Subjects in the safety run-in will receive open-label ruxolitinib and regorafenib; for the
      randomized, double-blind portion of the study all subjects will receive regorafenib and
      either ruxolitinib or placebo in a 1:1 blinded manner. Treatment for all subjects will
      consist of repeating 28-day cycles. Regorafenib will be self-administered for the first 21
      days of each cycle, and ruxolitinib/placebo will be self-administered during the entire
      28-day cycle. Treatment cycles will continue as long as the regimen is tolerated, and the
      subject does not meet the discontinuation criteria. When subjects discontinue regorafenib,
      ruxolitinib or placebo they will remain in the study and be followed for subsequent
      treatment regimens which are initiated and survival.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 1: Determination of the dose of ruxolitinib that is safe and tolerable in combination with regorafenib as measured by the number of dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) observed in the evaluation cohort</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2: Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Randomization until death due to any cause. Approximately 28 months.]</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Randomization through disease progression, or death due to any cause if sooner. Approximately 28 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PFS is defined as the time from randomization until the earliest date of disease progression determined by investigator assessment of objective radiographic disease assessments per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) v1.1, or death due to any cause, if sooner</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through end of study. Approximately 28 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Objective response rate determined by radiographic disease assessments per RECIST v1.1, by investigator assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through end of study.  28 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Duration of response determined by radiographic disease assessment per RECIST v1.1, by investigator assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of the treatment regimens assessed by a summary of adverse events and clinical laboratory assessments.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through approximately 30 days post treatment discontinuation. Approximately 28 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Control</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through end of study.  Approximately 28 months.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Disease control as measured by the percentage of subjects whose best response was not progressive disease (PD) (ie, complete response (CR), partial response (PR), or stable disease (SD) per RECIST v.1.1). Stable disease will be included if it occurs at least 6 weeks after randomization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">373</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ruxolitinib plus regorafenib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo plus regorafenib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ruxolitinib</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mg tablets to be administered by mouth
Ruxolitinib 15mg BID (NOTE: Starting dose of randomized portion of study may be 10mg BID based on results from safety run-in study. Dose of ruxolitinib may be increased during randomized study, based on results from safety run-in.)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ruxolitinib plus regorafenib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Jakafi ®</other_name>
    <other_name>Jakavi ®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Regorafenib</intervention_name>
    <description>Regorafenib 160mg once daily for the first 21 days of each 28-day cycle.  (NOTE: Dose interruptions and modifications for regorafenib are expected when toxicities occur in which dose interruptions or modifications are appropriate.)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ruxolitinib plus regorafenib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo plus regorafenib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Stivarga ®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mg matching placebo tablets to be administered by mouth</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo plus regorafenib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the colon or rectum that
             is metastatic.

          -  Progression after having been treated with fluoropyrimidine, oxaliplatin and
             irinotecan based chemotherapy, an anti-VEGF therapy and if KRAS wild type an
             anti-EGFR therapy.

          -  Radiographically measurable or evaluable disease (per RECIST v1.1)

          -  Life expectancy of ≥ 12 weeks.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 to 1

          -  Two or more weeks have elapsed from the completion of previous treatment regimen and
             subjects must have recovered or be at a new stable baseline from any related
             toxicities.

          -  Prior radiotherapy to disease sites is allowed with certain protocol-defined
             restrictions.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior treatment with regorafenib.

          -  Presence of active gastrointestinal disease or other condition that will interfere
             significantly with the absorption of drugs.

          -  Active peptic ulcer disease, inflammatory bowel disease (eg, ulcerative colitis,
             Crohn's disease), diverticulitis, or other gastrointestinal conditions with increased
             risk of perforation or gastrointestinal bleeding.

          -  Recent history (≤ 3 months) or ongoing partial or complete bowel obstruction unless
             due to disease under study and corrected with surgery.

          -  Blood pressure ≥ 140/90 mmHg.

          -  Active bleeding diathesis or history of any major bleeding, central nervous system
             (CNS) bleeding, or significant hemoptysis within 6 months of enrollment. Subjects
             with bleeding secondary to underlying disease (including gastrointestinal (GI)
             perforation or fistula) that has been corrected by surgery or alternative procedure
             may be included.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lance Leopold, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Incyte Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Incyte Corporation Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-855-463-3463</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Lafayette</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Jefferson City</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Canton</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 2, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 17, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Colon Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Ruxolitinib</keyword>
  <keyword>adenocarcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>regorafenib</keyword>
  <keyword>Jakavi ®</keyword>
  <keyword>Jakafi ®</keyword>
  <keyword>Stivarga ®</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
