<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="16603">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01862809</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999913103</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-C-N103</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01862809</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cigarette Smoking and Oral Microbiota</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Smoking on Oral Microbiota</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Normal bacteria and other tiny organisms (the microbiota) live in the mouth and nose. They
      contribute to human health in many ways, including digesting food and balancing hormones.
      Testing samples from the mouth can show how microbiotas are related to health and disease.
      However, the microbiota in a person's mouth differs depending on the methods of collection
      and the part of the mouth that is tested. Understanding what can change the microbiota
      (including mouth sites, and what a person eats or smokes) will give more information on how
      to study oral microbiota and smoking-related cancers and other diseases.

      Objectives:

        -  To see how smoking affects the microbiotas in mouth and nose.

        -  To determine which collection method for mouth specimens should be used for studying
           microbiota.

      Eligibility:

        -  Individuals at least 18 years of age who have been using tobacco products regularly for
           at least 5 years.

        -  Individuals at least 18 years of age who have never smoked.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history.

        -  Participants will have a dental exam. They will provide a saliva sample. The dentist
           will take swabs from the inside of the mouth, including the tongue, tonsils, gums, and
           teeth. The inside of the nose will also be swabbed.

        -  Participants will also fill out a questionnaire. It will ask about their history of
           smoking and consumption of alcohol, tea, and coffee. It will also ask about current
           medications, including antibiotics.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The oral microbial community (the microbiota), is centrally related to nutrition,
      metabolism, immunity, inflammation, and endocrine balance. Cigarette smoking is associated
      with serious health outcomes including cancer, cardiovascular disease and chronic lung
      disease. However, little is known about the relationship between cigarette smoking, oral
      microbiota and tobacco-related health outcomes. Microbiotas in the different sites of the
      same oral cavity vary widely. Recent studies indicated that the difference in microbial
      profiles between buccal mucosa and gingival plaque is as distinct as the difference between
      tongue and stool. To date, knowledge about the effect of smoking on oral microbiotas is
      lacking. As an initial step toward understanding the role of the oral microbiota in
      smoking-related health outcomes, we propose a pilot study to evaluate the effects of
      cigarette smoking on the microbiotas in buccal rinse obtained from the oral cavity and
      across 8 different oral cavity sites/niches (saliva, swabs from tongue dorsum, hard palate,
      buccal mucosa, keratinized gingiva, palatine tonsils, supragingival plaque, subgingival
      plaque). We will seek to recruit up to 50 volunteers through the Eastman Dental General
      Dentistry Clinic, Rochester, NY, including 25 current smokers with &gt;  5 years of smoking
      history and 25 never smokers as a comparison group. Age-group, gender, and race
      (Caucasian/African- American) will be matched for the two groups. In each subject, the
      buccal cell (mouthwash) collection will be collected according to the PLCO buccal cell
      collection protocol. In addition, collections across 8 different oral cavity sites will be
      done using a protocol developed for the Human Microbiome Project. These 9 collections will
      be used for high throughput sequencing of 16S rRNA microbial genes at the Institute of
      Genome Sciences, University of Maryland School of Medicine. The findings will provide
      information about the effect of smoking on microbial taxa composition and relative abundance
      at each collection site. This pilot study will demonstrate the effects of smoking on oral
      microbiotas across different oral cavity sites and will also demonstrate which oral
      collection site is most promising for the detailed study about cigarette smoking and oral
      microbiota. In addition, the data collected will provide a validation framework to use the
      PLCO buccal specimens for large-scale studies. The information about the validity of using
      PLCO buccal cell collection will be an invaluable asset for further large scale studies of
      the microbiota and cancer risk. We will also be able to investigate if there is any taxonomy
      or microbial diversity difference between heavy smokers and never-smokers. This pilot study
      will provide essential information about collection, design and analyses that will enable
      further studies of the relationships between cigarette smoking, the oral microbiome and
      tobacco-related cancers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>This pilot study will provide essential information about collection, design and analyses that will enable further studies of the relationships between cigarette smoking, the oral microbiome and tobacco-related cancers.</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Microbiota</condition>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Oral Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA

        This study will recruit a convenience sample of 50 volunteers (25 current smokers with at
        least 5 years of smoking history, 25 never smokers). Current smokers are defined as
        individuals who have smoked more than 100 cigarettes in their lifetime and have smoked 5
        or more cigarettes in the last 24 hours. Recent use of other tobacco products (pipe,
        cigar, snuff, cigarillos, and chewing tobacco) is an overall exclusion, but use in the
        remote past (&gt;  6 month ago) is acceptable in smokers. Never smokers are defined as
        individuals who have never smoked cigarettes nor used any other tobacco products including
        pipe, cigar, snuff, cigarillos, or chewing tobacco.

        The ethnic mix of the clinic is roughly 50% Caucasians and 50% African- Americans with a
        small number of unspecified or other racial groups. The median age is about 50 and the
        gender mix consists of an equal number of men and women. We  therefore will select smokers
        and frequency match to non-smokers based on ethnicity (White, African-American), gender
        (male, female), and age (above or below the median, estimated to be 50).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

        We will exclude pregnant women and    other    racial groups because they may represent
        very small numbers and thus be difficult to match. Hormonal changes associated with
        pregnancy and unique cultural habits associated with specific ethnic groups could be
        associated with highly unique or variable microbiome patterns, and therefore reduce the
        power to detect differences associated with smoking which is our primary goal. We will
        also exclude subjects with antibiotic usage in the last three months and subjects with
        previous diagnosed major periodontal disease or cancer because they might be potential
        confounders.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Neil E Caporaso, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Neil E Caporaso, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(240) 276-7228</phone>
    <email>caporasn@epndce.nci.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frank DN, St Amand AL, Feldman RA, Boedeker EC, Harpaz N, Pace NR. Molecular-phylogenetic characterization of microbial community imbalances in human inflammatory bowel diseases. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007 Aug 21;104(34):13780-5. Epub 2007 Aug 15.</citation>
    <PMID>17699621</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turnbaugh PJ, Hamady M, Yatsunenko T, Cantarel BL, Duncan A, Ley RE, Sogin ML, Jones WJ, Roe BA, Affourtit JP, Egholm M, Henrissat B, Heath AC, Knight R, Gordon JI. A core gut microbiome in obese and lean twins. Nature. 2009 Jan 22;457(7228):480-4. Epub 2008 Nov 30.</citation>
    <PMID>19043404</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang T, Cai G, Qiu Y, Fei N, Zhang M, Pang X, Jia W, Cai S, Zhao L. Structural segregation of gut microbiota between colorectal cancer patients and healthy volunteers. ISME J. 2012 Feb;6(2):320-9. doi: 10.1038/ismej.2011.109. Epub 2011 Aug 18.</citation>
    <PMID>21850056</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Oral Microbiota</keyword>
  <keyword>Cigarette Smoking</keyword>
  <keyword>Tobacco- Related Cancer</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mouth Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Smoking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
