<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="148114">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02064387</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>117159</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02064387</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose Escalation Study to Investigate the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, Pharmacodynamics, Immunogenicity and Clinical Activity of GSK2857916</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Open-label, Dose Escalation Study to Investigate the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, Pharmacodynamics, Immunogenicity and Clinical Activity of the Antibody Drug Conjugate GSK2857916 in Subjects With Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma and Other Advanced Hematologic Malignancies Expressing BCMA</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will assess the safety, pharmacokinetic (PK), pharmacodynamic (PD) and the
      therapeutic potential of GSK2857916 in subjects with multiple myeloma (MM) and other
      hematologic malignancies that express B cell maturation antigen (BCMA). The hypothesis is
      that GSK2857916 can be safely administered to subjects with BCMA positive malignancies at
      doses where target engagement can be demonstrated.  This study will determine if adequate
      target engagement of BCMA receptors translates into clinical benefit for subjects with MM
      and other BCMA positive hematologic malignancies. The study will consists of two parts: a
      Part 1 dose escalation phase and a Part 2 expansion phase for safety, and clinical activity
      testing. The study will enroll a total of approximately 80 subjects with relapsed/refractory
      MM or other BCMA-expressing hematologic malignancies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events (AEs) following single and repeat dose administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 480 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>AEs will be collected from the time the first dose of study treatment is administered until 30 days following discontinuation of study treatment regardless of initiation of a new cancer therapy or transfer to hospice</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in vital sign parameters following single and repeat dose administration.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (screening) and up to approximately 480 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital sign parameters include: systolic and diastolic blood pressure, temperature, and pulse rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline clinical laboratory parameters following single and repeat dose administration.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (screening) and up to approximately 480 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Laboratory parameters include: homology, clinical chemistry, urinalysis and additional parameters as needed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite of PK parameters following single dose intravenous (IV) administration of GSK2857916</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 448 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>GSK2857916 and cys Monomethyl auristatin F (cys-mc MMAF) PK parameters include: area under the concentration-time curve (AUC), maximum plasma drug concentration (Cmax), time to Cmax (tmax), clearance (CL), volume of distribution at steady state (Vss), and terminal half life (t1/2). PK parameters will be assessed from plasma and urine samples collected over a period of time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite of PK parameters following repeat dose IV administration of GSK2857916</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 448 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>GSK2857916 and cys-mc MMAF PK parameters include: AUC, Cmax, tmax, CL, Vss and trough plasma concentration (Ctrough). PK parameters will be assessed from plasma and urine samples collected over a period of time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of anti-drug antibody (ADA) following single and repeat dose administration of GSK2857916</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 448 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood, bone marrow, and tumor tissue samples will be collected during this study and analysed pre and post GSK2857916.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ADA titre following single and repeat dose administration of GSK2857916</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 448 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood, bone marrow, and tumor tissue samples will be collected during this study and analysed pre and post GSK2857916.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate (ORR) following single and repeat dose administration of GSK2857916 as measure of clinical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 480 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>ORR is defined as follows: for MM; the percentage of participant achieving confirmed partial response or better (&gt;=PR). In addition, the percentage of subjects with minor response (MR) will be assessed for clinical benefit rate (CBR). For other Hematologic Malignancies; the percentage of participants achieving PR or better (&gt;=PR)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule 1 Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive GSK2857916 intravenously over 60 minutes (one dose) every 3 weeks (21 day cycle) for a maximum of 16 cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule 2 Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants may receive GSK2857916 intravenously over 60 minutes (one dose) once weekly for three consecutive weeks followed by 1 week of rest (28 day cycle) for a maximum of 16 cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule 1 Part 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the dose and schedule of GSK2857916 evaluated in Part 1 that is selected for further evaluation in Part 2 for up to 16 cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule 2 Part 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants may receive the dose and schedule of GSK2857916 evaluated in Part 1 that is selected for further evaluation in Part 2 for a maximum of 16 cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK2857916</intervention_name>
    <description>A clear or opalescent solution for IV infusion with unit dose strength of 20 mg/mililiter (mL) for multiple dose levels.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule 2 Part 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule 1 Part 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule 1 Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule 2 Part 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Provide signed written informed consent, which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form.

          -  Male or female, 18 years or older (at the time consent is obtained).

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1.

          -  Part 1/dose escalation; Histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of
             Multiple Myeloma in a subject who fulfills all of the following: has undergone stem
             cell transplant, or is considered transplant ineligible, has been pretreated with at
             least the 3 following classes of anti-myeloma drugs: alkylators, proteasome
             inhibitors and immunomodulators, has demonstrated progression on, or within 60 days
             of completion of the last therapy.

        Part 2 /MM cohort; Histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of: Multiple
        Myeloma in a subject who fulfills all of the following: has undergone stem cell
        transplant, or is considered transplant ineligible, has been pretreated with at least the
        3 following classes of anti-myeloma drugs: alkylators, proteasome inhibitors and
        immunomodulators, has demonstrated progression on, or within 60 days of completion of the
        last therapy, and has measurable disease with at least one of the following: serum
        M-protein &gt;=0.5 gram (g)/decilitre (dL) (&gt;=5 g/Litre (L)), urine M-protein &gt;=200 milligram
        (mg)/24hour (h).

        Serum free light chain (FLC) assay: Involved FLC level &gt;=5 mg/dL (&gt;=50 mg/L) and an
        abnormal serum FLC ratio (&lt;0.26 or &gt;1.65) and biopsy proven plasmacytoma (should be
        measured within 28 days of Screening Visit).

        Part 2/Other BCMA positive Hematologic Malignancies cohort: Subject with one of the
        following hematologic malignancies: Waldenstrom's Macroglobulinemia (WM), Diffuse Large
        B-cell Lymphoma (DLBCL) and chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) that exhibits positive BCMA
        expression on tumor cells by Immunohistochemistry (IHC).  The BCMA positivity is defined
        as having approximately 60% of tumor cells staining positive for BCMA, and the staining
        intensity must be &gt;=2 on IHC scale 0-3. Eligible subjects with BCMA positive malignancies
        must also fulfill the prior treatment requirements as follows: DLBCL and WM: at least 2
        prior lines of systemic therapy containing at least one line of chemo-immunotherapy with
        anti-CD20 antibody, and either has undergone stem cell transplant or is considered
        transplant ineligible. CLL: at least 2 prior lines of systemic therapies, and who are
        refractory to fludarabine, and failed (or are ineligible) for rituximab, ofatumumab and
        bendamustine.

          -  Subjects with a history of autologous stem cell transplant are eligible for study
             participation provided the following eligibility criteria are met: transplant was &gt;
             100 days prior to study enrolment, no active infection; subject meets the remainder
             of the eligibility criteria outlined in this protocol.

          -  Adequate organ system functions as defined below Absolute neutrophil
             count&gt;=1.0x10^9/L, hemoglobin&gt;=8.0 g/dL, platelet&gt;=50x10^9/L, international
             normalized ration (INR) &lt;=1.5, Partial thromboplastin time &lt;=1.5xupper limit of
             normal (ULN), total bilirubin &lt;=1.25xULN, alanine aminotransferase and aspartate
             aminotransferase&lt;=1.5 X ULN, serum creatinine or calculated creatinine
             clearance&lt;1.2XULN &gt;=60 mL/min for Part 1;&gt;=50 mL/minute (min) for Part 2 if data
             supports loosening criteria, Albuminuria&lt;=500 mg/24h, left ventricular ejection
             fraction &gt;=50%, Troponin&lt;=1xULN, Calcium&lt;=1.1xULN

          -  A female subject is eligible to participate if she is of: Non-childbearing potential
             or women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test within
             72 hours of first dose of study treatment and agree to use effective contraception
             during the study and for 60 days following the last dose of study treatment.

          -  Men with a female partner of childbearing potential must have either had a prior
             vasectomy or agree to use effective contraception from the time of first dose of
             study until 60 days after the last dose of study treatment to allow for clearance of
             any altered sperm

          -  All prior treatment-related toxicities (defined by National Cancer Institute- Common
             Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Events, version 4) must be &lt;=Grade 1 at the time of
             enrollment except for alopecia, and grade 2 neuropathy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Systemic anti-myeloma therapy within 14 days, or plasmapheresis within 7 days prior
             to the first dose of study drug

          -  Use of an investigational drug within 14 days or five half-lives, whichever is
             shorter, preceding the first dose of study drug.  Prior treatment with a monoclonal
             antibody within 30 days of receiving the first dose of study drug.

          -  History of an allogeneic stem cell transplant.  Subjects with a history of an
             autologous stem cell transplant are NOT excluded if they meet inclusion criteria
             related to history of autologous stem cell transplant.

          -  Presence of active renal condition (infection, requirement for dialysis or any other
             condition that could affect subject's safety). Subjects with isolated proteinuria
             resulting from MM are eligible, provided they fulfil the inclusion criteria related
             to organ system function.

          -  Evidence of active mucosal or internal bleeding

          -  Any major surgery within the last four weeks.

          -  Any serious and/or unstable pre-existing medical, psychiatric disorder, or other
             conditions (including lab abnormalities) that could interfere with subject's safety,
             obtaining informed consent or compliance to the study procedures.

          -  Known active infection requiring antibiotic treatment

          -  Evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic diseases (e.g., unstable or uncompensated
             respiratory, hepatic, renal or cardiac disease

          -  Subjects with previous or concurrent malignancies are allowed only if the second
             tumor is not contributing to the subject's illness.  The subject must not be
             receiving active therapy, other than hormonal therapy for this disease and the
             disease must be considered medically stable for at least 2 years.

          -  Evidence of cardiovascular risk including any of the following: QT interval
             corrected&gt;=470 millisecond, evidence of current clinically significant uncontrolled
             arrhythmias, history of myocardial infarction, acute coronary syndromes (including
             unstable angina), coronary angioplasty, or stenting or bypass grafting within six
             months of Screening, Class III or IV heart failure as defined by the New York Heart
             Association functional classification system, uncontrolled hypertension, subjects
             with intra-cardiac defibrillators or permanent pacemakers, abnormal cardiac valve
             morphology (&gt;=grade 2) documented by echocardiogram (subjects with grade 1
             abnormalities [i.e., mild regurgitation/stenosis] can be entered on study).  Subjects
             with moderate valvular thickening should not be entered on study.

          -  Known immediate or delayed hypersensitivity reaction or idiosyncrasy to drugs
             chemically related to GSK2857916 or any of the components of the study treatment.

          -  Pregnant or lactating female.

          -  Known human immuno virus infection.

          -  Subjects with positive test for Hepatitis B surface (HBS-Ag) or Hepatitis B core
             (HBc)antigen

          -  Subjects with positive test for hepatitis C (HCV) infection are excluded regardless
             of viral load.  If hepatitis C antibody test is positive, a confirmatory Recombinant
             immunoblot assay (RIBA) test should be performed.  If the RIBA test is negative,
             subject is eligible for this trial

          -  Current active liver or biliary disease (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or
             asymptomatic gallstones, liver metastases or otherwise stable chronic liver disease
             per investigator's assessment).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 1, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 13, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple Myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>BCMA-expressing Advanced Hematologic Malignancies</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
