<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="84082">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02039349</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140042</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-AA-0042</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02039349</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Novel Compound for Alcoholism Treatment</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Novel Compound for Alcoholism Treatment: A Translational Strategy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Advancing Translational Science (NCATS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Rhode Island</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Hormones are naturally occurring chemicals in your body. Ghrelin is a hormone that is
      mainly produced by the stomach and stimulates appetite. Some studies suggest it may
      stimulate alcohol craving and use. Drugs have been developed that block ghrelin. Researchers
      want to know if people can tolerate a particular drug that blocks ghrelin. It will be given
      at two dose levels, combined with alcohol.

      Objective:

      - To determine if a drug that may decrease alcohol consumption when given along with alcohol
      is safe and tolerable.

      Eligibility:

        -  Healthy adults 21   65 years old who have 14 (women) to 21 (men) drinks a week.

        -  No one of childbearing potential can participate.

      Design:

        -  Participants will have 3 inpatient clinic visits; each will last 4 days.

        -  They will have physical exam and blood and urine tests.

        -  They will have breath tests for alcohol and smoking.

        -  They will answer health and mood questions.

        -  Researchers will measure their reaction to smelling alcohol and tasting a sweet drink.

        -  They will eat only the food provided by the clinic. They will keep a food diary 1 day
           before each stay.

        -  They will be randomly assigned to take the study drug or placebo 5 times each stay.

        -  On Day 3, they will drink alcohol after taking the drug. They will give many blood
           samples that day through a tube inserted in their skin.

        -  Smokers can take smoke breaks. Once, they will smoke a cigarette through a device.

        -  One week after the last stay, participants will have a follow-up visit to answer
           questions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: Ghrelin is a 28-aminoacid peptide that stimulates appetite and food intake. It is
      an endogenous ligand for the growth hormone secretagogue receptor (GHSR1a). Preclinical
      studies suggest that ghrelin modulates alcohol reward processing. Furthermore, findings from
      a translational human lab study at Brown University (PI: Leggio) indicate that intravenous
      (IV) ghrelin administration, compared to placebo, results in an acute increase in craving
      for alcohol during a cue-reactivity experiment in alcoholic individuals. Therefore, an
      orally bioavailable, ghrelin receptor antagonist, that can pass through the blood brain
      barrier holds particular promise as an AD treatment.

      This project has been recently funded by NCATS. The goals of this protocol are to generate
      preliminary evidence on the safety and efficacy of a ghrelin receptor antagonist (GHSR1a
      antagonist), PF-05190457, an existing molecule available under the NIH-Industry Pilot
      Program at NCATS.

      Study population: Non-treatment seeking heavy drinkers (n =15). The study will be conducted
      in the Inpatient Unit at the NIAAA Intramural Clinical Program.

      Study Design: Single-blind dose-escalating placebo-controlled inpatient study using
      PF-05190457, in non-treatment seeking heavy drinking subjects. This Phase 1b study will be a
      within-subject design.

      Outcome measures: Primary objectives will be to determine: 1) the number of adverse events
      (AEs) experienced, compared between all three PF-05190457 dose categories (0mg or placebo,
      50mg, and 100mg b.i.d.); and 2) the total concentration of the drug, compared between the
      two non-placebo drug doses (50mg and 100mg b.i.d.), when co-administered with alcohol. We
      hypothesize that both doses of PF-05190457, as compared to placebo, will not result in an
      increased number of AEs. As a secondary objective, we will determine whether PF-05190457
      dose-dependently affects the subjective effects of alcohol and craving. We will include
      pharmacokinetics (PK) and pharmacodynamic (PD) investigations conducted at University of
      Rhode Island (URI; Associate Investigator: Akhlaghi). The PK/PD component will include (i)
      measuring total, unbound or tissue concentrations of the drug using liquid chromatography
      tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS) and evaluation of biomarkers of effect and (ii)
      estimation of PK and PD parameters by the use of conventional and semi-mechanistic modeling
      approaches to assist in identifying an optimal dosing regimen of the drug in AD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Single Blind, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Side effects/adverse events and maximum tolerated dose of PF-05190457 alone and in combination with alcohol administration.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcoholism</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol-Related Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol Dependence</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol Drinking Related Problems</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol Drinking</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PF-05190457</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Males or females 21-65 years old (inclusive);

          -  Heavy drinking defined as on average at least 21 drinks per week for men or at least
             14 drinks for women based on the timeline follow-back (TLFB) done at screening.

          -  Be in good health as confirmed by medical history, physical examination, ECG,
             blood/urine lab tests;

          -  Female subjects must be of non childbearing potential as defined by at least one of
             the following criteria:

               1. Females 45     65 years old, who are menopausal, defined as follows:

                    -  Females who are between 45     55 years old: they will be considered
                       menopausal if they satisfy all the following three requirements during
                       screening: 1) they are in amenorrhea, defined as absence of menstruation
                       for the previous 12 months; 2) they have a negative urine pregnancy test;
                       and 3) they have a serum FSH level within the laboratory   s reference
                       range for postmenopausal females.

                    -  Females who are between 56     65 years old: they will be considered
                       menopausal if they are in amenorrhea, defined as absence of menstruation
                       for the previous 12 months before screening.

        OR

          -  Females 21-65 years old, who have a documented hysterectomy and/or bilateral
             oophorectomy.

          -  All other female subjects (including females with tubal ligations and females that do
             NOT have a documented hysterectomy) will be considered to be of childbearing
             potential.

          -  Male subjects must use one of the following methods of contraception from the first
             dose of study medication and until 28 days after dosing:

          -  Abstinence.

          -  A condom AND one of the following:

               -  Vasectomy for more than 6 months.

               -  Female partner who meets one of the following conditions:

                    -  Has had a tubal ligation, hysterectomy, or bilateral oophorectomy;

                    -  Is post menopausal;

                    -  Uses one of the following forms of contraception:

                         -  Copper or hormonal containing IUD;

                         -  Spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/suppository;

                         -  Diaphragm with spermicide;

                         -  Oral contraceptive;

                         -  Injectable progesterone;

                         -  Subdermal implant.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Interest in receiving treatment for heavy drinking.

          -  Current DSM-IV diagnosis (based on SCID) of substance dependence (other than
             nicotine); a negative urine drug screen will also be required.

          -  DSM-IV Axis I criteria for a lifetime diagnosis of schizophrenia, bipolar disorder,
             or other psychoses;

          -  Active illness within the past 6 months of the screening visit that meet the DSM-IV
             criteria for a diagnosis of major depressive disorder or anxiety disorder; subjects
             with a history of attempted suicide will be excluded;

          -  Clinically significant medical abnormalities (e.g., unstable hypertension, clinically
             significant EKG abnormalities, Creatinine greater than or equal to 2 mg/dL, liver
             cirrhosis, AST or ALT &gt;  3x the upper normal limit, hemoglobin &lt; 10.5 g/dl);

          -  Heart rate &gt; 100 at screening on two separate measurements given potential of study
             medication to increase heart rate.

             i) Females who are between 45     55 years old: they will be considered menopausal if
             they satisfy all the following three requirements during screening: 1) they are in
             amenorrhea, defined as absence of menstruation for the previous 12 months; 2) they
             have a negative urine pregnancy test; and 3) they have a serum FSH level within the
             laboratory   s reference range for postmenopausal females.

        ii) Females who are between 56     65 years old: they will be considered menopausal if
        they are in amenorrhea, defined as absence of menstruation for the previous 12 months
        before screening.

        OR

        b) Females 21-65 years old, who have a documented hysterectomy and/or bilateral
        oophorectomy.

        All other female subjects (including females with tubal ligations and females that do NOT
        have a documented hysterectomy) will be considered to be of childbearing potential.

          -  Male subjects must use one of the following methods of contraception from the first
             dose of study medication and until 28 days after dosing:

               1. Abstinence.

               2. A condom AND one of the following:

                  Vasectomy for more than 6 months.

                  Female partner who meets one of the following conditions:

                  Has had a tubal ligation, hysterectomy, or bilateral oophorectomy;

                  Is post menopausal;

                  Uses one of the following forms of contraception:

                  Copper or hormonal containing IUD;

                  Spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/suppository;

                  Diaphragm with spermicide;

                  Oral contraceptive;

                  Injectable progesterone;

                  Subdermal implant.

                  EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Interest in receiving treatment for heavy drinking.

          -  Current DSM-IV diagnosis (based on SCID) of substance dependence (other than alcohol
             and/or nicotine); a negative urine drug screen will also be required.

          -  DSM-IV Axis I criteria for a lifetime diagnosis of schizophrenia, bipolar disorder,
             or other psychoses;

          -  Active illness within the past 6 months of the screening visit that meet the DSM-IV
             criteria for a diagnosis of major depressive disorder or anxiety disorder; subjects
             with a history of attempted suicide will be excluded;

          -  Clinically significant medical abnormalities (e.g., unstable hypertension, clinically
             significant EKG abnormalities, Creatinine greater than or equal to 2 mg/dL, liver
             cirrhosis, AST or ALT &gt;  3 times the upper normal limit, hemoglobin &lt; 10.5 g/dl);

          -  Heart rate &gt; 100 at screening on two separate measurements given potential of study
             medication to increase heart rate.

          -  BMI less than or equal to 18.5 or anorexia given potential of the study medication to
             reduce appetite.

          -  BMI greater than or equal to 35 kg/m(2).

          -  Not advisable to abstain from using psychotropic medications, i.e. naltrexone,
             acamprosate, alcohol dehydrogenase inhibitors, topiramate, gabapentin, ondansetron,
             benzodiazepines, beta-blockers, H2-blockers, and alpha-1 blockers,  baclofen, and
             barbiturates, in addition to nonprescription drugs, dietary/herbal supplements, and
             hormone replacement therapy within 2 weeks of the study medication.

          -  History of epilepsy or alcohol-related seizures;

          -  patients who have diabetes and/or are treated with any drug with glucose lowering
             properties such as sulfonylurea, insulin, metformin, thiazolidinediones (TZD),
             Dipeptidyl peptidase-4(DPP4) inhibitors, or Glucagon-like peptide-1(GLP-1)agonists
             (due to the glucose-lowering properties of PF-05190457 observed in healthy
             volunteers);

          -  History of alcohol-induced flushing reactions.

          -  Clinically significant alcohol withdrawal symptoms, as assessed by a CIWA-Ar score &gt;
             8 at screening.

          -  Any other reason or clinical condition for which the PI or the MAI will consider
             unsafe for a possible participant to participate in this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lorenzo Leggio, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lorenzo Leggio, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-9398</phone>
    <email>leggiol@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-AA-0042.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Addolorato G, Capristo E, Leggio L, Ferrulli A, Abenavoli L, Malandrino N, Farnetti S, Domenicali M, D'Angelo C, Vonghia L, Mirijello A, Cardone S, Gasbarrini G. Relationship between ghrelin levels, alcohol craving, and nutritional status in current alcoholic patients. Alcohol Clin Exp Res. 2006 Nov;30(11):1933-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17067359</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Addolorato G, Leggio L, Agabio R, Colombo G, Gasbarrini G. Baclofen: a new drug for the treatment of alcohol dependence. Int J Clin Pract. 2006 Aug;60(8):1003-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16893442</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Addolorato G, Leggio L, Ferrulli A, Cardone S, Vonghia L, Mirijello A, Abenavoli L, D'Angelo C, Caputo F, Zambon A, Haber PS, Gasbarrini G. Effectiveness and safety of baclofen for maintenance of alcohol abstinence in alcohol-dependent patients with liver cirrhosis: randomised, double-blind controlled study. Lancet. 2007 Dec 8;370(9603):1915-22.</citation>
    <PMID>18068515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 3, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 15, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alcoholism</keyword>
  <keyword>Ghrelin</keyword>
  <keyword>Ghrelin Antagonism</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Alcohol Drinking</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcohol-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
