<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="85666">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01863550</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E1A11</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-02608</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA021115</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01863550</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bortezomib or Carfilzomib With Lenalidomide and Dexamethasone in Treating Patients With Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Phase III Trial of Bortezomib, Lenalidomide and Dexamethasone (VRd) Versus Carfilzomib, Lenalidomide, Dexamethasone (CRd) Followed by Limited or Indefinite Lenalidomide Maintenance in Patients With Newly Diagnosed Symptomatic Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized phase III trial studies bortezomib, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone to see
      how well it works compared to carfilzomib, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone in treating
      patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma. Bortezomib and carfilzomib may stop the
      growth of cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Drugs used in
      chemotherapy, such as lenalidomide and dexamethasone, work in different ways to stop the
      growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing.
      Giving bortezomib or carfilzomib together with lenalidomide and dexamethasone may kill more
      cancer cells
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To compare the overall survival between two strategies of lenalidomide maintenance
      following induction with a proteasome inhibitor-IMiD (lenalidomide) combination: limited
      duration of maintenance (24 months) versus indefinite maintenance therapy until disease
      progression.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To compare the progression-free survival between two strategies of lenalidomide
      maintenance following induction with a proteasome inhibitor-IMiD combination: limited
      duration of maintenance (24 months) or indefinite maintenance therapy until disease
      progression.

      II. To compare progression-free survival between bortezomib, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone
      (VRd) and carfilzomib, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone (CRd) induction followed by
      lenalidomide maintenance in patients with newly diagnosed symptomatic multiple myeloma.

      III. To compare induction rates of response between VRd and CRd arms. IV. To evaluate time
      to progression, duration of response and overall survival between VRd and CRd induction
      therapy.

      V. To compare induction rates of toxicity between VRd and CRd arms. VI. To evaluate toxicity
      during lenalidomide maintenance.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To compare the short and long-term health-related quality of life impact between two
      strategies of lenalidomide maintenance following induction with a proteasome inhibitor-IMiD
      combination: limited duration of maintenance (24 months) versus indefinite maintenance
      therapy until disease progression.

      II. To compare the impact on health-related quality of life between VRd and CRd induction
      therapy.

      III. To evaluate the association between early induction response and change in
      health-related quality of life.

      IV. To describe changes in health-related quality of life during the induction, active
      maintenance and observation phases.

      V. To evaluate correlation between treatment adherence during maintenance and health-related
      quality of life.

      VI. To compare induction minimal residual disease negativity rates between VRd and CRd arms.

      VII. To compare minimal residual disease negativity rates between two strategies of
      lenalidomide maintenance following induction with a proteasome inhibitor-IMiD combination:
      limited duration of maintenance (24 months) versus indefinite maintenance therapy until
      disease progression.

      VIII. To describe changes in minimal residual disease during the induction, active
      maintenance and observation phases and explore association with response.

      IX. To evaluate gene expression profiles of tumor cells at baseline among standard risk
      patients and explore the development of a prognostic gene expression signature for standard
      risk myeloma.

      X. To evaluate changes in gene expression profiles of tumor cells following treatment and
      elucidate response and resistance mechanisms.

      OUTLINE:

      INDUCTION: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms.

      ARM A: Patients receive bortezomib subcutaneously (SC) or intravenously (IV) on days 1, 4,
      8, and 11 of courses 1-8 and days 1 and 8 of courses 9-12; lenalidomide orally (PO) daily on
      days 1-14; and dexamethasone PO daily on days 1, 2, 4, 5, 8, 9, 11, and 12 of courses 1-8
      and days 1, 2, 8, and 9 of courses 9-12. Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for 12 courses in
      the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM B: Patients receive carfilzomib IV over 30 minutes on days 1, 2, 8, 9, 15, and 16;
      lenalidomide PO daily on days 1-21; and dexamethasone PO on days 1, 8, 15, and 22. Treatment
      repeats every 4 weeks for 9 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
      toxicity.

      MAINTENANCE: After completion of induction therapy, patients are then randomized to 1 of 2
      maintenance treatment arms.

      ARM C: Patients receive lenalidomide PO daily on days 1-21. Treatment repeats every 4 weeks
      for 24 courses in the absences of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM D: Patients receive lenalidomide PO daily on days 1-21. Courses repeat every 4 weeks in
      the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 3 months for 2 years,
      every 6 months for 3 years, and then annually for 10 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival for the maintenance analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From the maintenance randomization to death due to any cause or, censored at the date last known alive, assessed up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Kaplan-Meier (KM) method will be used to describe the overall survival function by arm.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival for the maintenance analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From the maintenance randomization until the earlier of progression or death due to any cause, assessed up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Weighted Cox regression will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival for the induction analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From the induction randomization until the earlier of progression or death due to any cause, assessed up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Kaplan-Meier method will be used to describe the progression-free survival function by arm using all data while ignoring maintenance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival for the induction analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From induction randomization to death due to any cause, or censored at the date last known alive, assessed up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The KM method will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rates including partial response (PR), very good partial response (VGPR), immunofixation negative complete response (IF-CR) and complete response (CR)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2.8 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be compared between induction arms using Fisher's exact test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rates including PR, VGPR, IF-CR and CR</measure>
    <time_frame>At 8.3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be compared between induction arms using Fisher's exact test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression (TTP) for the induction analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From the induction randomization to progression, or censored at the date of last disease evaluation for those without progression reported, assessed up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>TTP distributions will be estimated by induction arm using Kaplan-Meier methods.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response (DOR) for the induction analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From first objective response (partial response or better) since induction randomization until the earlier of progression or death due to any cause, or censored at date of last disease evaluation for those without events reported, assessed up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Duration of response will be estimated using Kaplan-Meier methods in the subset of patients achieving partial response or better while on induction therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of overall grade 3 or higher non-hematologic toxicity and grade 3 or higher toxicity by type during induction, active maintenance and observation phases using CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Fisher's exact test will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of grade 2 or higher peripheral neuropathy and cardiac toxicity during induction phase assessed using CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 36 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Fisher's exact test will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Neurotoxicity Trial Outcome Index (FACT-Ntx TOI) for the transition to maintenance analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From week 36 (the end) of induction therapy to week 24 (end of course 6) of maintenance therapy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be analyzed using linear mixed models.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the FACT-Ntx TOI for the short-term maintenance analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From the end of 2 years of maintenance to 3 years post maintenance randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be analyzed using linear mixed models.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the FACT-Ntx TOI for the long-term maintenance analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From the end of 2 years of maintenance to 5 years post maintenance randomization</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be analyzed using linear mixed models.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the FACT-Ntx TOI for the end of induction analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline (induction randomization) to 36 weeks (end) of induction therapy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be analyzed using linear mixed models.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the FACT-Ntx TOI for the early induction analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline (induction randomization) to 2.8 months of induction therapy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be analyzed using linear mixed models.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels and changes from related start of induction, active maintenance and observation phases</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be analyzed using linear mixed models.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to worsening of FACT-Ntx TOI for the induction analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From the baseline assessment at induction randomization to a decrease of 7 points, assessed up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be analyzed with KM methods and Cox regression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to worsening of Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Multiple Myeloma (FACT-MM) for the maintenance analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From the baseline assessment at maintenance randomization to a decrease of 4 points, assessed up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be analyzed with KM methods and Cox regression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">756</enrollment>
  <condition>Stage I Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Stage II Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (bortezomib, lenalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive bortezomib SC or IV on days 1, 4, 8, and 11 of courses 1-8 and days 1 and 8 of courses 9-12; lenalidomide PO daily on days 1-14; and dexamethasone PO daily on days 1, 2, 4, 5, 8, 9, 11, and 12 of courses 1-8 and days 1, 2, 8, and 9 of courses 9-12. Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for 12 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (carfilzomib, lenalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive carfilzomib IV over 30 minutes on days 1, 2, 8, 9, 15, and 16; lenalidomide PO daily on days 1-21; and dexamethasone PO on days 1, 8, 15, and 22. Treatment repeats every 4 weeks for 9 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (lenalidomide)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive lenalidomide PO daily on days 1-21. Treatment repeats every 4 weeks for 24 courses in the absences of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm D (lenalidomide)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive lenalidomide PO daily on days 1-21. Courses repeat every 4 weeks in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bortezomib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given SC or IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (bortezomib, lenalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LDP 341</other_name>
    <other_name>MLN341</other_name>
    <other_name>VELCADE</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (bortezomib, lenalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (carfilzomib, lenalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (lenalidomide)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm D (lenalidomide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CC-5013</other_name>
    <other_name>IMiD-1</other_name>
    <other_name>Revlimid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (bortezomib, lenalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (carfilzomib, lenalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Aeroseb-Dex</other_name>
    <other_name>Decaderm</other_name>
    <other_name>Decadron</other_name>
    <other_name>DM</other_name>
    <other_name>DXM</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>carfilzomib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (carfilzomib, lenalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kyprolis</other_name>
    <other_name>PR-171</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>quality-of-life assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (bortezomib, lenalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (carfilzomib, lenalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (lenalidomide)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm D (lenalidomide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>quality of life assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Optional correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (bortezomib, lenalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (carfilzomib, lenalidomide, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (lenalidomide)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm D (lenalidomide)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  STEP I: Patients must be diagnosed with symptomatic standard-risk multiple myeloma
             (SR-MM) as defined by all of the following:

               -  No evidence of t(4;14), t(14;16),t(14;20), or deletion 17p on fluorescent in
                  situ hybridization (FISH)

               -  Standard risk gene expression profile (GEP)70 signature (only if GEP has been
                  done and results are available)

               -  Serum lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) =&lt; 2 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  No more than 20% circulating plasma cells on white blood cell (WBC) differential
                  or 2,000 plasma cells/microliter of peripheral blood

          -  STEP I: Patients must have measurable or evaluable disease as defined by having one
             or more of the following:

               -  &gt;= 1g/dL monoclonal protein (M-protein) on serum protein electrophoresis

               -  &gt;= 200 mg/24 hrs of monoclonal protein on a 24 hour urine protein
                  electrophoresis

               -  Involved free light chain &gt;= 10 mg/dL AND abnormal serum immunoglobulin kappa to
                  lambda free light chain ratio (&lt; 0.26 or &gt; 1.65)

               -  Monoclonal bone marrow plasmacytosis &gt;= 30% (evaluable disease)

               -  Serum protein electrophoresis (SPEP), urine protein electrophoresis (UPEP), and
                  serum free light chain (FLC) assay, or bone marrow biopsy and or aspirate are
                  required to be performed within 28 days prior to randomization

                    -  NOTE: UPEP (on a 24-hour collection) is required, no substitute method is
                       acceptable; urine must be followed monthly if the baseline urine M-spike is
                       &gt;= 200 mg/24 hr; please note that if both serum and urine M-components are
                       present, both must be followed in order to evaluate response

                    -  NOTE: The serum free light chain test is required to be done if the patient
                       does not have measurable disease in the serum or urine; measurable disease
                       in the serum is defined as having a serum M-spike &gt;= 1 g/dL; measurable
                       disease in the urine is defined as having a urine M-spike &gt;= 200mg/24 hr

          -  STEP I: Hemoglobin &gt;= 8 g/dL

          -  STEP I: Untransfused platelet count &gt;= 75,000 cells/mm^3

          -  STEP I: Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1000 cells/mm^3

          -  STEP I: Calculated creatinine clearance &gt;= 30 mL/min

          -  STEP I: Bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 mg/dL

          -  STEP I: Serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase (SGPT) (alanine aminotransferase [ALT])
             and serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT) (aspartate aminotransferase [AST])
             &lt; 2.5 times the upper limit of normal

          -  STEP I: Patients must have received no more than one cycle (4 weeks or less) of prior
             chemotherapy and no more than 160mg of prior dexamethasone for treatment of
             symptomatic myeloma; they should not have been exposed to lenalidomide, bortezomib or
             carfilzomib for treatment of symptomatic myeloma; prior radiation therapy to
             symptomatic lesions is allowed provided 14 days have elapsed from the completion of
             radiation therapy

          -  STEP I: Prior systemic glucocorticoid use for the treatment of non-malignant
             disorders is permitted; prior or concurrent topical or localized glucocorticoid
             therapy to treat non-malignant comorbid disorders is permitted; note: concurrent use
             after registration on the study should be restricted to the equivalent of prednisone
             10 mg per day

          -  STEP I: Patients must not have active, uncontrolled seizure disorder; patients must
             have had no seizures in the last 6 months

          -  STEP I: Patients must not have uncontrolled intercurrent illness including
             uncontrolled hypertension, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina,
             uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia, uncontrolled psychiatric illness or social situation
             that would limit compliance with the study, or a prior history of Stevens Johnson
             Syndrome

          -  STEP I: Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (PS) 0, 1, or 2
             (PS 3 allowed if secondary to pain)

          -  STEP I: Patients with monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance or
             asymptomatic multiple myeloma are not eligible

          -  STEP I: Patients must not have grade 2 or higher peripheral neuropathy by Common
             Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) 4.0

          -  STEP I: Patients must not have active, uncontrolled infection

          -  STEP I: Patients may have a history of current or previous deep vein thrombosis or
             pulmonary embolism but must be willing to take some form of anti-coagulation as
             prophylaxis if they are not currently on full-dose anticoagulation

          -  STEP I: Patients should not have New York Heart Association classification III or IV
             heart failure or myocardial infarction within the previous 6 months

          -  STEP I: Patients with a history of prior malignancy are eligible provided they were
             treated with curative intent and do not require active therapy (currently treated
             basal cell, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, or carcinoma &quot;insitu&quot; of the cervix
             or breast are not excluded)

          -  STEP I: Females of childbearing potential (FCBP) must have a negative serum or urine
             pregnancy test with a sensitivity of at least 50 mIU/mL within 10-14 days prior to
             and again within 24 hours of starting lenalidomide and must either commit to
             continued abstinence from heterosexual intercourse or begin TWO acceptable methods of
             birth control, one highly effective method and one additional effective method AT THE
             SAME TIME, at least 28 days before she starts taking lenalidomide; FCBP must also
             agree to ongoing pregnancy testing; men must agree to use a latex condom during
             sexual contact with a FCBP even if they have had a successful vasectomy; all patients
             must be counseled at a minimum of every 28 days about pregnancy precautions and risks
             of fetal exposure

          -  STEP I: Sexually active males must be willing to use a condom (even if they have
             undergone a prior vasectomy) while having intercourse, while taking lenalidomide and
             for 4 weeks after stopping treatment

          -  STEP I: The following patients will be excluded:

               -  Pregnant women

               -  Nursing women

          -  STEP I: Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection is not excluded; known HIV
             positive patients must meet the following criteria:

               -  Cluster of differentiation (CD(4 cell count &gt;= 350/mm^3

               -  No history of acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS)-related illness

               -  Not currently prescribed zidovudine or stavudine

          -  STEP I: Patient enrolling to this study must agree to register to the mandatory
             RevAssist program, and be willing and able to comply with the requirements of
             RevAssist

          -  STEP I: Patients must be willing to provide biological samples as required by the
             study

          -  STEP II: Patients must not have experienced progression on step 1 induction therapy

          -  STEP II: Step 2 registration must be within 28 days of completing step 1 therapy

          -  STEP II: Patients must not have received any non-protocol therapy outside of the
             assigned induction therapy

          -  STEP II: ECOG performance status 0, 1, or 2 (PS 3 allowed if secondary to pain)

          -  STEP II: Any adverse event related to step 1 therapy must have resolved to grade 2 or
             less

          -  STEP II: Hemoglobin &gt;= 8 g/dL

          -  STEP II: Platelet count &gt;= 75,000 cells/mm^3

          -  STEP II: Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1000 cells/mm^3

          -  STEP II: Calculated creatinine clearance &gt;= 30 mL/min

          -  STEP II: Bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 mg/dL

          -  STEP II: SGPT (ALT) and SGOT (AST) &lt; 2.5 times the upper limit of normal

          -  STEP II: FCBP must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test with a sensitivity
             of at least 50 mIU/mL within 10-14 days prior to and again within 24 hours of
             starting lenalidomide and must either commit to continued abstinence from
             heterosexual intercourse or begin TWO acceptable methods of birth control, one highly
             effective method and one additional effective method AT THE SAME TIME, at least 28
             days before she starts taking lenalidomide; FCBP must also agree to ongoing pregnancy
             testing; men must agree to use a latex condom during sexual contact with a FCBP even
             if they have had a successful vasectomy; all patients must be counseled at a minimum
             of every 28 days about pregnancy precautions and risks of fetal exposure

          -  STEP II: Sexually active males must be willing to use a condom (even if they have
             undergone a prior vasectomy) while having intercourse, while taking lenalidomide and
             for 4 weeks after stopping treatment

          -  STEP II: The following patients will be excluded:

               -  Pregnant women

               -  Nursing women

          -  STEP II: Patient enrolling to this study must agree to register to the mandatory
             RevAssist program and be willing and able to comply with the requirements of
             RevAssist
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shaji Kumar</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shaji K. Kumar</last_name>
      <phone>507-538-7623</phone>
      <email>kumar.shaji@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Shaji K. Kumar</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone 21-phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bortezomib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
