<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="38366">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01708122</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13623-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UL1TR000124</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01708122</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intranasal Fentanyl as an Analgesic for Cystoscopic Procedures</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Randomized, Double Blind Study Comparing the Efficacy and Safety of Fentanyl Nasal Spray to Placebo as an Analgesic, in Patients Undergoing Outpatient Cystoscopic Procedures</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Los Angeles Biomedical Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Los Angeles Biomedical Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the efficacy of intranasally-administrated fentanyl
      spray to decrease the pain during cystoscopy (the passage of a telescopic instrument into
      the bladder for purpose of diagnosing the cause of blood in the urine, urinary complaints or
      any other problems with the urinary bladder). The current standard practice is to use
      Lidocaine jelly (a local anesthetic) given through the urethra to lubricate and decrease
      pain. In this study, an additional medicine (fentanyl) is used to reduce pain that occurs
      during and after the above procedure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this double-blind study, a nasal spray of either the drug (fentanyl -- an opioid
      analgesic) or placebo (normal saline) is administered before the procedure. There is a 50%
      chance that patients receive the drug or the placebo. In either case, local Lidocaine jelly
      is used as an anesthetic in the urethra. Each patient is compensated for time and traveling
      after the completion of his/her participation.

      Patients are asked to arrive between 7 and 11 PM on the evening prior to their procedure for
      an overnight admission to 5 East ward, on the 5th floor of the Harbor UCLA Medical Center in
      Torrance, California, United States. Once there, vital signs (blood pressure, pulse, oxygen
      saturation -- amount of oxygen in the blood, and breathing rate) is checked and an
      intravenous line is placed. Before, during and after the procedure, patients are asked to
      rate their pain on a scale of 0 to 10 with 0 being &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 being &quot;the worst pain
      possible.&quot;

      Regardless of whether patients are assigned to receive fentanyl or placebo, they receive the
      standard of care for this cystoscopic procedure.

      Once in the cystoscopy room, patients receive the study drug by nasal (into the nose) spray.
      The study drug is supplied in a pre-filled syringe that contains either 100 mcg of fentanyl
      or placebo (normal saline with no active medicine in it). Once the study drug is given, the
      vital signs are closely monitored(checked) until the effect of drug wears off, usually
      between 2 and 4 hours.

      Blood samples are drawn on several occasions. This blood is used to see how much of the
      study drug (fentanyl or placebo) appears in the blood.

      Adverse effects: The well-known adverse effects of opioids may occur after nasal as well as
      conventional routes of administration; however, severe adverse effects such as respiratory
      depression or hypotension do not seem to occur in any appreciable frequency.

      Intranasal fentanyl has been used safely and effectively in many studies. There are no
      reports of any serious side effects with the small dose (100 mcg) that is being used in this
      study. Intranasal fentanyl is generally well tolerated with no serious adverse events. In
      cancer patients treated for breakthrough pain, the main treatment related side effects were
      nausea, vertigo, dizziness, constipation, and somnolence. For local side effects, fentanyl
      displays little local irritation, nasal discomfort or taste experiences. Nasal irritation,
      skin pain, nasal mucosa ulcers and dysgeusia have been occasionally reported as minor side
      effects.

      The following minor side effects have been reported with other forms of fentanyl (oral,
      patch or intravenous): anxiety; confusion; difficulty walking; dizziness; drowsiness; dry
      mouth; headache; itching; nausea and vomiting.

      The following severe side effects have not been reported with intranasal fentanyl but have
      been reported with other forms of fentanyl (oral, patch or intravenous): allergic reactions
      (rash; hives; difficulty breathing; tightness in the chest; swelling of the mouth, face,
      lips, or tongue); excessive dizziness; excessive drowsiness; fainting; fatigue;
      hallucinations; muscle rigidity; seizures; shock (changes in skin color); slow heartbeat;
      respiratory depression or slowed breathing; trouble breathing and feeling of weakness.

      Advantages to patients:  If effective, less pain during and after the cystoscopic procedure
      and better tolerance of the procedure.

      Advantages to humanity: If effective, nasal fentanyl could be used as a means to reduce pain
      before and during cystoscopic procedures.

      These benefits may not happen and unexpected side effects may develop.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>0 - 10 Pain Numerical Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre, during and after procedure.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The NRS pain assessment (0 = no pain to 10 = worst possible pain) is recorded three times as outlined below:
baseline pain score at admission, when the subject checks in,
upon entry of the cystoscope into the urethral meatus,
2. and thirty minutes after the cystoscopic procedure has been completed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>O2 Saturation.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, and every 15 minutes until 3 hours post drug-administration.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>After administration of the study drug, the subject is monitored (pulse rate, blood pressure, respiratory rate and oxygen saturation), for any signs of respiratory depression or the presence of complications or side-effects including apnea or oxygen desaturation. O2 saturation is recorded every 15 minutes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive 100 mcg intranasal fentanyl in 0.1 mL solution.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive 0.1 mL of intranasal saline as placebo.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fentanyl</intervention_name>
    <description>100 mcg in 0.1 mL intranasal spray</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>fentanyl citrate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>saline</intervention_name>
    <description>Sodium Chloride 0.9% intranasal spray</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>normal saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        1. Urological indications for cystoscopic procedure.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of analgesia abuse or former opioid addiction.

          2. Allergy to fentanyl.

          3. Acute/chronic nasal problems such as rhinitis or sinusitis.

          4. Positive urine pregnancy test / lactation.

          5. Acute bronchial asthma / upper airway obstruction.

          6. Presence of bradycardia or a history of seizures.

          7. Concomitant use of drugs that inhibit CYP3A4 (e.g., ritonavir, ketoconazole,
             itraconazole, troleandomycin, clarithromycin, nelfinavir, nefazodone, amprenavir,
             aprepitant, diltiazem, erythromycin, fluconazole, fosamprenavir, MAO inhibitors and
             verapamil)

          8. 0-10 NRS pain score more than 3 on baseline.

          9. Any situation or condition which, in the investigator's opinion, puts the subject at
             significant risk, or could confound the study results.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Reznichek, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harbor UCLA Medical Center Urology Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torrance</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90502</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 15, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 30, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Los Angeles Biomedical Research Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Richard C Reznichek, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intranasal fentanyl</keyword>
  <keyword>Cystoscopy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Analgesics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fentanyl</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
