<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="168005">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01694199</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RBI.2012.003.P.2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01694199</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Multicenter, Randomized, Sham-Controlled, Double-Blinded Study to Evaluate the Analgesic Efficacy and Safety of Pulsed Radiofrequency Energy (PRFE) in Bunionectomy Surgery for the Treatment of Post-Operative Pain</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Regenesis Biomedical, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Regenesis Biomedical, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The clinical study's primary objective is to compare the overall analgesic effect of the
      Provant Therapy System (test device) to an identical sham device (placebo) in subjects
      experiencing post-operative pain following first metatarsal bunion surgery. The study
      hypothesis is that, over the first 72 hours (3 days) after the initial test device
      treatment, subjects treated with an active test device will show a statistically significant
      difference (reduction) in pain intensity scores when compared with subjects treated with a
      sham (placebo) device. Treatment with the test device will continue through the 168 hour (7
      day) timepoint. Safety will be followed through 28 days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    IDMC recommendation
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the overall analgesic efficacy (via SPID 0-72hrs) of the PROVANT® Therapy System to an identical sham device in Subjects experiencing post-bunionectomy surgical pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment with the test device twice per day, over 3 days (7 total treatments)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary efficacy endpoint will assess the Sum of time-weighted Pain Intensity Differences (SPID) from the time of initiation of the first postoperative treatment with the test device (T0) to seventy-two hours thereafter (T72).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TOTPAR-Pain Relief Experienced by Patients T0-72 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment with the test device twice per day, over 3 days (7 total treatments)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The total pain relief (TOTPAR) will be measured over 3 days (T0-72 hours)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid consumption measured in morphine equivalents T0-72 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment with the test device twice per day, over 3 days (7 total treatments)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>How much total rescue (supplemental) opioid medicine was required for pain relief, over the first 3 days?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject global assessment of quality of pain control at 72 hrs</measure>
    <time_frame>After 3 days of treatment (T0-72 hours)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first use of supplemental analgesic medication</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment with the test device twice per day, over 3 days (7 total treatments)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>When was the first dose of rescue (supplemental) opioid medicine required for pain relief, over the first 3 days?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">314</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-surgical Pain</condition>
  <condition>Bunionectomy Pain Model</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active study device with PRFE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This study arm receives pulsed radiofrequency energy (PRFE) from an active test device.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham study device with no PRFE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This study arm receives no pulsed radiofrequency energy (PRFE) from a sham test device.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pulsed Radiofrequency Energy (PRFE)</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is pulsed radiofrequencyenergy (PRFE).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active study device with PRFE</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Provant Therapy System</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No Pulsed Radiofrequency Energy (PRFE)</intervention_name>
    <description>Sham (placebo) with no therapeutic device activity</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham study device with no PRFE</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sham Provant Therapy System</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Pre-operative Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults aged 18-75 years old

          -  Subject is scheduled to undergo primary, unilateral first metatarsal bunionectomy (no
             collateral procedures) under regional/local anesthesia and sedation

          -  Subject meets the criteria for American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) Physical
             Status I or II.

          -  Subject is willing to be confined at the investigative site for approximately 4 days
             including the day of surgery.

          -  Subject is able to communicate meaningfully in English in order to complete study
             assessments and comply with all trial procedures.

          -  Willingness to give written informed consent and to comply with all parts of the
             study protocol.

          -  Female Subjects of child bearing potential are eligible only if they are not pregnant
             (negative pregnancy test at screening and before surgery), not lactating, and not
             planning to become pregnant during the study.

          -  Female Subjects must be post-menopausal, surgically sterile, abstinent, or
             practicing, or agree to practice, an effective method of birth control if they are
             sexually active for the duration of the study (effective methods of birth control
             include prescription hormonal contraceptives, intrauterine devices, double-barrier
             methods, and/or male partner sterilization).

        Pre-Operative Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is scheduled to undergo Base wedge osteotomy, and/or Long-Z Hart bunionectomy
             procedure or any other procedure that does not conform to the surgical protocol.

          -  Subject has received any investigational drug within 1 month prior to the Screening
             Visit or is enrolled in another clinical trial.

          -  Subject has a history of drug abuse within 5 years of the screening visit, including
             a history of opioid (narcotic) analgesic abuse.

          -  Subject has a history of any clinically significant cardiac, respiratory (except mild
             asthma), renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal, hematologic, endocrine or psychiatric
             disease or disorder, or any uncontrolled medical illness that in the investigator's
             judgment places the Subject at unacceptable risk for surgery or receipt of
             investigational therapy.

          -  Subject has an ongoing, uncontrolled painful condition that in the opinion of the
             Investigator might have a confounding influence on the safety or efficacy analysis
             for this study.

          -  Subject has received systemic corticosteroid administration within 1 month prior to
             surgery or is scheduled to receive systemic corticosteroid therapy at any time during
             the course of the study.

          -  Subject is unwilling to abstain from alcohol from at least midnight the night before
             surgery through completion of all In-patient Treatment Period procedures and
             discharge from the investigative site.

          -  Subject is unwilling to refrain from smoking during his/her stay at the investigative
             site.

          -  Subject is currently receiving treatment, or has received treatment within the last
             two weeks, with antipsychotic drugs, monoamine oxidase inhibitors, duloxetine,
             gabapentin, carbamazepine, phenytoin, pregabalin or is receiving treatment with
             antidepressants that are not on a stable dose (the same dose for &gt;1 month).

          -  Subject has a history of malignancy within the past five years with the exception of
             successfully treated non-metastatic basal cell or squamous cell carcinomas of the
             skin and/or localized carcinoma in situ of the cervix.

          -  Subject has current evidence of alcohol abuse (regularly drinks more than four units
             of alcohol per day; 1 unit = ½ pint of beer, 1 glass of wine, or 1 ounce of spirit).

          -  Infection (acute or chronic) involving the first metatarsal (or history of such
             infection) or any other disease of the foot/ankle that in the opinion of the
             investigator, places the Subject at increased risk for surgical complications or
             receipt of the investigational therapy.

          -  Implanted pacemaker, defibrillator, neurostimulator, bone stimulator, cochlear
             implant, or other implanted device with metal lead(s).

          -  Implanted metal in the index foot including planned intra-operative use of metallic
             screw or fixation device.

          -  History of malignancy in the treatment area.

          -  Subjects who are taking any dosage strength of daily opioids for more than 30
             consecutive days, within the past three months prior to surgery.

          -  Subject with fibromyalgia, complex regional pain syndrome or other chronic pain
             syndromes.

          -  Subjects with neuropathic or sensory abnormalities of the lower extremities. Abnormal
             vibratory sensation and/or Semmes-Weinstein monofilament tests.

          -  Subject with BMI &gt; 38.

          -  Subject with known hypersensitivity, intolerance or contraindication to
             acetaminophen, oxycodone, morphine or any agent used in the anesthetic protocol that
             in the opinion of the Investigator will put the Subject at increased risk.

        Post-Operative Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The Subject does not report a score of moderate or severe on a 4-point categorical
             rating scale (with categories of none, mild, moderate, or severe) plus a score of ≥4
             on an NPRS 11-point categorical rating scale within 8 hours after the end of surgery.
             End of surgery is defined as time of last suture.

          -  The Subject is not able to answer questions and follow commands.

          -  The surgical procedure from incision to closure was longer than 2 hours.

          -  The Subject has evidence of respiratory insufficiency, such as a respiratory rate
             that is less than 8 breaths per minute and arterial oxygen saturation by pulse
             oximetry of less than 95% with supplemental oxygen.

          -  There have been any significant deviations from the surgical or anesthetic protocols
             that would, in the opinion of the investigator, put the Subject at risk of
             participation in the trial, confound the analgesic endpoints of the trial or cause
             concern regarding the Subject's ability to participate in the trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Neil K. Singla, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Lotus Clinical Research, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lotus Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pasadena</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chesapeake Research Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pasadena</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Endeavor Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 14, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 24, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pulsed Radiofrequency Energy (PRFE)</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Post surgical</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioids</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain relief</keyword>
  <keyword>Medical device</keyword>
  <keyword>Endorphins</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
