<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="129401">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01846676</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>221-2010</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01846676</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Trial to Assess the ACE Program for Rehabilitation in Hearing Loss</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Trial to Assess the Active Communication Education Program for Rehabilitation in Patients With Hearing Loss Users of Hearing Aids</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Chile</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Chile</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Chile: Comité de Ética Científico</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      -  Introduction: Hearing loss is a prevalent condition in elderly population. However, the
           low adherence to hearing aids is a fact, with an estimation of use of 50 per cent. In
           2007 there was designed a rehabilitation program called ACE, which aims to improve
           rehabilitation directed to hearing aids users. The study hypothesis is that a
           counseling program will improve adherence to hearing aids in elderly population.

        -  Objective: To evaluate the utility of a standardized counselling program in patients
           with hearing loss.

        -  Material and Methods: A before/after trial will be carried out, approved by the
           Hospital ethics - committee. Patients with 65 years and older with hearing loss
           diagnosed by pure tone audiometry will be included. To assess adherence we will use the
           IOI-HA scale.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  Introduction: Hearing loss is a prevalent condition in elderly population. However, the
           low adherence to hearing aids is a fact, with an estimation of use of 50 per cent. In
           Chile, hearing aids are provided by the State for elderly population. In 2007 there was
           designed a rehabilitation program called Active Communication Education (ACE), that is
           a semistructured rehabilitation program for people with hearing loss, which aims to
           improve rehabilitation of hearing aids users by a strategy based on problem solution.

        -  The study hypothesis is that a counseling program will improve adherence to hearing
           aids in elderly population.

        -  Objective: To evaluate the utility of a standardized counseling program in patients
           with hearing loss.

        -  Material and Methods: A before/after clinical trial will be carried out, approved by
           the Hospital ethics - committee. Patients with 65 years and older diagnosed by pure
           tone audiometry who are beneficiaries of the Public GES hearing loss programme and
           receive a hearing aid will be included. The subjects will be randomized in two
           branches: Active branch, subject to the rehabilitation program; and passive branch,
           which was control, with usual management (no intervention). To assess adherence we will
           use the IOI-HA scale.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to the use of hearing aids in elderly population with hearing loss</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Hearing Loss</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Program counseling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active branch, subject to the rehabilitation program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No counseling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Passive branch, which was control, with usual management (no intervention).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Active Communication Education Program</intervention_name>
    <description>The program called Active Communication Education (ACE), that is a semistructured rehabilitation program for people with hearing loss, which aims to improve rehabilitation of hearing aids users by a strategy based on problem solution.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Program counseling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Bilateral hearing loss equal or higher than 40 decibels

          -  Age 65 years old or more

          -  Agree to be included in the study

          -  Have a relative to go to the intervention with the subject

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe organic brain impairment

          -  Physical or mental incapacity to understand the study questionnaires

          -  Structural pathology of the ear that produces hearing loss as chronic otitis media,
             ear canal tumor, or      tumor of the cerebellopontine angle
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Felipe Cardemil, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Chile</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Barros Luco Trudeau Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Miguel, Santiago</city>
        <state>Región Metropolitana</state>
        <zip>8900085</zip>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Chile</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 29, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Chile</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Felipe Cardemil</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Otolaryngology department, University of Chile</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hearing loss, rehabilitation programs, adherence to hearing aids.</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Deafness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
