<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="46934">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01928927</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACTG A5317</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UM1AI068636</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01928927</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Telmisartan to Reduce AIDS-Related Fibrotic and Inflammatory Contributors (TRAFIC Study)</brief_title>
  <acronym>TRAFIC</acronym>
  <official_title>Effects of Telmisartan on Fibrotic and Inflammatory Contributors to End-Organ Disease in HIV-Infected Patients Well Controlled on Antiretroviral Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AIDS Clinical Trials Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AIDS Clinical Trials Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main goal of this study is to see if a drug called telmisartan will decrease fibrosis
      (scarring) and inflammation (irritation) in people who are infected with HIV and doing well
      on their HIV medications. The study is also being done to see what effects telmisartan has
      on other signs of disease and inflammation in the body, and to see whether people who have
      HIV can take telmisartan safely and without side effects that make them want to stop the
      drug. Telmisartan is FDA-approved for treating high blood pressure and decreasing the chance
      of heart attacks and strokes in people over the age of 55 years of age who are at high risk
      for these events.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in percent collagen deposition on lymph node pathology from baseline to week 48</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percent collagen deposition defined as proportion of fibrotic/collagen area to total area</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in percent collagen deposition on subcutaneous abdominal adipose tissue pathology from baseline to week 48</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percent collagen deposition defined as proportion of fibrotic/collagen area to total area</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in biomarkers associated with inflammation, coagulation, and oxidative stress from baseline to week 4</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured as change from entry to week 4 in circulating hyaluronic acid, IL-6, TNF-alpha, sCD14, D-dimer, tissue factor, soluble TNF-alpha receptor levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in biomarkers associated with inflammation, coagulation, and oxidative stress from baseline to week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured as change from entry to week 24 in circulating hyaluronic acid, IL-6, TNF-alpha, sCD14, D-dimer, tissue factor, soluble TNF-alpha receptor levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in biomarkers associated with inflammation, coagulation, and oxidative stress from baseline to week 48</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured as change from entry to week 48 in circulating hyaluronic acid, IL-6, TNF-alpha, sCD14, D-dimer, tissue factor, soluble TNF-alpha receptor levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in circulating activated T cells from baseline to week 4</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured as change from entry to week 4 in the percentage of CD4 and CD8 cells that are CD38+/HLA-DR+</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in circulating activated T cells from baseline to week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured as change from entry to week 24 in the percentage of CD4 and CD8 cells that are CD38+/HLA-DR+</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in circulating activated T cells from baseline to week 48</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured as change from entry to week 48 in the percentage of CD4 and CD8 cells that are CD38+/HLA-DR+</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in inflammatory cell population type and number in lymphoid tissue biopsy specimens from baseline to week 48</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured as the change from entry to week 48 in the frequency of CD14+, CD16+,CD64+, and/or CD163+ macrophages and % activated (CD38+/HLA-DR+, Ki67+) CD4 and CD8 T cells.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in inflammatory cell population type and number in adipose tissue biopsy specimens from baseline to week 48</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured as the change from entry to week 48 in the frequency of CD14+, CD16+,CD64+, and/or CD163+ macrophages.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the proportion of CD4+ T cells in lymphoid tissue from baseline to week 48.</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured as the change from entry to week 48 in %CD3+CD4+ T cells.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in circulating CD4+ T cell count and phenotype of circulating CD4+ T cells from baseline to weeks 24.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured as the change from entry to week 24 in CD4+ T cell count and memory/naïve phenotype of the CD4+ T cells.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in circulating CD4+ T cell count and phenotype of circulating CD4+ T cells from baseline to weeks 48.</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured as the change from entry to week 48 in CD4+ T cell count and memory/naïve phenotype of the CD4+ T cells.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in markers of peripheral insulin resistance and dyslipidemia from baseline to week 48.</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured as change from entry to week 48 in HOMA-IR, fasting total cholesterol, fasting HDL cholesterol, fasting calculated LDL cholesterol, and fasting triglycerides.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in anthropometric measurements from baseline to week 24.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measures as change from study entry to week 24 in mid-waist circumference and waist-to-hip ratio</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in anthropometric measurements from baseline to week 48.</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measures as change from study entry to week 48 in mid-waist circumference and waist-to-hip ratio</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of metabolic syndrome at week 24.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Components of the metabolic syndrome will be defined according to the 2004 updated National Cholesterol Education Program Adult Treatment Panel III [NCEP ATP III] criteria) as the presence of any 3 of the following: Waist: &gt;40&quot; (101.6 cm) in men, &gt;35&quot; (88.9 cm) in women with the exception of Asian-Americans: &gt;35&quot; (88.9 cm) in men, 31&quot; (78.7 cm) in women; Fasting HDL-C &lt;40 mg/dL in men, &lt;50 mg/dL in women; Fasting TG ≥150 mg/dL; Diastolic blood pressure ≥85 mmHg or systolic blood pressure ≥130 mmHg; Fasting plasma glucose ≥100 mg/dL.
NOTE: This definition of metabolic syndrome may be subject to change in accordance with current guidelines at the time of the final analysis. It will be defined in the Final Statistical Analysis Plan prior to data review for final analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of metabolic syndrome at week 48.</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Components of the metabolic syndrome will be defined according to the 2004 updated National Cholesterol Education Program Adult Treatment Panel III [NCEP ATP III] criteria) as the presence of any 3 of the following: Waist: &gt;40&quot; (101.6 cm) in men, &gt;35&quot; (88.9 cm) in women with the exception of Asian-Americans: &gt;35&quot; (88.9 cm) in men, 31&quot; (78.7 cm) in women; Fasting HDL-C &lt;40 mg/dL in men, &lt;50 mg/dL in women; Fasting TG ≥150 mg/dL; Diastolic blood pressure ≥85 mmHg or systolic blood pressure ≥130 mmHg; Fasting plasma glucose ≥100 mg/dL.
NOTE: This definition of metabolic syndrome may be subject to change in accordance with current guidelines at the time of the final analysis. It will be defined in the Final Statistical Analysis Plan prior to data review for final analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety profile of telmisartan over the 48-week study period.</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Presence of any of the following: Grade &gt;/=2 signs and symptoms, any sign or symptom (of any Grade) that lead to study treatment discontinuation, and the site-determined relatedness of AEs/signs/symptoms to telmisartan therapy.
NOTE: As adipose tissue and lymph node biopsies are generally considered to be minimal risk procedures, biopsy safety profile will not formally be evaluated as an endpoint in this protocol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">54</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV-1 Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Telmisartan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive Telmisartan 40 mg daily during weeks 0-4 followed by telmisartan 80 mg daily during weeks 5-48.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: No study drug, week 0-48 evaluations</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Telmisartan</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Telmisartan</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Step 1 Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV-1 infection, documented by any licensed rapid HIV test or HIV enzyme or
             chemiluminescence immunoassay (E/CIA) test kit at any time prior to Step 1 entry and
             confirmed by a licensed Western blot or a second antibody test by a method other than
             the initial rapid HIV and/or E/CIA, or by HIV-1 antigen, or plasma HIV-1 RNA viral
             load &gt;2000 copies/mL on two occasions.

          -  On antiretroviral therapy (ART) continuously for ≥48 weeks prior to Step 1 entry.

          -  Documentation of HIV-1 RNA &lt;50 copies/mL at screening, performed by any US laboratory
             that has a CLIA certification or its equivalent.

          -  At least one HIV-1 RNA level &lt;200 copies/mL in the 48 weeks prior to Step 1 entry
             (not including the screening).

          -  No change in ART regimen in the 12 weeks prior to Step 1 entry (except as noted
             below).

        NOTE: Modifications of ART dosing during the 12 weeks prior to Step 1 entry are permitted.
        In addition, the change in formulation (eg, from standard formulation to fixed dose
        combination or single tablet regimen) is allowed within 12 weeks of Step 1 entry. A
        within-class single drug substitution (eg, switch from nevirapine to efavirenz or from
        atazanavir to darunavir) is allowed within 12 weeks of Step 1 entry, with the exception of
        a switch from any other NRTI to abacavir. No other changes in ART in the 12 weeks prior to
        Step 1 entry are permitted.

          -  No active plan to change ART for the 48-week study duration.

          -  Body mass index (BMI) 20-35 kg/m2.

          -  For females of reproductive potential, negative serum or urine pregnancy test within
             3 days prior to Step 1 entry.

          -  Ability and willingness of subject or legal guardian/representative to provide
             informed consent.

          -  Willingness to undergo the Step 1 entry and week 48 lymphoid and adipose tissue
             biopsies.

        Step 2 Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Entry lymphoid tissue and adipose tissue specimen for assay of the primary endpoint
             has been obtained.

          -  Willingness to undergo the week 48 lymphoid and adipose tissue biopsies.

        Step 1 Exclusion Criteria:

          -  More than one HIV-1 RNA &gt;200 copies/mL in the 48 weeks prior to Step 1 entry.

          -  One HIV-1 RNA 200-500 copies/mL in the 24 weeks prior to Step 1 entry that is not
             immediately preceded and followed by HIV-1 RNA &lt;50 copies/mL.

        NOTE: The preceding viral load &lt;50 copies/mL may be &gt;24 weeks prior to Step 1 entry.

          -  Confirmed systolic blood pressure &gt;160 mmHg or &lt;100 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure
             &gt;100 mmHg.

          -  Known untreated renal artery stenosis.

          -  Known cirrhosis or severe liver disease (eg, ascites, encephalopathy, history of
             variceal bleeding).

        NOTE: Potential subjects with chronic hepatitis B or C virus infection with no known
        cirrhosis or severe liver disease may participate in the study, provided there are no
        plans to start therapy for hepatitis C infection during the 48-week study duration.

          -  Unstable coronary artery disease/angina or decompensated congestive heart failure.

          -  Either breastfeeding or pregnant within 24 weeks prior to Step 1 entry.

          -  Use of thiazolidinediones or any angiotensin receptor blocker (ARB) or angiotensin
             converting enzyme inhibitor (ACEi) in the 24 weeks prior to Step 1 entry. If the
             subject took either of these classes of medications for less than 2 weeks in the 24
             weeks prior to Step 1 entry, the subject may enroll if 30 days have passed since the
             last dose. If the subject is diabetic and/or has a calculated glomerular filtration
             rate (GFR) &lt;60mL/min, aliskiren-containing medications are also prohibited.

          -  History of intolerance, other than cough, to any ARB or ACEi.

          -  Use of anticoagulants other than aspirin 81 mg or 325 mg daily. NOTE: If the subject
             is on aspirin 81 mg or 325 mg daily and is willing/able to stop therapy for 7 days
             prior to the biopsy procedures, the subject may enroll.

          -  Any known bleeding disorder or coagulopathy.

          -  Projected need for daily potassium supplementation for ≥2 weeks during the study
             period.

          -  The following laboratory values obtained within 30 days prior to Step 1 entry by any
             US laboratory that has a CLIA certification or its equivalent:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≤750 cells/mm3

               -  Hemoglobin ≤10 g/dL

               -  Platelet count ≤75,000/mm3

               -  Calculated creatinine clearance (CrCl) &lt;50 mL/min, as estimated by the
                  Cockcroft-Gault equation

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (SGOT) &gt;/=3x ULN (upper limit of normal)

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (SGPT) &gt;/=3x ULN

               -  Partial thromboplastin time (PTT) &gt;1.2x ULN

               -  Prothrombin time (PT) &gt;1.2x ULN

          -  Heritable connective tissue disorders (eg Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, osteogenesis
             imperfecta, Stickler syndrome, Marfan's syndrome).

        NOTE: Subjects with acquired/autoimmune chronic inflammatory diseases/connective tissue
        disorders who are clinically stable (in the opinion of the site investigator) and not on a
        prohibited medication may enroll with approval of the A5317 study chairs.

          -  Serious illness requiring systemic treatment and/or hospitalization until subject
             either completes therapy or is clinically stable on therapy, in the opinion of the
             site investigator, for at least 7 days prior to Step 1 entry.

          -  Active drug or alcohol use or dependence that, in the opinion of the site
             investigator, would interfere with adherence to study requirements.

          -  Any condition that, in the opinion of the site investigator, would compromise the
             subject's ability to participate in the study.

        Step 2 Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any AE associated with the Step 1 entry biopsy that would exclude the subject from
             undergoing follow-up biopsy at week 48.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jordan E. Lake, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>UCLA Care Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Netanya Sandler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Texas Medical Branch at Galveston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 22, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Telmisartan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Benzoates</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
