<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="62008">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01823536</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>V59P20E1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01823536</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Persistence of Immunogenicity of MenACWY Conjugate Vaccine 5 Years After Childhood Vaccination, and Immune Response to a Booster Dose</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase IV, Open-label, Controlled, Multi-center Study to Evaluate the 5-year Antibody Persistence Among Children Who Previously Received Novartis MenACWY Conjugate Vaccine at 2 to 10 Years of Age and to Assess the Immune Response to a Single Dose of Novartis MenACWY Conjugate Vaccine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Vaccines</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this extension study, V59P20E1, the sponsor is planning to assess 5-year antibody
      persistence in subjects who received one or two doses of MenACWY conjugate vaccine at 2 to
      10 years of age, and to evaluate response to a booster dose administered 5 years after
      primary vaccination
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with hSBA ≥1:8 in groups who previously received one or two doses of MenACWY vaccine (Groups A, B and D)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the persistence of the antibody response at 5 years postvaccination in children who previously received one or two doses of MenACWY in study V59P20, as measured by percentage of subjects with human Serum Bactericidal Assay (hSBA) ≥1:8 directed against N. meningitidis serogroups A, C, W-135, and Y.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>hSBA GMTs against N. meningitidis serogroups A, C, W-135 and Y on Day 1</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the persistence of the antibody response at 5 years postvaccination in children who previously received one or two doses of MenACWY in study V59P20, as measured by hSBA geometric mean titers (GMTs) directed against N. meningitidis serogroups A, C, W-135, and Y.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with hSBA ≥1:8 in vaccine-naive subjects (Groups C and E) on Day 1</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To compare antibody titers directed against N. meningitidis serogroups A, C, W-135, and Y between children vaccinated 5 years earlier with one or two doses of MenACWY and the vaccine-naive subjects in the same age group as measured by percentages of subjects with hSBA ≥1:8.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with hSBA ≥1:8 on Day 28 postvaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the antibody response to one dose of MenACWY in children who received one or two doses of the same vaccine 5 years earlier in study V59P20, as measured by percentage of subjects with hSBA ≥1:8, and hSBA GMTs directed against N. meningitidis serogroups A, C, W-135, and Y at 28 days postvaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>hSBA GMTs against N. meningitidis serogroups A, C, W-135 and Y on Day 28 postvaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To compare the antibody response to one dose of MenACWY in children who received one or two doses of the same vaccine 5 years earlier in study V59P20 and in vaccine-naive subjects in the same age group, as measured by percentage of subjects with hSBA ≥1:8, and hSBA GMTs directed against N. meningitidis serogroups A, C W-135, and Y at 28 days postvaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">465</enrollment>
  <condition>Meningococcal Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MenACWY-CRM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MenACWY</intervention_name>
    <description>Single dose at Day 1</description>
    <arm_group_label>MenACWY-CRM</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        In order to participate in this study, all subjects must meet ALL of the inclusion
        criteria described.

          1. Subject has (a) parent(s) or legal guardian(s) who has/have given written consent
             after the nature of the study has been explained according to local regulatory
             requirements.

          2. If the subject is of an age where, according to local regulations, informed assent is
             required, that subject has provided assent to participate in the study.

          3. Subject is in good health as determined by the outcome of medical history, physical
             examination, and clinical judgment of the investigator.

          4. A negative urine pregnancy test is required before female subjects of childbearing
             potential will be enrolled. Of childbearing potential is defined as status post onset
             of menses and not meeting any of the following conditions: menopausal for at least 2
             years, status after bilateral tubal ligation for at least 1 year, status after
             bilateral ovary removal, or status after hysterectomy.

          5. For subjects who participated in study V59P20 (Groups A, B and D only):

               -  subject who enrolled in Groups I, II or IV of study V59P20, has completed this
                  study and included in per protocol immunogenicity analysis;

               -  the date of first vaccination in study V59P20 occurred 54 to 66 months prior to
                  the collection of the blood sample at Visit 1.

          6. For vaccine-naive subjects (Groups C and E only):

               -  Individual is a male or female 7 to 10 years of age (group C) or 11 to 15 years
                  of age (Group E).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        In order to participate in this study, all subjects must meet NONE of the exclusion
        criteria described.

          1. If the subject is female of childbearing potential, sexually active, and has not used
             any of the acceptable contraceptive methods for at least 2 months prior to study
             entry and for the duration of the trial.

          2. Subject is a pregnant or breast-feeding female.

          3. Subjects' parents or legal guardians or subjects who are not able to comprehend and
             to follow all required study procedures for the whole period of the study.

          4. History of documented or suspected invasive meningococcal disease.

          5. Previous household contact with and/or intimate exposure to an individual with
             laboratory proven N. meningitidis infection within 60 days prior to enrollment and
             for the duration of the study.

          6. Have received any other meningococcal vaccine since participation in V59P20 or, if
             vaccine-naive subjects, have not received any meningococcal vaccine since birth.

          7. Suspected or known hypersensitivity reaction after a previous dose of Menveo, any
             component of this vaccine, including any other CRM197 and diphtheria toxoid.

          8. Any contraindication or precaution against vaccination with Novartis Menveo™ vaccine
             as highlighted in the package insert.

          9. Serious, chronic, or acute illnesses or diseases (i.e., cardiac, renal, neurologic,
             rheumatologic, metabolic, gastrointestinal, psychiatric, or other organ system).

         10. Any confirmed or suspected condition with impaired/altered function of immune system
             (immunodeficient or autoimmune conditions).

         11. Administration of any cancer chemotherapy, immune-modified or immunosuppressive
             agents or systemic corticosteroids for at least seven days at any dose in the past 12
             weeks or planned use throughout the study period (nasal or inhaled steroids are
             permitted, as are steroids applied to the skin).

         12. Administration of blood, blood products and/or plasma derivatives or any
             immunoglobulin preparation in the past 12 weeks or planned use throughout the study
             period.

         13. Administration of any vaccine within 28 days prior to the study enrollment or planned
             administration during the study period.

         14. Subjects participating in any clinical trial with another investigational product 28
             days prior to first study visit or intent to participate in another clinical study at
             any time during the study period.

         15. Subjects who have experienced a significant acute infection requiring systemic
             antibiotic treatment within the 5 days prior to enrolment or have experienced a body
             temperature ≥38°C (≥100.4°F) within the 3 days before the intended study vaccination.

         16. Any condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, would pose a health risk to
             the participant.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>15 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Novartis Vaccines and Diagnostics</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Novartis Vaccines</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>82 Children s Inv Research Prgm (ChIRP) 2900 Medical Center Parkway, Ste. 300</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bentonville</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72712</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>83 AR Pediatric Clinical Research 500 South University, Ste. 200</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>32 Prem Health Research Center 9317 Firestone Blvd.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Downey</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90241</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>27 KY Pediatric Adult Research 201 South 5th Street, Suite 102</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bardstown</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40004</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>36 Meridian Clinical Research 3319 N. 107th Street</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68134</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>33 Dr. Sender's and Associates 2054 South Green Road</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>31 Benchmark Research, Fort Worth 4504 Boat Club Rd., Suite 400A</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ft. Worth</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>76135</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>25 Benchmark Research, San Angelo 3555 Knickerbocker Rd.</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Angelo</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>76904</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>65 Westside Medical 1477 N 2000 W, Suite C</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clinton</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84015</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>29 J. Lewis Research, Inc. 6360 South 3000 East, Ste. 100</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>30 J. Lewis Research, Inc. 6360 South 3000 East, Ste. 100</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>37 Copperview Medical Associates 3556 West 9800 South</name>
      <address>
        <city>South Jordan</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>47 Wee Care Pediatrics 1792 W. 1700 S.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Syracuse</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84075</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>34 Rockwood Clinic P S 400 East Fifth Avenue</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>35 Rockwood Clinic-North Pediatrics 9001 N Country Homes Blvd</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99218</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>26 Benchmark Research 3800 Houma Blvd., Suite 345</name>
      <address>
        <city>Metairie</city>
        <state>LA</state>
        <zip>70006</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Ukraine</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Halperin SA, Gupta A, Jeanfreau R, Klein NP, Reisinger K, Walter E, Bedell L, Gill C, Dull PM. Comparison of the safety and immunogenicity of an investigational and a licensed quadrivalent meningococcal conjugate vaccine in children 2-10 years of age. Vaccine. 2010 Nov 23;28(50):7865-72. Epub 2010 Oct 29.</citation>
    <PMID>20943209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 11, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 28, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Meningitis</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Meningococcal Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
