<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="29913">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01658917</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>120175</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12-C-0175</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01658917</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Collecting Solid Tumor Tissue to Identify New Treatments</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Procurement of Solid Tumor Tissue to Identify Novel Therapeutic Targets</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Researchers are looking at different types of cancerous tissues to study new treatments.
      They are looking at solid tumors of the esophagus, stomach, liver, gall bladder, intestines,
      and other organs. Tumor and other tissue samples will be collected for study. Researchers
      also want to collect information on the operations used to obtain tumor samples. These
      samples will be used to develop new cancer treatments.

      Objectives:

      - To collect solid tumor and normal tissue samples to investigate new cancer therapies.

      Eligibility:

        -  Individuals at least 16 years of age who have precancerous or cancerous solid tumors.

        -  Participants will have surgery or biopsy to collect tumor samples for study.

      Design:

        -  Participants will provide blood samples before having the surgery or biopsy. Some may
           have leukapheresis to collect extra white blood cells for study.

        -  During the surgery or biopsy, pieces of the tumor or growth will be collected. Some
           normal tissue near the tumor will also be collected.

        -  Information on the cancer and the surgery will also be collected.

        -  Treatment will not be provided as part of this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

        -  Recent advances and insights into the molecular pathogenesis of cancer have led to the
           development of novel molecular and biologic targeted therapies for the treatment of
           advanced cancer patients. A critical challenge in extending these studies involves the
           identification and validation of new therapeutic targets for future cancer therapies.

        -  The Surgery Branch, NCI has an interest in identifying novel molecular and biologic
           targets to facilitate the development of future cancer therapies. In addition, we have
           the primary responsibility for providing surgical consultative services to the NIH. As
           such, we are uniquely positioned to acquire and perform important studies on solid
           tumor tissue to help identify therapeutic targets that may have significant clinical
           ramifications.

      OBJECTIVES:

        -  Primary Objective: To collect biologic samples from patients undergoing diagnostic or
           therapeutic interventions for premalignant, primary or metastatic solid tumors for the
           purpose of identifying novel molecular and biologic therapeutic targets

        -  Secondary Objectives: To collect detailed history, demographic, treatment data, and
           perioperative findings in order to categorize and track the specific procedures and
           outcomes.

      ELIGIBILITY:

        -  Patients greater than or equal to 16 years of age with radiographic evidence of,
           biochemical evidence of, or histologically/cytologically proven solid neoplasms who
           require diagnostic or therapeutic intervention as a part of the diagnosis and /or
           standard of care treatment and/or follow up for their neoplasm

        -  Patients must have laboratory and physical examination parameters within acceptable
           limits by standard of practice guidelines prior to planned intervention

      DESIGN:

        -  A tissue acquisition trial in which tissues will be obtained at the time of
           intervention

        -  Tissue and blood will be processed at the time of collection, stored and then
           transferred to Dr. Kammula   s laboratory for further processing.

        -  No investigational therapy will be given.

        -  It is anticipated that 1000 patients will be enrolled over a period of 10 years
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To collect biologic samples from patients undergoing diagnostic or therapeutic interventions for premalignant, primary or metastatic solid tumors for the purpose of identifying novel molecular and biologic therapeutic targets</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastrointestinal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Liver Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Patients must be greater than or equal to 16 years of age.

          -  Patients who have a premalignant, primary or metastatic solid tumors based upon
             either radiographic or biochemical testing, or histological/cytological analysis that
             requires surgery or biopsy as a part of the standard of care diagnosis, treatment
             and/or follow up

          -  Patients must have laboratory and physical examination parameters within acceptable
             limits by standard of practice guidelines prior to biopsy or surgery.

          -  Patients must be planning to undergo surgery or biopsy as part of their treatment
             plan. Note: Patients will not be enrolled exclusively for the procurement of tissue
             samples.

          -  Patients who agree to undergo leukapheresis must meet the following criteria:

          -  Seronegative for HIV

          -  Seronegative for hepatitis B surface antigen and seronegative for

        antibody to hepatitis C.

        - CBC within normal limits
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Udai S Kammula, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>June Kryk, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-1929</phone>
    <email>ncisbirc@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Udai S Kammula, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-8606</phone>
    <email>kammulau@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact NCI/Surgery Branch Recruitment Center</last_name>
      <phone>866-820-4505</phone>
      <email>ncisbirc@mail.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2012-C-0175.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Philip PA, Mooney M, Jaffe D, Eckhardt G, Moore M, Meropol N, Emens L, O'Reilly E, Korc M, Ellis L, Benedetti J, Rothenberg M, Willett C, Tempero M, Lowy A, Abbruzzese J, Simeone D, Hingorani S, Berlin J, Tepper J. Consensus report of the national cancer institute clinical trials planning meeting on pancreas cancer treatment. J Clin Oncol. 2009 Nov 20;27(33):5660-9. Epub 2009 Oct 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19858397</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubio-Viqueira B, Hidalgo M. Direct in vivo xenograft tumor model for predicting chemotherapeutic drug response in cancer patients. Clin Pharmacol Ther. 2009 Feb;85(2):217-21. Epub 2008 Nov 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19005462</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sausville EA, Burger AM. Contributions of human tumor xenografts to anticancer drug development. Cancer Res. 2006 Apr 1;66(7):3351-4, discussion 3354. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16585151</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 13, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 3, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>Tissue Acquisition</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gastrointestinal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
