<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="164924">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02018497</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LEMD001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02018497</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Essential Hypotension and Adaptability Registry</brief_title>
  <acronym>EssentialHAR</acronym>
  <official_title>Essential Arterial Hypotension and Adaptability Registry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>CES University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>CES University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Colombia: instituto nacional de vigilancia de medicamentos y alimentos INVIMA</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The essential arterial hypotension and adaptability registry is an observational,
      prospective, cohort type, descriptive and comparative research about the low arterial blood
      pressure with no identifiable cause, in a population that visits a cardiologist's office in
      Medellin, Colombia.

      The population consists of patients of any age and gender, which are classified according to
      their blood pressure in: normotensive, hypertensive and hypotensive. In addition, they are
      also classified according to their adaptability in hypo, normal adaptability and hyper.

      The aim is to evaluate how clinical, laboratory, paraclinical examinations and certain
      comorbidities behave between the three groups of blood pressure and adaptability in order to
      define the meaning of the essential hypotension and the adaptability and propose possible
      mechanisms mediating this relationship.

      HYPOTHESIS

      This hypothesis is the result of previous exploratory studies that has been already
      published.

      Causes of the diseases (Essential Hypotension) are multifactorial.

        1. The organism's ability to adapt to stress of any kind is vital for life. Type of stress
           that humans are exposed most often is the psychosocial stress.

        2. The organism´s response to stress involves the autonomic nervous, the endocrine and the
           inflammatory systems

        3. Stressor can be acute, sub-acute or chronic; isolated, simultaneous or repetitive;
           mild, moderate or severe, which will determine the total burden of stress.

        4. The organism has acute, sub-acute and chronic adaptation, and it has a limited reserve
           of response in each case.

        5. The individual's response to stress is not homogenous in the population, it may be:
           excessive, proportioned and deficient (Figure 1).

        6. Chronic stress requires resistance and resilience, which are also different between
           individuals (Figure 1). It is proposed that chronic stress is lower in hypotensive and
           higher in hypertensive (but the adaptability group could predominate over the blood
           pressure group).

        7. The adaptive response to chronic stress may contribute decisively to produce blood
           pressure essential disorders (Figure 2), high (excessive response) and low (deficient
           response).

        8. Essential disorders in blood pressure would be an indicator of the individual's
           adaptability to stress, and the associated diseases would be part of the same response
           spectrum.

        9. The physiological disorders or associated diseases to stress adaptability can be: a)
           the result of the adaptive response (for example, blood pressure essential disorders),
           or b) the lack of ability to adapt (for example, fibromyalgia and chronic fatigue
           syndrome) (Figure 1).

       10. It is considered that most of the individual's functions have their base in the Central
           Nervous System, which has a limited ability to fulfill these functions. If the reserve
           is low and the challenge too severe and prolonged, the Central nervous system would
           begin to relegate some functions and prioritize in others. Those relegated functions
           (such as pain control) may cause diseases such as fibromyalgia.

       11. The concept of essential: If the diseases afflicting an important mass of the
           population may be the result of the body's response to stress, in an attempt to
           maintain homeostasis, it is postulated that both the magnitude and direction of this
           response must have a distribution that is between one and two standard deviations of
           the Gaussian curve (see Figure 3), probably more or less than others.

       12. The concept of psychobiotype: The homeostasis (allostasis) is the result of both:
           biological (biostasis) and psychological (psychostasis) abilities. This concept propose
           that both components behave in similar direction and magnitude. For example, the
           hypotensive patients would fall their blood pressure by assuming the standing position
           (orthostatic stress), the blood glucose may fall within the first 2 hours of a 75 grams
           of glucose challenge (reactive hypoglycemia, metabolic challenge) (Figure 4) and they
           would have an increased susceptibility to stress (psychological stress), that may cause
           depression, among other pathologies. These responses would not be presented
           consistently in time.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      DEFINITIONS

      ESSENTIAL ARTERIAL HYPERTENSION: without identifiable cause

        -  In the doctor's office: one or more visits with Systolic Blood Pressure (SBP) numbers &gt;
           140 and Diastolic Blood Pressure (DBP) numbers &gt; 90 mmHg.

        -  Ambulatory blood pressure monitoring (ABPM):

      Vigil: BP &gt;135/85; Night: BP &gt; 120/75; During 24 hours: BP &gt; 130/80 (20,43,53)

        -  Patients with old diagnosis who are under antihypertensive medication.

      WHITE COAT HYPERTENSION: At least in one occasion; high blood pressure in the medical
      environment, and normal ABPM. They are assigned to the normal BP group.

      MASKED HYPERTENSION: Blood pressure are in normal or in hypotension ranges during the
      consultations. The ABPM numbers are over the upper limit. They are assigned to the
      hypertension group

      NORMOTENSION: All patients who are not included in the categories previously exposed,
      including those with white coat hypertension.

      ESSENTIAL HYPOTENSION

      SBP &lt; 90 mmHg at any position. DBP &lt; 60 mmHg at any position. A fall in systolic and/or
      diastolic blood pressure of 20 and 10 mmHg respectively, which occurs during the first 3
      minutes after getting up.

      Patients must be in the absence of medication for hypertension, and hypotension must be
      dismissed as a secondary manifestation of another disease or other condition such as:
      dehydration, medication causing hypotension for other conditions (like those used for
      prostatic hyperplasia and others) or secondary dysautonomia.

      There are 3 types of orthostatic hypotension Initial: in the first 30 seconds after assuming
      the standing position. It represents the 78% of the population of this registry.

      Classic: It occurs between the 1st and 3rd minute. Late: It occurs between 5 and 45 minutes
      later (no patients within this category.)

      ESTIMATION OF TARGET-ORGAN DAMAGE Electrocardiogram, two-dimensional and/or Doppler
      echocardiogram, creatinine and urinalysis, lipid and metabolic profile and microalbuminuria
      are requested to the patients; carotid Doppler is also requested in patients with suspect of
      disorder.

      ARTERIAL HYPERTENSION TREATMENT. Those with ambulatory blood pressure monitoring were
      treated if the numbers exceeded the normality levels, and prevail over the pressure levels
      obtained in the doctor's office.

      The treatment always starts with a low-sodium diet (by the nutritionist), increase in fruits
      and vegetables intake, weight loss, exercise, stop smoking, and changes in the lifestyle
      (stress).

      In patients without associate pathologies, the pharmacological first step is the use of
      Enalapril (ARA II if there is cough), as a second step the use of calcium channel blockers,
      and the third step is the use of diuretics like the Hydrochlorothiazide 12.5mg (or up to
      25mg). If there is orthostatic hypotension, it is considered to start with Amlodipine. In
      those patients with tachyarrhythmia, heart failure or coronary disease is used Metoprolol or
      Carvedilol.

      ESSENTIAL HYPOTENSION TREATMENT The treatment starts with the use of non-pharmacological
      measures consisting of postural hygiene (avoid assuming the standing position abruptly,
      avoid staying in the standing position for too long), eat salty (10 g), drink more than 2 or
      3 liters of water per day, do aerobic exercises (for a routine, it is recommendable to start
      with 10 minutes of walking, cycling or swimming, four times a week), and raise the head of
      the bed. If there is not improvement, the patient can wear gradient tights up to the waist.
      If there is not improvement after complying with these measures, and if symptoms are
      significant, it is prescribed Fluorohydrocortisone 0.05 daily or every other day, making
      emphasis on the need of keeping the recommendations about water and sodium. Instructions are
      given about the need of keeping in touch due to the risks of hypertension or if there is a
      weight gain greater than 3 kg in the first month. Counterpressure maneuvers are recommended
      if there is a threat of syncope, it is recommended to sit or lie down on the bed to abort
      the syncope episode. Midodrine (from 5 to 20mg daily, distributed at 06:00, 10:00 and 14:00
      hours or when needed, avoid it after 6:00 pm).

      ADAPTABILITY

      For the effects of what is mentioned here, adaptability is defined as the ability to
      maintain homeostasis through the neuroendocrine response to the stress of any type. There is
      experimental evidence, measuring the sympathetic nerve activity during the mathematical
      stress with microneurography of the peroneal nerve (muscle sympathetic nerve activity or
      MSNA) that the response may be increasing, neutral or decreasing.

      The alterations in blood pressure are considered objective, which may be the result of
      strategies and different responses to stress (adaptability), through the neuroendocrine
      system (mainly the sympathetic nervous system).

      The following variables are evaluated to describe the adaptability:

        1. SYMPTOMS OF HYPOTENSION: postural dizziness, dizziness after squatting, dizziness
           during childhood or adolescence (in elementary school, high school and occasionally in
           college) during the mass, at public events, religious processions or military parades.
           It is also taken into account the previous diagnosis of low pressure or &quot;hypoglycemia&quot;
           (which in our culture mainly refers to symptoms of orthostatic hypotension).

        2. HISTORY OF NEURALLY MEDIATED SYNCOPE OR VASOVAGAL SYNCOPE diagnosed by the scores of
           Calgary or Tilt-test; or vasovagal syncope (syncope caused by seeing blood, a
           venipuncture or donating blood; pain, by seeing or speaking about dramatic things, when
           coughing, swallowing, defecating, urinating, laughing, or other situations. If these
           situations occur with significant dizziness or pre-syncope, but it is not syncope
           itself, it is called vasovagal component.

        3. BLOOD PRESSURE

      The adaptability is classified as

        1. Hypo-adaptability: presence of at least one of the followings:

             1. Symptoms of hypotension and/or

             2. Neurally mediated syncope (clinical or at the tilt-test) or vasovagal syncope
                and/or

             3. Hypotension at the office or at the tilt-test

        2. Normal-adaptability: normal blood pressure and no symptoms of hypotension, no neurally
           mediated syncope or vasovagal syncope (spontaneous or induced in the tilt table test)
           and no presence of hypotension. Include those who develop permanent hypertension after
           70 yo.

        3. Hyper-adaptability: Arterial hypertension starting before 71 yo, with no identifiable
           cause, no symptoms of hypotension, neurally mediated syncope or vasovagal syncope.

      Adaptability scores (scores between 1 and 7 apply for hypo-adaptive only)

        1. Only the presence of symptoms

        2. Only essential hypotension

        3. Only neurally mediated syncope

        4. 1 and 2

        5. 1 and 3

        6. 2 and 3

        7. 1, 2 and 3

        8. Normotensive

        9. Hypertensive

       10. The patient does not remember

      Thus then, 3 groups of blood pressure are recognized at the moment of evaluating their
      impact on the comorbidities:

        1. Normotensive

        2. Hypotensive

        3. Hypertensive, that in turn can be:

             1. Hypertensive since the admission

             2. Previously hypotensive

             3. Previously normotensive

      Here the evidence shows that there are individuals with essential hypertension and are
      hypo-adaptive. How can we reconcile this? Possible explanations are:

      1. Other factors related to the elevation of blood pressure may be involved (greater genetic
      load, more structural changes, greater contribution of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone
      system, etc.) 2. A change in the neuroendocrine response pattern by altering central
      regulators may be altered 3. Factors associated with age, but more active in this group of
      patients 4. It must be investigated about other causes of hypertension.

      METHODS

      Cohort.

      LABORATORY EXAMINATIONS Complete blood count Basal glycemia and 2 hour post-load 75 g
      glucose Insulinaemia Glycated hemoglobin Serum ferritin Thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH)
      and sometimes free thyroxine (T4) Sodium and serum potassium Uric acid Lipid profile
      Creatinine Basal serum cortisol and/or post-Adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) 24-hour
      urinary free cortisol Post-dexamethasone cortisol: in those with high cortisol with not
      recognized cause 24-hour urine catecholamines (Epinephrine, Norepinephrine and
      Metanephrines) Microalbuminuria Others depending on the case, such as: gliadin antibodies,
      vanillylmandelic acid, PTH (parathyroid hormone), vitamin B12, folic acid, ANAs,
      testosterone, creatinine clearance, antibodies against human hemoglobin in stool,
      hypersensitive reactive C protein (RCP), 24-hours urinary sodium, brain natriuretic peptide,
      etc.

      There is not a single laboratory to make the blood tests, so there are different values of
      normality for some tests.

      PHYSICAL EXAMINATION

      ANTHROPOMETRIC MEASUREMENTS:

      In every medical consultation, the patient is weighed wearing trousers or skirt. The waist
      is measured at an equidistant level between the last rib and the iliac crest. The hip is
      measured at the level of the greater trochanter. Finally, the size that appears in the
      identity card of the patient, or the latest measurement is written down.

      TAKING OF BLOOD PRESSURE:

      It is performed using a mercury sphygmomanometer from Tycos brand (it is revised annually in
      accordance with the current rules of the Ministry of Health), and it is controlled that the
      mercury column falls to 2 mm per second.

      The bracelet must cover approximately the 80% of the forearm. We have three sizes of
      bracelets as needed, including a pediatric bracelet. This should be positioned at heart
      level.

      The appearance of the first sound and the disappearance of Korotkoff sounds are taken as
      systolic and diastolic blood pressure respectively.

      About 6 BP measurements are taken, two on supine position and the second one after 5 minutes
      supine, this second supine value is the one used to calculate the BP drop upon standing.
      Later, and having the bracelet previously inflated, the BP is taken immediately the supine
      position is assumed (first 30 seconds). Then, additional pressures are taken at the first,
      second and third minute.

      The same process is fulfilled for the HR. During the taking of blood pressure neither the
      patient nor the doctor talk, and it is avoided making any comments that might alter the
      patient psychologically, and potentially modify their blood pressure levels.

      ELECTROCARDIOGRAM (HEWLETT PACKARD AND MORTARA) It is made a careful reading of each plot,
      in which are recorded the HR, PR and cQT intervals, and QRS complex (automatic
      measurements).

      24 HOURS ECG MONITORING (HOLTER) With at least 18 hours of registration, it is specified the
      patient rhythm, if is under medication that may affect the heart rate variability (HRV) and,
      it is recorded the name and type of drug. The number of supraventricular and ventricular
      premature complexes are counted.

      The components of heart rate variability (HRV) allows calculating the sympathovagal balance
      (SVB) in 24 hours, in the day (06:00 to 22:00) and at night (22:00 to 6:00).

      Low frequency (LF), high frequency (HF), very low frequency (VLF), Total power (TP) LF or HF
      one = LF or HF x 100/ TP-VLF SVB = LFone/HFone

      AMBULATORY BLOOD PRESSURE MONITORING (ABPM) The systolic and diastolic BP and HR are
      registered in 24 hours, in the day and at night, as in the 24-hour Holter monitoring. This
      test is requested for all patients in order to define the presence of white coat
      hypertension or masked hypertension and to define an effective treatment.

      Morning surge in SBP: It results from the difference between the averages of SBP taken in
      the first 2 hours from awakening and the lower nighttime.

      COLOR DOPPLER ECHOCARDIOGRAM AND/OR STRESS ECHOCARDIOGRAM It is made the measurement of the
      heart and if the response to stress is positive or negative.

      The ejection fraction (EF) is usually measured by the technique of Simpson or in a
      qualitative way.

      Body surface area = (weight x height / 36) X 1/2 Cardiac mass  = 1.05 [(LVDD + SW + PW)3 -
      LVDD3] - 14 Cardiac mass index = cardiac mass / body surface area

      ABDOMINAL ULTRASOUND It is recorded the presence of fatty liver and abdominal aortic
      aneurysm

      UPPER GASTROINTESTINAL ENDOSCOPY AND COLONOSCOPY The main findings are recorded

      CORONARY ANGIOGRAPHY According to the judgment of the specialist who makes the examination,
      it is made a ventriculography and a qualitative or quantitative measurement of the EF.

      Indication: For those who belong to the protocol and will indicate it, it is tried that the
      indication belongs to a score between 7 and 9 (appropriate test for a specific indication)
      of the recommendation of the working group aforementioned.

      Indication:

        1. In patients with symptoms of acute coronary syndrome or positive test for myocardial
           ischemia in individuals with moderate or high cardiovascular risk

        2. In patients with sustained ventricular tachyarrhythmias with unidentifiable cause that
           stop spontaneously or require resuscitation

        3. In patients with left ventricular dysfunction at basal conditions (ejection fraction &lt;
           40%) and evidence of viability in the affected segments.

        4. Evidence of new segmental alteration of motility of unknown etiology, mainly if
           associated with symptoms of coronary disease.

        5. Suspected ischemic mitral regurgitation or interventricular septal defect.

        6. Presence on the CT scan of lesions &gt; 50% on the left main trunk or other vessels, or
           possibly obstructive lesions of debatable severity in symptomatic patients (when in the
           left main trunk, also in asymptomatic patients)

      It is classified according to the obstruction to coronary flow as follows:

        -  Lesion &lt; 50%, non-obstructive (if not the left main trunk)

        -  Between 50 - 69%, intermediate lesion (if not the left main trunk)

        -  &gt; 70% or &gt; 50% of the left main trunk, it is a significant obstructive lesion. It is
           neither specified the number of affected vessels nor the vessel diameter.

      ELECTROPHYSIOLOGICAL STUDY The patient must be in a fasting state and must stop taking
      medications that affect the study for at least 5 half-lives. It is made by puncturing the
      right femoral vein, electro-catheters are placed in the high right atrium, in the bundle of
      His and in the right ventricular apex. It is stimulated the double of the thresholds to 3
      cycle lengths (600, 500 and 430 ms) and three extra cycles, starting at 350 ms, and with
      successive decreases of 10 ms until the refractory period is found.

      The study is made at basal conditions and in presence of Isoproterenol up to 4
      micrograms/minute; the sedation is obtained with Midazolam, administered 10 minutes before
      starting the procedure.

      Sinus function tests: Sinoatrial conduction time (by Narula method), the sinus node recovery
      time (SNRT) and the corrected sinus node recovery time (CSNRT)). For the SNRT, it is
      stimulated to several cycle lengths for one minute, with decreases of 100 ms up to 430 ms,
      and the longest pause is considered as the recovery time; if greater than 1500 ms is
      considered abnormal.

      The CSNRT is the result of SNRT minus the cycle length of the patient. It is considered
      abnormal 500 ms or more (sensitivity of 85% and specificity of 90%). Additionally, at five
      minutes, it is evaluated the response of the heart rate to the infusion of 3 micrograms of
      Isoproterenol per minute (an increase of 25% from basal HR) and the intrinsic heart rate.

      This latter is made by administering Atropine 0.04 mg/kg and propranolol 0.2 mg/kg, the
      intrinsic heart rate is dependent on the age, and is calculated as follows:

      118.1 - (0.57 x age), for people under the age of 45 the value is adjusted + 14% and for
      people over the age of 45 + 18%.

      Indication:

        1. In patients with syncope and ischemic heart disease, when the initial evaluation
           suggests an arrhythmic cause, except when it was already defined to implant an
           implantable cardioverter-defibrillator (ICD).

        2. In patients with syncope and bundle branch block, when the noninvasive evaluation has
           not clarified the diagnosis.

        3. When brief and sudden palpitations precede syncope, when the noninvasive evaluation has
           not clarified the diagnosis.

        4. In some cases of Brugada syndrome, arrhythmogenic right ventricular cardiomyopathy and
           hypertrophic cardiomyopathy.

        5. In high-risk patients in whom other methods have not clarified the diagnosis.

      TILT TABLE TEST The patient is connected to the noninvasive blood pressure beat to beat
      monitor. Currently a Task Force Monitor is used.

      The patient must be fasting for at least 4 hours; should stay 5 minutes in supine position
      and then is bent at 60 degrees for 20 minutes. Then, it is administered 400 micrograms of
      sublingual nitroglycerin for 20 more minutes. The tilt table test is considered positive if
      the patient presents syncope or if the systolic blood pressure is lower than 60 mmHg. The
      hemodynamic variables, the heart rate variability, and the blood pressure are written down
      for those patients who have these values available.

      Other diagnoses written down on the tilt table test are:

        -  Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (POTS):

        -  Inappropriate sinus tachycardia (IST):

      It is defined as a HR greater than 90 bpm in supine position. - Orthostatic hypotension
      (OH): Fall in the systolic BP &gt; 20 mmHg or a systolic BP lower than 90 mmHg, at any time of
      the Tilt Table Test. It can be symptomatic or asymptomatic.

      - Asystole: Isoelectric line that last for more than 3 seconds on the electrocardiogram
      plot. The duration in seconds of the asystole is recorded.

        -  Chronotropic incompetence (CI):

      It refers to the inability of the heart to increase the HR more than 10% when standing up
      within the first 10 minutes, and if the HR in supine &lt; 70 bpm. Also, if this criterion is
      not met but the HR to 60 degrees is lower than 65 bpm.

      Indication:

      Single syncope episode of unknown origin in high risk patients, or recurrent syncope in
      absence of organic heart disease; or in presence of organic heart disease if cardiac
      etiology was previously dismissed.

      To show to the patient that he/she has this mechanism of syncope. To discriminate between
      reflex and orthostatic syncope To differentiate syncope from epilepsy To diagnose patients
      with recurrent unexpected falls To evaluate patients with recurrent syncope and psychiatric
      disease Many patients referred by other colleagues already have the Tilt-test.

      CAROTID SINUS MASSAGE (CSM) It is made during the tilt table test (TTT)

      Contraindications for the accomplishment of the procedure:

        1. History of cerebrovascular disease

        2. Acute myocardial infarction in the previous 3 months, or

        3. Presence of carotid bruit during the neck auscultation. The test consists of doing
           pressure and circular movements during 10 seconds on each carotid sinus, allowing an
           interval of 1 minute between both sides to avoid the additive effect of these two. The
           massage is made at 0 and 60 degrees tilt. It is considered a vasodilatory response if
           the systolic BP falls at least 50 mmHg, and chronotropic response if an asystole is
           induced for 3 or more seconds. If this latter occurs, it is expected the patient to
           recover and the carotid massage is repeated after applying atropine 1 mg. If still
           positive for syncope it is considered a mixed response to the CSM.

      OTHER EXAMINATIONS

      These tests are requested as needed to clarify other findings. Some of the diagnostic aids
      used are:

        1. Computerized axial tomography of brain, heart

        2. Brain or heart nuclear magnetic resonance

        3. Polysomnography

        4. Meta-iodo-benzyl-guanidine

        5. Extracranial circulation

        6. Renal and lower limbs arteries Duplex

        7. Heart or other structures biopsy

        8. Others

      DATABASE We have over 1100 variables in OpenClinica 3.1.4

      UPDATING INFORMATION It is made through the consultations, phone calls or emails sent to the
      patient email address. The patients should be contacted annually.

      Requested information:

        1. Updating of landlines, cell phones and e-mail addresses

        2. Full treatment

        3. Patient  is questioned about new family histories

        4. Patient is questioned about new comorbidities, when were they diagnosed and by whom,
           following the existing comorbidities in the database.

        5. Patient is questioned about  his/her current weight

        6. Paraclinical laboratory tests are requested to the patient to write them down in the
           medical history.

      COMORBIDITIES DIAGNOSTIC CRITERIA

        1. Depression:

           The diagnosis is made by a psychiatrist and/or if the patient meets the criteria of DSM
           IV. If there is difference between the psychiatric diagnosis and the DSM IV criteria,
           it always prevails the diagnosis made by the psychiatrist.

        2. Panic attack:

           The diagnosis is made by a psychiatrist, the DSM IV criteria or both, it always
           prevails the diagnosis made by the psychiatrist.

        3. Fibromyalgia:

           It is diagnosed by a rheumatologist.

        4. Postural Orthostatic Tachycardia Syndrome (POTS):

             -  Increase in the HR &gt; 30 bpm when standing up.

             -  Increase in the HR &gt; 40 bpm when standing up, between 12 and 18 years old.

             -  HR &gt; 120 bpm during the first 10 minutes of standing up, not associated with
                hypotension.

        5. Inappropriate sinus tachycardia:

           It is the HR average during the 24-hour Holter monitoring &gt; 90 bpm, in absence of
           medication or hyperthyroidism.

        6. Coronary heart disease:

           It is diagnosed by the ACS criteria or by the abnormal coronary angiogram.

        7. Acute coronary syndrome (ACS):

           It refers to clinical, enzymatic, electrocardiographic, echocardiographic or
           angiographic findings, diagnosis of acute coronary disease. It should be dismissed the
           cocaine abuse, Prinzmetal's angina and Takotsubo cardiomyopathy. This latter is
           classified as such in a separate box.

        8. Acute myocardial infarction (AMI):

           Term used when there is evidence of myocardial tissue necrosis in the clinical spectrum
           of myocardial ischemia.

           Ischemic symptoms. New changes or presumed new in the ST segment and T wave, or a new
           left bundle branch block (LBBB).

           Development of new Q waves on the ECG Evidence by images of loss of viable myocardium,
           or the emergence of a segmental defect in the motility.

           Identification of an intracoronary thrombus in an angiography or autopsy.

           Criteria for prior myocardial infarction:

           Pathological Q waves on the ECG, with or without symptoms, in absence of non-ischemic
           causes.

           Evidence by images of loss of viable myocardium, which is thinner and does not
           contract, in absence of non-ischemic cause.

           Pathological findings of a previous MI.

        9. Cerebrovascular disease (CVD) or transient cerebral ischemia (TCI):

           The TCI has traditionally been considered as a deficit lower than 24 hours in duration,
           and so it is considered in this protocol. Well-founded evidence suggests duration lower
           than 60 minutes, and no evidence of nerve damage proved by CT scan or MRI.

       10. Atrial fibrillation:

           Baseline low amplitude oscillations with irregular rhythm, with major episodes of 6
           minutes on the ECG, in presence or absence of symptoms, or associated with CHADS score
           &gt;= 1.

           Any evidence of clinical relevance.

       11. Diabetes mellitus:

           Fasting glucose &gt; 126 mgs/dl Occasional glucose &gt; 200 mgs/dl with symptoms Glucose load
           (75 g): &gt; 200 at 2 hours A1C &gt; 6.5.

       12. Cancer:

           It is diagnosed by oncologist. It includes basal cell carcinoma (BCC).

       13. Systolic or diastolic heart failure:

           Patients should be symptomatic. It is considered systolic if the ejection fraction is
           decreased, otherwise, it is considered diastolic. In case of being diastolic, it should
           be dismissed other causes of dyspnea, such as lung diseases. If the origin is cardiac,
           it must be present with increased brain natriuretic peptide, which is requested.

       14. Chronic fatigue syndrome or idiopathic chronic fatigue:

           Persistent or chronic fatigue, clinically evaluated, unexplained, which lasts for 6 or
           more consecutive months, of recent onset, not explained by exercising, not improved
           substantially with rest and that produces a substantial reduction in previous levels of
           occupational, social, educational and personal activities.

           The patient must have 4 of the following symptoms, which must have persisted or be
           recurrent for 6 or more consecutive months of illness, and must have not been preceded
           by fatigue: a) self-reporting of poor short-term memory or decreased ability to
           concentrate, as severe as to alter the previous functional ability, b) dry throat, c)
           armpit and cervical adenopathies, d) muscle pain, joint pain without redness, deformity
           or swelling, de-novo headache, e) unrefreshing sleep, and malaise post exercise that
           lasts more than 24 hours.

           Some individuals have fatigue for more than 6 months but they do not meet the criteria
           previously set out. For example, they have major depression (other less intense
           depressions do not exclude the diagnosis), so they better qualify for idiopathic
           chronic fatigue.

       15. Syncope:

           It refers to the transient loss of consciousness secondary to cerebral hypoperfusion,
           characterized by sudden onset, short duration, and spontaneous and complete recovery.

       16. Vasovagal syncope Emotion mediated syncope or orthostatic stress, usually preceded by
           autonomic activation prodromes (diaphoresis, pallor, nausea). It includes situational
           syncope and carotid sinus hypersensitivity.

      PSYCHO BIOTYPE EVALUATION

      Design to study in depth the Psycho Biotype hypothesis. It consist of consecutive patients
      of each BP group to whom the following test are apply:

        1. Big Five Questionary (BFQ) for personality.

        2. Modified  Coping Scale (Scale of modified coping strategies)

        3. Zung questionary for depression and anxiety

        4. MINI in those patients with moderate or severe depression and/or anxiety  at the Zung
           questionary, apply by a psychiatrist

      GENERAL OBJECTIVE

      To demonstrate if the essential arterial hypotension and/or the adaptability are clinically
      important and try to identify the mechanism involve.

      SPECIFIC OBJECTIVES

      To demonstrate that the three groups of blood pressure differ in the numbers taken as much
      in the doctor's office as in the ambulatory blood pressure monitoring.

      To inquire what variables are different between the groups of blood pressure. To inquire
      which comorbidities are more associated with each group of blood pressure and evaluate
      whether the differences persist after a multivariate analysis. The same will be done with
      the adaptability groups.

      To provide hypotheses or evidences to explain the findings of the study.

      DESIGN OF THE STUDY

      This is an observational, analytic, cohort type study that aims to compare the differences
      between groups of patients classified according to their BP numbers and their adaptability.

      To this end, variables of the clinical, paraclinical, imaging and comorbidities profile will
      be evaluated.

      The database is designed to be flexible. It allows choosing different conditions in
      different variables. The diagnoses have 3 options: No, New and Old. It is recorded the date
      of the physical examinations, the diagnoses and the paraclinical results to ensure accuracy
      in the calculation of the age and the relationship between the different variables during
      the analysis.

      The reports will be of prevalence (cross-sectional) and incidence (cohort). To evaluate the
      significance between the groups of blood pressure depending on morbidities and other
      variables, it is used a generalized linear model by adjusting the effect of the response
      variable based on the age, gender and tension group in all cases. In some cases, and when
      the response variable requires it, it is added the body mass index (BMI). When the response
      variable is qualitative, it is used a logit link function and it is obtained the
      corresponding Odds ratio with confidence intervals to 95%; while if the variable is
      quantitative it is used the identity function. Finally, the multiple comparison test of
      Tukey-Kramer is made in order to compare the groups of tension with a significance level of
      0.05.

      To evaluate the relationship between the blood pressure groups and the comorbidities, and
      other variables, the free events survival rates among participants using a Kaplan Meir
      survival curves, adjusted for age and other related variables.

      For the diagnosis of coronary disease, it was used a generalized linear model in which was
      evaluated the adjustment of the effect in the groups of tension by age, gender, and body
      mass index (BMI), diabetes mellitus (DM), systolic and diastolic blood pressure in supine,
      total cholesterol, HDL cholesterol, smoking, and blood pressure group. Variables were
      selected by the method of Backward maintaining in the model those variables with a
      significance level of 0.05.

      LIMITATIONS:

        1. Because patients were recruited at the doctor's office, some of them may decide not to
           take the required tests or decide not to come back.

        2. Some insurance companies may not provide some test, like the Ambulatory blood pressure
           monitoring.

        3. Also, the attending practitioner may be busy with too much work and has not available
           time to see the patients opportunely.

        4. The blood tests can be done at different sites and by different operators.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1995</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>15 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between Blood pressure group and comorbidities</measure>
    <time_frame>A 7-year prospective study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood pressure group: 1) Essential arterial hypotension, 2) normotension and 3) Essential arterial hypertension.
Comorbidities: As describe in the protocol, as a summary: 1) cardiovascular, 2) metabolic, 3) Endocrine, 4) psychiatric disorders: depression and panic disorder, 5) orthostatic intolerance: neurally mediated syncope, vasovagal syncope, inappropriate sinus tachycardia, Postural orthostatic syndrome, carotid sinus hypersensitivity;  6) others: chronic fatigue syndrome, fibromyalgia, arthritis, autoimmune diseases, pulmonary thromboembolism, OSA (obstructive sleep apnea), Alzheimer disease, Parkinson disease, others dementias, epilepsia, nephropathies, and others.
Cardiovascular mortality Total mortality</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between adaptability group and comorbidities</measure>
    <time_frame>A 7-year prospective study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Adaptability group: Hyper adaptable, normal adaptability, hypo adaptable. Comorbidities: As describe in the protocol, as a summary: 1) cardiovascular, 2) metabolic, 3) Endocrine, 4) psychiatric disorders: depression and panic disorder, 5) orthostatic intolerance: neurally mediated syncope, vasovagal syncope, inappropriate sinus tachycardia, Postural orthostatic syndrome, carotid sinus hypersensitivity;  6) others: chronic fatigue syndrome, fibromyalgia, arthritis, autoimmune diseases, pulmonary thromboembolism, OSA (obstructive sleep apnea), Alzheimer disease, Parkinson disease, others dementias, epilepsia, nephropathies, and others.
Cardiovascular mortality Total mortality</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between blood pressure group, adaptability group and comorbidities</measure>
    <time_frame>A 7-year prospective study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood pressure group: 1) Essential arterial hypotension, 2) normotension and 3) Essential arterial hypertension.
Adaptability group: Hyper adaptable, normal adaptability, hypo adaptable. Comorbidities: As describe in the protocol, as a summary: 1) cardiovascular, 2) metabolic, 3) Endocrine, 4) psychiatric disorders: depression and panic disorder, 5) orthostatic intolerance: neurally mediated syncope, vasovagal syncope, inappropriate sinus tachycardia, Postural orthostatic syndrome, carotid sinus hypersensitivity;  6) others: chronic fatigue syndrome, fibromyalgia, arthritis, autoimmune diseases, pulmonary thromboembolism, OSA (obstructive sleep apnea), Alzheimer disease, Parkinson disease, others dementias, epilepsia, nephropathies, and others.
Cardiovascular mortality Total mortality</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between blood pressure group, habits and anthropometric, metabolic, endocrine, Electrocardiogram, Holter, ambulatory blood pressure monitoring (ABPM)</measure>
    <time_frame>A 7-year prospective study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood pressure group: 1) Essential arterial hypotension, 2) normotension and 3) Essential arterial hypertension.
Habits: smoke and drink
Anthropometric variables: Body mass index, waist, hip
Metabolic variables: Fasting glucose, 2 hs postprandial plasma glucose, insulin plasma levels, homoeostasis model assessment (HOMA), total cholesterol, LDL, HDL, triglycerides.
Endocrine variables: plasma cortisol, free cortisol in 24 hs. urine, epinephrine, norepinephrine, metanephrines, vanilmandelic acid, ACTH, aldosterone, renin, thyrotropine, free thyroxine, triiodothyronine, testosterone
Electrocardiogram: HR; PR interval, QRS complex, cQT interval
Holter variables: HR, standard deviation of NN intervals (SDNN) and sympathovagal balance, at day, night and 24 hs.
ABPM: Systolic, diastolic, and heart rate, at day, night and 24 hs., BP matinal surge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between blood pressure group, adaptability group, habits anthropometric, metabolic, endocrine, electrocardiographic, Holter, ambulatory arterial blood pressure monitoring.</measure>
    <time_frame>A 7-year prospective study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood pressure group: 1) Essential arterial hypotension, 2) normotension and 3) Essential arterial hypertension.
Adaptability group: Hyper adaptable, normal adaptability, hypo adaptable.
Habits: smoke and drink
Anthropometric variables: Body mass index, waist, hip
Metabolic variables: Fasting glucose, 2 hs postprandial plasma glucose, insulin plasma levels, HOMA, total cholesterol, LDL, HDL, triglycerides.
Endocrine variables: plasma cortisol, free cortisol in 24 hs. urine, epinephrine, norepinephrine, metanephrines, vanilmandelic acid, ACTH, aldosterone, renin, thyrotropine, free thyroxine, triiodothyronine, testosterone
Electrocardiogram: PR interval, QRS complex, Heart rate, cQT interval
Holter variables: HR, SDNN and sympathovagal balance, at day, night and 24 hs.
ABPM: Systolic, diastolic, and heart rate, at day, night and 24 hs., BP matinal surge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>For metabolic disorders what it matters the most: the anthropometric variables vs blood pressure group vs adaptability group</measure>
    <time_frame>A 7-year prospective study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood pressure group: 1) Essential arterial hypotension, 2) normotension and 3) Essential arterial hypertension.
Adaptability group: 1) Hyper adaptable, 2) normal adaptability and 3) hypo adaptable.
Habits: smoke and drink, exercise
Anthropometric variables: Body mass index, waist, hip
Metabolic and other variables: Fasting glucose, 2 hs postprandial plasma glucose, insulin plasma levels, HOMA, total cholesterol, LDL, HDL, triglycerides; thyrotropine,
Holter variables: HR, standard deviation of NN intervals (SDNN) and sympathovagal balance, at day, night and 24 hs.
ABPM: Systolic, diastolic, and heart rate, at day, night and 24 hs., BP matinal surge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between adaptability group, habits and anthropometric, metabolic, endocrine, Electrocardiogram, Holter, ambulatory blood pressure monitoring (ABPM)</measure>
    <time_frame>A 7-year prospective study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Adaptability group: Hyper adaptable, normal adaptability, hypo adaptable.
Habits: smoke and drink Anthropometric variables: Body mass index, waist, hip
Metabolic variables: Fasting glucose, 2 hs postprandial plasma glucose, insulin plasma levels, HOMA, total cholesterol, LDL, HDL, triglycerides.
Endocrine variables: plasma cortisol, free cortisol in 24 hs. urine, epinephrine, norepinephrine, metanephrines, vanilmandelic acid, ACTH, aldosterone, renin, thyrotropine, free thyroxine, triiodothyronine, testosterone
Electrocardiogram: PR interval, QRS complex, Heart rate, cQT interval
Holter variables: HR, SDNN and sympathovagal balance, at day, night and 24 hs.
ABPM: Systolic, diastolic, and heart rate, at day, night and 24 hs., BP matinal surge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Syncope Registry</measure>
    <time_frame>Up 100 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical syncope characteristics (age of first syncope, number of syncope episodes, trauma, duration, clinical score, convulse, sphincter relaxation, etc.) Syncope cause Blood pressure group Adaptability group Prognosis</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Tilt table testing (TTT) registry</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 100 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>TTT protocol: describe the protocol, the time at positive response, nitroglycerine use, autonomic and hemodynamic variables.
TTT outcome for syncope: positive or negative TTT other outcomes: 1) Chronotropic incompetence, 2) arterial orthostatic hypotension, 3) carotid hypersensitivity, 4) POTS, 5) IST The relationship between TTT results and Clinical score for syncope in regard to: syncope behaviour and other orthostatic intolerance entities, symptoms and comorbidities.
The relationship between neurally mediated syncope response at the TTT and comorbidities.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sinus node function at the electrophysiological study (EPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 100 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>EPS variables: AH, AV, CL, sino atrial conduction time (SACT), sinus node recovery time (SNRT), corrected sinus node recovery time (CSNRT), response to Isoproterenol, intrinsic heart rate Diagnosis: control, sick sinus syndrome, IST, chronotropic incompetence at the TTT HR at the ECG HR at the Holter monitoring HR at the TTT HRV at the Holter monitoring Syncope, cardiac or neurally mediated HR at the physical treadmill test Relationship with the blood pressure group Relationship with the adaptability group</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Score for coronary artery disease</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 200 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Define how the blood pressure group and/or the adaptability group may add to the already known and include in this registry, in the diagnosis of cardiovascular complications as coronary artery disease, cerebrovascular disease, peripheral artery disease, nephropathy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Neurally Mediated Syncope: further of the transient lost of consciousness (TLC)</measure>
    <time_frame>A 7-year prospective study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood pressure group: 1) Essential arterial hypotension, 2) normotension and 3) Essential arterial hypertension.
Adaptability group: Hyper adaptable, normal adaptability, hypo adaptable. Comorbidities: As describe in the protocol, as a summary: 1) cardiovascular, 2) metabolic, 3) Endocrine, 4) psychiatric disorders: depression and panic disorder, 5) orthostatic intolerance: neurally mediated syncope, vasovagal syncope, inappropriate sinus tachycardia, Postural orthostatic syndrome, carotid sinus hypersensitivity;  6) others: chronic fatigue syndrome, fibromyalgia, arthritis, autoimmune diseases, pulmonary thromboembolism, OSA (obstructive sleep apnea), Alzheimer disease, Parkinson disease, others dementias, epilepsia, nephropathies, COPD, and others.
Mortality</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Psychobiotype: relationship between biological and psychological variables</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 100 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood pressure group: 1) Essential arterial hypotension, 2) normotension and 3) Essential arterial hypertension.
Adaptability group: Hyper adaptable, normal adaptability, hypo adaptable.
Psychiatric variables:
Big Five Questionary (BFQ) for personality.
Modify of the Coping Scale (Scale of modified coping strategies)
Zung questionary for depression and anxiety
MINI in those patients with moderate or severe depression and/or anxiety  at the Zung questionary</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>Blood Pressure</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Panic Attack</condition>
  <condition>Fibromyalgia</condition>
  <condition>POTS</condition>
  <condition>Inappropriate Sinus Tachycardia</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Heart Disease</condition>
  <condition>Acute Coronary Syndrome (ACS)</condition>
  <condition>Acute Myocardial Infarction (AMI)</condition>
  <condition>Cerebrovascular Disease (CVD)</condition>
  <condition>Transient Ischemic Attack (TIA)</condition>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Systolic Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Diastolic Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Fatigue Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Syncope</condition>
  <condition>Vasovagal Syncope</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Consecutive patients who consult a cardiologist</arm_group_label>
    <description>Consecutive patients who consult a cardiologist - electrophysiologist since June 2006, regardless of the age or gender in the city of Medellin, Colombia. They could have consulted previously (considered as the enrollment date) if they had, at least, one measurement of their BP in supine position, and an immediate measurement of their BP in standing position that allows diagnosing their group of blood pressure. All patients have a record in paper and/or magnetic file and in OpenClinica.
No interventions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Consecutive patients that visits a cardiologist's office in Medellin, Colombia. The
        population consists of patients of any age and gender, which are classified according to
        their blood pressure in: normotensive, hypertensive and hypotensive, they are also
        classified according to their adaptability in hypo, normo and hyper.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Any patient regardless of the age of gender

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any non-correctable secondary cause of increase or decrease in blood pressure

          -  or a pathology that alters the prognosis before the entrance of the patient into this
             registry.

          -  nephropathy prior to the admission,

          -  familial dyslipidemia,

          -  previous gastric bypass,

          -  pre-existing heart failure,

          -  chemotherapy-induced cardiotoxicity,

          -  arrhythmogenic right ventricular dysplasia,

          -  long QT syndrome,

          -  hypertrophic cardiomyopathy

          -  restrictive cardiomyopathy or sudden death syndromes other than coronary disease

          -  Down syndrome,

          -  having one single kidney before entering to this registry,

          -  polycystic kidney,

          -  disability to continue with the treatment

          -  organ transplantation (other than cornea),

          -  HIV positive,

          -  homocystinuria,

          -  myelomeningocele,

          -  autoimmune diseases,

          -  paraplegia,

          -  chronic infections (TB),

          -  myocarditis of any cause,

          -  blood dyscrasia with coagulation disorders,

          -  history of pulmonary embolism,

          -  sustained or non-sustained ventricular tachycardia,

          -  idiopathic tachycardia associated with syncope or complex which is not cured by
             radiofrequency ablation,

          -  pulmonary hypertension,

          -  diabetes insipidus,

          -  COPD,

          -  Gitelman syndrome,

          -  Cervical cancer associated with human Papillomavirus,

          -  multiple sclerosis,

          -  hemochromatosis,

          -  not compact ventricle.

        It is important to emphasize that all of these patients, currently excluded from the
        registry, may be studied in the future, they keep on follow-up and taken 6 BP.

        Additionally it is planned to compare the evolution of patients with secondary causes of
        hypertension or hypotension with essential disorders
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Luis Eduardo Medina, MD.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Researcher</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Luis Eduardo Medina, MD.</last_name>
    <phone>(574)2323218</phone>
    <email>essentialhypotension@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CES University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Medellín</city>
        <state>Antioquia</state>
        <zip>00</zip>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Luis E Medina, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(57)3104055903</phone>
      <email>essentialhypotension@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jose F Florez, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jose M Cotes, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Colombia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.essentialhypotension.com</url>
    <description>WebSite of Registry</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Medina E, Uribe W, Duque M, Alzate L. Severity of Compromise and level of Limitation in patients with Orthostatic Intolerance. XIth International Symposium on the autonomic nervous system, Puerto Rico, 24-30 October 2000. Summary</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Medina LE, Ospina J, Lemos MA, Cuartas G, Calle J, Gutierrez M, Torres Y. Essential hypotension registry: Psychometric measurements for anxiety, depression and coping strategies: Hypotension is associated with depression and anxiety. Is there a psycho-biotype? Preliminary Report. Clinical Autonomic Research. Vol 19, number 5, page 296, 2009. Summary</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Medina LE, Uribe W, Marin J, Aristizabal J, Velasquez J, Miranda A, Torres Y, Restrepo MA, Duque M. The importance of essential hypotension in syncope. A report of 877 patients. The essential hypotension registry. Clinical. Autonomic Research. Vol 20, number 2, page 140, 2010. Summary</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huber M, Knottnerus JA, Green L, van der Horst H, Jadad AR, Kromhout D, Leonard B, Lorig K, Loureiro MI, van der Meer JW, Schnabel P, Smith R, van Weel C, Smid H. How should we define health? BMJ. 2011 Jul 26;343:d4163. doi: 10.1136/bmj.d4163.</citation>
    <PMID>21791490</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pacák K, Palkovits M. Stressor specificity of central neuroendocrine responses: implications for stress-related disorders. Endocr Rev. 2001 Aug;22(4):502-48. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11493581</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Accurso V, Winnicki M, Shamsuzzaman AS, Wenzel A, Johnson AK, Somers VK. Predisposition to vasovagal syncope in subjects with blood/injury phobia. Circulation. 2001 Aug 21;104(8):903-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11514377</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karatsoreos IN, McEwen BS. Resilience and vulnerability: a neurobiological perspective. F1000Prime Rep. 2013 May 1;5:13. doi: 10.12703/P5-13. Print 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>23710327</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Selye H. A syndrome produced by diverse nocuous agents. 1936. J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci. 1998 Spring;10(2):230-1.</citation>
    <PMID>9722327</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>SELYE H. THE STRESS OF LIFE--NEW FOCAL POINT FOR UNDERSTANDING ACCIDENTS. Nurs Forum. 1965;4:28-38.</citation>
    <PMID>14280643</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ray O. The revolutionary health science of psychoendoneuroimmunology: a new paradigm for understanding health and treating illness. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2004 Dec;1032:35-51. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15677394</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McEwen BS. Protective and damaging effects of stress mediators. N Engl J Med. 1998 Jan 15;338(3):171-9. Review. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>9428819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chrousos GP. The hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis and immune-mediated inflammation. N Engl J Med. 1995 May 18;332(20):1351-62. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>7715646</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gruzelier J, Clow A, Evans P, Lazar I, Walker L. Mind-body influences on immunity: lateralized control, stress, individual differences predictors, and prophylaxis. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 1998 Jun 30;851:487-94. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9668642</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosengren A, Hawken S, Ounpuu S, Sliwa K, Zubaid M, Almahmeed WA, Blackett KN, Sitthi-amorn C, Sato H, Yusuf S; INTERHEART investigators. Association of psychosocial risk factors with risk of acute myocardial infarction in 11119 cases and 13648 controls from 52 countries (the INTERHEART study): case-control study. Lancet. 2004 Sep 11;364(9438):953-62.</citation>
    <PMID>15364186</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shin C, Abbott RD, Lee H, Kim J, Kimm K. Prevalence and correlates of orthostatic hypotension in middle-aged men and women in Korea: the Korean Health and Genome Study. J Hum Hypertens. 2004 Oct;18(10):717-23.</citation>
    <PMID>15116144</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fedorowski A, Stavenow L, Hedblad B, Berglund G, Nilsson PM, Melander O. Orthostatic hypotension predicts all-cause mortality and coronary events in middle-aged individuals (The Malmo Preventive Project). Eur Heart J. 2010 Jan;31(1):85-91. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehp329. Epub 2009 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>19696189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rose KM, Eigenbrodt ML, Biga RL, Couper DJ, Light KC, Sharrett AR, Heiss G. Orthostatic hypotension predicts mortality in middle-aged adults: the Atherosclerosis Risk In Communities (ARIC) Study. Circulation. 2006 Aug 15;114(7):630-6. Epub 2006 Aug 7.</citation>
    <PMID>16894039</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rose KM, Tyroler HA, Nardo CJ, Arnett DK, Light KC, Rosamond W, Sharrett AR, Szklo M. Orthostatic hypotension and the incidence of coronary heart disease: the Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities study. Am J Hypertens. 2000 Jun;13(6 Pt 1):571-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10912737</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benvenuto LJ, Krakoff LR. Morbidity and mortality of orthostatic hypotension: implications for management of cardiovascular disease. Am J Hypertens. 2011 Feb;24(2):135-44. doi: 10.1038/ajh.2010.146. Epub 2010 Sep 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20814408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferrier C, Esler MD, Eisenhofer G, Wallin BG, Horne M, Cox HS, Lambert G, Jennings GL. Increased norepinephrine spillover into the jugular veins in essential hypertension. Hypertension. 1992 Jan;19(1):62-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1730441</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kannel WB, Wolf PA, McGee DL, Dawber TR, McNamara P, Castelli WP. Systolic blood pressure, arterial rigidity, and risk of stroke. The Framingham study. JAMA. 1981 Mar 27;245(12):1225-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7206111</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miall WE. Systolic or diastolic hypertension--which matters most? Clin Exp Hypertens A. 1982;4(7):1121-31.</citation>
    <PMID>7116661</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miall WE, Lovell HG. Relation between change of blood pressure and age. Br Med J. 1967 Jun 10;2(5553):660-4.</citation>
    <PMID>6024522</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grassi G. Assessment of sympathetic cardiovascular drive in human hypertension: achievements and perspectives. Hypertension. 2009 Oct;54(4):690-7. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.108.119883. Epub 2009 Aug 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19720958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Franklin SS, Gustin W 4th, Wong ND, Larson MG, Weber MA, Kannel WB, Levy D. Hemodynamic patterns of age-related changes in blood pressure. The Framingham Heart Study. Circulation. 1997 Jul 1;96(1):308-15.</citation>
    <PMID>9236450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chobanian AV, Bakris GL, Black HR, Cushman WC, Green LA, Izzo JL Jr, Jones DW, Materson BJ, Oparil S, Wright JT Jr, Roccella EJ; Joint National Committee on Prevention, Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure. National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute; National High Blood Pressure Education Program Coordinating Committee. Seventh report of the Joint National Committee on Prevention, Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure. Hypertension. 2003 Dec;42(6):1206-52. Epub 2003 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>14656957</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mancia G, De Backer G, Dominiczak A, Cifkova R, Fagard R, Germano G, Grassi G, Heagerty AM, Kjeldsen SE, Laurent S, Narkiewicz K, Ruilope L, Rynkiewicz A, Schmieder RE, Boudier HA, Zanchetti A, Vahanian A, Camm J, De Caterina R, Dean V, Dickstein K, Filippatos G, Funck-Brentano C, Hellemans I, Kristensen SD, McGregor K, Sechtem U, Silber S, Tendera M, Widimsky P, Zamorano JL, Erdine S, Kiowski W, Agabiti-Rosei E, Ambrosioni E, Lindholm LH, Viigimaa M, Adamopoulos S, Agabiti-Rosei E, Ambrosioni E, Bertomeu V, Clement D, Erdine S, Farsang C, Gaita D, Lip G, Mallion JM, Manolis AJ, Nilsson PM, O'Brien E, Ponikowski P, Redon J, Ruschitzka F, Tamargo J, van Zwieten P, Waeber B, Williams B; Management of Arterial Hypertension of the European Society of Hypertension; European Society of Cardiology. 2007 Guidelines for the Management of Arterial Hypertension: The Task Force for the Management of Arterial Hypertension of the European Society of Hypertension (ESH) and of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC). J Hypertens. 2007 Jun;25(6):1105-87. No abstract available. Erratum in: J Hypertens. 2007 Aug;25(8):1749.</citation>
    <PMID>17563527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pickering TG, Shimbo D, Haas D. Ambulatory blood-pressure monitoring. N Engl J Med. 2006 Jun 1;354(22):2368-74. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16738273</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kikuya M, Hansen TW, Thijs L, Björklund-Bodegård K, Kuznetsova T, Ohkubo T, Richart T, Torp-Pedersen C, Lind L, Ibsen H, Imai Y, Staessen JA; International Database on Ambulatory blood pressure monitoring in relation to Cardiovascular Outcomes Investigators. Diagnostic thresholds for ambulatory blood pressure monitoring based on 10-year cardiovascular risk. Circulation. 2007 Apr 24;115(16):2145-52. Epub 2007 Apr 9.</citation>
    <PMID>17420350</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beckett NS, Peters R, Fletcher AE, Staessen JA, Liu L, Dumitrascu D, Stoyanovsky V, Antikainen RL, Nikitin Y, Anderson C, Belhani A, Forette F, Rajkumar C, Thijs L, Banya W, Bulpitt CJ; HYVET Study Group. Treatment of hypertension in patients 80 years of age or older. N Engl J Med. 2008 May 1;358(18):1887-98. Epub 2008 Mar 31.</citation>
    <PMID>18378519</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Freeman R, Wieling W, Axelrod FB, Benditt DG, Benarroch E, Biaggioni I, Cheshire WP, Chelimsky T, Cortelli P, Gibbons CH, Goldstein DS, Hainsworth R, Hilz MJ, Jacob G, Kaufmann H, Jordan J, Lipsitz LA, Levine BD, Low PA, Mathias C, Raj SR, Robertson D, Sandroni P, Schatz I, Schondorff R, Stewart JM, van Dijk JG. Consensus statement on the definition of orthostatic hypotension, neurally mediated syncope and the postural tachycardia syndrome. Clin Auton Res. 2011 Apr;21(2):69-72. doi: 10.1007/s10286-011-0119-5.</citation>
    <PMID>21431947</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robertson D. The pathophysiology and diagnosis of orthostatic hypotension. Clin Auton Res. 2008 Mar;18 Suppl 1:2-7. doi: 10.1007/s10286-007-1004-0. Epub 2008 Mar 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18368300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Task Force for the Diagnosis and Management of Syncope; European Society of Cardiology (ESC); European Heart Rhythm Association (EHRA); Heart Failure Association (HFA); Heart Rhythm Society (HRS), Moya A, Sutton R, Ammirati F, Blanc JJ, Brignole M, Dahm JB, Deharo JC, Gajek J, Gjesdal K, Krahn A, Massin M, Pepi M, Pezawas T, Ruiz Granell R, Sarasin F, Ungar A, van Dijk JG, Walma EP, Wieling W. Guidelines for the diagnosis and management of syncope (version 2009). Eur Heart J. 2009 Nov;30(21):2631-71. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehp298. Epub 2009 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>19713422</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carter JR, Ray CA. Sympathetic neural responses to mental stress: responders, nonresponders and sex differences. Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol. 2009 Mar;296(3):H847-53. doi: 10.1152/ajpheart.01234.2008. Epub 2009 Jan 23.</citation>
    <PMID>19168718</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sheldon R, Rose S, Connolly S, Ritchie D, Koshman ML, Frenneaux M. Diagnostic criteria for vasovagal syncope based on a quantitative history. Eur Heart J. 2006 Feb;27(3):344-50. Epub 2005 Oct 13.</citation>
    <PMID>16223744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holmes TH, Rahe RH. The Social Readjustment Rating Scale. J Psychosom Res. 1967 Aug;11(2):213-8.</citation>
    <PMID>6059863</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grubb BP, Kosinski DJ, Boehm K, Kip K. The postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome: a neurocardiogenic variant identified during head-up tilt table testing. Pacing Clin Electrophysiol. 1997 Sep;20(9 Pt 1):2205-12.</citation>
    <PMID>9309745</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bybee KA, Kara T, Prasad A, Lerman A, Barsness GW, Wright RS, Rihal CS. Systematic review: transient left ventricular apical ballooning: a syndrome that mimics ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction. Ann Intern Med. 2004 Dec 7;141(11):858-65. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15583228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Matthews DR, Hosker JP, Rudenski AS, Naylor BA, Treacher DF, Turner RC. Homeostasis model assessment: insulin resistance and beta-cell function from fasting plasma glucose and insulin concentrations in man. Diabetologia. 1985 Jul;28(7):412-9.</citation>
    <PMID>3899825</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Räihä I, Luutonen S, Piha J, Seppänen A, Toikka T, Sourander L. Prevalence, predisposing factors, and prognostic importance of postural hypotension. Arch Intern Med. 1995 May 8;155(9):930-5.</citation>
    <PMID>7726701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Furlan R, Jacob G, Palazzolo L, Rimoldi A, Diedrich A, Harris PA, Porta A, Malliani A, Mosqueda-Garcia R, Robertson D. Sequential modulation of cardiac autonomic control induced by cardiopulmonary and arterial baroreflex mechanisms. Circulation. 2001 Dec 11;104(24):2932-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11739308</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>White W, Shah H. Ambulatory blood pressure monitoring in clinical hypertension management. In: Hypertension. A Companion to Branwald Heart Disease, 2013, Second edition, Chapter 6, Page 59. Edited by Black H and Elliot W.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Devereux RB, Reichek N. Echocardiographic determination of left ventricular mass in man. Anatomic validation of the method. Circulation. 1977 Apr;55(4):613-8.</citation>
    <PMID>138494</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patel MR, Bailey SR, Bonow RO, Chambers CE, Chan PS, Dehmer GJ, Kirtane AJ, Wann LS, Ward RP. ACCF/SCAI/AATS/AHA/ASE/ASNC/HFSA/HRS/SCCM/SCCT/SCMR/STS 2012 appropriate use criteria for diagnostic catheterization: a report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation Appropriate Use Criteria Task Force, Society for Cardiovascular Angiography and Interventions, American Association for Thoracic Surgery, American Heart Association, American Society of Echocardiography, American Society of Nuclear Cardiology, Heart Failure Society of America, Heart Rhythm Society, Society of Critical Care Medicine, Society of Cardiovascular Computed Tomography, Society for Cardiovascular Magnetic Resonance, and Society of Thoracic Surgeons. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2012 May 29;59(22):1995-2027. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2012.03.003. Epub 2012 May 9.</citation>
    <PMID>22578925</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Narula OS, Samet P, Javier RP. Significance of the sinus-node recovery time. Circulation. 1972 Jan;45(1):140-58.</citation>
    <PMID>4108657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chadda KD, Banka VS, Bodenheimer MM, Helfant RH. Corrected sinus node recovery time. Experimental physiologic and pathologic determinants. Circulation. 1975 May;51(5):797-801.</citation>
    <PMID>1122582</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Desai JM, Scheinman MM, Strauss HC, Massie B, O'Young J. Electrophysiologic effects on combined autonomic blockade in patients with sinus node disease. Circulation. 1981 Apr;63(4):953-60.</citation>
    <PMID>7471352</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Albers GW, Caplan LR, Easton JD, Fayad PB, Mohr JP, Saver JL, Sherman DG; TIA Working Group. Transient ischemic attack--proposal for a new definition. N Engl J Med. 2002 Nov 21;347(21):1713-6. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>12444191</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fukuda K, Straus SE, Hickie I, Sharpe MC, Dobbins JG, Komaroff A. The chronic fatigue syndrome: a comprehensive approach to its definition and study. International Chronic Fatigue Syndrome Study Group. Ann Intern Med. 1994 Dec 15;121(12):953-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7978722</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andersen MM, Permin H, Albrecht F. Illness and disability in Danish Chronic Fatigue Syndrome patients at diagnosis and 5-year follow-up. J Psychosom Res. 2004 Feb;56(2):217-29.</citation>
    <PMID>15016582</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennett R. Fibromyalgia, chronic fatigue syndrome, and myofascial pain. Curr Opin Rheumatol. 1998 Mar;10(2):95-103. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9567202</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McEwen BS, Gianaros PJ. Central role of the brain in stress and adaptation: links to socioeconomic status, health, and disease. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2010 Feb;1186:190-222. doi: 10.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.05331.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20201874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 23, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 29, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>CES University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Luis Eduardo Medina</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Essential arterial hypotension</keyword>
  <keyword>Arterial hypotension</keyword>
  <keyword>Low blood pressure</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypotension</keyword>
  <keyword>Essential arterial hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Syncope</keyword>
  <keyword>Dysautonomia</keyword>
  <keyword>Stress</keyword>
  <keyword>Adaptability</keyword>
  <keyword>Reactivity</keyword>
  <keyword>Homeostasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Allostasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Allostatic load</keyword>
  <keyword>Distress</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemic Attack, Transient</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebrovascular Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatigue</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatigue Syndrome, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibromyalgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypotension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syncope</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tachycardia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tachycardia, Sinus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syncope, Vasovagal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Panic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Coronary Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure, Systolic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure, Diastolic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
