<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="161572">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02065895</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012P-000401</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02065895</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Gain on Closed-Loop Insulin</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Gain on Closed-Loop Insulin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Joslin Diabetes Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Juvenile Diabetes Research Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Joslin Diabetes Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test the ability of an advanced external Physiologic Insulin
      Delivery (ePID) algorithm (a step by step process used to develop a solution to a problem)
      to get acceptable meal responses over a range of gain.  Gain is defined as how much insulin
      is given in response to a change in a patient's glucose level.

      This study also examines the effectiveness of the external Physiologic Insulin Delivery
      (ePID) closed-loop insulin delivery computer software. The investigators would like to
      assess whether fasting target levels can be achieved as the closed-loop gain increases or
      decreases, and to evaluate the system's ability to produce an acceptable breakfast meal
      response.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There have been significant advances in diabetes management technology, including more
      sophisticated insulin pumps and more accurate real-time continuous glucose monitors.  The
      next technological development is widely thought to be the introduction of an algorithm
      linking the pump and sensor to form a closed-loop insulin delivery system.  The algorithm
      used for this purpose needs to be robust to changes in an individual's insulin sensitivity,
      and the sensor's sensitivity to glucose.  Insulin sensitivity (how much the patient's
      glucose level changes in response to a change in insulin delivery) and algorithm gain (how
      much insulin is delivered in response to a change in glucose) determine the systems overall
      closed-loop gain.  Ideally, the overall gain can be set to achieve the lowest possible peak
      postprandial glucose response without postprandial hypoglycemia.  However, if the
      algorithm's gain is set to a fixed value and the subject's insulin sensitivity changes, the
      overall-gain will change.  Some degradation in closed-loop performance might be acceptable
      during periods whenever the subject's insulin sensitivity is low (i.e., the subject is
      insulin resistant) and the risk of hypoglycemia may actually be reduced.  However, if the
      subject becomes more sensitive the system may become less stable and the risk of
      postprandial hypoglycemia may increase.  In addition to changes in insulin sensitivity,
      glucose sensors will sometimes over- or under-read blood glucose as sensor sensitivity
      increases or decreases.  This will result in a change in the closed-loop algorithm's
      effective target.  The purpose of this study is to evaluate the ability of an advanced
      Physiologic Insulin Delivery algorithm achieve an acceptable breakfast response as the gain
      and effective target glucose level changes.  Specifically:

        1. to assess the fasting glucose levels achieved as the overall closed-loop gain and
           effective target is increased or decreased, and

        2. determine the system's ability to produce an acceptable breakfast meal response under
           these conditions
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glucose Area Under the Curve (AUC) Breakfast</measure>
    <time_frame>8:00 AM to 12:00 PM with samples obtained every 10-15 minutes</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Breakfast closed loop control (artificial pancreas).  Closed-loop control calculates insulin delivery based on a minute to minute glucose signal, typically obtained from a glucose sensor.  In this study, the sensor signal is replaced by a gold-standard laboratory standard (YSI) glucose value and three different controller configurations are evaluated.  Low AUC is generally preferred.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak and nadir postprandial glucose concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>8: 00 AM to 12:00 PM</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Incidence of supplemental carbohydrate (15 grams of juice) used to prevent or correct hypoglycemia  (glucose less than 60 mg/dL)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Nighttime time-in-target (controller set-point plus and minus 15 mg/dL)</measure>
    <time_frame>12:00 AM - 8:00 AM</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Nighttime incidence of supplemental carbohydrate used to prevent or correct blood glucose less than 60 mg/dL.
Fasting glucose (8 AM value).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 1 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gain increase or decrease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Decrease insulin gain by a factor 0.8 and the target increased by 1/0.8 or gain increased by a factor 1.33 with the target lowered by a factor 1/1.33</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gain (reference)</intervention_name>
    <description>The latest revision of the PID algorithm to verify that the scaling factor used to set KP as a function of TDD is robust to the changes in gain and target resulting from over- or under-calibration of the glucose sensor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gain increase or decrease</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Target 120mg/dL</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gain decreased by a factor 0.8</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Gain increase or decrease</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Target increased by 1/0.8</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gain increased by a factor 1.33</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Gain increase or decrease</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Target lowered by a factor 1/1.33</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 1 diabetes for &gt; 3 years

          -  Manage diabetes  using a continuous glucose monitor and continuous subcutaneous
             insulin infusion pump

          -  Non obese (BMI &lt; 30)

          -  Aged 18 - 75 years old

          -  HbA1c &lt; 8 %

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  renal or hepatic failure

          -  cancer or lymphoma

          -  Malabsorption or malnourishment

          -  Mypercortisolism

          -  Alcoholism or drug abuse

          -  Anemia (hematocrit &lt; 36 in females and &lt;40 in males)

          -  Eating disorder

          -  Dietary restrictions

          -  Acetaminophen allergy

          -  Chronic acetaminophen use

          -  Glucocorticoid therapy

          -  History of Gastropareisis

          -  Use of Beta blockers
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Howard Wolpert, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Joslin Diabetes Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Astrid Atakov Castillo</last_name>
    <phone>617-309-1997</phone>
    <email>astrid.atakov-castillo@joslin.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stephanie Edwards, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>617-309-1996</phone>
    <email>stephanie.edwards@joslin.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Joslin Diabetes Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Astrid Atakov Castillo</last_name>
      <phone>617-309-1997</phone>
      <email>astrid.atakov-castillo@joslin.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Stephanie Edwards, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>617-309-1996</phone>
      <email>stephanie.edwards@joslin.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Howard Wolpert, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Garry Steil, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steil GM, Panteleon AE, Rebrin K. Closed-loop insulin delivery-the path to physiological glucose control. Adv Drug Deliv Rev. 2004 Feb 10;56(2):125-44. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14741112</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steil GM, Rebrin K, Janowski R, Darwin C, Saad MF. Modeling beta-cell insulin secretion--implications for closed-loop glucose homeostasis. Diabetes Technol Ther. 2003;5(6):953-64.</citation>
    <PMID>14709197</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steil GM, Rebrin K, Darwin C, Hariri F, Saad MF. Feasibility of automating insulin delivery for the treatment of type 1 diabetes. Diabetes. 2006 Dec;55(12):3344-50.</citation>
    <PMID>17130478</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weinzimer SA, Steil GM, Swan KL, Dziura J, Kurtz N, Tamborlane WV. Fully automated closed-loop insulin delivery versus semiautomated hybrid control in pediatric patients with type 1 diabetes using an artificial pancreas. Diabetes Care. 2008 May;31(5):934-9. doi: 10.2337/dc07-1967. Epub 2008 Feb 5.</citation>
    <PMID>18252903</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steil GM, Palerm CC, Kurtz N, Voskanyan G, Roy A, Paz S, Kandeel FR. The effect of insulin feedback on closed loop glucose control. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2011 May;96(5):1402-8. doi: 10.1210/jc.2010-2578. Epub 2011 Mar 2. PubMed PMID: 21367930; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3085208.</citation>
    <PMID>21367930</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loutseiko M, Voskanyan G, Keenan DB, Steil GM. Closed-loop insulin delivery utilizing pole placement to compensate for delays in subcutaneous insulin delivery. J Diabetes Sci Technol. 2011 Nov 1;5(6):1342-51.</citation>
    <PMID>22226251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buchanan TA, Xiang AH, Peters RK, Kjos SL, Berkowitz K, Marroquin A, Goico J, Ochoa C, Azen SP. Response of pancreatic beta-cells to improved insulin sensitivity in women at high risk for type 2 diabetes. Diabetes. 2000 May;49(5):782-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10905487</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Panteleon AE, Loutseiko M, Steil GM, Rebrin K. Evaluation of the effect of gain on the meal response of an automated closed-loop insulin delivery system. Diabetes. 2006 Jul;55(7):1995-2000.</citation>
    <PMID>16804068</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 7, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Joslin Diabetes Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Howard Wolpert</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Physician, Adult Diabetes</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Physiologic Insulin Delivery (PID)</keyword>
  <keyword>Closed Loop</keyword>
  <keyword>Sensor</keyword>
  <keyword>Insulin sensitivity</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
