<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="166436">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01833598</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCO 12-0656</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HS# 12-00346</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01833598</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Percutaneous Needle Tenotomy (PNT) Versus Platelet Rich Plasma (PRP) With PNT in the Treatment of Chronic Tendinosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Efficacy of Ultrasound Guided Percutaneous Needle Tenotomy (PNT) Versus Platelet Rich Plasma (PRP) With PNT in the Treatment of Chronic Tendinosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Tendinopathy is a clinical syndrome of chronic pain and tendon degeneration that impairs a
      person's ability to perform daily activities and recreation. Traditional conservative
      treatments include activity modification, exercises, ice/heat, and medications and
      corticosteroid injection. A newer treatment is percutaneous needle tenotomy (PNT), in which
      the affected area is repetitively needled to disrupt pathological tissue and induce
      bleeding. This turns a nonhealing chronic injury into an acute injury with enhanced healing
      capability. Another is Platelet Rich Plasma (PRP), whereby patients' own platelets are
      injected into the affected area, also activating growth factors. There has been promising
      research in these tendinopathy treatments but more research is needed.

      The investigators plan to expand on prior studies to identify a reproducible and efficacious
      treatment for chronic tendinopathy to reduce pain and improve function and quality of life.
      Our goal in this study is to assess the efficacy of ultrasound guided (USG) PNT versus PNT
      with peritendinous PRP as a treatment for chronic tendinopathy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subjects will be recruited over a 2 year period . The potential subjects will be identified
      on the basis of the presence of a tendinopathy that has failed conservative treatment,
      defined more specifically as a tendon injury that has not healed or responded over 3 months
      since initial injury with treatments including physical therapy, bracing, modalities, rest,
      and/or oral medications. We will also include corticosteroid injection in this failed
      treatment group. Preliminary results including safety will be analyzed at follow up at 2, 4,
      6, 8 and 12 weeks. Subjects will follow up in the office at 4 weeks post intervention. The
      other follow-ups will be performed by telephone.

      After clinically identifying the presence of tendinopathy, the potential subjects will be
      evaluated by a study team member using inclusion and exclusion criteria.  Patients will be
      randomized using envelopes with assignments into one of 2 groups: percutaneous needle
      tenotomy alone or PNT with peritendinous PRP injection. They will be assigned a number that
      identifies them.

      In order to blind all subjects to their treatment, the subjects will then undergo either a
      sham venipuncture if in the PNT-only group or a blood draw of 10 to 60ml by a study team
      member under sterile conditions if in the PNT +PRP group. (The subject will be blinded to
      whether or not blood is actually drawn by keeping the arm behind a curtain.) The amount of
      blood drawn in the PNT +PRP group will be determined by tendon affected, as large tendons
      will need more volume and concentration of the PRP and its contained factors: 10ml blood
      drawn for small tendons and 60ml blood for large tendons

      The PNT procedure will be performed by a fellowship-trained, board-certified interventional
      spine and sports medicine physician under direct and continuous ultrasound guidance (USG),
      with the injection syringe covered with opaque tape to blind the patient to their treatment.

      Post procedure, patients will be instructed to take over the counter (OTC) acetaminophen
      500mg or tramadol 50mg to be taken by mouth for pain relief every 6 hours as needed. Ice
      applied over the tendon will not be allowed for 3 days and NSAIDs are to be avoided after
      the intervention is performed for the remaining duration of the study due to their
      anti-inflammatory properties. We allow participants to be on anti-inflammatory medication
      prior to the intervention, but we do not want to disrupt the post-procedure inflammation
      process essential for healing.

      The post-procedure protocol also consists of relative rest until the first telephone
      follow-up appointment in 2 weeks, regardless of tenotomy site. Patients will be allowed to
      continue their usual activities of daily living during that period, regardless of an upper
      versus a lower extremity tenotomy site. Between weeks 2 and 4, patients will progressively
      advance to multi-planar isometric exercises and light resistance exercises as tolerated,
      according to instructions given.

      Gradual return to activities will be discussed at the office 4-week follow-up appointment.
      Patients will be instructed to perform isotonic exercises from weeks 1-6, then eccentric
      training from 6-10 weeks, and then finally plyometrics and sports-specific exercise around
      weeks 8-12. Unrestricted activity will be permitted around 12 weeks post procedure. Physical
      therapy will not be prescribed for the patients in this study. Subjects will follow up at 2,
      6, 8, and 12 weeks after the procedure over the telephone by a study team member and at week
      4 in the office by the attending physician. At each visit, a study team member will collect
      information for the questionnaire rating the subject's pain, function, sleep, general well
      being, pain medication usage, return to activities, and any complications. At each follow
      up, subjects will be assessed for primary and secondary outcome measures and adverse events.
       Patients will be instructed to contact the study team immediately if at any point they have
      concern for an adverse event.

      Subjects will be blinded to their treatment until the end of their participation in the
      study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activity Level</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Function, sleep, general well-being, return to normal activities, work, sports and reduction in pain medication usage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activity Level</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Function, sleep, general well-being, return to normal activities, work, sports and reduction in pain medication usage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activity Level</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Function, sleep, general well-being, return to normal activities, work, sports and reduction in pain medication usage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activity Level</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Function, sleep, general well-being, return to normal activities, work, sports and reduction in pain medication usage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activity Level</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Function, sleep, general well-being, return to normal activities, work, sports and reduction in pain medication usage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>bleeding, infection, tendon rupture, allergic reaction, paralysis, or stroke</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>bleeding, infection, tendon rupture, allergic reaction, paralysis, or stroke</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 6</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>bleeding, infection, tendon rupture, allergic reaction, paralysis, or stroke</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>bleeding, infection, tendon rupture, allergic reaction, paralysis, or stroke</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 12</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>bleeding, infection, tendon rupture, allergic reaction, paralysis, or stroke</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">86</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Tendinopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PNT + PRP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>percutaneous needle tenotomy with peritendinous platelet-rich plasma injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PNT alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>percutaneous needle tenotomy alone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PNT + PRP</intervention_name>
    <description>The PNT + PRP group will undergo needle tenotomy under direct and continuous ultrasound guidance with even distribution of PRP into the peritendinous area(s) of PNT around the affected tendon.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PNT + PRP</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>percutaneous needle tenotomy with peritendinous platelet-rich plasma injection</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PNT alone</intervention_name>
    <description>The PNT group will undergo needle tenotomy under direct and continuous ultrasound guidance local anesthesia into the affected tendon. 10 minutes after the injection, the ultrasound machine probe will be passed over the areas treated both to evaluate for any structural changes and for any complications.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PNT alone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>percutaneous needle tenotomy alone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  aged 18-100 years

          -  have pain (≥ 5/10 pain on the VAS) that is a direct result of tendinopathy as
             determined by history of injury and study team member physician's best judgment,

          -  ≥3 months of pain after injury that has failed conservative treatments or after
             corticosteroid (CSI) (must be 3 months after CSI to avoid theoretical tendon rupture)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  are taking coumadin, have a known coagulopathy or bleeding dyscrasia listed by
             patient report (patients will be asked if they have a bleeding disorder) and/or past
             medical history (PMH)

          -  are taking fluoroquinolones

          -  have undergone prior PNT or PRP for the affected tendon(s)

          -  have a known systemic illness such as vasculitis, an autoimmune or an inflammatory
             disease, uncontrolled diabetes, presence of other musculoskeletal injury or tendon
             rupture, or are or plan to become pregnant during the study.

               -  Patients taking aspirin or NSAIDs are not excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jonathan Kirschner, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexandra Voigt</last_name>
    <phone>212-659-9379</phone>
    <email>Alexandra.voigt@mountsinai.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jonathan Kirschner, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-659-9359</phone>
      <email>jonathan.kirschner@mountsinai.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jonathan Kirschner, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scott A, Ashe MC. Common tendinopathies in the upper and lower extremities. Curr Sports Med Rep. 2006 Sep;5(5):233-41. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16934204</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fredberg U, Stengaard-Pedersen K. Chronic tendinopathy tissue pathology, pain mechanisms, and etiology with a special focus on inflammation. Scand J Med Sci Sports. 2008 Feb;18(1):3-15. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0838.2007.00746.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18294189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Struijs PA, Kerkhoffs GM, Assendelft WJ, Van Dijk CN. Conservative treatment of lateral epicondylitis: brace versus physical therapy or a combination of both-a randomized clinical trial. Am J Sports Med. 2004 Mar;32(2):462-9.</citation>
    <PMID>14977675</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coombes BK, Bisset L, Vicenzino B. Efficacy and safety of corticosteroid injections and other injections for management of tendinopathy: a systematic review of randomised controlled trials. Lancet. 2010 Nov 20;376(9754):1751-67. Epub 2010 Oct 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20970844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McShane JM, Shah VN, Nazarian LN. Sonographically guided percutaneous needle tenotomy for treatment of common extensor tendinosis in the elbow: is a corticosteroid necessary? J Ultrasound Med. 2008 Aug;27(8):1137-44.</citation>
    <PMID>18645071</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McShane JM, Nazarian LN, Harwood MI. Sonographically guided percutaneous needle tenotomy for treatment of common extensor tendinosis in the elbow. J Ultrasound Med. 2006 Oct;25(10):1281-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16998100</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Housner JA, Jacobson JA, Misko R. Sonographically guided percutaneous needle tenotomy for the treatment of chronic tendinosis. J Ultrasound Med. 2009 Sep;28(9):1187-92.</citation>
    <PMID>19710216</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Skjong CC, Meininger AK, Ho SS. Tendinopathy treatment: where is the evidence? Clin Sports Med. 2012 Apr;31(2):329-50. doi: 10.1016/j.csm.2011.11.003.</citation>
    <PMID>22341021</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maffulli N, Longo UG, Denaro V. Novel approaches for the management of tendinopathy. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2010 Nov 3;92(15):2604-13. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.I.01744. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21048180</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paavola M, Kannus P, Järvinen TA, Järvinen TL, Józsa L, Järvinen M. Treatment of tendon disorders. Is there a role for corticosteroid injection? Foot Ankle Clin. 2002 Sep;7(3):501-13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12512406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bahr R, Fossan B, Løken S, Engebretsen L. Surgical treatment compared with eccentric training for patellar tendinopathy (Jumper's Knee). A randomized, controlled trial. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2006 Aug;88(8):1689-98.</citation>
    <PMID>16882889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nguyen RT, Borg-Stein J, McInnis K. Applications of platelet-rich plasma in musculoskeletal and sports medicine: an evidence-based approach. PM R. 2011 Mar;3(3):226-50. doi: 10.1016/j.pmrj.2010.11.007. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21402369</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finnoff JT, Fowler SP, Lai JK, Santrach PJ, Willis EA, Sayeed YA, Smith J. Treatment of chronic tendinopathy with ultrasound-guided needle tenotomy and platelet-rich plasma injection. PM R. 2011 Oct;3(10):900-11. doi: 10.1016/j.pmrj.2011.05.015. Epub 2011 Aug 26.</citation>
    <PMID>21872551</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Vos RJ, Weir A, van Schie HT, Bierma-Zeinstra SM, Verhaar JA, Weinans H, Tol JL. Platelet-rich plasma injection for chronic Achilles tendinopathy: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA. 2010 Jan 13;303(2):144-9. doi: 10.1001/jama.2009.1986.</citation>
    <PMID>20068208</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Jonge S, de Vos RJ, Weir A, van Schie HT, Bierma-Zeinstra SM, Verhaar JA, Weinans H, Tol JL. One-year follow-up of platelet-rich plasma treatment in chronic Achilles tendinopathy: a double-blind randomized placebo-controlled trial. Am J Sports Med. 2011 Aug;39(8):1623-9. doi: 10.1177/0363546511404877. Epub 2011 May 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21602565</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Filardo G, Kon E, Della Villa S, Vincentelli F, Fornasari PM, Marcacci M. Use of platelet-rich plasma for the treatment of refractory jumper's knee. Int Orthop. 2010 Aug;34(6):909-15. doi: 10.1007/s00264-009-0845-7. Epub 2009 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>19641918</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kon E, Filardo G, Delcogliano M, Presti ML, Russo A, Bondi A, Di Martino A, Cenacchi A, Fornasari PM, Marcacci M. Platelet-rich plasma: new clinical application: a pilot study for treatment of jumper's knee. Injury. 2009 Jun;40(6):598-603. Epub 2009 Apr 19.</citation>
    <PMID>19380129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naredo E, Cabero F, Beneyto P, Cruz A, Mondéjar B, Uson J, Palop MJ, Crespo M. A randomized comparative study of short term response to blind injection versus sonographic-guided injection of local corticosteroids in patients with painful shoulder. J Rheumatol. 2004 Feb;31(2):308-14.</citation>
    <PMID>14760802</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rutten MJ, Maresch BJ, Jager GJ, de Waal Malefijt MC. Injection of the subacromial-subdeltoid bursa: blind or ultrasound-guided? Acta Orthop. 2007 Apr;78(2):254-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17464615</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolf JM, Ozer K, Scott F, Gordon MJ, Williams AE. Comparison of autologous blood, corticosteroid, and saline injection in the treatment of lateral epicondylitis: a prospective, randomized, controlled multicenter study. J Hand Surg Am. 2011 Aug;36(8):1269-72. Epub 2011 Jun 25.</citation>
    <PMID>21705157</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Creaney L, Wallace A, Curtis M, Connell D. Growth factor-based therapies provide additional benefit beyond physical therapy in resistant elbow tendinopathy: a prospective, single-blind, randomised trial of autologous blood injections versus platelet-rich plasma injections. Br J Sports Med. 2011 Sep;45(12):966-71. doi: 10.1136/bjsm.2010.082503. Epub 2011 Mar 15.</citation>
    <PMID>21406450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaux JF, Le Goff C, Seidel L, Péters P, Gothot A, Albert A, Crielaard JM. [Comparative study of five techniques of preparation of platelet-rich plasma]. Pathol Biol (Paris). 2011 Jun;59(3):157-60. doi: 10.1016/j.patbio.2009.04.007. Epub 2009 May 28. French.</citation>
    <PMID>19481375</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koh ES, Williams AJ, Povlsen B. Upper-limb pain in long-term poliomyelitis. QJM. 2002 Jun;95(6):389-95.</citation>
    <PMID>12037247</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 29, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 12, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic tendinopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>platelet rich plasma</keyword>
  <keyword>tendonitis</keyword>
  <keyword>percutaneous tendon tenotomy</keyword>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>shoulder</keyword>
  <keyword>knee</keyword>
  <keyword>ankle</keyword>
  <keyword>foot</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tendinopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
