<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="115934">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01821768</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201209143</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01821768</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Axillary Ultrasound With or Without Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy in Detecting the Spread of Breast Cancer in Patients Receiving Breast Conservation Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Randomized Trial of Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy Versus no Additional Staging in Patients With Clinical T1-T2 N0 M0 Invasive Breast Cancer and Negative Axillary Ultrasound</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized clinical trial studies two different tests that are currently being used to
      detect the spread of breast cancer to the lymph nodes under the arm in candidates for breast
      conservation therapy. The two tests are sentinel lymph node biopsy (SLNB) and axillary
      ultrasound. The current standard of care is sentinel lymph node biopsy, which is a surgical
      procedure. Axillary ultrasound (AUS) may be just as good as SLNB for detecting the spread of
      cancer but without the surgical risks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this prospective randomized non-inferiority study we aim to determine the utility of
      axillary ultrasound (AUS) as a pre-operative staging modality for patients with clinically
      node-negative invasive breast cancer with the hope that it will be a minimally invasive
      replacement for SLNB.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Regional (axillary) recurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years from date of surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The distributions of the primary endpoints and complications across two arms will be summarized using contingency tables and compared by 2-sample Chi-square test or Fisher's exact test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease free survival Arm 1 versus Arm 2.</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 5 years form date of surgery to date of any disease recurrence.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as the interval between the date of registration to the date of first disease event. Kaplan-Meier product limit estimator will be used. The differences in OS and DFS between treatment arms will be compared using log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival Arm 1 versus Arm 2</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years from date of surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Defined as the interval  between the date of initial diagnosis until the date of death. Kaplan-Meier product limit estimator will be used. The differences in OS and DFS between treatment arms will be compared using log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">460</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: No sentinal lymph node biopsy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive no additional axillary surgery which is experimental.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Sentinel lymph node biopsy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive standard of care sentinel lymph node biopsy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Sentinel lymph node biopsy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient must be female.

          -  Patient must be at least 18 years of age.

          -  Patient's clinical stage must be documented as tumor size less than 5 cm, with no
             palpable nodes and no evidence of metastatic disease (T1 or T2 N0 M0)

          -  Patient must have a negative (normal) axillary ultrasound performed at Siteman Cancer
             Center.  Lymph nodes will be evaluated based on morphologic features.  AUS wil be
             considered positive (abnormal)if lymph nodes are noted to be completely hypoechoic
             (absent hilum) or have focal hypoechoic cortical thickening/lobulation greater than 4
             mm.

          -  Patient must have a tissue diagnosis of invasive breast carcinoma

          -  Patient must have Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) status &lt;/= 2, as
             documented in patient's medical record.

          -  Patient must be available for follow-up.

          -  A patient with a history of previous malignancy is eligible for this study as long as
             the patient meets the following criteria for a cancer survivor. A cancer survivor is
             eligible provided that the following criteria are met (1) The patient has undergone
             potentially curative therapy for all prior malignancies; (2) There has been no
             evidence of recurrence (except for effectively treated basal cell or squamous
             carcinoma of the skin, carcinoma in-situ of the cervix that has been effectively
             treated by surgery alone, or lobular carcinoma in-situ of the ipsilateral or
             contralateral breast treated by surgery alone); and (3) The patient is deemed by
             their treating physician to be at low riks for recurrence from prior malignancies.

          -  Patient, or the patient's legally acceptable representative, must provide a signed
             and date written informed consent prior to registration and any study-related
             procedures.

          -  Patient must provide written authorization to allow the use and disclosure of their
             protected health information.  NOTE: This may be obtained in either the
             study-specific informed consent or in a separate authorization form and must be
             obtained from the patient prior to study registration.

          -  Patient must be a candidate for sentinel lymph node biopsy (SLNB).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient in lactating (breast-feeding) or pregnant.

          -  Patient has concurrent invasive bilateral breast malignancies or multicentric
             disease.

          -  Patient has had previous ipsilateral axillary surgery such as excisional biopsy of
             lymph nodes(s), treatment of hidradenitis.

          -  Patient is considered  poor candidate surgical candidate due to non-malignant
             systemic disease.

          -  Patient has undergone or plans to undergo neoadjuvant chemotherapy of endocrine
             therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amy Cyr, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amy Cyr, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>314-747-8708</phone>
    <email>cyra@wudosis.wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amy Cyr, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>314-747-8708</phone>
      <email>cyra@wudosis.wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William Gillanders, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Natalia Tucker, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Timothy Eberlein, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julie Margenthaler, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rebecca Aft, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Catherine Appleton, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Valerie Reichert, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Imran Zoberi, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Timothy Pluard, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Foluso Ademuyiwa, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.siteman.wustl.edu</url>
    <description>Alvin J. Siteman Cancer Center at Barnes-Jewish Hospital and Washington University School of Medicine</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
