<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="31751">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01853618</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130120</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-C-0120</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01853618</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tremelimumab With Chemoembolization or Ablation for Liver Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of Tremelimumab, A Monoclonal Antibody Against CTLA-4, in Combination With Either Trans-Arterial Catheter Chemoembolization (TACE) or Radiofrequency Ablation (RFA) in Subjects With Hepatocellular Carcinoma (HCC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Tremelimumab is a cancer treatment drug that helps the immune system recognize and destroy
      cancer cells. Researchers want to see if it can be used to treat advanced liver cancer. The
      drug will be given with one of two types of treatment for liver cancer. The first type,
      transarterial catheter chemoembolization (TACE), injects chemotherapy drugs into the tumor
      through the main blood vessel that is feeding it. That blood vessel is then closed off to
      help keep the drugs in the tumor longer. The second type, radiofrequency ablation (RFA),
      uses a heated probe to destroy the tumor tissue. Researchers want to study how safe and
      effective these treatments are with the study drug.

      Objectives:

      - To test the safety and effectiveness of Tremelimumab with TACE or RFA for advanced liver
      cancer.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who have advanced liver cancer that has not responded
      to other treatments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Worldwide, hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is the fifth most common malignancy with a median
      survival of 6-9 months. For patients with advanced disease sorafenib is the only approved
      drug and this has limited benefit.

      Tremelimumab is a monoclonal antibody against CTLA4. Anti-CTLA4 therapy has been shown to
      enhance anti-tumor immunity by blocking tumor-induced immune suppression of cytotoxic T
      cells.

      Both trans-arterial catheter chemoembolization (TACE) and radiofrequency ablation (RFA) have
      been shown to induce a peripheral immune response.

      The underlying hypothesis of this study is that the effect of anti-CTLA4 treatment can be
      enhanced by TACE or RFA in patients with advanced hepatocellular carcinoma.

      Objectives:

      Primary:

      To assess the safety and feasibility of combining Tremelimumab with trans-arterial catheter
      chemoembolization (TACE) or radiofrequency ablation (RFA) in patients with advanced HCC.

      Secondary:

      To evaluate the following in patients with advanced HCC undergoing TACE or radiofrequency
      ablation (RFA) in combination with Tremelimumab:

        -  changes in immune parameters in the peripheral blood

        -  clinical indicators of efficacy (response rate, time to tumor progression, overall
           survival)

      Eligibility:

      Histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of HCC.

      Childs-Pugh A/B7 cirrhosis only is allowed. If patient does not have cirrhosis, this
      limitation does not apply.

      Barcelona Clinic Liver Cancer (BCLC) Stage B and C patients.

      Patients must have disease that is not amenable to potentially curative resection,
      radiofrequency ablation, or liver transplantation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and feasibility of combining Tremelimumab with trans-arterial catheter chemoembolization (TACE) or radiofrequency ablation (RFA) in patients with advanced HCC.</measure>
    <time_frame>4/10/13 to 12/31/2015</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Liver Cell Caricinoma</condition>
  <condition>Liver Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tremelimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trans-Arterial Cather Chemoembolization</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiofrequency Ablation (RFA)</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        2.1.1.1 Patients must have histopathological confirmation of hepatocellular carcinoma
        (HCC) by the Laboratory of Pathology of the NCI prior to entering this study OR
        histopathological confirmation of carcinoma in the setting of clinical and radiological
        characteristics which, together with the pathology, are highly suggestive of a diagnosis
        of HCC. Fibrolammelar variant is also allowed.

        2.1.1.2 Patients must have disease that is not amenable to potentially curative resection,
        transplantation or ablation. For Cohort A patients must have progressed on or been
        intolerant of prior sorafenib therapy.

        2.1.1.3 Disease must be technically amenable to transhepatic arterial chemoembolization
        (TACE) or radiofrequency ablation (RFA). Each case will be discussed at GI tumor board
        with interventional radiology. Patients must have evaluable disease.

        2.1.1.4 If liver cirrhosis is present, patient must have a Child-Pugh A/B7 classification.

        2.1.1.5 Age greater than or equal to 18 years

        2.1.1.6 Life expectancy of greater than 3 months.

        2.1.1.7 ECOG performance status 0-2.

        2.1.1.8 Patients must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below:

          -  leukocytes greater than or equal to 3,000/mcL

          -  absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1,000/mcL

          -  platelets greater than or equal to 60,000/mcL

          -  total bilirubin, If cirrhosis present: Part of Child Pugh requirement. If no
             cirrhosis: Bili should be less than or equal to 2 times ULN

          -  Serum albumin, If cirrhosis present: Part of Child Pugh requirement. If no cirrhosis:
             albumin should be greater than or equal to 2.5g/dl

          -  Patients are eligible with ALT or AST up to 5 times ULN.

          -  creatinine, less than 1.5 times institution upper limit of normal

        OR

        -creatinine clearance greater than or equal to 45 mL/min/1.73 m(2), as calculated below,
        for patients with creatinine levels above institutional normal

        2.1.1.9 Patients must have recovered from any acute toxicity related to prior therapy,
        including surgery. Toxicity should be less than or equal to grade 1 or returned to
        baseline.

        2.1.1.10 Patients must not have other invasive malignancies within the past 5 years (with
        the exception of non-melanoma skin cancers, non-invasive bladder cancer or localized
        prostate cancer for whom systemic therapy is not required).

        2.1.1.11 Patient must be able to understand and willing to sign a written informed consent
        document.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        2.1.2.1 Patients who have had standard of care chemotherapy, large field radiotherapy, or
        major surgery must wait 2 weeks prior to entering the study. For recent experimental
        therapies a 28 day period of time must elapse before treatment.

        2.1.2.2 Patients who have undergone prior liver transplantation are ineligible.

        2.1.2.3 Patients with known brain metastases will be excluded from this clinical trial
        because of their poor prognosis and because they often develop progressive neurologic
        dysfunction that would confound the evaluation of neurologic and other adverse events.

        2.1.2.4 Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
        systemic infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris,
        cardiac arrhythmia or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance
        with study requirements.

        2.1.2.5 History of chronic autoimmune disease (e.g., Addison   s disease, multiple
        sclerosis, Graves    disease, Hashimoto   s thyroiditis, rheumatoid arthritis,
        hypophysitis, etc.) with symptomatic disease within the 3 years before randomization.
        Note: Active vitiligo or a history of vitiligo will not be a basis for exclusion.

        2.1.2.6 Dementia or significantly altered mental status that would prohibit the
        understanding or rendering of Information and Consent and compliance with the requirements
        of the protocol.

        2.1.2.7 Diverticulitis (either active or history of) within the past 2 years. Note that
        diverticulosis is permitted.

        2.1.2.8 Active or history of inflammatory bowel disease (colitis, Crohn   s), irritable
        bowel disease, celiac disease, or other serious, chronic, gastrointestinal conditions
        associated with diarrhea. Active or history of systemic lupus erythematosus or Wegener   s
        granulomatosis.

        2.1.2.9 Currently receiving immunosuppressive doses of steroids or other immunosuppressive
        medications (inhaled and topical steroids are permitted)

        2.1.2.10 History of sarcoidosis syndrome

        2.1.2.11 Patients should not be vaccinated with live attenuated vaccines within 1 month of
        starting Tremelimumab treatment.

        2.1.2.12 HIV-positive patients receiving anti-retroviral therapy are excluded from this
        study due to the possibility of pharmacokinetic interactions between antiretroviral
        medications and Tremelimumab. HIV positive patients not receiving antiretroviral therapy
        are excluded due to the possibility that Tremelimumab may worsen their condition and the
        likelihood that the underlying condition may obscure the attribution of adverse events.

        2.1.2.13 History of hypersensitivity reaction to human or mouse antibody products.

        2.1.2.14 Pregnancy and breast feeding are exclusion factors. The effects of Tremelimumab
        on the developing human fetus are unknown. Enrolled patients must agree to use adequate
        contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study
        entry, the duration of study participation and 3 months after the end of the treatment.
        Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is
        participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately.

        2.1.2.15 Patients with unhealed surgical wounds for more than 30 days.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tim F Greten, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Suzanne Fioravanti, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 594-6544</phone>
    <email>fioravas@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tim F Greten, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-4723</phone>
    <email>gretentf@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>888-624-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-C-0120.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parkin DM, Bray F, Ferlay J, Pisani P. Estimating the world cancer burden: Globocan 2000. Int J Cancer. 2001 Oct 15;94(2):153-6. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>11668491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Llovet JM, Di Bisceglie AM, Bruix J, Kramer BS, Lencioni R, Zhu AX, Sherman M, Schwartz M, Lotze M, Talwalkar J, Gores GJ; Panel of Experts in HCC-Design Clinical Trials. Design and endpoints of clinical trials in hepatocellular carcinoma. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2008 May 21;100(10):698-711. Epub 2008 May 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18477802</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kantoff PW, Higano CS, Shore ND, Berger ER, Small EJ, Penson DF, Redfern CH, Ferrari AC, Dreicer R, Sims RB, Xu Y, Frohlich MW, Schellhammer PF; IMPACT Study Investigators. Sipuleucel-T immunotherapy for castration-resistant prostate cancer. N Engl J Med. 2010 Jul 29;363(5):411-22.</citation>
    <PMID>20818862</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 14, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 2, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Liver Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Monoclonal Antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>CTLA-4</keyword>
  <keyword>Ablative Therapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
