<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="99056">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01797458</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BB 39/11</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>The 3,2,1 Study</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01797458</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>European Study on Three Different Approaches to Managing Class 2 Cavities in Primary Teeth</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomised Control Trial on Three Different Approaches to Managing Class 2 Cavities in Primary Teeth</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Medicine Greifswald</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Dundee</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Lithuanian University of Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Medicine Greifswald</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this randomized clinical trial is to compare the clinical effectiveness of
      three treatments involving different caries management strategies (conventional
      restorations, Hall technique, and a non-restorative treatment of dental caries) to the
      management of class II carious primary molar in children 3-8 year-old from three different
      countries (Scotland, Lithuania, and Germany).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      At present, many materials and techniques are used to treat carious primary teeth. All of
      these have their proponents who claim they provide the best performance in terms of
      longevity, aesthetics, bio-compatibility, etc (Qvist, 2010; Yengopal et al., 2009). However,
      despite the great variety of techniques and materials, there is no definite evidence for the
      most effective approach when dental caries in primary molars is concerned, as yet. On the
      other hand, there is conclusive evidence that shows that glass-ionomer cement is an
      inappropriate material for class II restorations in primary teeth, due to its significant
      shorter longevity compared with other restorative materials like compomer and amalgam.

      Recently, there is re-surging interest in &quot;old&quot; techniques: such as opening-up cavities used
      in Denmark and Netherlands (Peretz &amp; Gluck, 2006; Gruythuysen et al., 2010) or stainless
      steel crowns with the advent of the Hall technique in Scotland (Innes et al., 2007).
      However, there is lack of comparative evidence from high quality clinical trials leading to
      uncertainty in the effectiveness of these techniques. In addition, these techniques are
      rarely compared with standard fillings.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Failure rate of the three treatment arms judged clinically</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Failure rate of the three treatment arms judged clinically after 1 and 2 years such as clear caries progression, secondary caries, loss of restoration, reversible pulpitis treated without requiring pulpotomy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of children experiencing irreversible pulpitis, dental abscess, or extraction</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of children experiencing irreversible pulpitis, dental abscess, or extraction judged clinically after 1 and 2 years</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Oral health status</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Child`s oral health status as assessed by the gingival status and bacterial plaque index judged clinically after 1 and 2 years</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Children behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Child's behavior as assessed by the Frankl Behavior Rating Scale</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of three caries management techniques for children, parents, and dentists</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Acceptability of the different management techniques for children, parents, and dentists</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Children perception of pain intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline assessment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Child's perception of pain intensity during treatment assessed with the Visual Analogue Scale of Faces</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">464</enrollment>
  <condition>Dental Caries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hall Technique</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This technique uses preformed Stainless Steel Crowns (SSCs) to restore carious primary molars. This technique does not require local anesthesia, caries removal or any tooth preparation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Opening-up Cavities</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is a less operative approach, whose aim is to facilitate plaque control in carious lesions, thus making cavities accessible for plaque removal. According to the new understanding of caries nature, it is clear that carious lesions can be arrested even in the case of dentinal involvement, provided that the main causal factor -bacterial plaque- is removed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Restorations</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Conventional restorations (dental fillings) with complete caries removal have been used as the standard treatment for carious primary teeth. Exist different materials to restore class II carious primary molars. Resin based materials and amalgam have been considered as appropriate materials in terms of longevity for class II restorations in primary teeth.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hall Technique</intervention_name>
    <description>Technique:
Removal of dental plaque and rest of aliments from the cavity
Selection of the SSC
If the contact points are very tight, orthodontic separator elastics could be placed through the mesial and distal contacts and the SSC has to be fitted at a subsequent appointment
Dry the crown and fill with glass-ionomer luting cement
Place the crown over the tooth
Removal of cement excesses from the crown margins
The child should be asked to keep biting on the crown until the cement has set</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hall Technique</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Opening-up Cavities</intervention_name>
    <description>Technique:
Use high-speed bur to remove the undermined enamel and make the cavity accessible for plaque removal. Do not remove the contact area
Clean, dry the cavity and apply Duraphat® varnish fluoride (50/mg/ml)
Show the cavity to patient/parents and give them tooth-brushing instructions
Tell to parents that good plaque control is the key for this treatment
The recall interval for these patients is every 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Opening-up Cavities</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional Restorations</intervention_name>
    <description>Technique:
Local anesthesia should be used when needed
Complete caries removal should be performed and cavity preparation should be done according to the material you have selected
Use a matrix band and a wedge to tightly hold the band against the tooth
Place the material
Check contacts and occlusion, and polish the restoration (only for resin based materials)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Restorations</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children aged 3-8 years (Germany: children who attend the Präventive Zahnmedizin und
             Kinderzahnheilkunde department at  Ernst-Moritz-Arndt-Universität Greifswald;
             Scotland: children who attend the paediatric dentistry department, School of
             Dentistry at University of Dundee; Lithuania: children who attend the paediatric
             dentistry department, Dental Faculty, Lithuanian University of Health Sciences)

          -  At least one primary molar tooth with caries into dentine involving two dental
             surfaces (diagnosed according to International Caries Detection and Assessment System
             - ICDAS, codes 3 to 5)

          -  Willing to be examined

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical or radiographic signs of pulpar or peri-radicular pathology

          -  Patients with a systemic disease requiring special considerations during their dental
             treatment.

          -  Parents/children who refuse to participate in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>8 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christian H Splieth, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Ernst-Moritz-Arndt-Universität Greifswald</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ernst-Moritz-Arndt-Universität Greifswald. Dental Faculty, Preventive and Paediatric Dentistry Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greifswald</city>
        <state>Mecklenburg-Vorpommern</state>
        <zip>17487</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christian H Splieth, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 3834 867101</phone>
      <email>splieth@uni-greifswald.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ruth M Santamaria</last_name>
      <phone>+49 3834 867136</phone>
      <email>ruth.santamaria@uni-greifswald.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christian H Splieth, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ruth M Santamaria</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lithuanian University of Health Sciences, Dental Faculty, Clinic of Dental and Oral Pathology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kaunas</city>
        <country>Lithuania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vita Machiulskiene, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <email>vita@med.kmu.lt</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Julija Narbutaite</last_name>
      <email>julinarb@takas.lt</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vita Machiulskiene, Pr. Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julija Narbutaite</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Dundee, Dentistry &amp; Nursing , College of Medicine, Unit of Dental and Oral Health School of Dentistry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dundee</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nicola P Innes, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+ 44 1382 425760</phone>
      <email>n.p.innes@dundee.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nicola P Innes, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Lithuania</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 21, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Medicine Greifswald</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Christian Splieth</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>class II carious primary molar</keyword>
  <keyword>Opening-up cavities</keyword>
  <keyword>Hall Technique</keyword>
  <keyword>Conventional restorations</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Dental Caries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
