<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="136095">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01805180</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CTS-5010</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01805180</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Spectra Optia PMN Cell Collection Procedure</brief_title>
  <acronym>PMNC</acronym>
  <official_title>A Controlled Evaluation of the Spectra Optia® Apheresis System's Granulocyte / Polymorphonuclear (PMN) Cell Collection Procedure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Terumo BCT</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Terumo BCT</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the procedures for the collection PMN cells on
      Terumo BCT's Spectra Optia® and COBE® Spectra Apheresis Systems.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the procedures for the collection of granulocyte/
      polymorphonuclear (PMN) cells on Terumo BCT's Spectra Optia® and COBE® Spectra Apheresis
      Systems and to establish the non-inferiority of the Spectra Optia Apheresis System with
      respect to the primary study endpoint, granulocyte/PMN cell collection efficiency.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Granulocyte/PMN cell collection efficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint is the granulocyte/PMN cell collection efficiency (CE) associated with the Granulocyte (PMN) Collection Procedures on the Spectra Optia and COBE Spectra Apheresis Systems.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Performance</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Comparison of collection efficiencies associated with the Granulocyte Cell Collection Procedures on the Spectra Optia and COBE Spectra Apheresis Systems for white blood cells and platelets. White Blood Cell (WBC) CE will be calculated using total WBC concentrations/counts obtained on an automated hematology analyzer. Platelet (PLT) CE will likewise be calculated using platelet concentrations/counts from an automated hematology analyzer.
Characterization of the collected blood product, including 1) Total PMN cell yield and PMN cell yield per liter blood processed 2) PMN cell viability and, in a subset of collections, PMN cell functionality. 3) Red blood cell (RBC) contamination. 4) Product volume.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Usability/assessment of system operation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Procedure time.
Number of operator adjustments aimed at establishing and maintaining the plasma/ cellular interface:  namely, on Spectra Optia, the adjustment of collection preference and, on COBE Spectra, the adjustment of the plasma pump flow rate.
Device malfunctions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Serious adverse events (SAEs) and unanticipated (serious) adverse device/procedure- related events (UADEs), adverse events (AEs).
Complete Blood Count with differential white cell count (CBCD).
Vital signs (temperature, heart rate, blood pressure).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Granulocyte/ Polymorphonuclear Cells</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Spectra Optia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Controlled evaluation of Granulocyte/Polymorphonuclear Cell Collection on the Spectra Optia device.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COBE Spectra</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Controlled evaluation of Granulocyte/Polymorphonuclear Cell Collection on the COBE Spectra device.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Granulocyte/Polymorphonuclear Cell Collection (COBE Spectra System)</intervention_name>
    <description>In Arm 1 the first PMN cell collection will be performed using the Spectra Optia System and the second PMN cell collection using the COBE Spectra System.</description>
    <arm_group_label>COBE Spectra</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Granulocyte/Polymorphonuclear Cell Collection (Spectra Optia System)</intervention_name>
    <description>In Arm 2 the first PMN cell collection will be performed using the COBE Spectra System and the second PMN cell collection using the Spectra Optia System.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Spectra Optia</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Acceptable health status and vital signs per the AABB blood donation guidelines to
             permit blood donation, including:

               1. Blood pressure ≥ 90/50 and ≤ 200/120 mmHg,

               2. Pulse &gt; 40 and &lt; 100 beats/min, and

               3. Temperature &lt; 99.5ºFahrenheit (F).

          -  Able to read, understand, and sign an English informed consent form.

          -  Age ≥ 18 years.

          -  Weight ≥ 50kg and &lt; 227kg.

          -  Male or non-pregnant, non-nursing female (a negative serum pregnancy test at
             screening and a negative urine pregnancy test prior to each mobilization).

          -  Acceptable screening laboratory test results prior to the first PMN cell
             mobilization, including:

               1. WBC count in the range: 3,500-10,800/uL,

               2. Hematocrit in the range: 38-65%,

               3. Platelet count in the range:  150,000-400,000/uL,

               4. Coagulation tests: PT not greater than 1.1 times the upper limit of the local
                  laboratory reference range; PTT not greater than 1.2 times the upper limit of
                  the local laboratory reference range,

               5. Serum electrolyte concentrations: potassium in the range 3.6-5.1 mmol/L; calcium
                  in the range 8.5-10.3 mg/dL,

               6. Serum creatinine not greater than 1.5mg/dL, and

               7. ALT not greater than 1.5 times the upper limit of the local laboratory reference
                  range. *** Up to two (2) of the above screening laboratory test results may fall
                  outside of these ranges, if in the judgment of the principal investigator or
                  designee, they do not constitute a significant risk to the subject.  Any excused
                  deviations from the above will be listed and summarized with the final
                  report.***

          -  Adequate dual peripheral venous access to allow collection of granulocytes (PMN
             cells) and return of remaining cells, platelets and plasma.

          -  If male, willing to use a condom during sexual relations with a female partner of
             child bearing potential until 48 hours following each G-CSF injection.

          -  If female, willing to use a medically-acceptable contraceptive until 48 hours
             following each G-CSF injection.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Positive screening for any of the following: HIV, HBV (except isolated HB core Ab
             reactivity), HCV, HTLV, Syphilis or West Nile Virus.

          -  Currently pregnant or breast-feeding.

          -  Collection or loss of specific volumes of whole blood or blood components during
             specified timeframes:

               1. more than 550mL of whole blood within the prior 56 days, or

               2. more than 3L of whole blood or 1.5L of red blood cells within the prior 12
                  months, or

               3. more than 12L of plasma within the prior 12 months, or

               4. a leukapheresis within the prior six weeks, or

               5. a plateletpheresis within the prior 48 hours or two within the prior 7 days or
                  twenty-four within the last 12 months, or

               6. a plasmapheresis within the prior 48 hours or two within the prior 7 days.

          -  History of congestive heart failure.

          -  History of uncontrolled hypertension (SBP/DBP &gt;200/120 mmHg).

          -  History or suspicion of active, peptic ulcer disease.

          -  History of diabetes mellitus.

          -  History of hematologic malignancy or chronic hematologic disorder.

          -  Family history (parents, siblings, children) of hematologic malignancy.

          -  History of deep vein thrombosis or venous thromboembolism, or bleeding disorder.

          -  History of sickle cell disease or a positive SickleDex screen.

          -  History of iritis or episcleritis.

          -  History of autoimmune condition or disorder, unless approved by principal
             investigator.

          -  Presence of psychological traits, or physiological or medical conditions that, in the
             opinion of the investigator, would make the subject unlikely to tolerate the
             procedures or complete the study.

          -  History of use/anticipated need for lithium.

          -  Received a G-CSF injection in the prior 4 months.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to ethylene oxide.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to G-CSF or hypersensitivity to any E. coli-derived products.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to HES or corn.

          -  Concurrent participation in another clinical trial or participation in a clinical
             trial within the past 30 days.

          -  Subject is being treated with calcium channel blockers and/or antiepileptic
             medications.   Note:  This applies only to Subjects at Bonfils Blood Center whose
             collected product will undergo neutrophil function testing.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raymond Goodrich, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Terumo BCT</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bonfils Blood Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80230</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hoxworth Blood Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45267-0055</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Blood Centers of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 5, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 1, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
