<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="48404">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01663428</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H12-00776</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01663428</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sup-ER Splint for Children With Birth Related Brachial Plexus Injury</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sup-ER Splinting: Does Early Passive Positioning in Supination and External Rotation in Children With Birth Related Brachial Plexus Injury Have Benefit?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's &amp; Women's Health Centre of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the ability of a newly designed splint called &quot;Sup-ER Splint&quot; to
      improve the arm function and anatomy of children with birth related brachial plexus
      injuries.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The brachial plexus is a group of 5 nerves from the spinal cord that provide the movement
      and sensation of an upper extremity. In some difficult deliveries, traction on the shoulder
      may lead to damage to the brachial plexus and will result in an arm that is paralyzed. This
      is called 'birth related brachial plexus injury' (BRBPI). This may occur in up to 1/1000
      births and the nerves may be injured minimally to severely. About 2/3 of children with this
      injury will recover to quite functional levels simply by maintaining looseness of joints
      while their nerves slowly heal. Some children have nerve injuries severe enough that they
      require surgical reconstruction with nerve grafts and nerve transfers to achieve even
      adequate function. One almost universally common outcome, even in children with otherwise
      &quot;good&quot; recovery, is that the motions of external rotation of the shoulder and supination of
      the forearm are weaker, later to recover, and often incomplete. Even beyond these direct
      functional weaknesses, because the arm is positioned poorly, joint contractures and
      imbalance of these motions can interfere with other upper extremity movements like elbow
      flexion, even when elbow flexion itself is well recovered. More importantly, lack of full
      motion leads to long term changes in the structure, growth, and posture of the shoulder
      requiring further musculoskeletal surgery, or a child with permanent deformity or
      disability. Surgery cannot completely correct this deformity. Any gains in active and
      passive range of motion during the first year of life may improve these long-term shoulder
      outcomes. The investigators have instituted a program of early passive repositioning mostly
      using a custom Sup-ER (Supination and External Rotation) splint during early growth and
      development to improve arm position and range of motion where ER and Sup are weak. In
      compliant patients in a pilot study, the speed and strength of recovery of ER and Supination
      are improved compared to historical controls. It is a novel splint and protocol designed by
      the investigators and has significantly changed the care received by patients in BC. This
      study will evaluate the use of Sup-ER splint in multiple centres over a five year period by
      assessing the arm function at common time points in recovery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    It was decided to change the study from a cohort to a randomized controlled trial.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Toronto Active Movement Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year of age</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alpha angle (glenoid version) and posterior displacement of humeral head (PDHH)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months of age</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Alpha angle (glenoid version) and posterior displacement of humeral head (PDHH) will be measured at baseline and 6 months of age by ultrasound.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Birth Related Brachial Plexus Injury</condition>
  <condition>Obstetrical Brachial Plexus Palsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sup-ER Splint</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Experimental group that will receive Sup-ER splint.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control (Currently accepted treatment)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group that will receive the currently accepted treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sup-ER Splint</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Sup-ER Splint</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Splint</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Currently accepted treatment</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Control (Currently accepted treatment)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of brachial plexus injury at birth.

          -  Significant deficit in external rotation and/or supination of the affected limb based
             on clinical assessment using the Toronto Active Movement Scale at 6 weeks of age:
             External Rotation ≤ 2 and/or Supination ≤ 2

          -  Tightness in Passive Range of Motion of external rotation: any angle of less than
             180°.

          -  Age 6-8 weeks for complete protocol fulfillment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Neuromuscular disorder.

          -  Unwillingness or inability to comply with the requirements of this protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Weeks</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>8 Weeks</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cynthia Verchere, MD FRCSC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.worldscientific.com/doi/abs/10.1142/S0218810402001229</url>
    <description>SPLINTING FOR PERIPHERAL NERVE INJURY IN UPPER LIMB</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 28, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 9, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>birth related brachial plexus injury</keyword>
  <keyword>brachial plexus</keyword>
  <keyword>splint</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
