<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="3045">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 04, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01740401</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>08-210</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>114660</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01740401</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CTLA-4 Blockade and Low Dose Cyclophosphamide in Patients With Advanced Malignant Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of CTLA-4 Blockade and Low Dose Cyclophosphamide in Patients With Advanced Malignant Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bhardwaj, Nina, M.D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bhardwaj, Nina, M.D.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to see whether the combination of low-dose Cyclophosphamide and
      Anti-CTLA4 (Ipilimumab) will stop tumor growth in patients with advanced skin cancer. The
      investigators expect to see an increase in response rate of the combination over Anti-CTLA-4
      alone and estimate a response rate of approximately 20 % in the proposed population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The transient removal of CTLA-4-mediated inhibition (CTLA-4 blockade) can induce effective
      anti-tumor immunity. Efficacy of CTLA-4 blockade as a single agent has been shown in
      melanoma 53. It has been hypothesized that anti-CTLA-4 antibody might deplete Treg cells 54,
      inducing autoimmunity. However, patients receiving Ipilimumab have not shown a decrease in
      Treg number or function in peripheral blood 55.

      This trial will answer the question if the combination of Anti-CTLA 4 (following a well
      established regimen of Ipilimumab) and Cyclophosphamide (given at immunomodulatory doses)
      will result in antitumor activity in patients with metastatic melanoma due to synergistic
      immunomodulating effects by overcoming tolerance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary objective of this study is:  Evaluate the anti-tumor activity of the combination of low dose Cyclophosphamide and CTLA-4 blockade using Objective Response Rate (ORR) by 12 weeks following mWHO RC.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Objective response rate (ORR) using mWHO RC Safety (CTEP v4.0; NCI CTCAE criteria) 2-stage design - 10 patients will be enrolled in Stage 1. The primary endpoint will be assessed when 10 patients have been followed for 12 weeks. In order to continue the study uninterrupted, additional patients will be enrolled in Stage 2 of the study, provided that safety does not become an issue. However, it is estimated that no more than 6 patients will be enrolled before the primary endpoint can be assessed in the initial 10 patients of the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The secondary objectives are: 1. Progression-free survival 2. T regulatory cell profile in peripheral blood</measure>
    <time_frame>Progression-free survival is measured from date of entry to date of 1st documented evidence of recurrence, confirmation of PD, or death (whichever is 1st). T regulatory cells are measured on D1 (pre CTX) &amp; D3 of each cycle.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Peripheral blood taken at baseline/various therapeutic time points/possibly maintenance cycles to evaluate T regulatory cells identified, serially monitored by polychromatic flow cytometry using FoxP3+/CD4+/CD127low/CD25hi markers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor-specific T cell responses will be measured in a subset of patients who have biopsy accessible tumor and have tumor biopsies taken.</measure>
    <time_frame>Two tumor punch biopsies (4mm in diameter) will be obtained before and after therapy (baseline and week 12, and optional during weeks 24, 36, and 48) if patients have accessible tumors.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>One of the tumor punch biopsy will be put in formalin for paraffin-embedding. The other tumor punch biopsy will be processed to obtain lysates to be used as antigens for the T cell assays.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">29</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cyclophosphamide, Ipilimumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment:
Cyclophosphamide 300 mg/m2 po - Day 1 of Weeks 1, 4, 7, and 10, for a total of 4 doses; (premedication prior to each dose of Cyclophosphamide 8mg Zofran po, then prn)
Ipilimumab 10 mg/kg iv - Day 3 of Weeks 1, 4, 7, and 10 for a total of 4 doses Maintenance treatment will be given on Weeks 24, 36, and 48 Ipilimumab 10 mg/kg iv</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide,  Ipilimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>This study consists of a Treatment Period, D1 Zofran 8mg pre-Cyclophosphamide 300mg/mg2 po and D3 Ipilimubab 10mg/kg iv wks 1,4,7 and 10; Tumor assessment at week 12; Follow-Up period weeks 13,16,and 20 with no treatment; Maintenance Period, D1 10mg/kg iv wks 24,36,48 and 60. Week 40=end of treatment; week 60=end of study</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cyclophosphamide, Ipilimumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ipilimumab (BMS-734016, MDX010, MDX-CTLA4)</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytoxin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Men &amp; women, ages ≥18

          2. Willing/able to give written informed consent.

          3. Histologic diagnosis of unresectable AJCC Stage III/IV malignant melanoma

          4. At least 2wks must have elapsed since last chemotherapy, immunotherapy, hormonal
             therapy, radiotherapy or major surgery &amp; beginning of protocol therapy. At least 6wks
             for nitrosoureas, mitomycin C, &amp; liposomal doxorubicin

          5. Toxicity related to prior therapy must either have returned to ≤ grade 1 or baseline.

          6. Two punch tumor biopsy at Screening and Wk12 (4mm diameter) must be provided for
             immune analysis/staining if patients have accessible disease.  Biopsies are optional
             during the Maintenance Period.Site of tumor biopsy s/n be only site of measurable
             disease. Minimum of 5 out of 1st 10 patients in stage I of the protocol must have
             biopsy accessible disease.

          7. Patients must have measurable disease defined as @ least 1 lesion that can be
             accurately measured in @ least 1 dimension (longest diameter to be recorded) as &gt;20
             mm with conventional techniques or as &gt;10 mm with spiral CT scan.

          8. Required values for initial laboratory tests:

               1. WBC ≥ 2000/uL

               2. ANC ≥ 1000/uL

               3. Platelets ≥ 50 x 103/uL

               4. Hemoglobin ≥ 9.5 g/dL

               5. Creatinine ≤ 3.0 x ULN

               6. AST/ALT ≤ 2.5 x ULN for patients without liver metastasis, ≤ 5 x ULN for
                  patients with liver metastasis

               7. Bilirubin ≤ 3.0 x ULN, (except patients with Gilbert's Syndrome, who  must have
                  a total bilirubin less than 3.0 mg/dL)

          9. Life expectancy of at least 4mos

         10. Patients w/stable, treated central nervous system (CNS) metastasis are eligible

         11. ECOG Performance Status Score 0-1

         12. Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must be using an adequate method of
             contraception to avoid pregnancy throughout study &amp; for up to 26wks after the last
             dose of investigational product, in such a manner that the risk of pregnancy is
             minimized.

             WOCBP include any female who has experienced menarche and who has not undergone
             successful surgical sterilization (hysterectomy, bilateral tubal ligation, or
             bilateral oophorectomy) or is not post-menopausal. Post-menopause is defined as:

               -  Amenorrhea ≥ 12 consecutive months w/o another cause, or

               -  For women with irregular menstrual periods and taking hormone replacement
                  therapy (HRT), documented serum follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) level ≥ 35
                  mIU/mL.

               -  Women who are using oral contraceptives, other hormonal contraceptives (vaginal
                  products/skin patches/implanted/injectable products), mechanical products such
                  as an intrauterine device or barrier methods (diaphragm/condoms/ spermicides) to
                  prevent pregnancy,are practicing abstinence or where their partner is sterile
                  (eg vasectomy) should be considered to be of childbearing potential.

               -  WOCBP must have a negative urine or serum pregnancy test (minimum sensitivity 25
                  IU/L or equivalent units of HCG) w/in 72hrs before the start of ipilimumab.

         13. Men of fathering potential must be using an adequate method of contraception to avoid
             conception throughout the study [and up to 26wks after last dose of investigational
             product] in a way that risk of pregnancy is minimized.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any other malignancy from which patient has been disease-free for less than 5yrs,
             with the exception of adequately treated &amp; cured basal or squamous cell skin cancer,
             superficial bladder cancer or carcinoma in situ of the cervix.

          2. Autoimmune disease: Patients with a history of inflammatory bowel disease, including
             ulcerative colitis and Crohn's Disease, are excluded from this study, as are patients
             with a history of symptomatic disease (eg rheumatoid arthritis, systemic progressive
             sclerosis [scleroderma], systemic lupus erythematosus, autoimmune vasculitis [eg
             Wegener's Granulomatosis]); motor neuropathy considered of autoimmune origin (eg
             Guillain-Barre Syndrome and Myasthenia Gravis).

          3. Any underlying medical or psychiatric condition, which in the opinion of investigator
             will make administration of ipilimumab hazardous or obscure interpretation of AEs,
             like a condition associated with frequent diarrhea.

          4. Uncontrolled or significant cardiovascular disease

          5. Any non-oncology vaccine therapy used for prevention of infectious diseases (for up
             to 1mo before/after any dose of ipilimumab).

          6. History of prior treatment with ipilimumab or prior CD137 agonist or CTLA 4 inhibitor
             or agonist.

          7. Concomitant therapy with any of following: IL 2, interferon, other non-study
             immunotherapy regimens; immunosuppressive agents; other investigation therapies; or
             chronic use of systemic corticosteroids (&gt;60mg prednisone/day).

          8. Prisoners or subjects who are compulsorily detained (involuntarily incarcerated) for
             treatment of either a psychiatric or physical (eg infectious) illness.

          9. Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP), defined above who:

               1. are unwilling/unable to use an acceptable method of contraception to avoid
                  pregnancy for their entire study period and for at least 26wks after cessation
                  of study drug, or

               2. have a positive pregnancy test at baseline, or

               3. are pregnant or breastfeeding.

         10. Persons of reproductive potential who are unwilling to use an adequate method of
             contraception throughout treatment &amp; for at least 26wks after ipilimumab is stopped.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nina Bhardwaj, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New York University Langone Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York University Langone Clinical Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 31, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 29, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Bhardwaj, Nina, M.D.</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Nina Bhardwaj</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Tumor Vaccine Program</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced Malignant Melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti CTLA4 Blockade</keyword>
  <keyword>Progression Free Survival</keyword>
  <keyword>Interventional Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase II Clinical Trial</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>T Cell Activation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cytotoxic T-lymphocyte antigen 4</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
